<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org">

<channel>
	<title>Cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml">
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastbuilddate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 15:22:19 +0000</lastbuilddate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updateperiod>
	hourly	</sy:updateperiod>
	<sy:updatefrequency>
	1	</sy:updatefrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Cancer before 40: Mayo Clinic expert shares 3 topics that younger patients often want to discuss</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/cancer-before-40-mayo-clinic-expert-shares-3-topics-that-younger-patients-often-want-to-discuss/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Sharon Theimer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Arizona]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403594</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->PHOENIX — Dr. Allison Rosenthal's experience facing a leukemia diagnosis while in medical school inspired her to pursue a career fighting cancer. It also gave her insight into aspects of life with cancer for people under 40. Now, Dr. Rosenthal is among the leaders of an effort at Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center to help […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/cancer-before-40-mayo-clinic-expert-shares-3-topics-that-younger-patients-often-want-to-discuss/">Cancer before 40: Mayo Clinic expert shares 3 topics that younger patients often want to discuss</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Allison-Rosenthal-talking-with-patient-1460376_3667864_0028-1024x576.jpg" alt="Dr. Allison Rosenthal talking with patient" class="wp-image-403646" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Allison-Rosenthal-talking-with-patient-1460376_3667864_0028-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Allison-Rosenthal-talking-with-patient-1460376_3667864_0028-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Allison-Rosenthal-talking-with-patient-1460376_3667864_0028-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Allison-Rosenthal-talking-with-patient-1460376_3667864_0028-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Allison-Rosenthal-talking-with-patient-1460376_3667864_0028-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>PHOENIX — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/rosenthal-allison-c-d-o/bio-20178616" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Allison Rosenthal's</a> experience facing a leukemia diagnosis while in medical school inspired her to pursue a career fighting cancer. It also gave her insight into aspects of life with cancer for people under 40. Now, Dr. Rosenthal is among the leaders of an effort at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> to help younger adults and older teens receive age-appropriate care and support. In this expert alert, Dr. Rosenthal shares three topics that younger people with cancer often want to discuss with their healthcare teams.</p>



<p>"I have a very big passion and motivation to take care of our younger cancer patients," Dr. Rosenthal explains. "These are some of the people who need the most support after treatment."</p>



<p>Advances in cancer treatments have made many of the cancers most common in younger people highly treatable and often curable, Dr. Rosenthal says.</p>



<p>Worldwide, roughly 1.3 million people ages 15 to 39 were diagnosed with cancer in 2022, the most recent statistics available, according to the <a href="https://gco.iarc.fr/today/en/dataviz/bars?mode=cancer&amp;age_start=3&amp;age_end=7&amp;populations=900&amp;multiple_populations=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">International Agency for Research on Cancer</a>. The most common cancers in that age group were <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/thyroid-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20354161" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">thyroid</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cervical-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352501" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cervical</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/testicular-cancer-care/symptoms-causes/syc-20352986" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">testicular</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/ovarian-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20375941" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ovarian</a>, blood cancers (<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/leukemia/symptoms-causes/syc-20374373" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">leukemias</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lymphoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20352638" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymphomas</a>) and <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-colorectal-cancer-in-young-adults/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colorectal</a>, agency figures show.</p>



<p>While long-term disease control or a cure is the objective, completing treatment doesn't necessarily mean that a younger person's experience with cancer is over, she adds.</p>



<p>"That means many adolescent or young adult cancer patients go on to live long lives, leaving them to navigate <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/category/survivorship/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer survivorship</a> for decades," says Dr. Rosenthal, a hematologist and oncologist at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/locations" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> in Phoenix. "There is the emotional impact that comes along with having experienced cancer, and that can be significant as they try to move forward in life. And there are also the physical effects and the long-lasting impact of that."</p>



<p>In addition to being a time of transition from pediatric medical care to adult care, the late teens and young adulthood typically are times of major life changes, adding challenges on top of cancer. The adolescent and young adult cancer program "is predicated on the idea that centering care around their unique needs improves their experience and outcomes," Dr. Rosenthal explains. In addition to individual feedback from patients, the program has a patient advisory council whose participants share what is important to them.</p>



<p>"We've tried to prioritize what we're working on based on the feedback we're getting from our patients who are in the midst of this experience," she says.</p>



<p>Dr. Rosenthal has observed that questions on these three topics are often on the minds of patients in their late teens, 20s and 30s during and after cancer treatment:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Wellness behaviors and <a href="https://mcpress.mayoclinic.org/her2plus-breast-cancer/heres-what-to-know-about-staying-active-with-breast-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">exercise</a>.</li>
</ul>



<p>"There are guidelines and recommendations for lifestyle choices including exercise, but it's a little bit hard to access those and to hold themselves accountable to pursue them," Dr. Rosenthal says.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/adolescent-young-adult-aya-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Connection with peers</a> with cancer and additional support to know that they're not alone.</li>
</ul>



<p>"And when their peers move on, to feel that they aren't left behind," Dr. Rosenthal explains.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2022/01/19/regaining-sexual-health-after-cancer-treatment/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sexual health</a> and relationships.</li>
</ul>



<p>"It's difficult for people to navigate," Dr. Rosenthal says. "It can be uncomfortable to ask about. It's hard to tell their peers about. There's a lot of work going into what we can proactively do to best support them."</p>



<p>Fertility can be impacted by cancer and its treatment, making conversations about <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/getting-pregnant/in-depth/fertility-preservation/art-20047512" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">fertility preservation</a> important.</p>



<p>Another priority for the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/adolescent-young-adult-cancer-program/sections/overview/ovc-20564751" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Adolescent and Young Adult Cancer Program</a> is <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/for-patients-and-visitors/advance-care-planning" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">advance care planning</a>. For older people with advanced cancers, involving palliative care earlier often helps them live longer and have a better quality of life, Dr. Rosenthal notes. That same approach could help younger patients.</p>



<p>"We're working on an advance care planning project specifically for young people with advanced cancers, to empower them to have a voice when they have time to have a voice, and not have that taken from them as well," Dr. Rosenthal says. "I know there's so much that can be done. Long-term outcomes, survivorship, quality of life — all of that is very important."</p>



<p>The program takes a multidisciplinary approach, including cancer specialists, social workers, health psychologists, and financial and vocational counselors.</p>



<p>"We're really fortunate that the majority of young adult patients who get cancer care are going to do well in the long term; there's going to be a lot of long-term survivors," Dr. Rosenthal says. "But if we aren't paying attention to the long-term treatment side effects, quality of life and the monitoring and maintenance of health, then we aren't providing the full service for these patients that they really deserve."</p>



<p><strong>JOURNALISTS:</strong> Global, regional and national statistics on cancer in people ages 15 to 39 are available <a href="https://gco.iarc.fr/today/en/dataviz/bars?mode=population&amp;age_start=3&amp;age_end=7" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>.</p>



<p>###<strong></strong></p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact: </strong><strong></strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Sharon Theimer, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/cancer-before-40-mayo-clinic-expert-shares-3-topics-that-younger-patients-often-want-to-discuss/">Cancer before 40: Mayo Clinic expert shares 3 topics that younger patients often want to discuss</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1_Dr-Allison-Rosenthal-talking-with-patient-1460376_3667864_0028.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Allison-Rosenthal-talking-with-patient-1460376_3667864_0028.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic takes the next step in making heavy particle therapy available in the Americas for patients with aggressive cancers</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-takes-the-next-step-in-making-heavy-particle-therapy-available-in-the-western-hemisphere-for-patients-with-aggressive-cancers/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Tia R. Ford]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 14:01:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Florida]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Duan Family]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403467</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->JACKSONVILLE, Fla. — In a bold step to transform cancer care,&nbsp;Mayo Clinic&nbsp;is bringing new hope for patients diagnosed with the most aggressive and treatment-resistant cancers. Today, Mayo Clinic opened the new 228,000-square-foot Duan Family Building at its Jacksonville, Florida location. The building will house the first carbon ion therapy program in the Americas, and advanced […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-takes-the-next-step-in-making-heavy-particle-therapy-available-in-the-western-hemisphere-for-patients-with-aggressive-cancers/">Mayo Clinic takes the next step in making heavy particle therapy available in the Americas for patients with aggressive cancers</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Duan_Family_Building-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Mayo Clinic takes the next step in making heavy particle therapy, carbon ion therapy, available in the Western Hemisphere for patients with aggressive cancers" class="wp-image-403471" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Duan_Family_Building-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Duan_Family_Building-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Duan_Family_Building-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Duan_Family_Building-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Duan_Family_Building-16-x-9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. — In a bold step to transform cancer care,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is bringing new hope for patients diagnosed with the most aggressive and treatment-resistant cancers. Today, Mayo Clinic opened the new 228,000-square-foot Duan Family Building at its Jacksonville, Florida location. The building will house the first carbon ion therapy program in the Americas, and advanced technology that can seamlessly deliver both carbon ions and protons to treat the same tumor.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Carbon ion therapy and other heavy particle therapies are the advanced radiation therapies of our future," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/willman-cheryl-l-m-d/bio-20537787" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cheryl Willman, M.D.</a>, executive director,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>. "When battling our patients' complex, currently radioresistant cancers at Mayo Clinic, we need the advantage of these next-gen radiation tools, which can be fine-tuned to target and treat aggressive tumors while minimizing the impact to surrounding tissue."</p>



<p>As a leading National Cancer Institute-designated Comprehensive Cancer Center with locations in Florida, Minnesota and Arizona, Mayo Clinic is uniquely qualified to bring carbon ion therapy, as well as the dual carbon ion and proton treatment option, to the Americas.</p>



<p>"Mayo Clinic is building a better future where more cures are possible&nbsp;—&nbsp;giving new hope to patients with aggressive cancers," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/-/media/kcms/gbs/patient-consumer/documents/2019/09/12/20/18/gianrico-farrugia.pdf?la=en&amp;hash=D1B315B05A8056FE1FA32F1738D86AA50D18CFD7" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gianrico Farrugia, M.D.</a>, president and CEO of Mayo Clinic. "This is the latest demonstration of our commitment&nbsp;to patient-centered healthcare transformation through our Bold. Forward. strategy."</p>



<p>While treatment with carbon ion therapy is expected to begin in 2028 and proton therapy in 2027, the opening of the Duan Family Building marks a significant milestone. Beginning this summer, other cancer treatment options will be offered in the new building, including photon therapy, immunotherapy, chimeric antigen receptor-T cell therapy (CAR-T cell therapy) and more, along with sophisticated imaging technology.</p>



<p>"The emerging treatments that will be offered in the Duan Family Building, including carbon ion therapy, are an important part of the integrated cancer practice at Mayo Clinic, ensuring constant, research-driven innovation in the care we are providing to patients," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/-/media/kcms/gbs/patient-consumer/documents/2019/09/12/20/18/kent-thielen.pdf?la=en&amp;hash=CB300258C2FA133B3C470D27393B2A81E2099699" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kent Thielen, M.D.</a>,&nbsp;CEO of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers, working with outside global experts, are also exploring the use of other heavy ions beyond carbon in clinical studies to evaluate their potential benefits in future cancer care.</p>



<p>This building and the advances in cancer care treatment technology housed within represent a significant investment, largely thanks to the generosity and vision of our benefactors.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Advancing radiation therapy</h2>



<p>Many patients with cancer require radiation therapy during their treatment.&nbsp;Different forms of radiation therapy have varying biological impacts on cancer cells.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Photon therapy:&nbsp;</strong>This is the most common form of radiation therapy, which uses X-rays or gamma rays — packets of light energy called photons — to treat cancer. Beams are directed at the tumor, preventing the cancer cells from growing or dividing.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Proton beam therapy:</strong> This particle therapy directs a precise dose of positively charged particles (protons) at cancer cells, destroying their genetic material while minimizing the impact on surrounding, healthy cells. This is especially beneficial for treating tumors near vital organs and cancer in children.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Carbon ion therapy:</strong> This heavy particle therapy delivers positively charged particles (carbon ions) that release their energy upon hitting the targeted cancerous tumor. The particles destroy cancer cells with very little damage to surrounding tissue. It is particularly effective against cancer cells that are resistant to other forms of radiation.</li>
</ul>



<p>Advances in radiation therapies, such as carbon ion and dual modality treatments of proton beam and carbon ion, enable clinicians to create highly individualized, precise and effective treatments, ultimately bringing more cures to patients.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How radiation therapies work</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-video aligncenter"><video controls="" loop="" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Animation_How-radiation-therapies-work.mp4"></video></figure>



<p></p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-hitachi-to-build-first-next-generation-carbon-ion-therapy-treatment-facility-in-north-america/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">In 2019</a>,&nbsp;Mayo Clinic and technology innovator&nbsp;<a href="https://www.hitachi.com/en/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hitachi</a>&nbsp;began working together to bring carbon ion therapy to the Americas.&nbsp;While carbon ion therapy was discovered in the United States in the 1970s, the technology has only been available for clinical care at a handful of centers in Asia and Europe.</p>



<p>###&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education, and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Tia R. Ford, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Media kit:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://mcmedia.mayo.edu/Share/hw6tif8n13r1i8wj22762s6b5p5a767t" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Duan Family Building media kit with soundbites, images, animation</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-takes-the-next-step-in-making-heavy-particle-therapy-available-in-the-western-hemisphere-for-patients-with-aggressive-cancers/">Mayo Clinic takes the next step in making heavy particle therapy available in the Americas for patients with aggressive cancers</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Duan_Family_Building-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Duan_Family_Building-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Duan Family]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Immunotherapy boosts chemotherapy in combating stage 3 colon cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/immunotherapy-boosts-chemotherapy-in-combating-stage-3-colon-cancer/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Alison Satake]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[ASCO25]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Chemotherapy]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Colon Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[deficient DNA mismatch repair (dMMR)]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Frank Sinicrope]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[immunotherapy]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[stage 3]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403282</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Late-breaking abstract featured at ASCO 2025 ROCHESTER, Minn. —&nbsp;Colon cancer is the third most prevalent form of cancer in the U.S., and while screening has helped detect and prevent colon cancer from spreading, major advancements in treating colon cancer have lagged. Now, new research led by Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center found that adding immunotherapy […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/immunotherapy-boosts-chemotherapy-in-combating-stage-3-colon-cancer/">Immunotherapy boosts chemotherapy in combating stage 3 colon cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"--><img decoding="async" width="800" height="534" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/Physician-assistant-and-nurse-tend-to-chemotherapy-patient_WF5510977_0434.jpg" alt="Physician assistant and nurse tend to chemotherapy patient, immunotherapy 
" class="wp-image-403293" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/Physician-assistant-and-nurse-tend-to-chemotherapy-patient_WF5510977_0434.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/Physician-assistant-and-nurse-tend-to-chemotherapy-patient_WF5510977_0434-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/Physician-assistant-and-nurse-tend-to-chemotherapy-patient_WF5510977_0434-768x513.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px">



<p><em>Late-breaking abstract featured at ASCO 2025</em></p>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. —&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353669" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Colon cancer</a> is the third most prevalent form of cancer in the U.S., and while screening has helped detect and prevent colon cancer from spreading, major advancements in treating colon cancer have lagged.</p>



<p>Now, new research led by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> found that adding immunotherapy to chemotherapy after surgery for patients with stage 3 (node-positive) colon cancer — and with a specific genetic makeup called deficient DNA mismatch repair (dMMR) — was associated with a 50% reduction in cancer recurrence and death compared to chemotherapy alone. Approximately 15% of people diagnosed with colon cancer exhibit dMMR and, to date, these tumors appear less sensitive to chemotherapy. The results of the multi-center <a href="https://meetings.asco.org/abstracts-presentations/244715">study</a> were presented during a plenary session at the <a href="https://www.asco.org/annual-meeting" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">2025 American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) Annual Meeting</a> in Chicago.</p>



<p>"The findings from our study represent a major advance in the adjuvant treatment of dMMR stage 3 colon cancer and will now change the treatment for this type of cancer," says oncologist <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/sinicrope-frank-a-m-d/bio-00028129" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Frank Sinicrope, M.D.</a>, who led the study. "It's extremely rewarding to be able to offer our patients a new treatment regimen that can reduce the risk of recurrence and improve their chances of survival."</p>



<p>Until now, the standard treatment after surgery for any stage 3 colon cancer has been chemotherapy. However, the researchers note that approximately 30% of patients experience cancer recurrence despite this treatment.&nbsp; <strong></strong></p>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3sJgL-vlwpQ" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Frank Sinicrope discusses Mayo Clinic immunotherapy study</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoid3sJgLvlwpQ" title="Dr. Frank Sinicrope - Mayo Clinic immunotherapy study – Stage 3 colon cancer" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3sJgL-vlwpQ?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites with Dr. Frank Sinicrope are in the downloads at the end of the post. Please "Courtesy: Mayo Clinic News Network."</strong></p>



<p>The clinical trial enrolled 712 patients with dMMR stage 3 colon cancer that had been surgically removed and who had cancer cells in their lymph nodes<a>.</a> The immunotherapy given in this study was an immune checkpoint inhibitor, known as atezolizumab, which activates one's immune system to attack and kill cancer cells, which are responsible for cancer recurrence and spread. The patients — who lived in the U.S. and Germany — received chemotherapy for six months along with immunotherapy and then continued with immunotherapy alone for another six months.</p>



<p>Dr. Sinicrope and others previously studied patients with colon cancer whose cells are unable to repair errors during DNA replication that create a nucleotide mismatch, a condition called dMMR. They noted that these patients' tumors showed a striking increase in inflammatory cells within the tumor, including those that express the target of immune checkpoint inhibitors. This sparked the idea of using immune checkpoint inhibitors to make the immune cells more effective in attacking and killing the cancer cells.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p>



<p>Based on the data from this study, Dr. Sinicrope recommends this combination of immunotherapy and chemotherapy treatment to be the new standard treatment for stage 3 deficient mismatch repair colon cancer. The research team plans to approach the <a href="https://www.nccn.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Comprehensive Cancer Network</a>, a nonprofit organization consisting of 33 leading cancer centers, including Mayo Clinic, with this recommendation. &nbsp;</p>



<p>The study included patients with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lynch-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20374714" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lynch syndrome</a>, the most common form of hereditary colon cancer, as these patients can have tumors that show deficient mismatch repair (dMMR).</p>



<p>"We're changing the paradigm in colon cancer treatment. By using immunotherapy at earlier stages of disease, we are achieving meaningful benefits for our patients," says Dr. Sinicrope.</p>



<p>Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://meetings.asco.org/abstracts-presentations/244715">abstract</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&nbsp;</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/immunotherapy-boosts-chemotherapy-in-combating-stage-3-colon-cancer/">Immunotherapy boosts chemotherapy in combating stage 3 colon cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/Physician-assistant-and-nurse-tend-to-chemotherapy-patient_WF5510977_0434-1x1-1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/Physician-assistant-and-nurse-tend-to-chemotherapy-patient_WF5510977_0434-16x9-1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[ASCO25]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Chemotherapy]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Colon Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[deficient DNA mismatch repair (dMMR)]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Frank Sinicrope]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[immunotherapy]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[stage 3]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic experts present key cancer research findings at ASCO</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-experts-present-key-cancer-research-findings-at-asco/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Kelley Luckstein]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 28 May 2025 18:08:28 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[ASCO]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News release]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403218</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center researchers will present their latest oncology findings at the 2025 American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) Annual Meeting, scheduled to be held May 30–June 3 at the McCormick Place Convention Center in Chicago. The event, recognized as one of the largest gatherings in the field of cancer […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-experts-present-key-cancer-research-findings-at-asco/">Mayo Clinic experts present key cancer research findings at ASCO</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="534" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/Claudia-Anderson-APRN-CNP-MSN-Medical-Oncology-Nurse-Practitioner-gestures-and-explains-something-to-two-Physician-Assistants_WF5510977_0088.jpg" alt="Medical oncology nurse practitioner gestures and explains something to two physician assistants" class="wp-image-403230" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/Claudia-Anderson-APRN-CNP-MSN-Medical-Oncology-Nurse-Practitioner-gestures-and-explains-something-to-two-Physician-Assistants_WF5510977_0088.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/Claudia-Anderson-APRN-CNP-MSN-Medical-Oncology-Nurse-Practitioner-gestures-and-explains-something-to-two-Physician-Assistants_WF5510977_0088-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/Claudia-Anderson-APRN-CNP-MSN-Medical-Oncology-Nurse-Practitioner-gestures-and-explains-something-to-two-Physician-Assistants_WF5510977_0088-768x513.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px">



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> researchers will present their latest oncology findings at the <a href="https://www.asco.org/annual-meeting" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">2025 American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) Annual Meeting,</a> scheduled to be held May 30–June 3 at the McCormick Place Convention Center in Chicago. The event, recognized as one of the largest gatherings in the field of cancer research, will feature 59 Mayo Clinic-authored abstracts highlighting advancements in cancer care.</p>



<p>Among the standout presentations are practice-changing studies focused on chemotherapy approaches, artificial intelligence (AI) applications in oncology, cancer care at home and new therapies for breast cancer and melanoma — all focused on improving treatment options for patients with cancer.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Highlights include:</h2>



<p><a href="https://meetings.asco.org/2025-asco-annual-meeting/16482?presentation=245969" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Plenary Session</strong></a><strong>:</strong> Randomized trial of standard chemotherapy alone or combined with atezolizumab as adjuvant therapy for patients with stage 3 deficient DNA mismatch repair (dMMR) colon cancer (Alliance A021502; ATOMIC)<br>Presentation time: Sunday, June 1, 1:05 to 1:17 p.m. CDT<br>Session title: Special Sessions<br><strong>Presenter:</strong> <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/sinicrope-frank-a-m-d/bio-00028129" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Frank Sinicrope, M.D.</a>, medical oncologist and gastroenterologist</p>



<p><a href="https://meetings.asco.org/2025-asco-annual-meeting/16446?presentation=251176#251176" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Clinical Science Symposium</strong></a><strong>:</strong> Perception and concerns of the hematology and oncology (HemOnc) workforce about artificial intelligence (AI) in clinical practice (CliPr) and medical education (MedED) <br>Presentation time: Saturday, May 31, 2:03 to 2:15 p.m. CDT<br>Session title: The Future Is Now: Innovations in Medical Education <br><strong>Presenter:</strong> <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/residencies-and-fellowships/hematologyoncology-fellowship-florida/meet-our-trainees/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Guilherme Sacchi de Camargo Correia, M.D.</a>, oncology fellow (senior author is <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/manochakian-rami-m-d/bio-20305894" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Rami Manochakian, M.D.</a>, thoracic medical oncologist)</p>



<p><a href="https://meetings.asco.org/2025-asco-annual-meeting/16356?presentation=244715#244715" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Oral Abstract Session</strong></a><strong>:</strong> Tissue-free circulating tumor DNA assay and patient outcome in a phase 3 trial of FOLFOX-based adjuvant chemotherapy (Alliance N0147) <br>Presentation time: Friday, May 30, 3:57 to 4:09 p.m. CDT<br>Session title: Gastrointestinal Cancer — Colorectal and Anal <br><strong>Presenter:</strong> <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/sinicrope-frank-a-m-d/bio-00028129" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Frank Sinicrope, M.D.</a>, medical oncologist and gastroenterologist</p>



<p><a href="https://meetings.asco.org/2025-asco-annual-meeting/16353?presentation=247740#247740" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Oral Abstract Session</strong></a><strong>:</strong> [212Pb]VMT-α-NET therapy in somatostatin receptor 2 (SSTR2) expressing neuroendocrine tumors (NETs): Dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) observation participants after one-year follow-up and preliminary report for expansion participants. <br>Presentation time: Friday, May 30, 4:09 to 4:21 p.m. CDT<br>Session title: Developmental Therapeutics — Molecularly Targeted Agents and Tumor Biology <br><strong>Presenter:</strong> <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/halfdanarson-thor-r-m-d/bio-00027794" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Thorvardur Halfdanarson, M.D.</a>, medical oncologist &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://meetings.asco.org/2025-asco-annual-meeting/16391?presentation=247047#247047" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Oral Abstract Session</strong></a><strong>:</strong> NeoACTIVATE arm C: Phase II trial of neoadjuvant atezolizumab and tiragolumab for high-risk operable stage 3 melanoma <br>Presentation time: Tuesday, June 3, 2025, 10:45 a.m. to 10:57 a.m. CDT<br>Session title: Melanoma/Skin Cancers <br><strong>Presenter:</strong> <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/hieken-tina-j-m-d/bio-20089011" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tina Hieken, M.D.</a>, breast and melanoma surgical oncologist</p>



<p><a href="https://meetings.asco.org/2025-asco-annual-meeting/16345?presentation=247910#247910" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Poster Session</strong></a><strong>:</strong> Cancer Care Beyond Walls (CCBW): A randomized pragmatic trial of home-based versus in-clinic cancer therapy administration <br>Session time: Sunday, June 1, 9 a.m. to noon CDT<br>Session title: Care Delivery and Quality Care <br><strong>Presenter:</strong> <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/dronca-roxana-s-m-d/bio-00028161" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Roxana Dronca, M.D.</a>, medical oncologist and the site deputy director of Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center in Florida</p>



<p><a href="https://meetings.asco.org/2025-asco-annual-meeting/16345?presentation=252215#252215" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Poster Session</strong></a><strong>:</strong> A pilot single-arm, pragmatic trial in progress of in-home versus in-clinic subcutaneous nivolumab administration through Cancer Care Beyond Walls (CCBW) program (connected access and remote expertise) <br>Session time: Sunday, June 1, 9 a.m. to noon CDT <br>Session Title: Care Delivery/Models of Care <br><strong>Presenter:</strong> <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/residencies-and-fellowships/hematologyoncology-fellowship-florida/meet-our-trainees/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dina Elantably, M.B., B.CH.</a>, oncology fellow (senior author is <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/dronca-roxana-s-m-d/bio-00028161" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Roxana Dronca, M.D.</a>, medical oncologist and the site deputy director of Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center in Florida)</p>



<p><a href="https://meetings.asco.org/2025-asco-annual-meeting/16372?presentation=248813#248813" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Poster Session</strong></a><strong>:</strong> Initial results of MC200710 investigating therapeutic vaccine (PDS0101) alone or with pembrolizumab prior to surgery or radiation therapy for locally advanced HPV associated oropharyngeal carcinoma, a phase 2 window of opportunity trial <br>Session time: Monday, June 2, 9 a.m. to noon CDT<br>Session title: Head and Neck Cancer <br><strong>Presenter:</strong> <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/routman-david-m-m-d/bio-20536269" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">David Routman, M.D.</a>, radiation oncologist</p>



<p><a href="https://meetings.asco.org/2025-asco-annual-meeting/16342?presentation=253018#253018" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Poster Session</strong></a><strong>:</strong> ALISertib in combination with endocrine therapy in patients with hormone receptor-positive (HR+), HER2-negative (HER2–) recurrent or metastatic breast cancer: The phase 2 ALISCA-Breast1 study <br>Session time: Monday, June 2, 9 a.m. to noon CDT <br>Session title: Breast Cancer — Metastatic <br><strong>Presenter:</strong> <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/haddad-tufia-c-m-d/bio-10029575" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tufia Haddad, M.D.</a>, medical oncologist</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://meetings.asco.org/2025-asco-annual-meeting/16339?presentation=244491#244491" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Poster Session</a>:</strong> Estrogen receptor expression in residual breast cancer following neoadjuvant chemotherapy <br>Session time: Monday, June 2, 9 a.m. to noon CDT<br>Session title: Breast Cancer — Local/Regional/Adjuvant <br><strong>Presenter:</strong> <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/residencies-and-fellowships/hematologyoncology-fellowship-minnesota/meet-our-trainees/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sarah Premji, M.D.</a>, oncology fellow (senior author is <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/goetz-matthew-p-m-d/bio-00027285" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Matthew Goetz, M.D.</a>, breast medical oncologist, and the Erivan K. Haub Family Professor of Cancer Research Honoring Richard F. Emslander, M.D.)</p>



<p>For more information about 2025 ASCO visit: <a href="https://www.asco.org/annual-meeting" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://www.asco.org/annual-meeting</a>.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact on-site at ASCO:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, 507-202-8655, <a href="mailto:luckstein.kelley@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">luckstein.kelley@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-experts-present-key-cancer-research-findings-at-asco/">Mayo Clinic experts present key cancer research findings at ASCO</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/Claudia-Anderson-APRN-CNP-MSN-Medical-Oncology-Nurse-Practitioner-gestures-and-explains-something-to-two-Physician-Assistants_WF5510977_1x1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/Claudia-Anderson-APRN-CNP-MSN-Medical-Oncology-Nurse-Practitioner-gestures-and-explains-something-to-two-Physician-Assistants_WF5510977_16x9.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[ASCO]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News release]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Understanding your risk: Are women likelier to have thyroid cancer than men are?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/understanding-your-risk-are-women-likelier-to-have-thyroid-cancer-than-men-are/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Sharon Theimer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Tue, 27 May 2025 14:15:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Surgery]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403182</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->International Thyroid Awareness Week is May 25-31 ROCHESTER, Minnesota— Globally, women are roughly twice as likely as men to be diagnosed with thyroid cancer. However, recent research shows that men face an equal risk. Mayo Clinic experts say that men and women alike should be aware of thyroid cancer risk. The thyroid is a small […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/understanding-your-risk-are-women-likelier-to-have-thyroid-cancer-than-men-are/">Understanding your risk: Are women likelier to have thyroid cancer than men are?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/16x9-thyroid-cancer-feat-image-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-403183" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/16x9-thyroid-cancer-feat-image-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/16x9-thyroid-cancer-feat-image-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/16x9-thyroid-cancer-feat-image-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/16x9-thyroid-cancer-feat-image.jpg 1216w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p><em>International Thyroid Awareness Week is May 25-31<br><br></em>ROCHESTER, Minnesota— Globally, women are roughly twice as likely as men to be diagnosed with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/thyroid-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20354161">thyroid cancer</a>. However, recent research shows that men face an equal risk. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic">Mayo Clinic</a> experts say that men and women alike should be aware of thyroid cancer risk.</p>



<p>The thyroid is a small gland located at the front of your neck. It plays a role in regulating the body's metabolism. Thyroid cancer happens when cells in the thyroid develop changes in their DNA.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Worldwide, thyroid cancer is the <a href="/Users/m086474/Downloads/CA%2520A%2520Cancer%2520J%2520Clinicians%2520-%25202024%2520-%2520Bray%2520-%2520Global%2520cancer%2520statistics%25202022%2520%2520GLOBOCAN%2520estimates%2520of%2520incidence%2520and%2520mortality%2520(1).pdf">seventh most common cancer</a>, statistics from the <a href="https://gco.iarc.who.int/media/globocan/factsheets/cancers/39-all-cancers-fact-sheet.pdf">Global Cancer Observatory</a> show.</p>



<p>Most forms of thyroid cancer can be cured, and minimally invasive surgery may be an option, sometimes sparing much of the noncancerous thyroid gland tissue, says Dr. Eric Moore, a head and neck surgeon and chair of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/ent-head-neck-surgery/sections/overview/ovc-20424084">otolaryngology</a> at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota, and medical director, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/international">Mayo Clinic International</a>.</p>



<p>“Some thyroid cancer, though rarer, is very aggressive and more difficult to treat,” Dr. Moore adds. “While these were once thought untreatable, we have made great strides in treatment of the most aggressive of these cancers, and our research and treatment have made transformative strides in the outcomes for our patients with these types of thyroid cancer.”</p>



<p>It’s not known in most cases what caused the DNA changes that triggered thyroid cancer: Exposure to high levels of radiation, such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/radiation-therapy/about/pac-20385162">radiation therapy</a> to the head and neck, may increase the risk, and some types of thyroid cancer may run in families.</p>



<p>In the past, it was believed that women developed thyroid cancer more than men.&nbsp;However, <a href="https://www.thyroid.org/patient-thyroid-information/ct-for-patients/november-2021/vol-14-issue-11-p-11-12/">more recent data</a> shows that women are often diagnosed with a less aggressive, relatively non-life-threatening form of thyroid cancer: When it comes to advanced thyroid cancer, the risks are the same for both men and women.</p>



<p>"Men have a risk, and we're not catching them as much," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/bernet-victor-m-d/bio-20055366">Dr. Victo</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/bernet-victor-m-d/bio-20055366" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">r</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/bernet-victor-m-d/bio-20055366">&nbsp;Bernet</a>, an endocrinologist at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/">Mayo Clinic</a> in Jacksonville, Florida.</p>



<p>The reason is unclear. But one theory is that women are more proactive about their health and seeing their doctor regularly, leading to more diagnoses.</p>



<p>"So, in actuality, they probably don't have as much of a higher risk than we thought," explains Dr. Bernet.</p>



<p>Thyroid cancer might not cause any symptoms at first. But as it grows, it can cause signs and symptoms, such as swelling in your neck; changes to your voice, such as increased hoarseness; neck and throat pain; and difficulty swallowing.</p>



<p>Most people with thyroid cancer that requires treatment will have surgery to remove part or all of the thyroid. Which operation your health care team might recommend depends on your type of thyroid cancer, the size of the cancer and it has spread beyond the thyroid to the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/swollen-lymph-nodes/symptoms-causes/syc-20353902">lymph nodes</a>. Your care team also considers your preferences when creating a treatment plan.</p>



<p>Operations used to treat thyroid cancer include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Removing all or most of the thyroid (thyroidectomy).</strong>&nbsp;An operation to remove the thyroid gland might involve removing all of the thyroid tissue (total thyroidectomy) or most of the thyroid tissue (near-total thyroidectomy). The surgeon often leaves small rims of thyroid tissue around the parathyroid glands to reduce the risk of damage to the parathyroid glands, which help regulate the calcium levels in your blood.</li>



<li><strong>Removing a portion of the thyroid (thyroid lobectomy).</strong>&nbsp;During a thyroid lobectomy, the surgeon removes half of the thyroid. Lobectomy might be recommended if you have a slow-growing thyroid cancer in one part of the thyroid, no suspicious nodules in other areas of the thyroid and no signs of cancer in the lymph nodes.</li>



<li><strong>Removing lymph nodes in the neck (lymph node dissection).</strong>&nbsp;Thyroid cancer often spreads to nearby lymph nodes in the neck. An ultrasound examination of the neck before surgery may reveal signs that cancer cells have spread to the lymph nodes. If so, the surgeon may remove some of the lymph nodes in the neck for testing.</li>
</ul>



<p>At Mayo Clinic, people with thyroid cancer are cared for by a team that includes a variety of specialties, such as endocrinologists; endocrine and head and neck surgeons; ear, nose and throat specialists; oncologists; radiologists; and pathologists. Team members have access to the latest technology, techniques and evidence, and weigh <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/thyroid-cancer/care-at-mayo-clinic/mac-20354170">treatment options</a> to create a personalized plan for each patient.</p>



<p>Among Mayo physicians dedicated to treating thyroid cancer, Mayo Clinic’s <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/overview/ovc-20457302">Advanced Thyroid Cancer Multidisciplinary Clinic</a> focuses on advanced and aggressive thyroid cancers. <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/departments-divisions/department-otorhinolaryngology/divisions/head-neck-cancer-reconstructive-surgery/thyroid-cancer">Mayo researchers</a> are studying the full range of the disease, from early stages to advanced cancers, to constantly refine the understanding and approach to all aspects of thyroid cancer and help physicians achieve the best outcomes for patients.</p>



<p><strong>JOURNALISTS:</strong> Global, regional and national statistics on thyroid cancer are available <a href="https://vizhub.healthdata.org/gbd-results?params=gbd-api-2021-permalink/97ab8442743f35239f289482753597bc">here</a> (free log-in may be required).</p>



<p>###<strong></strong></p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact: </strong><strong></strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Sharon Theimer, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/understanding-your-risk-are-women-likelier-to-have-thyroid-cancer-than-men-are/">Understanding your risk: Are women likelier to have thyroid cancer than men are?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/1x1-thyroid-cancer-feat-image.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/16x9-thyroid-cancer-feat-image.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>&nbsp;Who should be screened for skin cancer?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/who-should-be-screened-for-skin-cancer/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 23 May 2025 12:26:11 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Michael Colgan]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Skin Cancer]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403067</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Editor’s Note: May is National Skin Cancer Awareness Month&nbsp; Skin cancer&nbsp;is the most common cancer in the U.S.&nbsp;&nbsp;More than 6 million adults are treated for it each year, says&nbsp;Dr. Michael Colgan, a Mayo Clinic Health System dermatologist in Eau Claire, Wisconsin. Melanoma is an aggressive form of skin cancer. In 2025, an estimated 104,960 cases […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/who-should-be-screened-for-skin-cancer/">&nbsp;Who should be screened for skin cancer?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Skin-Caner-2-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Skin cancer check" class="wp-image-386963" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Skin-Caner-2-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Skin-Caner-2-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Skin-Caner-2-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Skin-Caner-2-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Skin-Caner-2-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p><em>Editor’s Note: May is National Skin Cancer Awareness Month&nbsp;</em></p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/skin-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20377605?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Skin cancer</a>&nbsp;is the most common cancer in the U.S.&nbsp;&nbsp;More than 6 million adults are treated for it each year, says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/michael-colgan-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Michael Colgan</a>, a Mayo Clinic Health System <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/dermatology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dermatologist </a>in Eau Claire, Wisconsin.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/melanoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20374884" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Melanoma</a> is an aggressive form of skin cancer. In 2025, an estimated 104,960 cases of invasive melanoma will be diagnosed in the U.S., and an estimated 8,430 people will die of melanoma, according to the <a href="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2025/2025-cancer-facts-and-figures-acs.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Cancer Society</a>. When detected early, however, the five-year survival rate for melanoma is 99%.</p>



<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/07/a-medical-illustration-of-normal-skin-and-three-types-of-skin-cancer-squamous-cell-carcinoma-basal-cell-carcinoma-and-melanoma-original.jpg" alt="a medical illustration of normal skin and three types of skin cancer - squamous cell carcinoma, basal cell carcinoma and melanoma" class="wp-image-195338" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/07/a-medical-illustration-of-normal-skin-and-three-types-of-skin-cancer-squamous-cell-carcinoma-basal-cell-carcinoma-and-melanoma-original.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/07/a-medical-illustration-of-normal-skin-and-three-types-of-skin-cancer-squamous-cell-carcinoma-basal-cell-carcinoma-and-melanoma-original-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px"></figure></div>


<p>When it comes to who may be most at risk of developing melanoma, it is often thought that those with darker complexions do not have to take the same precautions as those with fair complexions. The reality is that no one is immune to melanoma.&nbsp;</p>



<p>While people with a darker complexion may have significantly increased protection from the sun, they are still prone to developing melanoma skin cancer. More commonly for those with a darker complexion, melanoma develops on the extremities — hands and feet — with worse tumors at the time of diagnosis and poorer subsequent outcomes if not caught early.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Skin checks</strong></h2>



<p>That is why it is incredibly important to become familiar with your skin and conduct regular skin exams at home. When performing skin checks, you'll want to look out for:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>A new growth on the skin that might look like a mole, bump or scab.</li>



<li>A rough patch on the skin.</li>



<li>A sore on the skin that won’t heal.</li>



<li>Changes to a mole or freckle — getting bigger or changing color.</li>



<li>Itchy skin around a skin growth.</li>



<li>Pain around a skin growth.</li>
</ul>



<p>Regardless of your <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/melanoma-in-darker-skin-tones-race-and-sex-play-a-role-mayo-study-finds/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">skin color</a>, if you notice any of the above, then you should see a healthcare professional. A skin check by a dermatologist usually only takes a few minutes, but that short time spent in the doctor's office could add years to your life if skin cancer is detected early.</p>



<p>For higher risk individuals, including those with a personal or family history of melanoma, people over age 65, those with a suppressed immune system, people that burn easily, as well as those who have light-colored eyes and hair, a baseline evaluation with a dermatologist is critical and then continued at recommended intervals going forward, as determined by your healthcare team.</p>



<p>Most skin cancers can be prevented by taking a few simple precautions to protect yourself from the sun. It is recommended that you wear sunscreen year-round and reapply during peak sun conditions.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/who-should-be-screened-for-skin-cancer/">&nbsp;Who should be screened for skin cancer?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/07/a-Black-family-in-swimsuits-on-the-beach-laughing-and-having-fun-in-the-sun-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/07/a-Black-family-in-swimsuits-on-the-beach-laughing-and-having-fun-in-the-sun-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Michael Colgan]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Skin Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers develop first salivary gland regenerative biobank to combat chronic dry mouth</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-first-salivary-gland-regenerative-biobank-to-combat-chronic-dry-mouth/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Alison Satake]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 21 May 2025 14:00:58 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Discovery Science]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[chronic dry mouth]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jeffrey Janus]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Nagarajan Kannan]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=402912</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. —&nbsp;Millions of people are affected by chronic dry mouth, or xerostomia, an agonizing side effect of damaged salivary glands. While chemotherapy and radiation treatment for head and neck cancer are the most common causes of this, aging, certain medications and other factors, including diabetes, stroke,&nbsp;Alzheimer's disease&nbsp;and&nbsp;HIV/AIDS, can also cause chronic dry mouth. Currently, […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-first-salivary-gland-regenerative-biobank-to-combat-chronic-dry-mouth/">Mayo Clinic researchers develop first salivary gland regenerative biobank to combat chronic dry mouth</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/GettyImages-1470214826-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Photo of older man drinking water" class="wp-image-403038" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/GettyImages-1470214826-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/GettyImages-1470214826-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/GettyImages-1470214826-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/GettyImages-1470214826-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/GettyImages-1470214826-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Getty Images</figcaption>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. —&nbsp;Millions of people are affected by chronic dry mouth, or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/dry-mouth/symptoms-causes/syc-20356048" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">xerostomia</a>, an agonizing side effect of damaged salivary glands. While chemotherapy and radiation treatment for head and neck cancer are the most common causes of this, aging, certain medications and other factors, including <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/diabetes/symptoms-causes/syc-20371444" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">diabetes</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stroke/symptoms-causes/syc-20350113" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stroke</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/alzheimers-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350447" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alzheimer's disease</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hiv-aids/doctors-departments/ddc-20373532?_escaped_fragment_=&amp;lastinitial=P&amp;page=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">HIV/AIDS</a>, can also cause chronic dry mouth. Currently, there is no cure for it.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have established the world's first biobank of human salivary gland tissue-organoids that opens the door to research to find a cure.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="683" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/1716990_WF81191_0007-resized-683x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-403041" style="width:184px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/1716990_WF81191_0007-resized-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/1716990_WF81191_0007-resized-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/1716990_WF81191_0007-resized-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/1716990_WF81191_0007-resized.jpg 988w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 683px) 100vw, 683px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Nagarajan Kannan, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"This unique biobank resource overcomes a major barrier we've faced in the field, namely: limited access to standardized salivary specimens suited for salivary gland regeneration research. This collection provides a foundation for regenerative therapy development, especially for radiation-induced chronic dry mouth," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/kannan-nagarajan-ph-d-m-s/bio-20233074" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nagarajan Kannan, Ph.D.</a>, lead author of the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41536-025-00410-5" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> published in NPJ Regenerative Medicine. Dr. Kannan is also the director of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/stem-cell-and-cancer-biology/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Stem Cell and Cancer Biology Laboratory</a>.</p>



<p>Nearly 70% of patients with head and neck cancer who are undergoing radiation therapy experience permanent damage to their salivary glands. People with this condition experience diminished quality of life from a constant feeling like cotton is lining their mouths. Besides being uncomfortable, chronic dry mouth can lead to difficulties with chewing, tasting, speaking and swallowing. It also can cause tooth decay.</p>



<p>"Chronic dry mouth can extend long after radiation treatments are complete. It's among the top concerns I hear from patients with head and neck cancer. Unfortunately, there aren't many therapeutics available commercially for these patients," says&nbsp;co-author <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/janus-jeffrey-jeff-r-m-d/bio-20206511" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jeffrey Janus, M.D.</a>, an ear, nose and throat specialist at Mayo Clinic in Florida.</p>



<p>One promising avenue of research is the cultivation of rare regenerative cells to greater numbers that can help people someday heal and grow new, healthy salivary gland cells. The biobank consists of specimens collected from 208 donors. From this repository, researchers have already found biomarkers for mature, saliva-producing cells, and with the help of a high-resolution protein map, they have identified the potential tissue origin of rare, self-renewing salivary cells.</p>



<p>The research team also developed a radiation injury model, which paired with the biobank, provides an integrated platform to discover new, personalized regenerative biotherapeutics.</p>



<p>This is a collaboration between <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-medicine/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/laboratory-medicine-pathology/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathology</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/ent-head-neck-surgery/sections/overview/ovc-20424084" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Otolaryngology</a>.</p>



<p>Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41536-025-00410-5" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&nbsp;</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-first-salivary-gland-regenerative-biobank-to-combat-chronic-dry-mouth/">Mayo Clinic researchers develop first salivary gland regenerative biobank to combat chronic dry mouth</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/GettyImages-1470214826-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/GettyImages-1470214826-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[chronic dry mouth]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jeffrey Janus]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Nagarajan Kannan]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Research News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Prostate cancer: screening and treatment options</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/prostate-cancer-screening-and-treatment/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Deb Balzer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 19 May 2025 17:05:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Diversity]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Cycle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Video]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Carlos Vargas]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Prostate Specific Antigen]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Proton Beam]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Radiation Therapy]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[screening]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=348086</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Prostate cancer is one of the most common cancers in the world. While many prostate cancers grow slowly and remain localized, other types are aggressive and spread quickly. That's why Dr. Carlos Vargas, a Mayo Clinic radiation oncologist, encourages regular screening. He says the goal of screening is to detect prostate cancer early, when it's […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/prostate-cancer-screening-and-treatment/">Prostate cancer: screening and treatment options</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/middle-aged-black-man-gazing-out-windowGettyImages-1171712738_16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="middle-aged man gazing out window" class="wp-image-343228" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/middle-aged-black-man-gazing-out-windowGettyImages-1171712738_16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/middle-aged-black-man-gazing-out-windowGettyImages-1171712738_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/middle-aged-black-man-gazing-out-windowGettyImages-1171712738_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/middle-aged-black-man-gazing-out-windowGettyImages-1171712738_16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/middle-aged-black-man-gazing-out-windowGettyImages-1171712738_16x9.jpg 1688w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>


<p></p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prostate-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353087?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Prostate cancer</a> is one of the most common cancers in the world. While many prostate cancers grow slowly and remain localized, other types are aggressive and spread quickly. That's why <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/vargas-carlos-e-m-d/bio-20123913?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Carlos Vargas</a>, a Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/radiation-oncology/sections/overview/ovc-20188591" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">radiation oncologist</a>, encourages regular <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/psa-test/in-depth/prostate-cancer/art-20048087" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">screening</a>. He says the goal of screening is to detect prostate cancer early, when it's still confined to the prostate gland and has the best chance for successful treatment.</p>



<p>"It's important to get adequate screening, and screening for prostate cancer is relatively simple. You can have a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/psa-test/about/pac-20384731?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">prostate-specific antigen, or PSA, test</a> with your primary care doctor once a year, and with this, you can tailor adequate procedures based on your age and other risk factors," says Dr. Vargas.</p>



<p>The prostate-specific antigen test is a blood test used to measure the amount of prostate-specific antigen in your blood. High levels may indicate the presence of cancer, and other conditions may also increase this level. It's important to discuss with your healthcare professional if the prostate-specific antigen test is right for you based on your personal risk level and age.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/EJKL5mjYHaU" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Carlos Vargas discusses prostate cancer screening and treatment.</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeEJKL5mjYHaU" title="Dr. Carlos Vargas - Prostate cancer - Screening and treatment options" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EJKL5mjYHaU?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video is available in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy</strong>:<strong> Mayo Clinic News Network. Name super/CG: Carlos Vargas, M.D/Radiation Oncology/Mayo Clinic</strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Who is at risk?</strong></h2>



<p>Risk factors include age, family history and race. The most common age is around 50 or older.</p>



<p>If you have a blood relative who has or has had prostate cancer or a family history of genes that increase the risk of breast cancer — BRCA1 or BRCA2 — or a strong family history of breast cancer, your risk of prostate cancer may be higher. In the U.S., prostate cancer is deadlier for Black men than men of other races. They are more likely to get prostate cancer and more than twice as likely to die from prostate cancer than other men.</p>



<p>"Early detection is very important. If we can find prostate cancer early, it is treatable and curable, " says Dr. Vargas.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Active surveillance</strong></h2>



<p>Not all prostate cancers need to be treated, says Dr. Vargas. Some cancers can remain under <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/active-surveillance-for-prostate-cancer/about/pac-20384946?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">active surveillance</a>.</p>



<p>"When we find very early prostate cancer, we can watch it for many years. And in case prostate cancer becomes more aggressive, then we can treat it there. The problem is when you are not screened, and then you find a very aggressive prostate cancer that is still localized, or it has already metastasized, in which case, the chances of controlling the cancer, curing you and saving your life are much lower."</p>



<p>In active surveillance, regular follow-up tests may be performed to monitor the progression of your cancer.</p>



<p>"That's why screening is very important and why we encourage screening for prostate cancer. It doesn't mean that you must be treated. If prostate cancer is found, we can then determine what is the most appropriate course of action for your prostate cancer based on your age and your risk group."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="611" height="344" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/04/Prostate-cancer-16-x-9.png" alt="Medical illustration of normal prostate and cancerous prostate" class="wp-image-119143" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/04/Prostate-cancer-16-x-9.png 611w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/04/Prostate-cancer-16-x-9-300x169.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 611px) 100vw, 611px"></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Treatment options</h2>



<p>Along with active surveillance, a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prostate-cancer/care-at-mayo-clinic/mac-20353097?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">full range</a> of treatments for prostate cancer is available, including radiation therapy; hormone therapy; cryosurgery; chemotherapy; and surgery, including robotic prostatectomy.</p>



<p><strong>"</strong>One of the things that has really changed over the last few years is the management of radiation with patients with metastatic prostate cancer," says Dr. Vargas. "We have found that many patients with metastatic prostate cancer still benefit from radiation to the prostate."</p>



<p>"And we have also found that many patients who have just a few sites of metastatic disease, meaning that the cancer is not widely spread, can also benefit from aggressive treatment where we do a combination of radiation therapy and systematic therapy to put you back in remission where disease cannot be found, and extend your life," he says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="700" height="394" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/Mayo-Clinic-Proton-Beam-treatment-room-16x9-1.jpg" alt="Mayo Clinic Proton Beam treatment room" class="wp-image-315559" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/Mayo-Clinic-Proton-Beam-treatment-room-16x9-1.jpg 700w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/Mayo-Clinic-Proton-Beam-treatment-room-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 700px) 100vw, 700px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><sub>A Mayo Clinic proton beam treatment room</sub></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Another radiation technique includes intensity-modulated <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/home/orc-20185488">proton b</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/home/orc-20185488?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">e</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/home/orc-20185488" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">am therapy</a> with pencil beam scanning. Dr. Vargas says proton therapy is effectively used to treat patients with prostate cancer.</p>



<p>"It's a very localized treatment that allows us to treat the prostate, localizing the treatment to the prostate, hoping to minimize significant adverse events that may happen from the treatment," says Dr. Vargas.</p>



<p>Talk with your healthcare professional to learn more about prostate cancer screening and if it's right for you.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Related posts:</strong></h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-importance-of-exercise-for-men-with-prostate-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Importance of exercise for men with prostate cancer</a>."</li>



<li>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-new-prostate-biopsy-technique-reduces-infection-risk/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Prostate biopsy technique reduces infection risk</a>."</li>



<li>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-podcast-living-as-a-prostate-cancer-survivor/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A podcast: Living as a prostate cancer survivor</a>."</li>
</ul>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity">



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/prostate-cancer-screening-and-treatment/">Prostate cancer: screening and treatment options</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/PensiveMan1x1.jpeg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/PensiveMan16x9.jpeg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Carlos Vargas]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Prostate Specific Antigen]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Proton Beam]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Radiation Therapy]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[screening]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Farmer inspires new potential bladder cancer treatment</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/farmer-inspires-new-potential-bladder-cancer-treatment/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Alison Satake]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 19 May 2025 12:30:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Clinical Trials]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Elisabeth Heath]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jacob Orme]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Paras Shah]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Stephen Boorjian]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=402792</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Minnesota farmer Craig Smith's bladder cancer treatment has inspired a clinical trial. Learn more at Mayo Clinic. <p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/farmer-inspires-new-potential-bladder-cancer-treatment/">Farmer inspires new potential bladder cancer treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-center-align-caption"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/CraigSmith-tractor16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Farmer and Mayo patient Craig Smith and red tractor" class="wp-image-402794" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/CraigSmith-tractor16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/CraigSmith-tractor16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/CraigSmith-tractor16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/CraigSmith-tractor16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/CraigSmith-tractor16x9.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mayo Clinic patient, farmer Craig Smith</figcaption>



<p>September marks the start of soybean harvest in Mankato, Minnesota, a busy time of year when farmers can't afford to be away from their fields for long. So, when Craig Smith, 66, began experiencing a burning sensation while urinating, he went to his family physician right away.</p>



<p>He was prescribed antibiotics, but his symptoms worsened. When Smith began to pass blood, his wife insisted that they drive straight to Mayo Clinic in Rochester — about an hour and a half away. There, Mayo Clinic physicians diagnosed him with metastatic urothelial cancer, or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/bladder-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20356104" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bladder cancer</a>, which had spread to his spine.</p>



<p>Smith recalls receiving a phone call late that night from his Mayo Clinic doctor, who asked him if he wanted to just maintain his health for a few years or cure his cancer.</p>



<p>"I said, 'I'd like you to cure it,'" says Smith.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Seeking a bladder cancer cure</strong></h2>



<p>Smith's father had been a farmer, which was his dream too. But his father suggested he gain additional skills to supplement his farming income. Following his father's advice and encouragement from his high school welding teacher, Smith pursued his teaching certificate in welding. What he initially thought would be five or six years of teaching turned into a 45-year career developing welding programs at several local schools while also raising cattle and growing soybeans and corn on his 2,000-acre farm. Through his welding programs, he has trained several welders now employed by local manufacturing companies.</p>



<p>After his diagnosis in 2023, Smith took a hiatus from teaching and farming to focus on his cancer treatments at <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/mankato" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System in Mankato</a>, which included chemotherapy, radiation and immunotherapy.</p>



<p>Metastatic urothelial cancer that has spread beyond the bladder usually is considered incurable and inoperable. However, Smith responded well to chemotherapy and radiation to his spine, which made his oncologist, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/orme-jacob-j-m-d-ph-d/bio-20545524" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jacob Orme, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, and urologist, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/shah-paras-h-m-d/bio-20571894" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Paras Shah, M.D.</a>, consider Smith for a new, surgical approach to treatment.</p>



<p>Smith proceeded with the proposed surgery and had his bladder, prostate and 36 lymph nodes removed.</p>



<p>"In Mr. Smith's bladder, we found viable cancer cells that would have led to a relapse. Now, however, he is nearly two years from diagnosis and remains disease-free," says Dr. Shah.</p>



<p>Smith's positive response to treatment and surgery has spurred a clinical trial testing this aggressive approach in other bladder cancer patients. Currently, 17 participants are enrolled, and the results so far have been promising.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote has-medium-font-size" style="padding-top:var(--wp--preset--spacing--30);padding-bottom:var(--wp--preset--spacing--30)"><blockquote><p>"It takes brave patients like Mr. Smith and these other patients that we've seen who are excited for the possibility of a cure but also are excited about the possibility of helping other people with cancers like them in the future."</p><cite>Jacob orme, M.D., Ph.D.</cite></blockquote></figure>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="480" height="640" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/CSMith-JOrme.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-402796" style="width:261px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/CSMith-JOrme.jpg 480w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/CSMith-JOrme-225x300.jpg 225w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 480px) 100vw, 480px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Craig Smith and Jacob Orme, M.D., Ph.D., at Mayo Clinic in Rochester</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Advances in cancer treatment, such as immunotherapy that harnesses the body's immune system to fight cancer and the identification of biomarkers in the blood or urine that show how well a patient is responding to treatment, are helping the physicians select who will benefit most from surgery.</p>



<p>"The impetus for this study is to attack the cancer from multiple approaches, including treatments that cover head-to-toe and treatments that are directed right at the source tumor," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/boorjian-stephen-a-m-d/bio-00092877" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stephen A. Boorjian, M.D.</a>, who is the David and Anne Luther Chair of Urology at Mayo Clinic and a lead proponent of the study.</p>



<p>"We want to remove the root of the cancer after we've burned off the leaves," adds Dr. Orme.</p>



<p>A team of researchers, physicians and clinical trials staff expedited the clinical trial through an accelerated pathway called a Rapid Activation Trial. It's part of a larger effort at Mayo Clinic to launch new clinical trials swiftly and effectively.</p>



<p>"Shortening activation timelines allows us to make a difference to more patients and their families," says Michelle Monosmith, Mayo Clinic Office of Clinical Trials operations administrator.</p>



<p>The study is supported by a generous donation by Ronald J. and Carol T. Beerman to Mayo Clinic and has been prioritized by Dr. Boorjian and Chair of Oncology <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/heath-elisabeth-i-m-d/bio-20576547" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Elisabeth Heath, M.D.</a>, to achieve more cures for men and women with bladder cancer.</p>



<p>"Our only goal is to help our patients live better and longer," says Dr. Orme.</p>



<p>That's what Smith plans to do as he continues to farm, teach and spend time with his family.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/farmer-inspires-new-potential-bladder-cancer-treatment/">Farmer inspires new potential bladder cancer treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/CraigSmith-tractor1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/05/CraigSmith-tractor16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Elisabeth Heath]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jacob Orme]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Paras Shah]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Stephen Boorjian]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Beyond tired with cancer-related fatigue</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-beyond-tired-with-cancer-related-fatigue/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Tue, 13 May 2025 14:30:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Toure Barksdale]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=399896</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;I am thrilled to say I am a breast cancer survivor. It has been almost six months since I finished treatment. But I can't shake the fatigue. I was never a napper, but I find myself feeling desperate to close my eyes in the middle of the workday. I don't feel sharp in […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-beyond-tired-with-cancer-related-fatigue/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Beyond tired with cancer-related fatigue</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1000" height="563" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/Young-adult-female-cancer-patient-wearing-headscarf-and-bathrobe-sitting-in-the-kitchen-looking-out-window_shutterstock_1074889493_16x9.jpg" alt="Young adult female cancer patient wearing headscarf and bathrobe, sitting in the kitchen looking out window, fatigue," class="wp-image-217503" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/Young-adult-female-cancer-patient-wearing-headscarf-and-bathrobe-sitting-in-the-kitchen-looking-out-window_shutterstock_1074889493_16x9.jpg 1000w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/Young-adult-female-cancer-patient-wearing-headscarf-and-bathrobe-sitting-in-the-kitchen-looking-out-window_shutterstock_1074889493_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/Young-adult-female-cancer-patient-wearing-headscarf-and-bathrobe-sitting-in-the-kitchen-looking-out-window_shutterstock_1074889493_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px">



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;</strong>I am thrilled to say I am a breast cancer survivor. It has been almost six months since I finished treatment. But I can't shake the fatigue. I was never a napper, but I find myself feeling desperate to close my eyes in the middle of the workday. I don't feel sharp in my thinking, and I fall asleep in front of the TV at night. I'm worried. How can I get past this stage? I want my life back.<strong></strong></p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:&nbsp;</strong><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-coping-with-cancer-related-fatigue/">Cancer-related fatigue</a>&nbsp;can be distressing. It is a persistent, subjective sense of physical, emotional and cognitive tiredness and/or exhaustion related to cancer or cancer treatment that is not proportional to recent activity. It interferes with daily function and quality of life. Cancer-related fatigue is different from the usual tiredness we all experience. It's more intense, it's not temporary and it's not relieved by rest alone.</p>



<p>Several factors can contribute to cancer-related fatigue. The cancer itself can lead to fatigue.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Some cancers weaken muscles, damage organs or alter hormones, which can cause fatigue.</p>



<p>Sometimes treatment damages healthy cells in addition to cancer cells. Treatments such as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/chemotherapy/about/pac-20385033">chemotherapy</a>, molecular targeted therapy,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/hormone-therapy-for-breast-cancer/about/pac-20384943">hormonal therapies</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/radiation-therapy/about/pac-20385162">radiation</a>&nbsp;all may cause fatigue.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Side effects of treatment may result in a blood problem called&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/anemia/symptoms-causes/syc-20351360">anemia</a>, pain or stress, all of which can add to your fatigue.&nbsp;</p>



<p>If you're not feeling well, your activity level may lower, which causes the body to decondition, causing fatigue. Preexisting conditions, such as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/anxiety/symptoms-causes/syc-20350961">anxiety</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/depression/symptoms-causes/syc-20356007">depression</a>,&nbsp;also may worsen with cancer and play a role in fatigue.</p>



<p>Cancer-related fatigue can happen at any stage. It might start before treatment, become more pronounced during treatment, and sometimes linger even after treatment has ended. Everyone experiences this differently.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The duration of cancer-related fatigue can be variable. For some people, it might improve a few weeks after finishing treatment. For others, it can last for months or even longer. It affects a lot of cancer patients but doesn't always get proper attention from healthcare professionals. It's important to communicate with your healthcare team about any ongoing fatigue.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Treatments can include physical therapy and exercise guidance to help increase activity levels, medications, complementary and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/complementary-alternative-medicine/about/pac-20393581">integrative medicine</a>&nbsp;approaches such as yoga and tai chi, and psychological and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/consumer-health/in-depth/mindfulness-exercises/art-20046356">mindfulness-based strategies</a>&nbsp;to manage emotional stress and monitor fatigue levels. As every patient is different, a combination of these approaches typically works best.</p>



<p>While there's no way to prevent cancer-related fatigue, several self-care strategies can help boost energy levels, including:&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Staying as active as possible, even if it's just light exercise. Start slow and find a routine.</li>



<li>Eating a balanced diet and staying hydrated. When you have cancer, you may need more protein and nutrients than ever. Drink plenty of fluids, and limit caffeine.</li>



<li>Setting a regular sleep schedule, taking short naps if needed, and finding time to relax and reduce stress.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>If you need guidance or you are experiencing fatigue that is not responding to these modalities, ask your primary care team for help. You may need help from family and friends to help with household tasks too. —&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/barksdale-toure-m-d/bio-20517681"><strong><em>Touré Barksdale, M.D.</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Physical Medicine &amp; Rehabilitation, Rochester, Minnesota</em></strong><em></em></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-beyond-tired-with-cancer-related-fatigue/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Beyond tired with cancer-related fatigue</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/03/woman-tired-sad-cancer-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/03/woman-tired-sad-cancer-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Toure Barksdale]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</atom:link></channel>
</rss> 