<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org">

<channel>
	<title>Cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml">
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastbuilddate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 14:08:34 +0000</lastbuilddate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updateperiod>
	hourly	</sy:updateperiod>
	<sy:updatefrequency>
	1	</sy:updatefrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.9.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic study finds chemotherapy before surgery improves survival in early-stage pancreatic cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-finds-chemotherapy-before-surgery-improves-survival-in-early-stage-pancreatic-cancer/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Chloe Corey]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 14:08:32 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Surgery]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Chemotherapy]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Mark Truty]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Zhi Ven Fong]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Pancreatic Cancer]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=409432</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — A Mayo Clinic study is providing new insights into how treatment sequence can affect survival in patients with early-stage&nbsp;pancreatic cancer, suggesting that many patients may benefit from receiving chemotherapy before surgery.&nbsp; The findings, published in the JNCCN—Journal of the National Comprehensive Cancer Network, were based on more than 1,400 patients treated across […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-finds-chemotherapy-before-surgery-improves-survival-in-early-stage-pancreatic-cancer/">Mayo Clinic study finds chemotherapy before surgery improves survival in early-stage pancreatic cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="574" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/chemotherapy-drug-being-administered-intravenously-by-a-nurse_1552844_3779313_0064_16x9-1024x574.jpg" alt="chemotherapy drug being administered intravenously by a nurse" class="wp-image-405972" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/chemotherapy-drug-being-administered-intravenously-by-a-nurse_1552844_3779313_0064_16x9-1024x574.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/chemotherapy-drug-being-administered-intravenously-by-a-nurse_1552844_3779313_0064_16x9-300x168.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/chemotherapy-drug-being-administered-intravenously-by-a-nurse_1552844_3779313_0064_16x9-768x431.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/chemotherapy-drug-being-administered-intravenously-by-a-nurse_1552844_3779313_0064_16x9-1536x862.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/chemotherapy-drug-being-administered-intravenously-by-a-nurse_1552844_3779313_0064_16x9.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A Mayo Clinic study is providing new insights into how treatment sequence can affect survival in patients with early-stage&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pancreatic-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20355421" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pancreatic cancer</a>, suggesting that many patients may benefit from receiving <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/chemotherapy/about/pac-20385033" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chemotherapy</a> before surgery.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The findings, published in the <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fjnccn.org%2Fview%2Fjournals%2Fjnccn%2F24%2F2%2Farticle-p27.xml&amp;data=05%7C02%7CDeboom.Emily%40mayo.edu%7Cdae0a8e36f874fed8dfe08de65c3612b%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C639060086987855425%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=1X5dHNT9bLW58K54krBrpu%2BWUZQn3PNMQ1ZnTalwdqo%3D&amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">JNCCN<em>—</em>Journal of the National Comprehensive Cancer Network</a>, were based on more than 1,400 patients treated across <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/locations" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic's campuses</a> in Minnesota, Arizona and Florida. Researchers found that when pancreatic tumors were in contact with the superior mesenteric vein — a major blood vessel by the pancreas — patients who underwent surgery first experienced reduced survival rates. In contrast, patients who received chemotherapy before surgery had similar survival outcomes to those whose tumors were not touching the vein.</p>



<p>"Many patients with early-stage pancreatic cancer undergo surgery first because it is historically believed to be the best chance for cure," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/fong-zhi-ven-m-d-dr-ph/bio-20555871" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Zhi Ven Fong, M.D., Dr.PH.</a>, surgical oncologist at Mayo Clinic in Arizona and co-senior author of the study. "Our findings suggest that chemotherapy first, even in cases thought to be more straightforward, provides patients with the best opportunity for long-term survival."</p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/detecting-pancreatic-cancer-through-changes-in-body-composition-and-metabolism/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pancreatic cancer</a> is notoriously aggressive, and progress over the past decade to increase patient survival has been limited. Chemotherapy before surgery, called neoadjuvant chemotherapy, aims to shrink the tumor and target cancer cells that may have spread. This approach increases the chance of complete tumor removal during an operation and improves survival outcomes.</p>



<p>"Our data confirms what we've seen in practice at Mayo Clinic for years," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/truty-mark-j-m-d-m-s/bio-20055639" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mark Truty, M.D.</a>, surgical oncologist at Mayo Clinic in Minnesota and co-senior author. "The timing of surgery relative to chemotherapy is critically important for patient outcomes."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Rethinking pancreatic tumor classification</strong></h2>



<p>The study also highlights opportunities to refine how pancreatic cancer is classified. Current guidelines from the National Comprehensive Cancer Network categorize tumors by how much they touch certain critical blood vessels. Those with less than 180 degrees on the vein are considered upfront resectable, meaning surgery should be performed right away without chemotherapy first. Mayo Clinic's data suggest that these patients may do better if chemotherapy is considered before surgery.</p>



<p>"Our findings suggest that guidelines could be updated to reclassify tumors with any vein involvement as borderline resectable and to only include cancers with no vein involvement as upfront resectable," says Dr. Fong.</p>



<p>The findings reinforce Mayo Clinic's approach, which already prioritizes chemotherapy before surgery for all pancreatic cancer patients, regardless of stage. Researchers believe this evidence will encourage continued discussion within the oncology community and support thoughtful refinements to national treatment recommendations.</p>



<p>"Our hope is that this study empowers both patients and clinicians to think carefully about treatment sequencing," says Dr. Truty. "We want people to know they have options, and that starting with chemotherapy may be the best path forward."</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Chloe Corey, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-finds-chemotherapy-before-surgery-improves-survival-in-early-stage-pancreatic-cancer/">Mayo Clinic study finds chemotherapy before surgery improves survival in early-stage pancreatic cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/chemotherapy-drug-being-administered-intravenously-by-a-nurse_1552844_3779313_0064_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/chemotherapy-drug-being-administered-intravenously-by-a-nurse_1552844_3779313_0064_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Chemotherapy]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Mark Truty]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Zhi Ven Fong]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Pancreatic Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Diet tips during cancer treatment</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-diet-tips-during-cancer-treatment/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[pattymiller]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 13:47:42 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Diet]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=409960</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;My husband has been diagnosed with cancer. I know his treatment will be hard on him, and I want to help in any way with his diet. What do you recommend for us? ANSWER:&nbsp;Cancer treatments can take a toll on a person's body. Your husband's treatment may cause nausea, changes in appetite, taste […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-diet-tips-during-cancer-treatment/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Diet tips during cancer treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-man-in-the-kitchen-reading-a-recipe-and-preparing-food-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a man in the kitchen, reading a recipe and preparing food, diet, nutrition" class="wp-image-100756" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-man-in-the-kitchen-reading-a-recipe-and-preparing-food-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-man-in-the-kitchen-reading-a-recipe-and-preparing-food-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-man-in-the-kitchen-reading-a-recipe-and-preparing-food-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p></p>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;</strong>My husband has been diagnosed with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20370594" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer</a>. I know his treatment will be hard on him, and I want to help in any way with his diet. What do you recommend for us?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong>&nbsp;Cancer treatments can take a toll on a person's body. Your husband's treatment may cause nausea, changes in appetite, taste and smell, diarrhea, or constipation, making it harder to meet his nutritional needs. Fortunately, there are <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/in-depth/cancer/art-20045046" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">strategies</a> you can use to cope with these side effects.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Supporting nutrition during cancer treatment</h2>



<p><strong>Weight changes.&nbsp;</strong>Weight changes are common. Weight loss without trying can reduce muscle mass, stamina and quality of life. Weight gain can lead to the development of other diseases, like diabetes or heart disease. Try to maintain your weight during treatment, even if it's outside a normal range.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Appetite changes.&nbsp;</strong>Cancer and cancer treatment may make you lose your appetite or eat more than usual.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>If you lose your appetite:&nbsp;<ul><li>Eat smaller snacks that are high in calories, including yogurt, nuts, peanut butter and avocado.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li></ul><ul><li>Eat more when your appetite is better.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li></ul><ul><li>Food may sound unappealing even when you're hungry, making it difficult to eat. Try to find something that's appetizing.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li></ul>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Keep snacks on hand.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li>If you eat more when stressed:<ul><li>Choose snacks such as fruits, vegetables and popcorn.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</li></ul>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Find ways to manage stress without food, such as going for a walk or calling a friend.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Nausea.&nbsp;</strong>Feeling sick or throwing up due to your treatments makes it hard to eat. Small changes to what and how you eat may help you feel better.&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Eat foods that are easy on your stomach, such as crackers, toast, broth or broth-based soups, ice pops, hard candies, plain pasta and rice.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Eat five or six small meals a day. Smaller meals are often easier to keep down.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Don't skip meals or snacks. Even when you're not hungry, try to eat; an empty stomach can make nausea worse.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>



<li>Sip small amounts of fluid during meals and throughout the day.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>



<li>Try pretzels or crackers with your medicines if your care team says it's OK.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Taste and smell changes.&nbsp;</strong>Cancer treatment can alter the taste or smell of food. Some people say food tastes bland. Others say it tastes metallic or too sweet or salty. You may need to try different foods to find what works for you.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>To help with taste changes:&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Brighten the flavor. Add a little lemon, lime or vinegar unless your mouth is sore.</li>



<li>Try strong flavors. Use spices such as cinnamon, ginger, basil or rosemary.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>



<li>Make foods sweeter. Add sugar or another sweetener if food tastes bitter or sour.</li>



<li>Use marinades before cooking.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>



<li>Choose other proteins. If meat doesn't taste good, try beans, nuts or fish.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Use plastic or bamboo utensils. These may help if food tastes metallic.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Try new foods. You won't have expectations about the taste.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>To help with strong smells:&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Cook food in the microwave or use a crockpot or instant cooker in the garage.</li>



<li>Eat foods cold or at room temperature.</li>



<li>Cover food while it cooks.</li>



<li>Use a window or fan to help remove unpleasant odors.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>



<li>Drink from a covered cup.</li>



<li>Ask a friend to cook for you.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Sore throat, mouth or trouble swallowing.&nbsp;</strong>When your throat is sore or it's hard to swallow, eating may be painful or tiring. These tips can help:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Soften the texture. Opt for smooth foods, such as cooked cereal, mashed potatoes or scrambled eggs.</li>



<li>Cool things down. Choose smoothies, ice pops or a bowl of ice cream.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Take smaller bites and cut food into tiny pieces.</li>



<li>Avoid what bothers you. Spicy, sour, crunchy or vinegar-based foods, citrus fruits, tomato sauce or carbonated beverages can cause discomfort.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Suck on ice chips or ice pops.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Diarrhea and constipation.&nbsp;</strong>Bowel changes are unpleasant but common side effects of cancer treatment.&nbsp;</p>



<p>To help with diarrhea:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Eat small, frequent meals and snacks.</li>



<li>Choose soft, low-fiber foods.</li>



<li>Avoid caffeine and alcohol.</li>



<li>Limit lactose found in milk and yogurt.</li>



<li>Avoid sugar substitutes such as sorbitol, xylitol or mannitol, which are often found in sugar-free candy or gum.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Drink plenty of fluids, including electrolyte-containing fluids, to stay hydrated.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>For constipation, aim to:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Drink enough fluid to stay hydrated and keep stools soft. Try to drink eight to 10 cups of water each day. Warm coffee, tea or broth-based soup in the morning can help your bowels move. Use the bathroom when you feel the urge.</li>



<li>Move your body. Even short walks help your digestive system work better.</li>



<li>Keep regular mealtimes.</li>



<li>Eat a high-fiber diet.<br><br></li>
</ul>



<p>Your husband's care team is an excellent resource for what you can expect during treatment and for the symptoms that may affect his diet and weight.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/grace-fjeldberg-rd" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Grace Fjeldberg</em></a><em>, Registered Dietitian Nutritionist, Nutrition/Oncology, Mayo Clinic Health System, Mankato, Minnesota</em></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-diet-tips-during-cancer-treatment/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Diet tips during cancer treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-man-in-the-kitchen-reading-a-recipe-and-preparing-food-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-man-in-the-kitchen-reading-a-recipe-and-preparing-food-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Diet]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic offers newly FDA-approved robotic nipple-sparing mastectomy surgery</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-offers-newly-fda-approved-robotic-nipple-sparing-mastectomy-surgery/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[jftmayo]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 16:37:32 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Florida]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Surgery]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jeffrey Johnson]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Mara Piltin]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=410010</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center is expanding surgical options for patients undergoing treatment or risk reducing procedures for breast cancer through the adoption of robotic nipple-sparing mastectomy at its Minnesota and Florida campuses. Following recent Food and Drug Administration approval of the use of this platform and device for these procedures, Mayo […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-offers-newly-fda-approved-robotic-nipple-sparing-mastectomy-surgery/">Mayo Clinic offers newly FDA-approved robotic nipple-sparing mastectomy surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Surgical-assistant-during-robotic-surgery_WF6912002_0030-1024x683.jpg" alt="Surgical assistant during robotic surgery" class="wp-image-410006" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Surgical-assistant-during-robotic-surgery_WF6912002_0030-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Surgical-assistant-during-robotic-surgery_WF6912002_0030-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Surgical-assistant-during-robotic-surgery_WF6912002_0030-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Surgical-assistant-during-robotic-surgery_WF6912002_0030-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Surgical-assistant-during-robotic-surgery_WF6912002_0030.jpg 1687w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is expanding surgical options for patients undergoing treatment or risk reducing procedures for breast cancer through the adoption of robotic nipple-sparing mastectomy at its Minnesota and Florida campuses. Following recent Food and Drug Administration approval of the use of this platform and device for these procedures, Mayo Clinic surgeons are now offering a minimally invasive approach designed to improve cosmetic outcomes, preserve skin and nipple viability, and broaden opportunities for potential sensory restoration.</p>



<p>Nipple-sparing mastectomy preserves the nipple–areolar complex and healthy breast skin, creating a more natural appearing reconstructed breast after reconstruction. The improved cosmetic result can offer meaningful psychological benefits for patients compared with traditional mastectomy. Many patients, however, continue to experience visible scarring, diminished or absent sensation in the breast and nipple, and risk of loss of nipple or skin due to low blood flow.</p>



<p>The robotic approach provides a way to address some of these challenges by enabling a small, lateral incision, gentle tissue retraction with gas insufflation, and enhanced visualization of the surgical field. Mayo Clinic surgeons also are integrating sensory restoring procedures in some cases, including neurotization (reinnervation) of the nipple–areolar complex, to help patients regain protective sensation of their reconstructed breasts.</p>



<p>"When we remove the breast tissue and keep the envelope of the breast skin and nipple, it provides the most natural-appearing breast from a cosmetic standpoint," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/piltin-mara-a-d-o/bio-20487425" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mara Piltin, D.O.</a>, a surgical oncologist at Mayo Clinic in Jacksonville, Florida. "The next step is to improve the process so that patients regain feeling in their breasts and are not constantly seeing scars that remind them of their cancer journey. It will positively impact their sexual health, self-image and recovery."</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic continues to lead in NSM innovation, consistently refining surgical techniques and expanding clinical trials to enhance patient outcomes. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/johnson-jeffrey-e-m-d/bio-20519730" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jeffrey E. Johnson, M.D.</a>, a surgical oncologist at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, explains, "At Mayo Clinic, our goal is to ensure that more patients can benefit from innovations that support not only their physical recovery but also their emotional well-being so every patient can move forward with confidence and hope."</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> <br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center&nbsp;</strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs&nbsp;in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-offers-newly-fda-approved-robotic-nipple-sparing-mastectomy-surgery/">Mayo Clinic offers newly FDA-approved robotic nipple-sparing mastectomy surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Surgical-assistant-during-robotic-surgery_WF6912002_0030_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Surgical-assistant-during-robotic-surgery_WF6912002_0030_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jeffrey Johnson]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Mara Piltin]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Why should I be concerned about radon?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-why-should-i-be-concerned-about-radon/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[pattymiller]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 16:24:13 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Lung Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[radon]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=409713</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;Our neighbors were selling their home and had it tested for radon. The test was positive. Why should we be concerned about radon, and should we have our home tested too? ANSWER:&nbsp;The positive test for radon in your neighbors' home has given you a heads-up that your home should be tested as well. […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-why-should-i-be-concerned-about-radon/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Why should I be concerned about radon?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Radon-graphic-WF-1369388086-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-409730" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Radon-graphic-WF-1369388086-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Radon-graphic-WF-1369388086-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Radon-graphic-WF-1369388086-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Radon-graphic-WF-1369388086-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Radon-graphic-WF-1369388086-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p></p>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;</strong>Our neighbors were selling their home and had it tested for <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/radon-the-odorless-invisible-threat/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">radon</a>. The test was positive. Why should we be concerned about radon, and should we have our home tested too?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:&nbsp;</strong>The positive test for radon in your neighbors' home has given you a heads-up that your home should be tested as well.</p>



<p>Radon is an odorless, invisible radioactive gas. It's naturally released from rocks, soil and water — and it can get trapped inside your home, office or school. There's no known safe level of radon. Unfortunately, there are no symptoms associated with radon exposure, unlike with carbon monoxide poisoning.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Why radon is so dangerous</strong></h2>



<p>Breathing high levels of radon over time can lead to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lung-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20374620" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lung cancer</a>&nbsp;since this gas is a Class A carcinogen. It's the No. 1 cause of lung cancer in <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/connected-care/can-you-get-lung-cancer-if-youve-never-smoked/cpt-20413370" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">nonsmokers</a> and the second-leading cause of lung&nbsp;cancer overall. Nationwide, 21,000 people die from radon-caused lung cancer each year.</p>



<p>Smoking and secondhand smoke, combined with exposure to high radon levels, increase your risk of lung cancer. If you or your family are experiencing breathing issues, consult with a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/lung-cancer-screening/about/pac-20385024" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pulmonologist</a>.</p>



<p>Radon can be found in any home — old or new — and typically enters through cracks in the foundation caused by natural settling and windows. Radon levels often are higher in lower levels and basements. Across the U.S., 1 in 15 homes have elevated radon levels, and levels are higher in the Midwest. For example, radon levels range from 4.7 picocuries per liter of air (pCi/L) in Indiana to 9.6 pCi/L in North Dakota. The nationwide average is 1.3 pCi/L.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Testing for radon</strong></h2>



<p>There's a simple solution to this close-to-home health hazard: testing. That's what the Environmental Protection Agency urges all homeowners to do, especially those in high-radon areas. Testing is the only way to determine the radon level in your home.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Radon-test-GettyImages-2063907346-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Home inspector doing a radon test setup in the lowest bedroom of a home." class="wp-image-409733" style="width:728px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Radon-test-GettyImages-2063907346-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Radon-test-GettyImages-2063907346-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Radon-test-GettyImages-2063907346-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Radon-test-GettyImages-2063907346-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Radon-test-GettyImages-2063907346-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Home inspector doing a radon test setup in the lowest bedroom of a home.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>You can find radon testing kits at hardware or other home maintenance stores and online. They cost around $20 or less and are easy to use. It typically takes two to seven days for results. Although there's no safe level of radon, look for test results of 4.0 pCi/L or less.&nbsp;</p>



<p>If your home tests higher than 4.0 pCi/L, then you'll need to have a professional&nbsp;fix the radon issue, which includes installing venting equipment. The equipment looks like a big tube that reaches below the foundation&nbsp;of your home and vents radon up and out of the house.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The cost of a radon mitigation system varies according to the size and design of your home, as well as the system being installed. Costs average $1,000-$2,000. Check with your local city and county housing agencies to see if they have funds available for low-interest loans or grants for radon mitigation, and learn if you're eligible for these funds.</p>



<p>Once the mitigation system has been installed, your home should be tested again to make sure the fix is effective. Even if your home passes the first test, you should retest every two years.</p>



<p>Also, radon testing isn't required when selling a home. However, if you're a buyer, you should insist on it. If levels are high, you may be able to negotiate the costs of the mitigation with the seller.</p>



<p>Radon testing and mitigation are investments in your home — and in your health.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/elizabeth-morton-pac"><em>Elizabeth Morton</em></a>,&nbsp;<em>Physician Assistant, Pulmonology, Mayo Clinic Health System, Mankato, Minnesota</em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-why-should-i-be-concerned-about-radon/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Why should I be concerned about radon?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Radon-test-GettyImages-2063907346-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Radon-graphic-WF-1369388086-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Lung Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[radon]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What&nbsp;cancer&nbsp;screenings&nbsp;should I&nbsp;prioritize&nbsp;this&nbsp;year?&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-cancer-screenings-should-i-prioritize-this-year/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[justingottlieb]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:26:24 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jamie Bakkum-Gamez]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=409479</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;A close friend of mine recently had an abnormal result on a routine&nbsp;Pap test&nbsp;that led to a cancer diagnosis.&nbsp;I know cancer screenings are important, but&nbsp;it's&nbsp;hard to keep track of which ones I should prioritize.&nbsp;Could you help me&nbsp;better understand cervical cancer screening and&nbsp;other screenings I should&nbsp;consider&nbsp;now?&nbsp; ANSWER:&nbsp;Cancer screenings play a critical role in protecting […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-cancer-screenings-should-i-prioritize-this-year/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What&nbsp;cancer&nbsp;screenings&nbsp;should I&nbsp;prioritize&nbsp;this&nbsp;year?&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Women-doctor-consult-WF7543353_0004-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-409630" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Women-doctor-consult-WF7543353_0004-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Women-doctor-consult-WF7543353_0004-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Women-doctor-consult-WF7543353_0004-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Women-doctor-consult-WF7543353_0004-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Women-doctor-consult-WF7543353_0004-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong>&nbsp;<br>A close friend of mine recently had an abnormal result on a routine&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/pap-smear/about/pac-20394841" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pap test</a>&nbsp;that led to a cancer diagnosis.&nbsp;I know cancer screenings are important, but&nbsp;it's&nbsp;hard to keep track of which ones I should prioritize.&nbsp;Could you help me&nbsp;better understand <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cervical-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352506" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cervical cancer screening</a> and&nbsp;other screenings I should&nbsp;consider&nbsp;now?&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong>&nbsp;<br>Cancer screenings play a critical role in protecting long-term health. They can detect cancer early, when treatment is most effective, and in some cases help prevent cancer before it develops. While screening recommendations&nbsp;vary based&nbsp;on age, sex, family history and personal risk&nbsp;factors, several key&nbsp;cancer&nbsp;screening&nbsp;tests should be reviewed regularly.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Cervical cancer screening is an important part of preventive care and has helped significantly reduce deaths from this disease. Understanding how screening works can help people stay up to date.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Cervical cancer:&nbsp;Why screening is essential</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cervical-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352506" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cervical cancer</a>&nbsp;is&nbsp;most often caused by long-term infection with certain high-risk types of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hpv-infection/symptoms-causes/syc-20351596" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">human papillomavirus (HPV)</a>.&nbsp;HPV is common, and&nbsp;while most&nbsp;of these&nbsp;infections are cleared by a person's immune system,&nbsp;other&nbsp;HPV&nbsp;infections&nbsp;can persist for years without causing symptoms.&nbsp;People&nbsp;also&nbsp;can become&nbsp;infected with HPV more than once in their lifetime.&nbsp;That's&nbsp;why routine screening is the best way to detect abnormal changes early.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The Pap test&nbsp;and HPV&nbsp;test</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p>During a Pap test, a healthcare professional gently collects cells from the cervix, which is the lower part of the uterus that opens into the vagina. These cells are examined for abnormal changes that could develop into cancer if left untreated. The test is usually quick and can be done during a routine gynecologic visit.&nbsp;</p>



<p>An HPV test is often done at the same time as a Pap test using the same cell sample,&nbsp;and&nbsp;it&nbsp;checks for high-risk types of HPV that are most likely to lead to cervical cancer.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Cervical cancer screening does more than look for cancer. Pap tests and HPV tests can&nbsp;identify&nbsp;precancerous changes in the cervix. When these changes are found and treated early, cervical cancer&nbsp;often&nbsp;can&nbsp;be&nbsp;prevented.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Cervical cancer screening recommendations</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Ages 21 to 29:</strong>&nbsp;A Pap test every three years.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Ages 30 to 65:</strong>&nbsp;Several screening options may be&nbsp;appropriate:&nbsp;
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>HPV test alone every five years.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Pap&nbsp;test&nbsp;every three years.&nbsp;</li>



<li>combined Pap and HPV&nbsp;(called co-testing)&nbsp;testing every five years.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Over age 65:</strong>&nbsp;Some people may be able to stop screening if they&nbsp;have&nbsp;consistently&nbsp;normal&nbsp;Pap or co-test&nbsp;results and no history of&nbsp;severe&nbsp;cervical&nbsp;precancer. The&nbsp;decision&nbsp;to stop cervical cancer screening&nbsp;should always be made&nbsp;together with a&nbsp;healthcare professional.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>If a Pap or HPV test shows abnormal results,&nbsp;additional&nbsp;evaluation may be recommended. This can include repeat testing,&nbsp;a&nbsp;colposcopy&nbsp;—&nbsp;a cervical exam&nbsp;done by a clinician using&nbsp;a special magnifying scope&nbsp;—&nbsp;or&nbsp;a cervical&nbsp;biopsy. While abnormal results can be concerning, they often detect changes long before cancer develops, allowing for effective treatment and careful follow-up.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Other cancer screenings to review</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p>Depending on age and personal risk factors, other cancer screenings&nbsp;also&nbsp;may&nbsp;be recommended.&nbsp;A healthcare professional can help&nbsp;determine&nbsp;which screenings&nbsp;you&nbsp;should&nbsp;schedule.&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mammogram/about/pac-20384806" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Breast cancer screening</strong></a>&nbsp;with&nbsp;mammography&nbsp;is&nbsp;advised&nbsp;for many people beginning at midlife.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Low-dose&nbsp;</strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/lung-cancer-screening/about/pac-20385024" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>CT screening for lung cancer</strong></a>&nbsp;for those with a significant history of smoking&nbsp;may be&nbsp;appropriate&nbsp;every&nbsp;year.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/in-depth/colon-cancer-screening/art-20046825" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Colorectal cancer screening</strong></a>&nbsp;is&nbsp;recommended for most adults beginning at midlife and sometimes earlier for those with a family history or other risk factors. Screening options include colonoscopy and stool-based tests. These screenings can detect colorectal cancer at an early stage or remove precancerous polyps before they develop into cancer.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Anal cancer</strong>&nbsp;is less common, but&nbsp;it's&nbsp;also associated with HPV infection. Routine screening&nbsp;isn't&nbsp;recommended for the general population. However, people with certain risk factors, such as a weakened immune system or a history of HPV-related&nbsp;precancers or cancers, may&nbsp;benefit&nbsp;from closer monitoring. Symptoms,&nbsp;including rectal bleeding, pain,&nbsp;itching&nbsp;or a lump,&nbsp;should always be evaluated by a healthcare professional.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Make&nbsp;screening part of your routine</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p>An annual visit with a primary care clinician or gynecologist is a good opportunity to review your screening history, discuss vaccines and address new symptoms or concerns. Keeping track of when your last Pap&nbsp;test, HPV&nbsp;test,&nbsp;mammogram&nbsp;or colorectal screening&nbsp;occurred&nbsp;can help ensure&nbsp;that&nbsp;care&nbsp;isn't&nbsp;delayed.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Cervical Cancer Awareness Month&nbsp;is&nbsp;an important reminder that prevention works. Through regular screening and&nbsp;timely&nbsp;follow-up, cervical cancer is one of the most preventable cancers. Taking a proactive approach to screenings this year can&nbsp;help&nbsp;protect health now and in the future.&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/appointments/find-a-doctor/search-results?searchterm=Jamie+N.+Bakkum-Gamez%2c+M.D.&amp;locations=" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Jamie&nbsp;Bakkum-Gamez, M.D.</em></a><em>,&nbsp;Gynecological&nbsp;Oncologist, Mayo Clinic,&nbsp;Rochester, Minnesota&nbsp;&nbsp;</em>&nbsp;</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-cancer-screenings-should-i-prioritize-this-year/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What&nbsp;cancer&nbsp;screenings&nbsp;should I&nbsp;prioritize&nbsp;this&nbsp;year?&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/02/a-middle-aged-woman-in-a-doctors-office-discussing-medical-concerns-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Women-doctor-consult-WF7543353_0004-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jamie Bakkum-Gamez]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New CT imaging oral contrast agent improves visualization of bowel anatomy, clinical trial data show</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-ct-imaging-oral-contrast-agent-improves-visualization-of-bowel-anatomy-clinical-trial-data-show/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Ethan Grove]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 19:24:51 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Joel Fletcher]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=409666</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — In a new pilot feasibility study, researchers from Mayo Clinic, the University of Washington School of Medicine, the University of California San Francisco, and Nextrast Inc. found that a new imaging oral agent, also known as a "contrast agent," helps radiologists better see bowel structures and disease in CT imaging when compared […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-ct-imaging-oral-contrast-agent-improves-visualization-of-bowel-anatomy-clinical-trial-data-show/">New CT imaging oral contrast agent improves visualization of bowel anatomy, clinical trial data show</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/image-1024x683.png" alt="A technologist prepares a patient for a CT scan" class="wp-image-409648" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/image-1024x683.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/image-300x200.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/image-768x512.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/image-1536x1024.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/image.png 1687w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">A technologist prepares a patient for a CT scan.</figcaption>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — In a new <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00261-025-05308-w" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pilot feasibility study</a>, researchers from <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>, the University of Washington School of Medicine, the University of California San Francisco, and Nextrast Inc. found that a new imaging oral agent, also known as a "contrast agent," helps radiologists better see bowel structures and disease in CT imaging when compared with the current oral contrast agents.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Fletcher_1577788_3776409_0013-300x200.jpg" alt="Portrait of Dr. Joel Fletcher" class="wp-image-409652" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Fletcher_1577788_3776409_0013-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Fletcher_1577788_3776409_0013-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Fletcher_1577788_3776409_0013-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Fletcher_1577788_3776409_0013-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Fletcher_1577788_3776409_0013.jpg 1688w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Joel Fletcher, M.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>The introduction of a new oral contrast agent for CT imaging addresses common challenges in the diagnosis of bowel diseases, says by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/fletcher-joel-g-m-d/bio-20053419" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Joel Fletcher, M.D.</a>, lead author on the study and medical director of the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/ct-clinical-innovation-center/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic CT Clinical Innovation Center</a>. "The new oral contrast agent," he explains, "is ingested by patients prior to CT imaging and helps detect pathologies within and outside of the bowel wall in ways current imaging agents do not."</p>



<p>"We carefully designed this new class of oral contrast agent to overcome many of the diagnostic shortcomings of existing contrast agents for a broad range of diseases," says <a href="https://radiology.ucsf.edu/people/benjamin-yeh" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Benjamin Yeh, M.D.</a>, a co-author on the study, radiologist at the University of California at San Francisco and co-founder of Nextrast, which created the new agent. "The Clinical Phase 2 results confirm that our dark agent can reveal previously impossible-to-detect findings, including very small bowel tumors and subtle inflammatory conditions that are often missed with conventional agents at CT."</p>



<p>In their <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00261-025-05308-w" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">paper</a>, the authors report findings that suggest this new agent significantly improves visualization of inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) or cancer within the abdomen, and may provide earlier and more confident diagnoses.</p>



<p>The study compared CT scans of 32 patients with the dark borosilicate oral contrast agent and scans with conventional water or iodine-based oral contrast agents, to look at anatomical structures and disease presence.</p>



<p>"The novel dark borosilicate contrast agent has the potential to improve the assessment of numerous pathologies, including the detection of cancer and inflammatory disorders," says <a href="https://rad.uw.edu/people/amileto" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Achille Mileto, M.D.</a>, a radiologist at the University of Washington School of Medicine and first author of the study.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/CT-Image-1024x576.jpg" alt="CT images from a patient who ingested the new oral solution that better distends the stomach (see the white S) and small bowel (asterisks) so that enhancing pathologies inside and outside the bowel wall can be better displayed and detected by radiologists." class="wp-image-409656" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/CT-Image-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/CT-Image-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/CT-Image-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/CT-Image.jpg 1360w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">CT images from a patient who ingested the new oral solution that better distends the stomach (see the white S) and small bowel (asterisks) so that enhancing pathologies inside and outside the bowel wall can be better displayed and detected by radiologists.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Evaluators identified clinically relevant findings in seven patients that were not detected using the standard contrast.</p>



<p>"CT scans performed with the new agent will likely do a better job of displaying pathologies in the stomach and proximal small bowel, areas where CT with traditional oral contrast performs poorly," Dr. Fletcher says. "Pathologies within the lumen will be better displayed because the lumen is more distended, and the brightness of the pathologies on the CT images will be increased, making them more conspicuous.”</p>



<p>The researchers say further study using a larger patient population is needed, but the initial findings show promise.</p>



<p>Review the <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00261-025-05308-w" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic&nbsp;<br></strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Ethan Grove, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-ct-imaging-oral-contrast-agent-improves-visualization-of-bowel-anatomy-clinical-trial-data-show/">New CT imaging oral contrast agent improves visualization of bowel anatomy, clinical trial data show</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/image_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/image_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Joel Fletcher]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What does it mean to be in a cancer clinical trial?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-does-it-mean-to-be-in-a-cancer-clinical-trial/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[justingottlieb]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 14:11:19 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Judy Boughey]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=409078</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;Our daughter was recently diagnosed with cancer. She's interested in participating in a clinical trial but doesn't really know what that means or how to get involved. Can you help? ANSWER:&nbsp;A cancer diagnosis can feel overwhelming and often comes with a long list of decisions to make.&nbsp; Many people are surprised to learn […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-does-it-mean-to-be-in-a-cancer-clinical-trial/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What does it mean to be in a cancer clinical trial?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="938" height="527" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/Cancer-Clincal-Trial16x9.jpg" alt="Female in a gray sweater filling out a consent and privacy form." class="wp-image-368882" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/Cancer-Clincal-Trial16x9.jpg 938w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/Cancer-Clincal-Trial16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/Cancer-Clincal-Trial16x9-768x431.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 938px) 100vw, 938px">



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;</strong>Our daughter was recently diagnosed with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20370594">cancer</a>. She's interested in participating in a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center/cancer-care/about-cancer-clinical-trials" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">clinical trial</a> but doesn't really know what that means or how to get involved. Can you help?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:&nbsp;</strong>A cancer diagnosis can feel overwhelming and often comes with a long list of decisions to make.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Many people are surprised to learn that clinical trials aren't just for people who have run out of standard treatment options, but are an important part of cancer care at every stage and most aspects of diagnosis and treatment. They help physicians study new and better ways to diagnose, treat and improve the quality of life for people. They also give patients access to promising treatments that they might not otherwise receive.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What happens in a cancer clinical trial?</strong></h2>



<p>During a clinical trial, participants may receive specific interventions or potentially the standard treatment. Researchers measure how safe and effective the interventions are and usually compare them to standard treatments. These may include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>New cancer drugs or drug combinations.</li>



<li>New medical procedures or devices.</li>



<li>New surgical techniques.</li>



<li>New ways to use existing treatments.</li>



<li>Lifestyle or behavioral approaches.</li>
</ul>



<p>One of the biggest misconceptions is that joining a trial means you might not receive treatment or be given a placebo. Most clinical trials compare a new treatment with the current standard of care.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Who's eligible for a trial?</strong></h2>



<p>Your daughter’s care team is the best starting point. Feel free to ask if she is a candidate for any trial. Physicians at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> routinely review whether patients qualify for available trials. If there's a study that's potentially right for your daughter, your team can connect her with research coordinators and help navigate eligibility, consent, scheduling and next steps.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>How do people find and sign up for trials?</strong></h2>



<p>Patients can find out about trials in several ways:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Direct referral from their care team (medical oncologist, surgical oncologist, radiation oncologist, radiologist to name a few).</li>



<li>Search tools, such as the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic clinical trials website</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ClinicalTrials.gov</a>.</li>



<li>Trial navigators or research coordinators who help determine eligibility and guide enrollment.<br></li>
</ul>



<p>When a clinician identifies that a patient may be a good candidate for a study, they review the study purpose, what participation involves, potential risks and benefits, and available alternatives. Patients can take time to decide whether to participate and may bring family members or caregivers into these conversations.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Clinic Trials Beyond Walls: Expanding who can participate</strong></h2>



<p>Participating in a clinical trial typically has meant frequent trips to a major medical center, which is something that can be difficult for people balancing work, caregiving responsibilities, transportation needs or facing financial strain.&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-to-expand-access-to-state-of-the-art-cancer-care-through-transformational-gift/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic's Cancer Trials Beyond Walls</a> is an initiative that brings elements of cancer clinical trials closer to home, such as lab draws, remote patient monitoring and virtual visits. This brings the benefits of research directly to patients' doorsteps and makes trial participation more manageable for families.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Telehealth-blood-pressure-man-WF4999678_0355-16x9-jpg-1024x576.jpg" alt="Young male patient takes his own blood pressure reading during a virtual telehealth visit." class="wp-image-409517" style="width:586px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Telehealth-blood-pressure-man-WF4999678_0355-16x9-jpg-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Telehealth-blood-pressure-man-WF4999678_0355-16x9-jpg-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Telehealth-blood-pressure-man-WF4999678_0355-16x9-jpg-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Telehealth-blood-pressure-man-WF4999678_0355-16x9-jpg.jpg 1484w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> Patient takes his blood pressure reading during a virtual telehealth visit. </figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>Mayo Clinic's decentralized research initiative uses telehealth, remote monitoring, mobile phlebotomy and home-based services so patients can complete parts of a clinical trial without traveling.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The care of these patients being managed at home, with the support of a dedicated clinical team, may include vital sign monitoring, symptom reporting, medication administration or follow-up assessments.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Why do clinical trials matter so much?</strong></h2>



<p>Every cancer therapy available today exists because patients such as your daughter volunteered to participate. Volunteering for trials is a crucial way to advance medical treatment.<br><br>Joining a trial may give your daughter access to cutting-edge care and contribute to future breakthroughs.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/boughey-judy-c-m-d/bio-20054836" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Judy Boughey, M.D.,</em></a><em>&nbsp;Surgical Oncology, Mayo Clinic in Rochester&nbsp;</em></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-does-it-mean-to-be-in-a-cancer-clinical-trial/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What does it mean to be in a cancer clinical trial?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/Cancer-Clincal-Trial1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/Cancer-Clincal-Trial16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Judy Boughey]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Predicting prostate cancer recurrence through power of AI</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/earlier-more-personalized-follow-up-care-through-prostate-specific-antigen-psa-monitoring-supported-by-ai-powered-by-mayo-clinic-platform/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[jftmayo]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 17:13:46 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Mark Waddle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=409485</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — To help meet the potentially complex needs of patients after prostate cancer treatment and offer the precision and care necessary in the follow-up journey, Mayo Clinic’s Department of Radiation Oncology developed the PSA Control Tower. This is an intelligent monitoring tool designed to support clinicians in keeping a close, ongoing watch over […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/earlier-more-personalized-follow-up-care-through-prostate-specific-antigen-psa-monitoring-supported-by-ai-powered-by-mayo-clinic-platform/">Predicting prostate cancer recurrence through power of AI</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Doctor-discusses-health-with-senior-patient-in-hospital_284569472-1024x576.jpg" alt="Doctor sitting next to a senior male patient lying and sitting up in hospital bed, discussing health, treatment, and diagnosis. Doctor using a digital tablet to review health chart with the patient." class="wp-image-409453" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Doctor-discusses-health-with-senior-patient-in-hospital_284569472-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Doctor-discusses-health-with-senior-patient-in-hospital_284569472-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Doctor-discusses-health-with-senior-patient-in-hospital_284569472-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Doctor-discusses-health-with-senior-patient-in-hospital_284569472.jpg 1080w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — To help meet the potentially complex needs of patients after prostate cancer treatment and offer the precision and care necessary in the follow-up journey, Mayo Clinic’s Department of Radiation Oncology developed the PSA Control Tower. This is an intelligent monitoring tool designed to support clinicians in keeping a close, ongoing watch over patients after treatment.</p>



<p>Traditionally, the follow-up care for prostate cancer patients follows a standard schedule and relies on manual review. This process can be time-consuming and may delay care due to administrative steps. Subtle but important changes in test results can be missed or recognized too late. Because of this, patients often need faster intervention and a more personalized approach to care.</p>



<p>Prostate cancer follow-up depends on understanding prostate-specific antigen (PSA) trends over time. Each PSA test is important, but spotting early signs of recurrence requires regular contact and ongoing monitoring. As patient numbers grow and care becomes more complex, this process can be difficult to manage. Health systems are under increasing pressure to provide reliable follow-up without adding strain to care teams.</p>



<p>The PSA Control Tower brings together clinical information and PSA trends, using intelligent tools to support care teams in understanding which patients may need attention and when. By bringing potential concerns to light earlier, the system helps teams stay connected to patients. Throughout the process, clinical expertise, thoughtful judgment, and human connection continue to guide every decision.</p>



<p>Behind the scenes, the PSA Control Tower is powered by <a href="https://www.mayoclinicplatform.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Platform</a>, which provides a secure environment where Mayo Clinic staff have access to large amounts of de-identified patient data. This enables teams to study patterns over time and build predictive models using information such as lab results, clinical notes, imaging and pathology.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Dr.-Mark-Waddle_1652626_3911824_0002-200x300.jpg" alt="Portrait of Dr. Mark Waddle" class="wp-image-409486" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Dr.-Mark-Waddle_1652626_3911824_0002-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Dr.-Mark-Waddle_1652626_3911824_0002-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Dr.-Mark-Waddle_1652626_3911824_0002.jpg 750w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mark Waddle, M.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>“Our hope is that the PSA Control Tower will be a rare win-win-win for patients, physicians and hospital systems,” says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/waddle-mark-r-m-d/bio-20532761" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mark Waddle, M.D.</a> “The ‘Control Tower’ will allow each and every patient to be monitored 24/7 — for peace of mind that all patients are being followed per guidelines and that abnormal PSA values are acted upon.”</p>



<p>As new data are introduced, the predictive models continue to learn and improve. Through Mayo Clinic Platform technology, clinicians will be able to easily view PSA trends and recurrence risk through clear dashboards, giving them timely information to support informed conversations and personalized care while keeping clinical expertise and compassion at the center.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A scalable vision for the future</strong></h2>



<p>The PSA Control Tower reflects Mayo Clinic’s Bold. Forward. vision for precision oncology, which includes combining advanced analytics, secure data access, and seamless clinical integration. As this model expands beyond Mayo Clinic, it offers a path toward earlier detection, more efficient workflows, and scalable, data-driven follow-up care for prostate cancer patients nationwide.</p>



<p>“This allows our care providers to see more new patients, treat more complex patients, and focus effort related to prostate cancer follow-up on the patients that truly need their expertise and time,” says Dr. Waddle.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center&nbsp;</strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the <a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs&nbsp;in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong> </p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/earlier-more-personalized-follow-up-care-through-prostate-specific-antigen-psa-monitoring-supported-by-ai-powered-by-mayo-clinic-platform/">Predicting prostate cancer recurrence through power of AI</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Doctor-discusses-health-with-senior-patient-in-hospital_284569472_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Doctor-discusses-health-with-senior-patient-in-hospital_284569472.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Mark Waddle]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Mayo Clinic study advances personalized prostate cancer education with an EHR-integrated AI agent&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-study-advances-personalized-prostate-cancer-education-with-an-ehr-integrated-ai-agent/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[rebeccabromelkamp]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 17:45:18 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[AI and Digital Health]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Arizona]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Wei Liu]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=409383</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->PHOENIX&nbsp;—&nbsp;Mayo Clinic&nbsp;researchers have developed and evaluated MedEduChat, an electronic health record (EHR)&nbsp;that&nbsp;works with&nbsp;a&nbsp;large language model to provide accurate, patient-specific prostate cancer education.&nbsp;&nbsp; The findings are published in&nbsp;Nature Portfolio Digital Medicine&nbsp;and highlight&nbsp;a new approach&nbsp;to delivering&nbsp;timely, individualized guidance for people navigating a prostate cancer diagnosis.&nbsp;&nbsp; Cancer patients often face uncertainty as they process complex information about their […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-study-advances-personalized-prostate-cancer-education-with-an-ehr-integrated-ai-agent/">New Mayo Clinic study advances personalized prostate cancer education with an EHR-integrated AI agent&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Man-using-computer-tablet-shutterstock_151335656-16x9--1024x576.jpg" alt="Man smiling, using computer tablet" class="wp-image-409385" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Man-using-computer-tablet-shutterstock_151335656-16x9--1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Man-using-computer-tablet-shutterstock_151335656-16x9--300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Man-using-computer-tablet-shutterstock_151335656-16x9--768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Man-using-computer-tablet-shutterstock_151335656-16x9--1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Man-using-computer-tablet-shutterstock_151335656-16x9-.jpg 1604w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>PHOENIX&nbsp;—&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;researchers have developed and evaluated MedEduChat, an electronic health record (EHR)&nbsp;that&nbsp;works with&nbsp;a&nbsp;large language model to provide accurate, patient-specific <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prostate-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353087" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">prostate cancer</a> education.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The findings are published in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41746-025-02166-0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nature Portfolio Digital Medicine</a>&nbsp;and highlight&nbsp;a new approach&nbsp;to delivering&nbsp;timely, individualized guidance for people navigating a prostate cancer diagnosis.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Cancer patients often face uncertainty as they process complex information about their diagnosis and treatment options. Limited time with clinicians can make it difficult for patients to receive the detailed answers they need to understand decisions that shape their care.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>This&nbsp;MedEduChat&nbsp;study&nbsp;demonstrates&nbsp;how advanced AI, grounded in Mayo-validated clinical data, can help bridge these gaps by delivering clear, conversational explanations based on each patient's own health record.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Understanding the patient experience using&nbsp;AI</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p>Fifteen prostate cancer patients interacted with&nbsp;MedEduChat&nbsp;for 20 to 30 minutes as part of a mixed-method usability study conducted at Mayo Clinic campuses in Arizona and Minnesota.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Patients reported higher confidence after using the tool, with Health Confidence Scores increasing from 9.9 to 13.9 on a 16-point scale. Usability scores were also high;&nbsp;average survey responses ranked MedEduChat&nbsp;83.7 out of 100.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Patients noted that&nbsp;MedEduChat&nbsp;helped them understand their diagnosis in a more accessible way. The&nbsp;tool&nbsp;provided relief by explaining unfamiliar or complex terms&nbsp;in a clear and concise manner.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The conversational format&nbsp;helped&nbsp;participants replace incorrect assumptions with medically accurate information derived from their own EHR.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Clinician-evaluated accuracy and safety</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/liu-wei-ph-d/bio-20055721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Wei Liu, Ph.D.</a>,&nbsp;a radiation oncology medical physicist,&nbsp;and three Mayo Clinic clinicians independently reviewed 85 anonymized question-and-response pairs. They rated MedEduChat's answers as highly correct (2.9 out of 3), complete (2.7 out of 3) and safe (2.7 out of 3).&nbsp;</p>



<p>Clinicians also noted strong patient-readiness and moderate personalization, reflecting&nbsp;MedEduChat's ability to tailor explanations to each person's age, treatment history and cancer stage.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Although&nbsp;MedEduChat&nbsp;delivered&nbsp;accurate&nbsp;and clinically aligned information, clinicians emphasized the importance of ongoing monitoring to prevent errors that could arise from incomplete or inconsistently documented EHR data.</p>



<p>The research team incorporated a&nbsp;multilayer&nbsp;approach&nbsp;to address these concerns and guide future system enhancements.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Combining patient-centered education with AI</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p>MedEduChat&nbsp;was designed with a structured educational model that combines closed-domain clinical data, semi-structured guidance and personalized interaction.</p>



<p>Patients can explore diagnosis details, learn about treatment options and side effects, and review lifestyle considerations and follow-up expectations. The tool draws only from validated sources,&nbsp;such as Mayo Clinic materials and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nccn.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Comprehensive Cancer Network</a>&nbsp;guidelines.</p>



<p>"This research demonstrates how large language models can be safely and effectively integrated into real clinical systems to improve cancer education,"&nbsp;according&nbsp;to Dr. Liu.&nbsp;"By combining advanced AI with Mayo Clinic's electronic health records, MedEduChat delivers personalized, accurate and easy-to-understand explanations tailored to each patient's medical history."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Expanding AI&nbsp;cancer research</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p>The study team plans to translate this work into clinical use across all three Mayo Clinic campuses&nbsp;in Arizona,&nbsp;Florida&nbsp;and Minnesota. Next steps include expanding MedEduChat beyond radiation oncology to additional cancer specialties. These efforts aim to make personalized AI-assisted education a routine part of cancer care.</p>



<p>This research was funded by the National Cancer Institute, the Eric and Wendy Schmidt Fund for AI Research and Innovation, the Fred C. and Katherine B. Andersen Foundation, and The Kemper and Ethel Marley Fund in Cancer Research.</p>



<p>###&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</strong>&nbsp;<br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection,&nbsp;prevention&nbsp;and treatment to change lives.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo&nbsp;Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion,&nbsp;expertise&nbsp;and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for&nbsp;additional&nbsp;Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-study-advances-personalized-prostate-cancer-education-with-an-ehr-integrated-ai-agent/">New Mayo Clinic study advances personalized prostate cancer education with an EHR-integrated AI agent&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Man-using-computer-tablet-shutterstock_151335656.-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Man-using-computer-tablet-shutterstock_151335656-16x9-.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Wei Liu]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic integrated care&nbsp;enables treatment for rare, complex cancer&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-integrated-care-enables-treatment-for-rare-complex-cancer/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[jftmayo]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 13:49:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer Patient Stories]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Surgery]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Eric Moore]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=408894</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER,&nbsp;Minn.&nbsp;—&nbsp;A&nbsp;multidisciplinary surgical team&nbsp;at&nbsp;Mayo Clinic&nbsp;has successfully treated an exceptionally rare and life-threatening cancer that&nbsp;invaded a&nbsp;patient's&nbsp;heart and airway. The procedure&nbsp;combined&nbsp;advanced cardiac surgery with complex airway reconstruction and&nbsp;represents&nbsp;a significant achievement in modern cancer care.&nbsp; Tami Channel's&nbsp;thyroid cancer&nbsp;was so advanced&nbsp;that&nbsp;her family&nbsp;had begun&nbsp;planning hospice care. The&nbsp;tumor had&nbsp;severely compromised&nbsp;her&nbsp;airway&nbsp;and&nbsp;had encased her carotid artery and jugular vein, two of the body's most […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-integrated-care-enables-treatment-for-rare-complex-cancer/">Mayo Clinic integrated care&nbsp;enables treatment for rare, complex cancer&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-16x9-1-1024x768.jpg" alt="Tami Channel, a Mayo Clinic patient, was treated for a rare cancer" class="wp-image-408920" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-16x9-1-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-16x9-1-300x225.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-16x9-1-768x576.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-16x9-1.jpg 1500w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER,&nbsp;Minn.&nbsp;—&nbsp;A&nbsp;multidisciplinary surgical team&nbsp;at&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;has successfully treated an exceptionally rare and life-threatening cancer that&nbsp;invaded a&nbsp;patient's&nbsp;heart and airway. The procedure&nbsp;combined&nbsp;advanced cardiac surgery with complex airway reconstruction and&nbsp;represents&nbsp;a significant achievement in modern cancer care.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Tami Channel's&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/thyroid-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20354161" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">thyroid cancer</a>&nbsp;was so advanced&nbsp;that&nbsp;her family&nbsp;had begun&nbsp;planning hospice care. The&nbsp;tumor had&nbsp;severely compromised&nbsp;her&nbsp;airway&nbsp;and&nbsp;had encased her carotid artery and jugular vein, two of the body's most vital blood vessels.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Primary cancers&nbsp;of&nbsp;the heart are extremely rare. Most tumors that appear in the heart are benign, and malignant cardiac tumors such as sarcomas account for only a&nbsp;small&nbsp;fraction of all cancers. Airway tumors involving the throat or trachea are also uncommon and often detected late because early symptoms can&nbsp;resemble&nbsp;routine respiratory&nbsp;issues. When&nbsp;a malignant&nbsp;growth extends into both the heart and the airway, the risks multiply quickly because the tumor can narrow or block breathing passages and interfere with the heart's ability to function.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Faced with a tumor that had grown into vital structures and left the patient's airway&nbsp;nearly the&nbsp;width of a toothpick, the care team, including&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/ryder-mabel-m-d/bio-20055734" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mabel Ryder, M.D.</a>,&nbsp;a Mayo Clinic endocrinologist,&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/moore-eric-j-m-d/bio-20053794" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Eric Moore, M.D.</a>,&nbsp;a&nbsp;Mayo Clinic head and neck surgeon,&nbsp;recognized that conventional treatment would not be enough.&nbsp;Tami needed&nbsp;a highly complex&nbsp;surgery — and it needed to happen quickly.&nbsp;As a matter of priority, Tami would undergo an unscheduled thoracotomy and bypass, an emergency open-chest operation that requires opening the chest cavity, supporting circulation through a heart-lung machine, and working around critical airways and blood vessels. Few hospitals could coordinate such a demanding procedure so quickly.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="973" height="547" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-Dr.-Eric-Moore-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-408921" style="aspect-ratio:1.778836609092714;width:613px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-Dr.-Eric-Moore-16x9-1.jpg 973w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-Dr.-Eric-Moore-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-Dr.-Eric-Moore-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 973px) 100vw, 973px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Tami Channel with Dr. Eric Moore</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>"We were able to make it happen because it needed to be done," Dr. Moore says. "That's the Mayo difference."&nbsp;</p>



<p>The operating room reflected Mayo's integrated model: anesthesiology, perfusion, bronchoscopy, cardiothoracic surgery,&nbsp;and head and neck surgery, with each discipline contributing seamlessly.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"It felt like&nbsp;a choreographed&nbsp;ballet," Dr. Moore says. "This kind of multidisciplinary precision doesn't just happen — it's the Mayo model in action."&nbsp;</p>



<p>During the same operation, specialists reconstructed the airway to restore safe breathing. Procedures of this complexity rely on close coordination among cardiac surgeons, thoracic and airway surgeons, ear, nose and throat&nbsp;specialists, anesthesiologists,&nbsp;oncologists,&nbsp;and critical care teams. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;experts&nbsp;are&nbsp;uniquely positioned to manage these cases because they can move quickly from diagnosis&nbsp;to&nbsp;complex&nbsp;surgery&nbsp;and recovery.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This successful intervention shows what is possible when specialists collaborate on rare cancers that cross organ systems.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>###&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic&nbsp;</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion,&nbsp;expertise&nbsp;and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for&nbsp;additional&nbsp;Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong> &nbsp;<br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the <a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives. &nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:&nbsp;</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:Newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-integrated-care-enables-treatment-for-rare-complex-cancer/">Mayo Clinic integrated care&nbsp;enables treatment for rare, complex cancer&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Eric Moore]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</atom:link></channel>
</rss> 