<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org">

<channel>
	<title>Cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml">
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastbuilddate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 12:49:34 +0000</lastbuilddate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updateperiod>
	hourly	</sy:updateperiod>
	<sy:updatefrequency>
	1	</sy:updatefrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic leads 4 decades of advances in breast cancer care</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-leads-4-decades-of-advances-in-breast-cancer-care/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[brittanycordeiro]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 12:48:56 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Cycle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Breast Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=406539</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->From early detection to targeted therapies, breast cancer survival has reached record highs — with Mayo Clinic leading what's next. ROCHESTER, Minn. — For more than 40 years, Mayo Clinic has been at the forefront of breast cancer innovation, transforming a once-limited diagnosis into a story of record survival rates, groundbreaking therapies and renewing hope […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-leads-4-decades-of-advances-in-breast-cancer-care/">Mayo Clinic leads 4 decades of advances in breast cancer care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Dr-Boughey-in-surgery-breast-cancer-CU-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-406544" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Dr-Boughey-in-surgery-breast-cancer-CU-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Dr-Boughey-in-surgery-breast-cancer-CU-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Dr-Boughey-in-surgery-breast-cancer-CU-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Dr-Boughey-in-surgery-breast-cancer-CU-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Dr-Boughey-in-surgery-breast-cancer-CU-16-x-9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>


<p><em>From early detection to targeted therapies, breast cancer survival has reached record highs — with Mayo Clinic leading what's next.</em></p>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — For more than 40 years, Mayo Clinic has been at the forefront of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a> innovation, transforming a once-limited diagnosis into a story of record survival rates, groundbreaking therapies and renewing hope for millions of patients worldwide. &nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Detecting cancer earlier</strong></h2>



<p>Mammography revolutionized breast cancer care in the 1980s by finding tumors earlier, making them more treatable. Advances in digital mammography and 3D tomosynthesis have since improved accuracy, reduced false alarms and revealed cancers hidden in dense breast tissue.</p>



<p>Genetic testing has also reshaped care. Discoveries of BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutations — and later, additional <a href="https://perspectivesinmedicine.cshlp.org/content/14/8/a041318" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">genetic markers</a> — have allowed healthcare teams to personalize screening and prevention. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> researchers, such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/yadav-siddhartha-m-b-b-s-m-d/bio-20489847" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Siddhartha Yadav, M.B.B.S., M.D.</a>, and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/couch-fergus-j-ph-d/bio-00027515" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Fergus Couch, Ph.D.</a>, have helped refine <a href="https://www.nejm.org/doi/10.1056/NEJMoa2005936" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">risk predictions</a> so patients and care teams can make more informed choices about surgery, surveillance or medication.</p>



<p>"By offering more precise, individualized risk estimates, our work supports shared decision-making between patients and their care teams to reduce the risk of breast cancer," says Dr. Yadav, a Mayo Clinic medical oncologist. He is expanding this work to better understand how inherited genetic changes influence tumor biology, treatment response and long-term outcomes in breast and ovarian cancers.</p>



<p>New tools such as <a href="https://pubs.rsna.org/doi/10.1148/rg.2021200167" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">contrast-enhanced digital mammography</a>, which uses a special dye along with mammography, are showing promise in detecting cancers that traditional scans may miss. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/patel-bhavika-m-d/bio-20130475" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bhavika Patel, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic radiologist, is leading clinical trials that show its potential to move toward more personalized screening. "We aim to match the right test to the right woman at the right time because earlier detection means treatment can start sooner, which improves outcomes and saves lives," says Dr. Patel.</p>



<p>Dr. Yadav and Dr. Patel predict that over the next 10 years, risk assessment and breast imaging will work together to become even more personalized and integrated with artificial intelligence (AI) to tailor care and improve outcomes for every patient.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Understanding breast cancer subtypes</strong></h2>



<p>In the 1990s, researchers discovered that breast cancer is a collection of biologically distinct subtypes: hormone receptor–positive, HER2-positive and <a href="https://www.bmj.com/content/381/bmj-2022-071674" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">triple-negative breast cancer</a> (TNBC). This opened the door to more personalized treatment.</p>



<p>At Mayo Clinic, researchers are now pushing this even further with studies led by breast medical oncologists <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/leon-ferre-roberto-a-m-d/bio-20463845" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Roberto Leon-Ferre, M.D.</a>, and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/goetz-matthew-p-m-d/bio-00027285" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Matthew Goetz, M.D.</a>, that <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-study-finds-triple-negative-breast-cancer-tumors-with-an-increase-in-immune-cells-have-lower-risk-of-recurrence-after-surgery/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">suggest</a> people who have early-stage TNBC and high levels of immune cells within their tumors (called immune infiltrating cells or TILs) may have a lower risk of recurrence and better survival rates even when not treated with chemotherapy.</p>



<p>Based on this work, Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/laboratory-medicine-pathology/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Laboratory of Medicine and Pathology</a> routinely reports TILs in all patients with early-stage TNBC. And Dr. Leon-Ferre and Dr. Goetz are developing a national clinical trial to evaluate TIL levels in patients with stage 1 TNBC. "The data will inform whether patients need or do not need chemotherapy, and could change standard practice," says Dr. Leon-Ferre.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>New treatments, better outcomes</strong></h2>



<p>Tamoxifen was one of the first breakthroughs in hormone-targeted therapy. Two decades later, trastuzumab transformed outcomes for HER2-positive breast cancer. And new classes of drugs — including hormone therapies like aromatase inhibitors, CDK4/6 inhibitors, PARP inhibitors and immunotherapies — have dramatically extended survival for many patients.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers are leading national trials of next-generation therapies, like Dr. Goetz's study of drugs that more effectively block or degrade the <a href="https://academic.oup.com/endo/article/162/12/bqab191/6364076" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">estrogen receptor</a>. Other trials are testing whether lower doses of tamoxifen can reduce side effects while still decreasing risk of further breast cancer events.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/haddad-tufia-c-m-d/bio-20055534" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tufia Haddad, M.D.</a>, breast medical oncologist at Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, is leading efforts to identify novel therapies to transform cancer care, such as showing the Aurora A kinase inhibitor, alisertib, <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaoncology/fullarticle/2802267" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">can reduce or eradicate breast cancer</a> stem cells within a tumor to shrink or stabilize the disease.&nbsp;She is now studying it in combination with different endocrine therapies, in hopes that a lower dose with fewer side effects will be better for patients.</p>



<p>Further, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/chumsri-saranya-m-d/bio-20114242" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Saranya Chumsri, M.D.</a>, also a breast medical oncologist at the cancer center, is leading vaccine clinical trials in <a href="https://aacrjournals.org/clincancerres/article/26/5/1045/83151/Rapid-Generation-of-Sustainable-HER2-specific-T" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">HER2-positive</a> and TNBC that may one day prevent cancer from returning altogether.</p>



<p>"In 10 years, we will see growth of a new class of targeted treatment approaches to intercept cancer that is detected at a microscopic stage. Preventing cancer will become the new cure," says Dr. Haddad.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Smarter chemotherapy and genomic testing</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="893" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Genomic-mapping-for-breast-cancer-1024x893.jpg" alt="Medical illustration of genomic mapping for breast cancer" class="wp-image-406545" style="width:384px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Genomic-mapping-for-breast-cancer-1024x893.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Genomic-mapping-for-breast-cancer-300x262.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Genomic-mapping-for-breast-cancer-768x670.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Genomic-mapping-for-breast-cancer.jpg 1290w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure></div>


<p>Chemotherapy has become smarter and more tolerable with advances like shorter intervals between chemotherapy cycles and better supportive care. Mayo Clinic researchers are now exploring optimized treatment schedules and new combinations.</p>



<p>Genomic tests such as <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33444922/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Oncotype DX</a> analyze tumor biology to predict whether chemotherapy will help, sparing many women from unnecessary treatment. Liquid biopsies — blood tests that detect cancer DNA — are beginning to guide real-time treatment decisions.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Advances in surgery and radiation</strong></h2>



<p>Surgery and radiation also have evolved with a focus on survival and quality of life. Research proved that breast-conserving surgery with radiation was as effective as mastectomy, and <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1245/s10434-024-15715-w" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">sentinel lymph node surgery</a> reduced the need for extensive operations, sparing many patients from long-term complications.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/boughey-judy-c-m-d/bio-20054836" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Judy Boughey, M.D.</a>, surgical oncologist and chair of Breast and Melanoma Surgical Oncology at Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24101169/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">led a national study</a> in the 2010s that dramatically changed the management of breast cancer for advanced disease, allowing even more patients to avoid axillary lymph node dissection.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Robotic-surgery-mastectomy-Dr-Boughey-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Robotic breast cancer surgery with Dr. Judy Boughey and team" class="wp-image-406549" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Robotic-surgery-mastectomy-Dr-Boughey-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Robotic-surgery-mastectomy-Dr-Boughey-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Robotic-surgery-mastectomy-Dr-Boughey-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Robotic-surgery-mastectomy-Dr-Boughey-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Robotic-surgery-mastectomy-Dr-Boughey-16-x-9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">            Dr. Judy Boughey and team perform surgery with robotic assistance</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Newer surgical techniques — skin- and nipple-sparing mastectomy, immediate reconstruction, and robotic approaches — <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11701-023-01547-5" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">are designed with both survival and quality of life</a> in mind. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/jakub-james-w-m-d/bio-20055124" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">James Jakub, M.D.</a>, surgical oncologist, performed the first robotic <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/protective-mastectomies-that-preserve-nipple-safe-for-women-at-high-breast-cancer-risk/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">nipple-sparing mastectomy</a> at Mayo Clinic in 2021 as part of a national clinical trial. Now, Mayo Clinic is the highest enrolling site in this clinical trial with principal investigator <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/piltin-mara-a-d-o/bio-20487425" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mara Piltin, D.O.</a>, a Mayo Clinic surgical oncologist.</p>



<p>"These are <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1245/s10434-024-15111-4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">significant advances</a>, and in the future, we hope to eliminate surgery within the axilla (armpit area), use ablative therapies for tumors, inject medicines directly into the tumor and preserve sensation to the nipple-areolar during mastectomy," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mclaughlin-sarah-a-m-d/bio-20055048" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sarah McLaughlin, M.D.</a>, breast surgical oncologist at Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center.</p>



<p>Radiation also has become more precise and efficient, with shorter treatment courses and advanced options such as <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0360301621006520?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">proton therapy</a>. Mayo's Proton Beam Therapy Program has <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/10-years-10000-lives-mayo-experts-highlight-the-journey-and-future-of-proton-beam-and-particle-therapy-at-mayo-clinic/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">treated 10,000 patients in 10 years</a> — far exceeding national averages — and new technologies like <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10549-020-05641-2" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">carbon ion therapy</a> are on the horizon. &nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/BCAM-Timeline-1920x1080-01-1024x576.jpg" alt="Timeline infographic for breast cancer research 2025" class="wp-image-406556" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/BCAM-Timeline-1920x1080-01-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/BCAM-Timeline-1920x1080-01-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/BCAM-Timeline-1920x1080-01-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/BCAM-Timeline-1920x1080-01-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/BCAM-Timeline-1920x1080-01-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A future of hope</strong></h2>



<p>Since 1989, breast cancer deaths in the U.S. have dropped nearly 40%. That progress is the result of decades of discovery — better imaging, smarter drugs, less invasive surgery and personalized medicine.</p>



<p>"Breast cancer care is one of the fastest-evolving areas in medicine," says Dr. Boughey. "Every clinical trial takes another step forward to improve outcomes and reduce side effects for patients."</p>



<p>For patients with breast cancer and their families, the last four decades tell a story of hope: survival is higher than ever, treatment is more personalized, and the future has never looked brighter.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and to providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</strong><strong> </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong> </p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Brittany Cordeiro, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-leads-4-decades-of-advances-in-breast-cancer-care/">Mayo Clinic leads 4 decades of advances in breast cancer care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Dr-Boughey-in-surgery-breast-cancer-CU-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Dr-Boughey-in-surgery-breast-cancer-CU-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Breast Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New study links genetic variation to chemotherapy-related liver damage in patients with colorectal cancer liver metastases</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-study-links-genetic-variation-to-chemotherapy-related-liver-damage-in-patients-with-colorectal-cancer-liver-metastases/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Chloe Corey]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 13:57:48 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Patrick Starlinger]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=406472</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — A new international study led by&nbsp;Mayo Clinic&nbsp;researchers has identified a genetic factor that may explain why some patients with&nbsp;colorectal cancer&nbsp;that has spread to the liver experience more severe liver damage after chemotherapy. For patients with&nbsp;colorectal liver metastases, surgery offers the best chance of long-term survival. To improve outcomes, many patients receive chemotherapy […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-study-links-genetic-variation-to-chemotherapy-related-liver-damage-in-patients-with-colorectal-cancer-liver-metastases/">New study links genetic variation to chemotherapy-related liver damage in patients with colorectal cancer liver metastases</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Liver-damage-illlustration-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-406485" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Liver-damage-illlustration-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Liver-damage-illlustration-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Liver-damage-illlustration-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Liver-damage-illlustration-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Liver-damage-illlustration-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>


<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A new international study led by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;researchers has identified a genetic factor that may explain why some patients with&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353669" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colorectal cancer</a>&nbsp;that has spread to the liver experience more severe liver damage after chemotherapy.</p>



<p>For patients with&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stage-4-colon-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20584697" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colorectal liver metastases</a>, surgery offers the best chance of long-term survival. To improve outcomes, many patients receive chemotherapy before surgery. While this approach can shrink tumors to make them more operable, one potential side effect is injury to the liver. Until now, it hasn't been clear why certain patients' livers are more prone to chemotherapy-associated liver injury.</p>



<p>"This is the first study to clearly show that a genetic predisposition plays a significant role in how the liver tolerates chemotherapy," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/starlinger-patrick-p-m-d-ph-d/bio-20533712" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Patrick Starlinger, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;hepatobiliary and pancreas surgeon and senior author of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/ebiom/article/PIIS2352-3964(25)00372-X/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;published in The Lancet eBioMedicine.</p>



<p>In this study, the researchers reviewed 551 patients who had chemotherapy followed by surgery to remove the tumor. They looked at liver health tests to see how chemotherapy affected liver function and genetic markers that are already linked to liver disease in other settings.&nbsp;</p>



<p>They found that a specific gene variant in the PNPLA3 gene, which is known to affect fat metabolism in the liver, was strongly linked to liver injury after chemotherapy. Patients with two copies of this variant were especially vulnerable, and all of them developed signs of significant liver injury after chemotherapy.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Genetic differences help explain global variation</strong></h2>



<p>According to Dr. Starlinger, the PNPLA3 variant is common worldwide, but its prevalence differs by population. For example, in Japan, the mutation is present in more than 41% of the population. It's found in more than 71% among people of Peruvian descent, but fewer than 10% of people in some European populations have it.</p>



<p>Because the genetic variation is more common in certain groups, such as people of Asian or Latin American descent, this may help explain why previous studies in different countries have reported conflicting results about the benefits of giving chemotherapy before and/or after surgery when treating colorectal liver metastases.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Personalizing care to maximize benefit, minimize risk</strong></h2>



<p>The findings suggest that a blood test to check for the PNPLA3 variant, along with monitoring liver health, could help doctors identify patients at higher risk for liver damage from chemotherapy.</p>



<p>"These findings offer us insight into how we can adjust treatment strategies to best manage the care for patients diagnosed with colorectal liver metastases, while potentially avoiding a negative side effect of chemotherapy," says Dr. Starlinger. "Chemotherapy may still be an appropriate treatment option, and with this information, we can personalize treatment for each patient — for example, tailoring chemotherapy or allowing more time for the liver to recover before surgery."</p>



<p>For a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding, review the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/ebiom/article/PIIS2352-3964(25)00372-X/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>.</p>



<p>###&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:&nbsp;</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Chloe Corey, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-study-links-genetic-variation-to-chemotherapy-related-liver-damage-in-patients-with-colorectal-cancer-liver-metastases/">New study links genetic variation to chemotherapy-related liver damage in patients with colorectal cancer liver metastases</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Liver-damage-illlustration-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Liver-damage-illlustration-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Patrick Starlinger]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic experts present key radiation oncology findings at ASTRO</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-experts-present-key-radiation-oncology-findings-at-astro/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Jessica Saenz]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 22:01:43 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=406510</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center researchers will present their latest radiation oncology findings at the 2025 American Society for Radiation Oncology (ASTRO) Annual Meeting, scheduled to be held Sept. 27–Oct. 1 at the Moscone Center in San Francisco. The ASTRO Annual Meeting is recognized as the largest radiation oncology gathering in the […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-experts-present-key-radiation-oncology-findings-at-astro/">Mayo Clinic experts present key radiation oncology findings at ASTRO</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="574" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/1647887_3909974_0017_16x9-1024x574.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-406469" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/1647887_3909974_0017_16x9-1024x574.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/1647887_3909974_0017_16x9-300x168.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/1647887_3909974_0017_16x9-768x431.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/1647887_3909974_0017_16x9-1536x862.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/1647887_3909974_0017_16x9.jpg 1688w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> researchers will present their latest radiation oncology findings at the <a href="https://www.astro.org/meetings-and-education/micro-sites/2025/annual-meeting" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">2025 American Society for Radiation Oncology (ASTRO) Annual Meeting</a>, scheduled to be held Sept. 27–Oct. 1 at the Moscone Center in San Francisco. The ASTRO Annual Meeting is recognized as the largest radiation oncology gathering in the world, and this year's event will feature 14 education sessions and 45 abstracts highlighting Mayo Clinic's advancements in radiation oncology.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic's presentations this year span innovative clinical research, advanced imaging techniques and innovative treatment approaches that are reshaping radiation oncology and diversifying its benefits to patients.</p>



<p>Highlights of the event include:</p>



<p><a href="https://amportal.astro.org/sessions/pro-04-21554/liquid-biopsy-early-detection-of-cancer-106372" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Education Session:</strong></a><strong> </strong>Liquid Biopsy Early Detection of Cancer<br><strong>Presentation time: </strong>Saturday, Sept. 27, 1:17–1:32 p.m. PDT<br><strong>Session title: </strong>PRO 04 - Liquid Biopsies in Cancer<br><strong>Description:</strong> Dr. Aadel Chaudhuri will co-lead this session highlighting Mayo Clinic's leadership in advancing liquid biopsy (circulating tumor DNA, or ctDNA) technologies for cancer care, with a focus on clinical applications in post-treatment monitoring and early detection. The session is designed for clinicians and colleagues, emphasizing practical use, near-term innovations and Mayo's role in shaping precision medicine.<br><strong>PRESENTER: </strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/chaudhuri-aadel-a-m-d-ph-d/bio-20564708" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Aadel Chaudhuri, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, radiation oncologist</p>



<p><a href="https://amportal.astro.org/sessions/ss-05-21603/mid-treatment-ctdna-to-predict-outcomes-in-stage-iib-iiic-nsclc-treated-with-mri-adapted-chem-106753" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Scientific Session:</strong></a><strong> </strong>127 - Mid-Treatment ctDNA to Predict Outcomes in Stage IIB-IIIC NSCLC Treated with MRI-Adapted Chemoradiation<br><strong>Presentation time: </strong>Sunday, Sept. 28, 2:30–2:40 p.m. PDT<br><strong>Session title: </strong>SS 05 - Lung 1: NSCLC Locally Advanced and Oligometastatic<br><strong>Description: </strong>This study showed that a simple, Medicare-covered blood test could help care teams identify — before treatment begins — which patients with stage 3 lung cancer are most likely to benefit from treatment and which may be at higher risk of relapse. Repeating the test during the second week of therapy revealed early signs of whether treatment was working, well before changes appeared on scans. This could potentially create an opportunity to adjust treatment sooner, possibly sparing patients from ineffective therapy and added side effects.<br><strong>PRESENTER: </strong><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/liquid-biopsy-translational-immunogenomics/faculty-staff" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ayesha Hashmi, M.D.</a>, postdoctoral research fellow, Radiation Oncology (senior author is Aadel Chaudhuri, M.D., Ph.D.)</p>



<p><a href="https://amportal.astro.org/sessions/ss-07-21562/early-outcomes-of-a-phase-iii-randomized-controlled-trial-comparing-ultra-hypo-fractionated-5-106426" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Scientific Session:</strong></a><strong> </strong>144 - Early Outcomes of a Phase III Randomized Controlled Trial Comparing Ultra-Hypo Fractionated 5 Fraction Treatment vs. Hypofractionated 15 Fraction Treatment for Patients Receiving Regional Nodal Irradiation<br><strong>Presentation time: </strong>Sunday, Sept. 28, 5:25–5:35 p.m. PDT<br><strong>Session title: </strong>Breast Cancer 1: Redefining Radiation Schedules: Hypofractionation and APBI Across the Breast Cancer Spectrum<br><strong>Description: </strong>This is a phase 3 clinical trial that compared a five-fraction course of regional nodal irradiation to the standard 15 or more fractions used in breast cancer, finding that toxicity, quality of life and implant outcomes were more favorable with the shorter regimen. This supports five treatments as a safe and more convenient alternative.<br><strong>PRESENTER: </strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/vargas-carlos-e-m-d/bio-20123913" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Carlos Vargas, M.D.</a>, radiation oncologist</p>



<p><a href="https://amportal.astro.org/sessions/pqa-03-21637/csf-derived-cfdna-methylation-profiling-to-distinguish-true-progression-from-radiation-necros-107560" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Poster Q&amp;A:</strong></a><strong> </strong>2596 - CSF-Derived cfDNA Methylation Profiling to Distinguish True Progression from Radiation Necrosis and Pseudoprogression in GBM Patients<br><strong>Presentation time: </strong>Monday, Sept. 29, 8–9 a.m. PDT<br><strong>Session title: </strong>PQA 03 - Central Nervous System, Professional Development/Medical Education<br><strong>Description:</strong> This study evaluated whether a test measuring DNA in cerebrospinal fluid could serve as a useful companion to post-radiation imaging in glioblastoma. If effective, this test could help distinguish true tumor progression from treatment-related changes, guiding whether patients need a biopsy or can be safely monitored.<br><strong>PRESENTER: </strong><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/liquid-biopsy-translational-immunogenomics/faculty-staff" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lili Greiner</a>, research assistant, Liquid Biopsy and Translational Immunogenomics Lab (senior author is Aadel Chaudhuri, M.D., Ph.D.)</p>



<p><a href="https://amportal.astro.org/sessions/address-02-21739/presidential-address-109081" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Presidential Address</strong></a><br><strong>Presentation time: </strong>Monday, Sept. 29, 1:02–1:30 p.m. PDT<br><strong>Session title:</strong> Address 02 - Presidential Address<br><strong>Description: </strong>In his presidential address, Dr. Sameer Keole, a Mayo Clinic radiation oncologist, will discuss the meeting's theme, "Rediscovering Radiation Medicine and Exploring New indications," radiation therapy's potential uses for nonmalignant disease and the future of radiation oncology.<br><strong>PRESENTER: </strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/keole-sameer-r-m-d/bio-20055672" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sameer Keole, M.D.</a>, president of ASTRO</p>



<p>Learn more about <a href="https://www.astro.org/meetings-and-education/micro-sites/2025/annual-meeting" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">2025 ASTRO</a>.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and to providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Brittany Cordeiro, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-experts-present-key-radiation-oncology-findings-at-astro/">Mayo Clinic experts present key radiation oncology findings at ASTRO</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/1647887_3909974_0017_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/1647887_3909974_0017_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A:  Should I get screened for prostate cancer?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-should-i-get-screened-for-prostate-cancer/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[pattymiller]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 12:14:04 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Mohammed Solaiman]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=406197</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->QUESTION:&nbsp;I'm a guy in my late 40s and trying to pay more attention to my health. But I'm confused about whether I should be screened for prostate cancer. Can you help? ANSWER:&nbsp;The importance of all health screenings is that they can detect issues early.&nbsp;Prostate cancer&nbsp;is one of the most common cancers in the world, and […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-should-i-get-screened-for-prostate-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A:  Should I get screened for prostate cancer?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/10/middle-aged-man-perhaps-Middle-Eastern-sitting-at-a-home-office-desk-with-computer-monitors-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="middle aged man, perhaps Middle Eastern, sitting at a home office desk with computer monitors" class="wp-image-321567" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/10/middle-aged-man-perhaps-Middle-Eastern-sitting-at-a-home-office-desk-with-computer-monitors-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/10/middle-aged-man-perhaps-Middle-Eastern-sitting-at-a-home-office-desk-with-computer-monitors-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/10/middle-aged-man-perhaps-Middle-Eastern-sitting-at-a-home-office-desk-with-computer-monitors-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/10/middle-aged-man-perhaps-Middle-Eastern-sitting-at-a-home-office-desk-with-computer-monitors-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/10/middle-aged-man-perhaps-Middle-Eastern-sitting-at-a-home-office-desk-with-computer-monitors-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p><strong>QUESTION:&nbsp;</strong>I'm a guy in my late 40s and trying to pay more attention to my health. But I'm confused about whether I should be <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/prostate-cancer-screening-and-treatment/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">screened</a> for prostate cancer. Can you help?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong>&nbsp;The importance of all health screenings is that they can detect issues early.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prostate-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353087?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Prostate cancer</a>&nbsp;is one of the most common cancers in the world, and the second-leading cause of cancer deaths among men in the U.S.&nbsp;</p>



<p>While many prostate cancers grow slowly and remain localized, other types are aggressive and spread quickly. Screening can find prostate cancer early, when it's still confined to the prostate gland. That's when patients have the best chance for successful treatment. If caught early (stage 1), the survival rate after five years is almost 100%. At stage 4, the survival rate is 37% to50% at the five-year mark.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>It's recommended that men begin talking about prostate cancer screening with a healthcare professional around age 50. During this discussion, you and your clinician will decide if the prostate-specific antigen test is right for you based on your personal risk level and age, as well as the chance of overdiagnosis or underdiagnosis, possible biopsy complications, and testing intervals.</p>



<p>The screening is relatively simple. The most common is a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/psa-test/about/pac-20384731?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">prostate-specific antigen, or PSA, test</a>. It's conducted by your primary care clinician once a year. Here's what you need to know about the PSA test:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>It's a blood test used to measure the amount of prostate-specific antigen in your blood.&nbsp;</li>



<li>High levels may indicate the presence of cancer. However, other conditions may also increase this level.</li>



<li>Screening intervals are personalized. Based on test results, men with low long-term risk may decide to discontinue testing or lengthen the time between tests. Those with higher PSA levels may require more frequent screening.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Who's at risk?</strong></h2>



<p>Risk factors include age, family history and race.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Age:</strong>&nbsp;The risk for prostate cancer is highest beginning at age 50 or older.</p>



<p><strong>Family history:</strong>&nbsp;If you have a blood relative who has or has had prostate cancer, a family history of genes such as BRCA1 or BRCA2 that increase the risk of breast cancer, or a strong family history of breast cancer, your risk may be higher.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Race:</strong>&nbsp;In the U.S., prostate cancer is deadlier for Black men than for men of other races. They're more likely to get prostate cancer and more than twice as likely to die from it than other men. Black men should consider being screened starting at age 40.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Active surveillance</strong></h2>



<p>Not all prostate cancers need to be treated — some can remain under&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/active-surveillance-for-prostate-cancer/about/pac-20384946?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">active surveillance</a>. When prostate cancer is found early, it can be watched for many years. If it becomes aggressive, treatment can begin. In active surveillance, regular follow-up tests may be performed to monitor the progression of your cancer.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Treatment options</strong></h2>



<p>Along with active surveillance, a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prostate-cancer/care-at-mayo-clinic/mac-20353097?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">full range</a>&nbsp;of treatments for prostate cancer is available, including radiation, hormone therapy, chemotherapy, cryosurgery and surgery, including robotic removal of all or part of the prostate.</p>



<p>Many patients who have just a few sites of metastatic disease, meaning that the cancer isn't widely spread, also can benefit from aggressive treatment. This treatment combines radiation and oral or IV cancer medication therapy to put the cancer into remission and extend the patient's life.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Another radiation technique includes intensity-modulated&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/home/orc-20185488">proton b</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/home/orc-20185488?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">e</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/home/orc-20185488" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">am therapy</a>&nbsp;with pencil beam scanning. This localized treatment can minimize significant adverse events from the treatment.</p>



<p>Talk with your healthcare professional to learn more about prostate cancer screening and if it's right for you.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/mohammed-solaiman-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Mohammed Solaiman, M.D.</em></a><em>, Family Medicine, Mayo Clinic Health System</em>, <em>St. Peter, Minnesota</em></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-should-i-get-screened-for-prostate-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A:  Should I get screened for prostate cancer?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/10/middle-aged-man-perhaps-Middle-Eastern-sitting-at-a-home-office-desk-with-computer-monitors-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/10/middle-aged-man-perhaps-Middle-Eastern-sitting-at-a-home-office-desk-with-computer-monitors-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Mohammed Solaiman]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>10 years, 10,000 lives: Mayo experts highlight the journey and future of proton beam and particle therapy at Mayo Clinic</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/10-years-10000-lives-mayo-experts-highlight-the-journey-and-future-of-proton-beam-and-particle-therapy-at-mayo-clinic/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Jessica Saenz]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 13:06:12 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Anita Mahajan]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Nadia Laack]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=406131</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn.&nbsp;—&nbsp;A decade after opening, the&nbsp;Mayo Clinic Proton Therapy Program­&nbsp;in Rochester, Minnesota, has treated 10,000 patients. Annually, the program treats 30%–40% more patients than most comparable centers in the country. And, with&nbsp;new technology&nbsp;and facility expansions, it will soon be able to treat nearly 75% more patients each year with even more precise and effective therapies. […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/10-years-10000-lives-mayo-experts-highlight-the-journey-and-future-of-proton-beam-and-particle-therapy-at-mayo-clinic/">10 years, 10,000 lives: Mayo experts highlight the journey and future of proton beam and particle therapy at Mayo Clinic</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Proton-beam-therapy-patient-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Patient receiving proton beam therapy" class="wp-image-406139" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Proton-beam-therapy-patient-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Proton-beam-therapy-patient-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Proton-beam-therapy-patient-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Proton-beam-therapy-patient-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Proton-beam-therapy-patient-16-x-9.jpg 1604w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn.<strong>&nbsp;</strong>—<strong>&nbsp;</strong>A decade after opening, the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/home/orc-20185488" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proton Therapy Program</a>­&nbsp;in Rochester, Minnesota, has treated 10,000 patients. Annually, the program treats 30%–40% more patients than most comparable centers in the country. And, with&nbsp;<a href="https://mayomagazine.mayoclinic.org/2024/10/carbon-ion-therapy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">new technology</a>&nbsp;and facility expansions, it will soon be able to treat nearly 75% more patients each year with even more precise and effective therapies.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/laack-nadia-n-m-d/bio-20054933" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nadia Laack, M.D.</a>, chair of the Department of Radiation Oncology at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mahajan-anita-m-d/bio-20358158" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Anita Mahajan, M.D.</a>,&nbsp;radiation oncologist and medical director of Mayo Clinic’s particle therapy center,&nbsp;discuss how Mayo is using tomorrow's standard of care today.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A bold step toward precision and efficiency</strong></h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic took a bold step by launching its program in 2015 with pencil beam scanning — an ultranarrow beam that conforms its radiation dose to the shape of the tumor. This allowed a focus on accuracy for complex tumors, many of which were considered untreatable due to their location.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic, with technology vendors, has continued to elevate this therapy by developing precise tracking technology such as its custom eye-tracking device for&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/eye-melanoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20372371" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">melanoma of the eye</a>.</p>



<p>The team's high level of fine-tuning extends to its scheduling. "Most proton systems have one accelerator for four rooms, treating only one at a time," explains Dr. Mahajan. "A patient could be set up in their room, but waiting an hour."</p>



<p>To solve this, Dr. Mahajan helped develop a system that radiation therapists use to communicate and coordinate beam use to minimize patient wait time and discomfort and allow more patients to be treated.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Locking in on a moving target</strong></h2>



<p>Heartbeats and breathing create constant movement in the body, making chest and abdominal tumors a moving target and previously impossible to treat safely.</p>



<p>"With our colleagues in Arizona and the vendor, we developed a way to track lung tumors to ensure the beam only turns on when it's within target," says Dr. Laack.</p>



<p>This technology helped extend proton beam therapy's effectiveness beyond cancer.</p>



<p>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-utilizing-proton-beam-radiation-for-dangerous-heart-rhythms/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cardiac ablation with proton beam</a>&nbsp;is an example of how we've taken everything to the next level," says Dr. Laack. "Our physicists and the Department of Cardiovascular Medicine developed tools that now allow us to confidently and accurately deliver radiation doses to the heart."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Automating an improved patient experience</strong></h2>



<p>Mobility restrictions and constant adjustment can be&nbsp;uncomfortable&nbsp;and time-consuming for patients. They can slow down treatment. Regular bodily functions, including gas, bowel movements and fluid retention, also require ongoing rescanning and radiation plan adjustments for treatment accuracy.</p>



<p>Plan adjustments previously delayed treatment by several days. Automation has helped reduce turnaround time to just one day.</p>



<p>"It's remarkable to have next-day planning because of automation," adds Dr. Laack. "But we can imagine a future where patients lie down comfortably, and we scan and treat them with a custom plan tailored to their current anatomy."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Building on a future-ready foundation</strong></h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic is amid a leap forward in heavy particle therapy, decades in the making.</p>



<p>"For 20 years, we've studied data and deepened our understanding of tumor genetics so we could offer the most comprehensive treatment portfolio," says Dr. Laack.</p>



<p>This commitment manifested in the June 2025 opening of the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-takes-the-next-step-in-making-heavy-particle-therapy-available-in-the-western-hemisphere-for-patients-with-aggressive-cancers/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Duan Family Building</a>&nbsp;in Jacksonville, Florida. The building will house the first carbon ion therapy facility in the Americas and introduce powerful radiation delivery for complex and proton-beam- resistant tumors.</p>



<p>In August 2025, the Andersen Building in Rochester also reached a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E64A1WxCx0w" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">major milestone</a>, adding 360-degree gantry technology that delivers proton beam within a millimeter of accuracy and real-time CT imaging to enable faster, more precise treatment for nearly twice as many patients.</p>



<p>"It's an engineering marvel that represents innovation, collaboration and hope," says Dr. Laack. "It's the promise that every patient who walks through our doors will receive the most precise, personalized and compassionate care available anywhere in the world."</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and to providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Brittany Cordeiro, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/10-years-10000-lives-mayo-experts-highlight-the-journey-and-future-of-proton-beam-and-particle-therapy-at-mayo-clinic/">10 years, 10,000 lives: Mayo experts highlight the journey and future of proton beam and particle therapy at Mayo Clinic</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Proton-beam-therapy-patient-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Proton-beam-therapy-patient-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Anita Mahajan]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Nadia Laack]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Get the facts on ovarian cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-get-the-facts-on-ovarian-cancer/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[pattymiller]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 12:33:49 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Sandeep Basu]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=406011</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;I've heard that ovarian cancer is hard to detect. Can you tell me more about the symptoms and if there are any screenings? ANSWER:&nbsp;Ovarian cancer is relatively rare. However, it's often fatal in later stages of the disease. The cancer begins in the ovaries and spreads to the abdomen and pelvis if it […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-get-the-facts-on-ovarian-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Get the facts on ovarian cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-middle-aged-white-woman-worried-concerned-with-her-head-in-her-hands-looking-at-a-computer-laptop-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="a middle-aged white woman worried, concerned with her head in her hands looking at a computer laptop" class="wp-image-319485" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-middle-aged-white-woman-worried-concerned-with-her-head-in-her-hands-looking-at-a-computer-laptop-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-middle-aged-white-woman-worried-concerned-with-her-head-in-her-hands-looking-at-a-computer-laptop-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-middle-aged-white-woman-worried-concerned-with-her-head-in-her-hands-looking-at-a-computer-laptop-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-middle-aged-white-woman-worried-concerned-with-her-head-in-her-hands-looking-at-a-computer-laptop-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-middle-aged-white-woman-worried-concerned-with-her-head-in-her-hands-looking-at-a-computer-laptop-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;</strong>I've heard that <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/ovarian-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20375941" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ovarian cancer</a> is hard to detect. Can you tell me more about the symptoms and if there are any screenings?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:&nbsp;</strong>Ovarian cancer is relatively rare. However, it's often fatal in later stages of the disease. The cancer begins in the ovaries and spreads to the abdomen and pelvis if it isn't diagnosed and treated early. It primarily affects older women; about half of those diagnosed are age 63 or older.</p>



<p>Here are some statistics for ovarian cancer:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>In the U.S., it's the second-most common female reproductive organ cancer after uterine cancer.</li>



<li>The risk of getting ovarian cancer in a woman's lifetime is about 1 in 91. Nearly 21,000 women are diagnosed with ovarian cancer every year.</li>



<li>Roughly 250 women die of this disease each week.</li>



<li>Even though uterine cancer is 3 times more common, the number of women dying from ovarian cancer each year is almost the same (around 13,000 deaths). This death rate points to the difficulty of detecting this aggressive form of cancer.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Recognizing the symptoms</strong></h2>



<p>As with any cancer, early diagnosis of ovarian cancer can improve the chances of successful treatment. If you are experiencing these symptoms, see your healthcare clinician:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Quickly feeling full when eating</li>



<li>Abdominal bloating or swelling</li>



<li>Weight loss</li>



<li>Frequent need to urinate</li>



<li>Changes in bowel habits</li>



<li>Discomfort in the pelvic area</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Understanding the risk factors</strong></h2>



<p>A family history of ovarian cancer and personal factors can increase your risk of ovarian cancer, including:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Obesity</li>



<li>Hormone replacement therapy</li>



<li>Personal history of cancer or endometriosis</li>



<li>Increasing age or reproductive history and infertility</li>
</ul>



<p>Some factors that can decrease your risk include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Oral contraceptive use</li>



<li>Pregnancy and breastfeeding</li>



<li>Removal of the ovaries and fallopian tubes</li>



<li>Hysterectomy or tubal ligation<br></li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Detecting ovarian cancer</strong></h2>



<p>There are well-established screening programs for certain cancers, such as breast, colon and cervical cancer, which can help prevent these cancers from developing. Screening also can detect cancer at an early stage when treatments are more effective.</p>



<p>Unfortunately, there isn't a universal screening program for ovarian cancer. That's because testing options often lead to high rates of false-positive and false-negative results. Also, ovarian cancer doesn't predictably develop precancerous cells, and it's difficult to get tissue samples from the ovaries.</p>



<p>The most relevant tools for finding ovarian cancer are imaging tests, such as an ultrasound, and tumor markers that can be found in the blood, such as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ca-125-test/about/pac-20393295" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer antigen 125</a>, or&nbsp;CA 125.</p>



<p>Ultrasounds are good at identifying cysts or other masses growing on the ovaries. The challenging part is that these masses are quite common, and most are not cancers. While the appearance of an ovarian mass can give some clues about its chance of being cancerous, with an ultrasound, it's often difficult to tell the difference between masses that are cancers and those that aren't.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What is CA 125?</strong></h2>



<p>CA 125 is a protein in the blood that can be elevated when ovarian cancers are present. However, it also can be elevated with other conditions, such as menstruation, uterine fibroids and endometriosis, leading to false-positive results.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Early detection is the goal of a good screening program, but CA 125 can miss a significant number of early-stage ovarian cancers.</p>



<p>Ultrasounds and CA 125 tests have been evaluated as potential screening tools. Unfortunately, they can't consistently detect ovarian cancer early enough to improve patient outcomes. They also have a high false-positive result rate, increasing the risk of unnecessary stress, anxiety and surgery.</p>



<p>However, in some situations, these tests are used to screen for ovarian cancer, such as in patients with genetic mutations that put them at high risk for cancer and in patients previously treated for ovarian cancer.</p>



<p><em>By&nbsp;</em><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/sandeep-basu-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Sandeep Basu, M.D.,</em></a><em>&nbsp;Breast Cancer Care, Hematology and Oncology, Mayo Clinic Health System, Eau Claire, Wisconsin</em></p>



<p><strong>Related post:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-capture-first-signs-of-ovarian-cancer-risk/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic researchers capture first signs of ovarian cancer risk</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-get-the-facts-on-ovarian-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Get the facts on ovarian cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-middle-aged-white-woman-worried-concerned-with-her-head-in-her-hands-looking-at-a-computer-laptop-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-middle-aged-white-woman-worried-concerned-with-her-head-in-her-hands-looking-at-a-computer-laptop-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Sandeep Basu]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New genetic biomarker flags aggressive brain tumors</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-genetic-biomarker-flags-aggressive-brain-tumors/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[mbroadfoot]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 22:31:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Discovery Science]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Neurosciences]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Gelareh Zadeh]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=405928</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — Clinicians typically classify meningiomas — the most common type of brain tumor — into three grades, ranging from slow-growing to aggressive. But a new multi-institutional study suggests that appearances may be deceiving. If a tumor shows activity in a gene called telomerase reverse transcriptase (TERT), it tends to recur more quickly, even […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-genetic-biomarker-flags-aggressive-brain-tumors/">New genetic biomarker flags aggressive brain tumors</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/meningioma-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Black and white brain scan image of a meningioma" class="wp-image-405943" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/meningioma-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/meningioma-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/meningioma-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/meningioma-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/meningioma-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p><br>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Clinicians typically classify meningiomas — the most common type of brain tumor — into three grades, ranging from slow-growing to aggressive.</p>



<p>But a new multi-institutional study suggests that appearances may be deceiving. If a tumor shows activity in a gene called telomerase reverse transcriptase (TERT), it tends to recur more quickly, even if it looks low-grade under the microscope.</p>



<div class="wp-block-group is-nowrap is-layout-flex wp-container-core-group-is-layout-6c531013 wp-block-group-is-layout-flex">
<p>The findings, published Sept. 1 in <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanonc/article/PIIS1470-2045(25)00267-0/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lancet Oncology</a>, could significantly change how doctors diagnose and treat meningiomas.</p>
</div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="937" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Zadeh-Gelareh-937x1024.jpg" alt="Photo of Mayo Clinic neurosurgeon Gelareh Zadeh, M.D., Ph.D." class="wp-image-405939" style="width:208px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Zadeh-Gelareh-937x1024.jpg 937w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Zadeh-Gelareh-274x300.jpg 274w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Zadeh-Gelareh-768x839.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Zadeh-Gelareh-1405x1536.jpg 1405w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Zadeh-Gelareh-1874x2048.jpg 1874w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 937px) 100vw, 937px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Gelareh Zadeh, M.D., Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"High TERT expression is strongly linked to faster disease progression," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/zadeh-gelareh-m-d-ph-d/bio-20579723" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gelareh Zadeh, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, a neurosurgeon at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> and senior author of the study. "This makes it a promising new biomarker for identifying patients who may be at greater risk of developing aggressive disease."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>An early warning sign</strong></h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/meningioma/symptoms-causes/syc-20355643" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Meningiomas</a> — tumors of the meninges, the protective tissue that surrounds the brain and spinal cord — are generally considered benign. But a small subset of these tumors has a mutation in the TERT gene, which is linked to faster growth and a shorter time before the tumor returns after treatment.</p>



<p>TERT is the active part of telomerase, an enzyme that maintains telomeres, the protective ends of chromosomes. In most healthy adult cells, TERT is switched off. But if it becomes switched back on, it can fuel cancer development by driving unchecked cell growth.</p>



<p>In this study, the researchers wanted to see whether high TERT expression, even in the absence of the TERT genetic mutation, also predicted worse outcomes. They looked at more than 1,200 meningiomas from patients across Canada, Germany and the U.S., and they found that nearly one-third of them had high TERT expression despite not having the mutation.</p>



<p>These patients had earlier tumor regrowth compared to those without TERT expression, though their outcomes were better than patients with full-blown TERT mutations.</p>



<p>"TERT-positive tumors behaved like they were one grade worse than their official diagnosis," says Dr. Zadeh. "For example, a grade 1 tumor with TERT expression acted more like a grade 2."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Guiding treatment decisions</strong></h2>



<p>The findings suggest that testing for TERT activity could help doctors predict which patients are at higher risk for recurrence and may need closer monitoring or more intensive treatment.</p>



<p>"Because meningiomas are the most common primary brain tumor, this biomarker could influence how thousands of patients are diagnosed and managed worldwide," says Dr. Zadeh.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="819" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/ChloeGuiMayoHeadshot-819x1024.jpg" alt="Photo of Mayo Clinic research collaborator Chloe Gui, M.D." class="wp-image-405944" style="width:204px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/ChloeGuiMayoHeadshot-819x1024.jpg 819w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/ChloeGuiMayoHeadshot-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/ChloeGuiMayoHeadshot-768x960.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/ChloeGuiMayoHeadshot-1229x1536.jpg 1229w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/ChloeGuiMayoHeadshot-1638x2048.jpg 1638w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 819px) 100vw, 819px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Chloe Gui, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"TERT expression can help us more accurately identify patients with aggressive meningiomas," Chloe Gui, M.D., a neurosurgery resident at the University of Toronto, Mayo Clinic research collaborator and the study's lead author, explains on a <a href="https://www.buzzsprout.com/1391338?client_source=large_player&amp;iframe=true&amp;referrer=https://www.buzzsprout.com/1391338.js?container_id=buzzsprout-large-player&amp;player=large#" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">podcast hosted by The Lancet Oncology</a>. "This information allows us to offer treatment tailored to the tumor's behavior." "This information allows us to offer treatment tailored to the tumor's behavior."</p>



<p>The team is currently investigating ways to incorporate TERT expression into the clinical workflow. The research is part of a larger effort at Mayo Clinic called the Precure initiative, focused on developing tools that empower clinicians to predict and intercept biological processes before they evolve into disease or progress into complex, hard-to-treat conditions.</p>



<p>Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanonc/article/PIIS1470-2045(25)00267-0/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&nbsp;</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and to providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact: </strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Tia Ford, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-genetic-biomarker-flags-aggressive-brain-tumors/">New genetic biomarker flags aggressive brain tumors</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/meningioma-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/meningioma-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Gelareh Zadeh]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Shorter, less intense radiation-chemo regimen effective for HPV-linked oropharyngeal cancer, Mayo study shows</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/shorter-less-intense-radiation-chemo-regimen-effective-for-hpv-linked-oropharyngeal-cancer-mayo-study-shows/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Kelley Luckstein]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 22:30:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Chemotherapy]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Daniel Ma]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[human papillomavirus (HPV)]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[minimally invasive surgery]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[radiation]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=405823</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — A Mayo Clinic study finds that a shortened, less intense course of radiation and chemotherapy after minimally invasive surgery for HPV-positive oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma (HPV+OPSCC) results in less toxicity, substantially lowering the rates of treatment-related side effects while maintaining high cure rates. The findings were published in The Lancet Oncology. "This […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/shorter-less-intense-radiation-chemo-regimen-effective-for-hpv-linked-oropharyngeal-cancer-mayo-study-shows/">Shorter, less intense radiation-chemo regimen effective for HPV-linked oropharyngeal cancer, Mayo study shows</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="682" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/chemotherapy-drug-being-administered-intravenously-by-a-nurse_1552844_3779313_0064-1024x682.jpg" alt="chemotherapy drug being administered intravenously by a nurse" class="wp-image-405971" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/chemotherapy-drug-being-administered-intravenously-by-a-nurse_1552844_3779313_0064-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/chemotherapy-drug-being-administered-intravenously-by-a-nurse_1552844_3779313_0064-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/chemotherapy-drug-being-administered-intravenously-by-a-nurse_1552844_3779313_0064-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/chemotherapy-drug-being-administered-intravenously-by-a-nurse_1552844_3779313_0064-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/chemotherapy-drug-being-administered-intravenously-by-a-nurse_1552844_3779313_0064.jpg 1688w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> study finds that a shortened, less intense course of radiation and chemotherapy after minimally invasive surgery for HPV-positive <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/throat-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20366462" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">oropharyngeal</a> squamous cell carcinoma (HPV+OPSCC) results in less toxicity, substantially lowering the rates of treatment-related side effects while maintaining high cure rates. The findings were published in <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanonc/article/PIIS1470-2045(25)00324-9/abstract" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">The Lancet Oncology</a>.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Daniel-Ma_1659198_3934950_0007-300x200.jpg" alt="Portrait of Dr. Daniel Ma" class="wp-image-405969" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Daniel-Ma_1659198_3934950_0007-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Daniel-Ma_1659198_3934950_0007-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Daniel-Ma_1659198_3934950_0007-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Daniel-Ma_1659198_3934950_0007-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Daniel-Ma_1659198_3934950_0007.jpg 1688w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Daniel Ma, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"This is a game-changer for patients," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/ma-daniel-j-m-d/bio-10031781" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Daniel Ma, M.D.</a>, senior author of the study and head and neck radiation oncologist at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>. "We've significantly reduced the burden of long-term side effects without compromising the effectiveness of the treatment. This shorter, less intensive regimen allows patients to return to their lives more quickly and with a better quality of life."</p>



<p>Standard treatments for HPV-related oropharyngeal cancer typically involve seven weeks of daily radiation and chemotherapy, or surgery followed by six weeks of radiation and chemotherapy. While highly effective, these treatments often lead to significant long-term side effects due to high toxicity, such as jawbone failure, dry mouth, changes in taste and challenges with swallowing. "These greatly affect the quality of life for patients, many of whom are young, in their 40s and 50s," says Dr. Ma.</p>



<p>In the randomized phase 3 study, Mayo Clinic researchers compared the standard treatment to a new approach involving minimally invasive transoral surgery followed by a two-week course of gentler radiation therapy called de-escalated regimen of adjuvant radiotherapy (DART). DART uses about half as much radiation and a reduced dose of chemotherapy, one-fifth of the standard dose.</p>



<p>The results demonstrated that the less intensive treatment approach significantly reduced both severe (grade 3 or higher) and moderate (grade 2) toxicities, indicating fewer adverse events and improved symptom burden for patients following treatment. Importantly, disease control rates were comparable to the standard treatment for intermediate-risk patients.</p>



<p>For specific high-risk patients, namely those with five or more lymph nodes and disease extending outside of the lymph nodes, the standard treatment showed slightly better disease control, potentially due to chemotherapy-related factors rather than radiation. The researchers add that these patients should still receive the standard six-week treatment.</p>



<p>The study involved 228 patients treated at Mayo Clinic in Minnesota and Arizona. The researchers say that this study represents the largest cohort of postsurgical de-escalation patients in the published literature.</p>



<p>Further, ongoing research will continue to explore using biomarkers such as circulating DNA to find the best patient populations for this treatment strategy.</p>



<p>Review the <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanonc/article/PIIS1470-2045(25)00324-9/abstract" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">paper</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&nbsp;</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic<br></strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong> </p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/shorter-less-intense-radiation-chemo-regimen-effective-for-hpv-linked-oropharyngeal-cancer-mayo-study-shows/">Shorter, less intense radiation-chemo regimen effective for HPV-linked oropharyngeal cancer, Mayo study shows</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/chemotherapy-drug-being-administered-intravenously-by-a-nurse_1552844_3779313_0064_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/chemotherapy-drug-being-administered-intravenously-by-a-nurse_1552844_3779313_0064_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Chemotherapy]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Daniel Ma]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[human papillomavirus (HPV)]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[minimally invasive surgery]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[radiation]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Reconnect with exercise during cancer treatment</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-reconnect-with-exercise-during-cancer-treatment/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[pattymiller]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 12:49:47 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q&A]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=405702</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC: I've always been active, but after being diagnosed with breast cancer and starting my treatment, I'm a little worried about getting back into my routine. Is it OK to exercise during cancer treatment? ANSWER: Exercise decreases the risk of developing cancer. Studies have shown there is a 30%- 35% reduction in the […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-reconnect-with-exercise-during-cancer-treatment/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Reconnect with exercise during cancer treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1604" height="902" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/exercise-woman-gym-16-x-9.jpg" alt="middle-aged woman on a machine at gym exercising, exercise, African American," class="wp-image-405709" style="width:758px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/exercise-woman-gym-16-x-9.jpg 1604w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/exercise-woman-gym-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/exercise-woman-gym-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/exercise-woman-gym-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/exercise-woman-gym-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1604px) 100vw, 1604px"></figure>


<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: </strong>I've always been active, but after being diagnosed with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a> and starting my treatment, I'm a little worried about getting back into my routine. Is it OK to exercise during cancer treatment?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER: </strong>Exercise <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/adult-health/in-depth/cancer-prevention/art-20044816" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">decreases</a> the risk of developing cancer. Studies have shown there is a 30%- 35% reduction in the risk of breast cancer among the most physically active women compared with those who are least active. Exercise also plays a protective role in many other cancers, including lung, endometrial, colon, kidney, bladder and esophageal<strong>.</strong></p>



<p>However, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/in-depth/cancer-survivor/art-20044015" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">exercise</a> can also be helpful during and after cancer treatment. According to the American Cancer Society, research shows that exercise during cancer treatment can improve physical functioning and quality of life.</p>



<p>Moderate exercise can:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Increase strength and endurance.</li>



<li>Strengthen the cardiovascular system.</li>



<li>Reduce depression.</li>



<li>Decrease anxiety.</li>



<li>Diminish fatigue.</li>



<li>Improve mood.</li>



<li>Raise self-esteem.</li>



<li>Lessen pain.</li>



<li>Improve sleep.</li>
</ul>



<p>Of course, there may be certain issues that prevent or affect a person's ability to exercise due to disease or type of treatment, including:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Anemia — having a low number of red blood cells or quantity of hemoglobin or protein.</li>



<li>Weak immune system.</li>



<li>Some forms of radiation treatment.</li>



<li>Some surgeries limit certain exercises.</li>
</ul>



<p>Some people should use extra care to reduce the risk of injury, including <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-aging-and-the-benefits-of-exercising/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">older people</a> and those with bone disease, arthritis, or nerve damage, also called peripheral neuropathy.</p>



<p>Exciting studies show that regular physical activity is linked to increased life expectancy after a cancer diagnosis. In many cases, it also decreases the risk of cancer recurrence. Multiple studies in cancer survivors, with the strongest evidence in breast and colon cancer survivors, have suggested that physically active cancer survivors have a lower risk of cancer recurrence and improved survival compared with those who are inactive.</p>



<p>The American Cancer Society, the American Institute for Cancer Research, the American College of Sports Medicine, and the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services all advocate physical activity for cancer patients and survivors.</p>



<p>The American Cancer Society recommends cancer survivors take these actions:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Participate in regular physical activity.</li>



<li>Avoid inactivity and return to normal daily activities as soon as possible after diagnosis.</li>



<li>Exercise at least 150 minutes per week.</li>



<li>Include strength training exercises at least two days per week.</li>
</ul>



<p>Not everyone is ready to head to the gym during or after cancer therapy. However, reconnecting with an activity you like to do can increase your enjoyment and ability to stick with an exercise program. Exercise may include a bike ride with friends or chasing your dog around the park.</p>



<p>Walking is a great activity for almost everyone, and swimming can be a wonderful alternative for those with joint issues. Yoga is fantastic for strengthening, flexibility and balance concerns.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/kaye-sturz-np" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Kaye Sturz,</em></a><em> D.N.P., Hematology/Oncology, Mayo Clinic Health System, Eau Claire, Wisconsin</em></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-reconnect-with-exercise-during-cancer-treatment/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Reconnect with exercise during cancer treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/exercise-woman-gym-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/exercise-woman-gym-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers discover ‘hidden pocket’ in cancer-promoting enzyme</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-discover-hidden-pocket-in-cancer-promoting-enzyme/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Kate Ledger]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 11:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Florida]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Evette Radisky]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=405573</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->For years, cancer researchers have been trying to halt a type of molecule that's involved in several cancers. The molecules — enzymes known as trypsins — split proteins that help tumors grow and spread. Mayo Clinic cancer biologist Evette Radisky, Ph.D., previously found that one trypsin, called mesotrypsin, plays a role in breast, prostate, pancreatic […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-discover-hidden-pocket-in-cancer-promoting-enzyme/">Mayo Clinic researchers discover ‘hidden pocket’ in cancer-promoting enzyme</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="538" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Mesotrypsin.crypticpocket-1024x538.png" alt="A computational rendering of mesotrypsin shows the enzyme's active site (yellow) and the nearby cryptic pocket (green). The pocket is exposed temporarily when the purple region moves, stabilizing the enzyme in an inactive state." class="wp-image-405583" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Mesotrypsin.crypticpocket-1024x538.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Mesotrypsin.crypticpocket-300x158.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Mesotrypsin.crypticpocket-768x404.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Mesotrypsin.crypticpocket-1536x807.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Mesotrypsin.crypticpocket.png 1640w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">A computational rendering of mesotrypsin shows the enzyme's active site (yellow) and the nearby cryptic pocket (green). The pocket is exposed temporarily when the purple region moves, stabilizing the enzyme in an inactive state.</figcaption>



<p><br>For years, cancer researchers have been trying to halt a type of molecule that's involved in several cancers. The molecules — enzymes known as trypsins — split proteins that help tumors grow and spread.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="450" height="600" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Evette-Radisky.vert_.crop_.jpg" alt="Portrait of Dr. Evette Radisky" class="wp-image-405578" style="width:270px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Evette-Radisky.vert_.crop_.jpg 450w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Evette-Radisky.vert_.crop_-225x300.jpg 225w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Evette Radisky, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Mayo Clinic cancer biologist <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/radisky-evette-s-ph-d/bio-00094471" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Evette Radisky, Ph.D.</a>, previously found that one trypsin, called mesotrypsin, plays a role in breast, prostate, pancreatic and lung cancer. Like other enzymes, the molecule has an active site that kicks off reactions with other molecules. Researchers have tried to block the active site but haven’t found a molecule with a specific enough lock-and-key fit to jam the active region.</p>



<p>Recently, however, Dr. Radisky's lab at Mayo Clinic in Florida discovered a new way to block mesotrypsin. They found a "hidden pocket" in the molecule.</p>



<p>"The hidden pocket is separate from the active site, but we found that blocking it has a similar effect of locking the enzyme in an inactive state," says Dr. Radisky, principal investigator of the study that appeared in <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adu9129" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Science Advances</a>. The team now is taking steps to discover drugs that fit the hidden pocket.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A mystery in the data</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="667" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Coban-Mathew-A._16094085_202109280353.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-405580" style="width:276px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Coban-Mathew-A._16094085_202109280353.jpg 667w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Coban-Mathew-A._16094085_202109280353-250x300.jpg 250w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 667px) 100vw, 667px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mathew Coban</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"It was a serendipitous finding," says the study’s lead author, Mathew Coban, of the pocket's discovery. As a research technologist in the Radisky lab and a master's degree student at <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a>, Coban had aimed to understand the structure of mesotrypsin through X-ray crystallography.</p>



<p>The complex technique, which records scattered X-rays as shadows, can describe the overall folds of amino acids in the enzyme and suggest complementary molecules that fit like a puzzle. While reviewing the X-ray crystallography results, Coban noticed a segment of the enzyme that looked out of place. The research team thought it might be an error in the data and set the results aside.</p>



<p>But Coban continued to wonder about the strange area. He had the idea to begin looking for alternate nooks in the mesotrypsin enzyme that could potentially contribute to a stable, non-active enzyme.</p>



<p>What Coban found was a site that was hidden. The team dubbed it a "cryptic pocket." The pocket, adjacent to the active site, opened at moments when mesotrypsin stabilized itself. The next step was clear. "If the pocket is there some of the time, maybe a drug would be able to bind at that site and trap the enzyme in its inactive state," he says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Finding a drug that binds</strong></h2>



<p>The team worked with a colleague, Thomas Caulfield, Ph.D., a former Mayo researcher and drug discovery expert, to conduct a computational screen of potential drug compounds that might fit in the cryptic pocket. They found a single molecule that could bind in the cryptic pocket and inhibit the activity of mesotrypsin.</p>



<p>Importantly, the researchers note, the molecule blocks mesotrypsin selectively, without affecting other trypsins. This could mean less toxicity or fewer side effects for a patient. The finding also means that other cryptic pockets may exist in other trypsin molecules related to cancer, presenting new potential drug targets. &nbsp;</p>



<p>The team is continuing to look for drug molecules that fit mesotrypsin even better. "Based on the structural information of mesotrypsin that we have now, we've been able to do more computational prediction to identify additional, more potent compounds that we’re now testing in the laboratory," says Dr. Radisky.</p>



<p>"This has been an important step in the understanding of this key enzyme. Our next steps will be to start testing how well our candidate drug molecules fit the cryptic pocket and block cancer invasion and metastasis in models of disease," she says.</p>



<p><em>The study was funded by grants from the National Institutes of Health, Mayo Clinic Medical Scientist Training Program and Department of Energy Office of Science User Facility. &nbsp;The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-discover-hidden-pocket-in-cancer-promoting-enzyme/">Mayo Clinic researchers discover ‘hidden pocket’ in cancer-promoting enzyme</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Mesotrypsin_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Mesotrypsin_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Evette Radisky]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</atom:link></channel>
</rss> 