<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org">

<channel>
	<title>Cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml">
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastbuilddate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 19:48:05 +0000</lastbuilddate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updateperiod>
	hourly	</sy:updateperiod>
	<sy:updatefrequency>
	1	</sy:updatefrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Is stomach cancer on the rise in young adults?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-is-stomach-cancer-on-the-rise-in-young-adults/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Chloe Corey]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 11:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Gastroenterology]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Cycle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Surgery]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Travis Grotz]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[stomach cancer]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407736</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;My 39-year-old brother was just diagnosed with gastric cancer. The diagnosis was especially shocking because of his age. Is this becoming more common? Does age affect the approaches to treatment? ANSWER:&nbsp;Stomach cancer, also referred to as gastric cancer, was once thought of as a disease of older adults. However, it is increasingly affecting […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-is-stomach-cancer-on-the-rise-in-young-adults/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Is stomach cancer on the rise in young adults?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/11/an-adult-man-and-boy-walking-on-a-hike-near-the-beach-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="an adult man and boy walking on a hike near the beach" class="wp-image-105592" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/11/an-adult-man-and-boy-walking-on-a-hike-near-the-beach-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/11/an-adult-man-and-boy-walking-on-a-hike-near-the-beach-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/11/an-adult-man-and-boy-walking-on-a-hike-near-the-beach-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong>&nbsp;My 39-year-old brother was just diagnosed with <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-stomach-cancer-concerns/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gastric cancer</a>. The diagnosis was especially shocking because of his age. Is this becoming more common? Does age affect the approaches to treatment?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:&nbsp;</strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stomach-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352438" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stomach cancer</a>, also referred to as gastric cancer, was once thought of as a disease of older adults. However, it is increasingly affecting people under the age of 50, mirroring a similar shift that is observed with colorectal and other gastrointestinal cancers. It's important to note that while this shift in early-onset stomach cancer is unsettling, the overall incidence of stomach cancer remains relatively stable.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A changing risk profile</strong></h2>



<p>Researchers are investigating the reasons behind these trends, and several factors appear to play a role.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Diet is among the most likely contributors to the increase in early-onset stomach cancer. Over the past several decades, the typical American diet has shifted dramatically toward ultra-processed foods. These foods can promote chronic inflammation and alter the gut microbiome, which is the ecosystem of microbes that live in your intestines. The microbiome supports digestive health. Both inflammation and microbiome changes have been linked to a greater risk of developing gastrointestinal cancers over time. Other possible mechanisms include direct DNA damage and carcinogenesis from harmful food additives, as well as the displacement of protective nutrients such as fiber, vitamins and antioxidants.</p>



<p>Traditional risk factors for stomach cancer remain relevant as well.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/h-pylori/symptoms-causes/syc-20356171" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Infection with Helicobacter pylori</a>, a bacterium that can cause inflammation of the stomach lining or ulcers, is a significant risk factor. Smoking, frequent consumption of smoked or preserved foods, obesity and heavy alcohol use can also increase risk.</p>



<p>Younger people diagnosed with stomach cancer often lack these classic risk factors, making their diagnoses more perplexing. This difference has prompted increased attention to lifestyle, dietary and environmental influences that might contribute to the disease.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The challenge of early detection for stomach cancer</strong></h2>



<p>Early detection of stomach cancer remains difficult, particularly in younger adults. The symptoms of this disease can be subtle, including persistent indigestion, bloating, and mild upper abdominal pain or heartburn that does not respond to over-the-counter remedies. These nonspecific symptoms are often mistaken for minor gastrointestinal issues.</p>



<p>When symptoms persist for several weeks or when additional warning signs appear, such as unexplained weight loss, vomiting or severe abdominal pain, further evaluation is needed.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stomach-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352443" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">An upper endoscopy with biopsy</a>&nbsp;is the standard method for diagnosing stomach cancer.</p>



<p>Because early symptoms may be overlooked, younger patients are sometimes diagnosed at more advanced stages of the disease.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Treatment approaches and innovations</strong></h2>



<p>Treatment for stomach cancer depends on the tumor's stage, location and molecular characteristics rather than the patient's age.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Surgery remains a cornerstone of care for localized disease. In recent years, surgical techniques have advanced significantly, with more minimally invasive and robotic approaches that can reduce recovery time and improve long-term quality of life. In addition to these less invasive techniques, novel reconstructive procedures, such as J-pouch and double-tract reconstructions, are helping restore digestive function and reduce long-term complications after partial or total removal of the stomach. These approaches aim to improve nutrition absorption, reduce reflux and help patients return to eating habits that more closely resemble those before their diagnosis.</p>



<p>Oncologists can also analyze tumors for biomarkers such as HER2, PD-L1 and markers of microsatellite instability to guide treatment decisions and predict patient outcomes, especially in patients with advanced stomach cancer. Identifying these biomarkers helps determine whether targeted therapy or immunotherapy may be appropriate. This approach allows treatment to be more personalized for increased precision and efficacy.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/HIPEC-medical-illustration-16x9-1.jpg" alt="HIPEC medical illustration, a therapy for treating stomach cancer" class="wp-image-351683" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/HIPEC-medical-illustration-16x9-1.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/HIPEC-medical-illustration-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px"></figure></div>


<p>For patients whose disease has spread within the abdominal cavity, an innovative therapy called&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/hyperthermic-intraperitoneal-chemotherapy/about/pac-20583315" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hyperthermic intraperitoneal chemotherapy (HIPEC)</a>&nbsp;offers a promising option. In this procedure, following surgical removal of visible tumors, <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-new-chemotherapy-approach-for-treating-stomach-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heated chemotherapy</a> is circulated throughout the abdominal cavity to destroy remaining cancer cells.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Because stomach cancer is relatively uncommon, outcomes tend to be better when care is provided at multidisciplinary centers, like Mayo Clinic, that have extensive experience treating this disease. Collaboration among surgical, medical and radiation oncologists ensures that each patient receives an individualized treatment plan.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A reason for optimism</strong></h2>



<p>Stomach cancer remains a serious disease, but progress in early recognition and treatment is improving outcomes. Advances in surgery, precision medicine and supportive care have made it possible for many people to live longer and with a better quality of life after treatment.</p>



<p>It is essential that anyone experiencing persistent gastrointestinal symptoms, especially those that do not respond to routine, over-the-counter care, seek out a timely medical evaluation. Awareness, early detection and access to expert, coordinated care can make a meaningful difference.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/grotz-travis-e-m-d-m-s/bio-20342285" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>Travis Grotz, M.D.</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Hepatobiliary and Pancreas Surgery, Mayo Clinic, Minnesota</em></strong></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-is-stomach-cancer-on-the-rise-in-young-adults/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Is stomach cancer on the rise in young adults?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/11/an-adult-man-and-boy-walking-on-a-hike-near-the-beach-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/11/an-adult-man-and-boy-walking-on-a-hike-near-the-beach-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Travis Grotz]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[stomach cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Shaping the future of breast cancer care–one trainee at a time</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/shaping-the-future-of-breast-cancer-care-one-trainee-at-a-time/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Kate Ledger]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 13:37:06 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Education]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Florida]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Breast Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Kristin Robinson]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic College of Medicine & Science]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Graduate of Biomedical Sciences]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic School of Graduate Medical Education]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[mayo clinic school of health sciences]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407556</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Tailor Hofman, originally from St. Peter, Minnesota, was in middle school when her great-grandmother was diagnosed with breast cancer and underwent a mastectomy. "My great-grandma and I shared a close bond," Hofman says. "Her experience had a significant emotional impact on our family, particularly because we're a family of many women."&nbsp; Years later, Hofman was […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/shaping-the-future-of-breast-cancer-care-one-trainee-at-a-time/">Shaping the future of breast cancer care–one trainee at a time</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image is-style-left-align-caption"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Tailor_Hofman_with_great-grandmother-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Tailor Hofman with her great-grandmother, Anne Hansen, in 2002 whose diagnosis with cancer inspired Tailor's career." class="wp-image-407572" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Tailor_Hofman_with_great-grandmother-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Tailor_Hofman_with_great-grandmother-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Tailor_Hofman_with_great-grandmother-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Tailor_Hofman_with_great-grandmother-16-x-9.jpg 1241w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Tailor Hofman with her great-grandmother, Anne Hansen, in 2002. Tailor says her great-grandmother's experience with breast cancer was part of her motivation to pursue a career in radiography, to  help patients who are dealing with cancer. She graduated from Mayo Clinic School of Health Sciences in Rochester in 2017 and is a radiographer at Mayo Clinic.</figcaption></figure>


<p>Tailor Hofman, originally from St. Peter, Minnesota, was in middle school when her great-grandmother was diagnosed with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a> and underwent a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mastectomy/about/pac-20394670">mas</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mastectomy/about/pac-20394670" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">tectomy</a>.<br><br>"My great-grandma and I shared a close bond," Hofman says. "Her experience had a significant emotional impact on our family, particularly because we're a family of many women."&nbsp;</p>



<p>Years later, Hofman was inspired to train for a career where she could help other women through breast cancer screening. She applied to the radiography program at&nbsp;<a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/health-sciences-education/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic School of Health Sciences</a>&nbsp;to become a radiologic technologist — also known as a radiographer — working with doctors in assessing and evaluating patients, often using breast imaging.&nbsp; </p>



<p>Across the schools of&nbsp;<a href="https://college.mayo.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic College of Medicine and Science</a>, programs are training future leaders in approaches that address the breast cancer journey, from the first moment of screening to the years after a diagnosis. Often inspired by the cancer diagnoses of family and friends, students are learning cutting-edge approaches and bringing Mayo Clinic's primary value — the needs of the patient come first — to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352475" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer care</a>.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Making a difference in testing and treatment&nbsp;</strong></h2>



<p>Today, Hofman's work as a Mayo Clinic radiographer allows her to build relationships with patients starting from their first screenings.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"The team in breast imaging has unique insight into the care they provide," says Jessica Lodermeier, director of the radiography program in Rochester, Minnesota, which graduates up to 34 students a year. "They understand the emotional stress and anxiety that can accompany this very important yearly exam for women."&nbsp;</p>



<p>Radiographers perform medical exams using X-rays and other technology to create images that are interpreted by doctors for diagnosis and treatment of disease. Mayo's program allows them to add specialized training in <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-mri-for-dense-breasts-what-to-know/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ct-scan/about/pac-20393675" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">computerized tomography (CT</a>), mammography and other areas.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The School of Health Sciences has radiography programs on Mayo campuses in Rochester and Florida and offers a radiography internship program in Arizona. Instructors are experienced radiologic technologists, working side by side with students to share their expertise.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Our faculty is devoted to each student learner, and building on their interests in specific areas, such as various breast imaging technologies," says Lodermeier, who is also an alumna of the program. "For many students who choose radiography, it's to make a difference — caring for patients by assisting in testing and treatment of breast cancer and other serious diseases."&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Combining advanced techniques and compassionate care</strong></h2>



<p>Programs at Mayo Clinic also are training clinicians in specialized care for patients with breast cancer. One such program is a fellowship that focuses on breast imaging, offered through&nbsp;<a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/residencies-and-fellowships/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic School of Graduate Medical Education</a>. A fellowship program exists on each of Mayo's campuses, admitting a total of about six trainees a year.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Fellows learn numerous advanced imaging technologies, including modalities not offered at many institutions, such as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials/tests-procedures/contrast-enhanced-mammography" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">contrast-enhanced digital mammography (CEDM)</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/molecular-breast-imaging/about/pac-20394710" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">molecular breast imaging (MBI)</a>. These approaches can improve cancer detection.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="608" height="608" data-id="407570" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Hofman_Tailor_J._16248261_20250317.-1-x-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-407570" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Hofman_Tailor_J._16248261_20250317.-1-x-1.jpg 608w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Hofman_Tailor_J._16248261_20250317.-1-x-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Hofman_Tailor_J._16248261_20250317.-1-x-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Tailor Hofman</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="608" height="608" data-id="407573" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Villalba_Michael_D.-1-x-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-407573" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Villalba_Michael_D.-1-x-1.jpg 608w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Villalba_Michael_D.-1-x-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Villalba_Michael_D.-1-x-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Michael Villalba</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="608" height="608" data-id="407567" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Detry_Anna_M._30185956_20220705.-1-x-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-407567" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Detry_Anna_M._30185956_20220705.-1-x-1.jpg 608w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Detry_Anna_M._30185956_20220705.-1-x-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Detry_Anna_M._30185956_20220705.-1-x-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Anna Detry</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p><br>In Florida, the Breast Imaging Fellowship program — which accepts one fellow a year — involves rigorous training rotations that take place in the state-of-the-art facilities of the Duan Family Building. The training&nbsp;&nbsp;emphasizes compassion, says program director&nbsp;<a href="https://quarterly.mayo.edu/directoryui/personDetails/15542629" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kristin Robinson, M.D.</a>&nbsp;Among recent trainees in Florida was&nbsp;Michael Villalba, D.O., who completed the program and was hired to join Mayo staff as a physician in diagnostic radiology specializing in breast imaging.&nbsp;  </p>



<p>The compassionate care Dr. Villalba provided during a biopsy made an impression&nbsp;on patient Shelley Norwood.&nbsp;"His passion shines&nbsp;through&nbsp;in&nbsp;how he engages with patients," Norwood says. "You can see it&nbsp;in&nbsp;his face and hear it in his voice. He exemplifies the Mayo mission and values."&nbsp;</p>



<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="760" height="428" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Dr.-Kristin-Robinson-and-patient-16-x-9.jpg" alt="Dr. Kristin Robinson, discussing cancer care with a patient." class="wp-image-407569" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Dr.-Kristin-Robinson-and-patient-16-x-9.jpg 760w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Dr.-Kristin-Robinson-and-patient-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 760px) 100vw, 760px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Kristin Robinson (right) speaks with a patient</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>This approach is embedded in the fellowship training, says Dr. Robinson. "We're not just reading images,” she says. "We're caring for people."&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Improving outcomes for patients</strong></h2>



<p>Mayo is also training students who have an eye on patients' futures.&nbsp;Anna Detry&nbsp;is a fourth year Ph.D. student at&nbsp;<a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a>. Training under the mentorship of cancer researcher&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/hawse-john-r-iv-ph-d/bio-00093391" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">John Hawse IV, Ph.D.</a>, she aims to improve outcomes for patients who have recurrent breast tumors that have become resistant to treatment.</p>



<p>Detry took interest in studying breast cancer after family friends faced cancer diagnoses. Her studies focus on a form of breast cancer classified as estrogen receptor positive (ER+), which is usually treated effectively by drugs that block estrogen pathways. However, when tumors do recur, they may no longer respond to the same treatments.&nbsp; </p>



<p>So far, her research has identified a previously unstudied protein, highly prevalent in metastatic ER+ tumors, that appears to help recurrent tumors thrive. "We're looking specifically at that protein to figure out how it's driving drug resistance and how we can target it," says Detry. The research team is now testing approaches to disable or eliminate the protein and restore the tumor's sensitivity to treatment.</p>



<p>Interacting with clinician collaborators at Mayo Clinic has helped shape Detry's thinking as a researcher-in-training who's zeroed in on what's next for patients. "When I was applying to graduate school, what drew me to Mayo was the patient-centric focus of everything, even very basic science studies," she says. "Being in a hospital setting and working with clinicians here constantly keeps the patient centered in all our work and in the forefront of our minds." </p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/shaping-the-future-of-breast-cancer-care-one-trainee-at-a-time/">Shaping the future of breast cancer care–one trainee at a time</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Dr.-Kristin-Robinson-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Dr.-Kristin-Robinson-and-patient-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Breast Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Kristin Robinson]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic College of Medicine &amp; Science]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Graduate of Biomedical Sciences]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic School of Graduate Medical Education]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[mayo clinic school of health sciences]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers find enhancing the body’s ‘first responder’ cells may boost immune therapy for cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-find-enhancing-the-bodys-first-responder-cells-may-boost-immune-therapy-for-cancer/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Kate Ledger]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 17:14:37 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Haidong Dong]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jessica Lancaster]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407363</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic researchers have identified a specific immune cell that can be targeted to give a boost to standard immunotherapies for cancer. Two research teams, working collaboratively but using distinct approaches, found that "first-responder" immune cells known as myeloid cells can be manipulated to enhance the activity of tumor-killing T cells. The […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-find-enhancing-the-bodys-first-responder-cells-may-boost-immune-therapy-for-cancer/">Mayo Clinic researchers find enhancing the body’s ‘first responder’ cells may boost immune therapy for cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image is-style-left-align-caption"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="562" height="316" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/TcellsANDmacrophages-16-x-9.jpg" alt="A live cell microscopy image of a tumor’s environment shows the interaction of tumor-killing T-cells (magenta) and macrophages (green round cells). They are surrounded by stiff tumor tissue (green fibers) and non-fluorescent tumor cells (black areas). Image captured by Tina Kwok." class="wp-image-407397" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/TcellsANDmacrophages-16-x-9.jpg 562w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/TcellsANDmacrophages-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 562px) 100vw, 562px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Live cell microscopy image of a tumor’s environment shows the interaction of tumor-killing T-cells (magenta) and macrophages (green round cells),  surrounded by stiff tumor tissue (green fibers) and non-fluorescent tumor cells (black areas). Image captured: Tina Kwok.</figcaption></figure>


<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> researchers have identified a specific immune cell that can be targeted to give a boost to standard immunotherapies for cancer. Two research teams, working collaboratively but using distinct approaches, found that "first-responder" immune cells known as myeloid cells can be manipulated to enhance the activity of tumor-killing T cells.</p>



<p>The finding suggests that enhanced myeloid cells may boost certain immune checkpoint therapies, which are the standard of care for some cancers but may not have lasting effects. A clinical trial is now being developed at Mayo Clinic to test the enhanced cells in patients.</p>



<p></p>



<p>In a study in <a href="https://jitc.bmj.com/content/13/10/e012164" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Journal for ImmunoTherapy of Cancer</a>, Mayo Clinic researchers detailed how they found a way to boost cancer-killing T cells. The goal was to improve treatments that interfere with immunosuppressive proteins, PD-1 and PD-L1, which together suppress T cells' ability to fight cancer. Even though PD-L1 immunotherapies aim to block PD-L1, the researchers found that the molecule can persist through a natural recycling process that puts it back in play.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dong-Haidong_12985848_20220816-240x300.jpg" alt="Portrait of Dr. Haidong Dong" class="wp-image-407368" style="width:204px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dong-Haidong_12985848_20220816-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dong-Haidong_12985848_20220816.jpg 640w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Haidong Dong, M.D., Ph.D</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Our study found the importance of the recycling process, and we present a way to address it," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/dong-haidong-m-d-ph-d/bio-00027557" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Haidong Dong, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, a cancer immunology researcher at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center/cancer-care" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> and principal investigator of the study.</p>



<p>The research team developed an antibody, H1A, which they found can reduce PD-L1 in human myeloid cells and keep it from recycling. The protein PD-L1 is present in abundance on the surface of myeloid cells. When the protein was prevented from recycling on myeloid cells, the cells then boosted the action of cancer-killing T cells.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Hsu-Michelle-A._30026716_202509162045-240x300.jpg" alt="Portrait of Michelle Hsu" class="wp-image-407367" style="width:200px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Hsu-Michelle-A._30026716_202509162045-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Hsu-Michelle-A._30026716_202509162045.jpg 640w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Michelle Hsu</figcaption></figure></div>


<p></p>



<p>"We now have a tool that can completely remove PD-L1 and in doing so we have more myeloid cell activation," says lead author of the study, Michelle Hsu, who conducted the research as her graduate thesis at <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a>. "Identifying the myeloid cell was an unexpected discovery," she says. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Lancaster-Jessica-N._21667098_202502181545-240x300.jpg" alt="Portrait of Dr. Jessica Lancaster" class="wp-image-407369" style="width:186px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Lancaster-Jessica-N._21667098_202502181545-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Lancaster-Jessica-N._21667098_202502181545.jpg 640w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Jessica Lancaster, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Another Mayo Clinic team took a different approach and arrived at a similar conclusion about the importance of myeloid cells. A research team led by immunology researcher <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/lancaster-jessica-n-ph-d/bio-20482482" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jessica Lancaster, Ph.D.</a>, at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/arizona" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Arizona</a>, reported in <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2589004225017997" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">iScience</a> that macrophages, a type of myeloid cell, play a role in activating the cancer-killing T cells.</p>



<p></p>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-CcIVENx1zI"><br>Watch animation</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidCcIVENx1zI" title="Tcell and macrophage" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-CcIVENx1zI?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><em><strong>Animation available in the downloads:</strong>  Live cell microscopy shows a cancer-killing T cell (magenta) as it migrates and interacts with macrophages (blue) in the tumor microenvironment. Black spaces are packed with non-fluorescent tumor cells. Image captured by Tina Kwok, Mayo Clinic.</em><br></p>



<p>Using the complex approach of live-cell microscopy, the team found that in mice, T cells interact closely with the macrophages and create a molecular environment that has greater capacity to kill a tumor.</p>



<p>"This is a paradigm shift for PD-L1 immunotherapy, which has traditionally focused on the interaction of the tumor and the T cells," says Dr. Lancaster. "We found that it’s important to co-opt the macrophage, which acts as another immune cell partner."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Kwok-Tina_30026717_202506271753-240x300.jpg" alt="Portrait of Tina Kwok" class="wp-image-407366" style="width:179px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Kwok-Tina_30026717_202506271753-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Kwok-Tina_30026717_202506271753.jpg 640w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Tina Kwok</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><br>Further, says lead author Tina Kwok, who completed the studies during her Ph.D. research at Mayo Clinic, "We can directly reprogram tumor macrophages to be more pro-inflammatory. They can become better T-cell activators and drive better tumor control. Reprogramming of the macrophage may be key to being able to prevent therapy resistance and change outcomes for patients."</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p>Based on the findings from both labs, a phase 1 clinical trial of H1A is being planned. The research could ultimately better address resistance to immunotherapy and expand treatment options for people with cancer.</p>



<p>Review the studies in <a href="https://jitc.bmj.com/content/13/10/e012164" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Journal for ImmunoTherapy of Cancer</a> and <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2589004225017997" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">iScience</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center <br></strong>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact</strong>: </p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-find-enhancing-the-bodys-first-responder-cells-may-boost-immune-therapy-for-cancer/">Mayo Clinic researchers find enhancing the body’s ‘first responder’ cells may boost immune therapy for cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/TcellsANDmacrophages-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/TcellsANDmacrophages-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Haidong Dong]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jessica Lancaster]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic study sheds light on colorectal cancer risk in overlooked group</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-sheds-light-on-colorectal-cancer-risk-in-overlooked-group/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Jessica Saenz]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 15:57:14 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Gastroenterology]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Nicholas LaRusso]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[research Dr. Saqr Alsakarneh]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407172</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Primary sclerosing cholangitis (PSC) causes inflammation and scarring of the bile ducts. This rare liver disease is often accompanied by inflammatory bowel disease (IBD). Together, these diseases increase the risk of colorectal cancer by more than sixfold compared to the general population. Until recently, it&nbsp;wasn't&nbsp;clear whether that increased colorectal cancer risk extended to people with […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-sheds-light-on-colorectal-cancer-risk-in-overlooked-group/">Mayo Clinic study sheds light on colorectal cancer risk in overlooked group</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image is-style-left-align-caption"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Gastro-researcher-WF3829116_0189-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Gastroenterology researchers look at screen" class="wp-image-407268" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Gastro-researcher-WF3829116_0189-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Gastro-researcher-WF3829116_0189-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Gastro-researcher-WF3829116_0189-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Gastro-researcher-WF3829116_0189-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Gastro-researcher-WF3829116_0189-16-x-9.jpg 1900w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Gastroenterology researchers look at screen</figcaption></figure>


<p>Primary sclerosing cholangitis (PSC) causes inflammation and scarring of the bile ducts. This rare liver disease is often accompanied by inflammatory bowel disease (IBD). Together, these diseases increase the risk of colorectal cancer by more than sixfold compared to the general population.</p>



<p>Until recently, it&nbsp;<a>wasn't</a>&nbsp;clear whether that increased colorectal cancer risk extended to people with PSC alone, but Mayo Clinic researchers have helped answer this question. Their findings could help open the door to earlier colorectal cancer screening and better prevention for people with PSC.</p>



<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="608" height="608" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr.-Saqr-Alsakarneh-30425105_20250701-1-x-1.jpg" alt="Photo of Dr. Saqr Alsakarneh" class="wp-image-407174" style="width:166px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr.-Saqr-Alsakarneh-30425105_20250701-1-x-1.jpg 608w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr.-Saqr-Alsakarneh-30425105_20250701-1-x-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr.-Saqr-Alsakarneh-30425105_20250701-1-x-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Saqr Alsakarneh</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We wanted to answer something that was overlooked in the guidelines because these patients are a smaller group and have been understudied in research," says Dr.&nbsp;Saqr Alsakarneh, a fellow in the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/gastroenterology-hepatology-digestive-care/sections/overview/ovc-20348241?customer_id=919-955-2329&amp;mc_id=google&amp;campaign=8927988164&amp;geo=9199032&amp;kw=mayo%20clinic%20gastroenterology&amp;ad=458309235531&amp;network=g&amp;sitetarget=&amp;adgroup=111165104350&amp;extension=&amp;target=kwd-367650091164&amp;matchtype=e&amp;device=c&amp;account=9199552329&amp;invsrc=arizona&amp;placementsite=arizona&amp;gad_source=1&amp;gad_campaignid=8927988164&amp;gbraid=0AAAAAD8Qu28LZ_ykDEhzwUdztX41xIe9R&amp;gclid=Cj0KCQjw58PGBhCkARIsADbDilxBHSas-T8H9QdFt0dNSntXtQI6tzhJ5Pej5p9tpWeYJda5z2MOamwaAuh3EALw_wcB">Department of Gastroenterology at Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;and lead author of the study,&nbsp;published in&nbsp;<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/apt.70303">Alimentary Pharmacology and Therapeutics</a>. </p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><br><strong>Searching data for cancer prevention blind spots</strong></h2>



<p>In the largest population-based analysis of its kind, Dr. Alsakarneh and his co-authors analyzed data from 115 million de-identified health records from 65 healthcare organizations across the U.S. Their goal was to understand long-term risk of colorectal and other gastrointestinal cancers in people with PSC.</p>



<p>The researchers found that&nbsp;people with PSC without IBD have&nbsp;<a>nearly three</a>&nbsp;times the risk of developing colorectal cancer compared to the general population.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"This is important because it challenges the current assumption that only&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/primary-sclerosing-cholangitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20355797">primary sclerosing cholangitis</a>&nbsp;with IBD causes colorectal cancer," says&nbsp;Dr.&nbsp;<a>Alsakarneh</a>.</p>



<p>While colorectal cancer prevention guidelines recommend annual screening and increased surveillance for people who have PSC and IBD, no specific guidelines exist for people with only PSC. Dr. Alsakarneh says this is a missed opportunity for early detection of colorectal cancer, which is highly preventable with proper screening.</p>



<p>In addition to discovering an increased risk for colorectal cancer, the study&nbsp;confirmed an association between PSC alone and higher rates of bile duct,&nbsp;<a>liver</a>&nbsp;and pancreatic cancers. While previous research has suggested this connection, the study provides large-scale data to support the need for continued vigilance and screening strategies tailored to people with PSC.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Translating discovery to better care</strong></h2>



<p>Dr. Alsakarneh says these findings are an important first step toward a better understanding of PSC and cancer risk, although more studies are needed to confirm how this information should be incorporated into healthcare guidelines.</p>



<p>"Before anything is put into guidelines, the first step is always to validate the findings," says Dr. Alsakarneh. "Colleagues from the gastrointestinal community have reached out and are interested, so this is something we are working on."</p>



<p>As researchers investigate further, Dr. Alsakarneh says&nbsp;<a>it's</a>&nbsp;important that clinicians with PSC patients be aware of this association, tune into emerging evidence and keep their patients informed as findings develop.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Continuing a legacy of PSC discovery at Mayo Clinic</strong></h2>



<p>Dr. Alsakarneh's research continues a legacy of PSC discovery at Mayo Clinic that&nbsp;dates back to&nbsp;the '70s. That was when&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/larusso-nicholas-f-m-d/bio-20053658" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Nicholas LaRusso</a>, a gastroenterologist at Mayo Clinic, first began studying the cluster of symptoms that he eventually helped describe and define as PSC in a 1980&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/7399227/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>.  </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="819" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/LaRusso-Nicholas-F._10157514_20220913-819x1024.jpg" alt="Dr. Nicholas LaRusso" class="wp-image-407260" style="width:159px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/LaRusso-Nicholas-F._10157514_20220913-819x1024.jpg 819w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/LaRusso-Nicholas-F._10157514_20220913-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/LaRusso-Nicholas-F._10157514_20220913-768x960.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/LaRusso-Nicholas-F._10157514_20220913.jpg 900w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 819px) 100vw, 819px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Nicholas LaRusso</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"It's important to me that this study comes from Mayo Clinic because Dr. LaRusso, who still has a lab here, made so much progress in this disease. He is the reason I came to Mayo Clinic to do my training," says Dr. Alsakarneh.</p>



<p>Alongside Dr. LaRusso, Dr. Alsakarneh next plans to lead Mayo Clinic research investigating why and how PSC increases cancer risk.</p>



<p></p>



<p>Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/apt.70303" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-sheds-light-on-colorectal-cancer-risk-in-overlooked-group/">Mayo Clinic study sheds light on colorectal cancer risk in overlooked group</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Gastro-researcher-WF3829116_0189-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Gastro-researcher-WF3829116_0189-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Nicholas LaRusso]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[research Dr. Saqr Alsakarneh]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic collaborates on new drug study showing improved survival for early breast cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-collaborates-on-new-drug-study-showing-improved-survival-for-early-breast-cancer/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[ltedesco7]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 13:45:28 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Matthew Goetz]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407178</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic researchers collaborated on a new study showing that the drug abemaciclib improves survival for people with high-risk, early-stage breast cancer. In the phase 3 monarchE trial, two years of abemaciclib (Verzenio) plus endocrine therapy reduced the risk of death by 15.8% compared with endocrine therapy alone among patients with a […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-collaborates-on-new-drug-study-showing-improved-survival-for-early-breast-cancer/">Mayo Clinic collaborates on new drug study showing improved survival for early breast cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-left-align-caption"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Woman-pills-water-1138085252-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Woman looking at hand holding pills, water glass in other hand, in home" class="wp-image-407183" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Woman-pills-water-1138085252-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Woman-pills-water-1138085252-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Woman-pills-water-1138085252-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Woman-pills-water-1138085252-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Woman-pills-water-1138085252-16-x-9.jpg 1677w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Shutterstock</figcaption>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> researchers collaborated on a new study showing that the drug abemaciclib improves survival for people with high-risk, early-stage <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a>.</p>



<p>In the phase 3 monarchE trial, two years of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements/abemaciclib-oral-route/description/drg-20406567" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">abemaciclib</a> (Verzenio) plus endocrine therapy reduced the risk of death by 15.8% compared with endocrine therapy alone among patients with a common type of early-stage breast cancer.</p>



<p>The clinical trial enrolled more than 5,600 patients at over 600 sites across 38 countries. All participants had breast cancer that was hormone receptor-positive (HR+) and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/in-depth/breast-cancer/art-20045654" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">human epidermal growth factor receptor 2-negative (HER2-)</a>, a subtype that includes 70% of all breast cancers, and also had cancer in at least one underarm lymph node, a factor linked to higher risk of recurrence.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="812" height="812" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr.-Matthew-P-Goetz-._12369616_20250331-1-x-1.jpg" alt="Headshot of Dr. Matthew P Goetz" class="wp-image-407182" style="width:222px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr.-Matthew-P-Goetz-._12369616_20250331-1-x-1.jpg 812w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr.-Matthew-P-Goetz-._12369616_20250331-1-x-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr.-Matthew-P-Goetz-._12369616_20250331-1-x-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr.-Matthew-P-Goetz-._12369616_20250331-1-x-1-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 812px) 100vw, 812px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Matthew Goetz</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"This is the first therapy to significantly prolong survival for this patient population in over two decades," says study co-author <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/goetz-matthew-p-m-d/bio-20054460" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Matthew Goetz, M.D.</a>, a breast medical oncologist at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>. "With the addition of just one drug to standard endocrine therapy, we are not only seeing fewer recurrences but are also reducing the chance for breast cancer death."</p>



<p>These findings, published in the <a href="https://www.annalsofoncology.org/article/S0923-7534(25)04948-8/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Annals of Oncology</a>, establish abemaciclib plus endocrine therapy as the new standard of care for this high-risk group.</p>



<p>Abemaciclib is a CDK4/6 inhibitor, a type of drug that blocks proteins involved in cancer cell division. It is the first drug in its class approved by the Food and Drug Administration to treat node-positive, high-risk early breast cancer. Dr. Goetz previously led the <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28968163/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">MONARCH 3 clinical trial</a>, which led to the <a href="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/resources-information-approved-drugs/fda-approves-abemaciclib-initial-therapy-hr-positive-her2-negative-metastatic-breast-cancer" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">FDA approval</a> of abemaciclib in combination with hormone therapy for advanced HR+/HER2- breast cancer.</p>



<p>"Abemaciclib was developed to target estrogen receptor-positive breast cancer in a way that's different than chemotherapy by slowing the proliferation of cancer cells," Dr. Goetz says. "We now can confidently state that the benefits seen early on, in terms of reducing recurrence, result in improved survival, which is what matters most to patients." &nbsp;</p>



<p>While most patients with HR+/HER2- breast cancer have good long-term outcomes, those with lymph-node involvement or large or high-grade tumors are more likely to experience recurrence.</p>



<p>Among patients who took abemaciclib with endocrine therapy, 32% fewer experienced disease spread after seven years compared with those who only received endocrine therapy. This confirms that abemaciclib helps lower the risk of recurrence even after treatment with the drug has ended. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Continued follow-up will determine whether the survival benefit deepens over time. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.annalsofoncology.org/article/S0923-7534(25)04948-8/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding. The study was led by Eli Lilly.&nbsp;</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-collaborates-on-new-drug-study-showing-improved-survival-for-early-breast-cancer/">Mayo Clinic collaborates on new drug study showing improved survival for early breast cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Woman-pills-water-1138085252-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Woman-pills-water-1138085252-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Matthew Goetz]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New genomic test could spare some people with melanoma from lymph node biopsy surgery&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-genomic-test-could-spare-some-people-with-melanoma-from-lymph-node-biopsy-surgery/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Susan Murphy]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 14:55:25 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Discovery Science]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Individualized Medicine]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Alexander Meves]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Tina Hieken]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Melanoma]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407092</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — A genomic test co-developed by Mayo Clinic and SkylineDx can identify whether people with melanoma are at low or high risk for cancer in their lymph nodes — a finding that could guide treatment decisions and help some people avoid lymph node biopsy surgery. The study results are published in JAMA Surgery. […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-genomic-test-could-spare-some-people-with-melanoma-from-lymph-node-biopsy-surgery/">New genomic test could spare some people with melanoma from lymph node biopsy surgery&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9MELANOMA1-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-407094" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9MELANOMA1-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9MELANOMA1-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9MELANOMA1-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9MELANOMA1-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9MELANOMA1.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">A 3D illustration shows a cross-section of skin with melanoma spreading into the bloodstream and lymphatic system. (Getty Images)</figcaption>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A genomic test co-developed by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> and <a href="https://www.skylinedx.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">SkylineDx</a> can identify whether people with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/melanoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20374884" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">melanoma</a> are at low or high risk for cancer in their <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/swollen-lymph-nodes/symptoms-causes/syc-20353902%C2%A0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymph nodes</a> — a finding that could guide treatment decisions and help some people avoid lymph node biopsy surgery. The study results are <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamasurgery/fullarticle/2840207" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">published</a> in JAMA Surgery.</p>



<p>In the largest prospective study of its kind, about 93% of people classified as low risk had no cancer in their lymph nodes, while about 25% in the high-risk group did. The multicenter clinical trial enrolled 1,761 people with early- or intermediate-stage melanoma at nine U.S. cancer centers between 2021 and 2024.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Decoding the tumor’s genomic blueprint</strong></h2>



<p>The test measures the activity of eight genes in a melanoma tumor and combines that data with a person's age and tumor thickness to estimate the chance that cancer has reached the lymph nodes. The Merlin CP-GEP Test analyzes tissue from the tumor already collected during an initial biopsy, so no additional procedure or visit is required for the test.</p>



<p>Sentinel lymph node biopsy is performed under anesthesia to remove one or a few lymph nodes and check for microscopic cancer. The procedure usually requires a second incision and can have side effects, yet nearly 80% of people who undergo the surgery have no cancer in their lymph nodes.</p>



<p>"Surgery will always be central to cancer care, but this study shows that sentinel lymph node surgery might be avoided for selected patients with melanoma," says first author <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/hieken-tina-j-m-d/bio-20089011" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tina Hieken, M.D.</a>, a surgical <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/oncology/sections/overview/ovc-20198225" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">oncologist</a> at the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> and co-principal investigator of the study. "This test lets us use a patient's own tumor biology to guide care with true precision."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Turning molecular insight into clinical impact</strong></h2>



<p>Melanoma is the deadliest form of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/skin-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20377605" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">skin cancer</a>. While early-stage disease can often be treated successfully, once melanoma spreads to the lymph nodes, the risk of recurrence increases. Determining whether the cancer has reached the lymph nodes is a key step in guiding treatment.</p>



<p>"Melanoma progression is driven by subtle molecular processes that we're only beginning to understand," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/meves-alexander-m-d-m-b-a/bio-00027476" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alexander Meves, M.D.</a>, a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/dermatology/sections/overview/ovc-20420526" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dermatologist</a> at the Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center who led earlier validation studies of the test. "This work translates that biology into tools that can improve care."</p>



<p>Researchers are now studying how incorporating the test into melanoma care might help healthcare professionals understand the risk of recurrence and guide follow-up care.</p>



<p>For a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding information, review the <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamasurgery/fullarticle/2840207" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong> </p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-genomic-test-could-spare-some-people-with-melanoma-from-lymph-node-biopsy-surgery/">New genomic test could spare some people with melanoma from lymph node biopsy surgery&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/1x1MELANOMA.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9MELANOMA1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Alexander Meves]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Tina Hieken]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Melanoma]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-radiation-therapy-for-patients-with-breast-cancer/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 12:50:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Health & Wellness]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Cycle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Video]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Laura Vallow]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395065</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Radiation therapy is a common component of breast cancer treatment for patients. The high-powered beams of intense energy kill cancer cells and reduce the risk of the cancer recurring. Dr. Laura Vallow, chair of the Radiation Oncology Department at Mayo Clinic in Florida, explains how innovation is transforming radiation treatments. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-radiation-therapy-for-patients-with-breast-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Patient-with-radiation-tech-1461606_3648465_0034-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Patient with radiation technician, radiation therapy" class="wp-image-407114" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Patient-with-radiation-tech-1461606_3648465_0034-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Patient-with-radiation-tech-1461606_3648465_0034-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Patient-with-radiation-tech-1461606_3648465_0034-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Patient-with-radiation-tech-1461606_3648465_0034-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Patient-with-radiation-tech-1461606_3648465_0034-16-x-9.jpg 1604w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>


<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/radiation-therapy/about/pac-20385162" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Radiation therapy</a> is a common component of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352475" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer treatment</a> for patients. The high-powered beams of intense energy kill cancer cells and reduce the risk of the cancer recurring.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/vallow-laura-a-m-d/bio-20054004">Dr. Laura Vallow</a>, chair of the Radiation Oncology Department at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a>, explains how innovation is transforming radiation treatments.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=me4OE84cerE" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidme4OE84cerE" title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/me4OE84cerE?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:05) is in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/SCRIPT-MCM-Radiation-therapy-for-breast-cancer.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Patients with breast cancer now have more options when it comes to radiation treatments. The goal is to remove any remaining cancer cells following chemotherapy or surgery.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"In other situations, we use radiation if the cancer is more advanced, or spread to the lymph nodes," says Dr. Vallow.</p>



<p>Advancements in technology allow healthcare professionals to treat patients more safely. One technique called "prone positioning" reduces the chance of beams targeting other organs. For this procedure, patients lie on their stomachs.</p>



<p>"We take advantage of gravity, the breast pulls away from the body, and we can treat the breast without exposing the underlying lung and heart to unnecessary radiation," explains Dr. Vallow.</p>



<p>Intensity-modulated radiation therapy is cutting-edge. Unlike traditional radiation, this procedure delivers X-rays directly to the targeted area from multiple angles, allowing for higher, more effective doses.</p>



<p>"Before intensity-modulated radiation therapy, we were not able to conform the dose around the chest wall," says Dr. Vallow.</p>



<p>For patients undergoing radiation therapy, it's crucial to stay hydrated and try to sleep well to fight fatigue. It's also important to use sunscreen after treatment.</p>



<p><strong>Related Posts:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-leads-4-decades-of-advances-in-breast-cancer-care/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic leads 4 decades of advances in breast cancer care</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-research-improves-dense-breast-cancer-screening-and-early-detection/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic research improves dense breast cancer screening and early detection</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/top-10-questions-about-breast-cancer-answered/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Top 10 questions about breast cancer answered</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-treats-first-person-in-the-us-with-a-novel-radiopharmaceutical-therapy-for-breast-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic treats first person in the US with a novel radiopharmaceutical therapy for breast cancer</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-mri-for-dense-breasts-what-to-know/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: MRI for dense breasts — what to know</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-how-to-decide-which-breast-cancer-surgery-is-right-for-you/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: How to decide which breast cancer surgery is right for you</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ready-for-10-13-back-on-the-bench-judges-metastatic-breast-cancer-journey-inspires-hope/">(VIDEO) Back on the bench: Judge’s metastatic breast cancer journey inspires hope</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-do-you-need-to-know-about-dense-breasts/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What do you need to know about dense breasts?</a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/wp-admin/post.php?post=406974&amp;action=edit"></a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-radiation-therapy-for-patients-with-breast-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Patient-with-radiation-tech-1461606_3648465_0034.-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Patient-with-radiation-tech-1461606_3648465_0034-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Laura Vallow]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic uncovers hidden driver fueling aggressive prostate cancer&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-uncovers-hidden-driver-fueling-aggressive-prostate-cancer/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Jessica Saenz]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 12:44:55 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407064</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Treatments such as chemotherapy, hormone therapy and immunotherapy have had limited success against advanced prostate cancer due to the tumor's ability to rewire and survive. But hope is on the horizon, thanks to a new Mayo Clinic study that uncovers how prostate cancer exploits a protein&nbsp;in order to&nbsp;resist targeted therapies and evade the immune system. […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-uncovers-hidden-driver-fueling-aggressive-prostate-cancer/">Mayo Clinic uncovers hidden driver fueling aggressive prostate cancer&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="855" height="481" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Prostate-Cancer-Tumor-Tissue-with-soluble-Nucleoporins-16-x-9.jpg" alt="Medical illustration: Prostate cancer-tumor tissue with soluble nucleoporins" class="wp-image-407073" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Prostate-Cancer-Tumor-Tissue-with-soluble-Nucleoporins-16-x-9.jpg 855w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Prostate-Cancer-Tumor-Tissue-with-soluble-Nucleoporins-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Prostate-Cancer-Tumor-Tissue-with-soluble-Nucleoporins-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 855px) 100vw, 855px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Prostate cancer-tumor tissue with soluble nucleoporins</figcaption>



<p>Treatments such as chemotherapy, hormone therapy and immunotherapy have had limited success against advanced <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prostate-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353087" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">prostate cancer</a> due to the tumor's ability to rewire and survive. But hope is on the horizon, thanks to a new <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic/quality/top-ranked" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> study that uncovers how prostate cancer exploits a protein&nbsp;in order to&nbsp;resist targeted therapies and evade the immune system.</p>



<p>Nuclear pores are entries to the nucleus made up of proteins called <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/genome-function-stability-nuclear-organization-cancer/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">nucleoporins</a>. While nucleoporins usually stay at their post and help regulate the flow of molecules that can come in and out of the nucleus, researchers discovered that soluble POM121 — a subtype of the nucleoporin POM121 — uses its ability to navigate freely to help cancer cells grow and spread.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr._Rodriguez-Bravo_Mayo_20251016111732-1x1-1-1024x1024.jpg" alt="Photo: Dr. Veronica Rodriguez-Bravo" class="wp-image-407070" style="width:217px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr._Rodriguez-Bravo_Mayo_20251016111732-1x1-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr._Rodriguez-Bravo_Mayo_20251016111732-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr._Rodriguez-Bravo_Mayo_20251016111732-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr._Rodriguez-Bravo_Mayo_20251016111732-1x1-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr._Rodriguez-Bravo_Mayo_20251016111732-1x1-1.jpg 1402w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Veronica Rodriguez-Bravo</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><br><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/rodriguez-bravo-veronica-ph-d/bio-20526592" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Veronica Rodriguez-Bravo</a>, associate professor in the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/departments-divisions/department-biochemistry-molecular-biology/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</a> at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center/about-us" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> and senior author of the&nbsp;<a href="https://aacrjournals.org/cancerdiscovery/article/doi/10.1158/2159-8290.CD-25-0629/764547/Off-Pore-Nucleoporin-sPOM121-Transcriptionally">study</a>&nbsp;published in Cancer Discovery, says her team's research revealed that soluble POM121, known as sPOM121, builds specialized hubs in the nucleus that rewire gene activity.</p>



<p></p>



<p><br>"Nobody had looked at the role of this soluble 'off-pore' nucleoporin because in gene expression analyses across databases, everything is classified under the primary nucleoporin. But through detailed analysis we saw an increase in sPOM121 in prostate cancer when compared to noncancerous tissue and a further increase in metastatic therapy resistant tumors," says Dr. Rodriguez-Bravo.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Off-Pore-NUP-fotor-20251016111643-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-407072" style="width:650px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Off-Pore-NUP-fotor-20251016111643-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Off-Pore-NUP-fotor-20251016111643-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Off-Pore-NUP-fotor-20251016111643-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Off-Pore-NUP-fotor-20251016111643-16-x-9.jpg 1026w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure></div>


<p>"We started digging for its purpose and found it had a distinctly relevant role in driving prostate cancer progression to lethal stages of the disease," says Dr. Rodriguez-Bravo. The study combined patient tumor analyses, molecular profiling and preclinical models to identify the protein and test its role in metastatic prostate cancer.</p>



<p>The study builds on her&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30100187/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">previous research</a>, which identified POM121's key role in transporting cancer-promoting proteins into the nucleus.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>'Logistic centers' that promote cancer</strong></h2>



<p>As a soluble protein, sPOM121 can roam freely in the nucleus, where DNA instructions are stored. "Because it's not attached to the structure that surrounds the nucleus, it can form condensates — which act like logistic centers — and bind to other proteins that regulate gene accessibility and activation," says Dr. Rodriguez-Bravo.</p>



<p>Most notably, sPOM121 partners with a protein called SMARCA5 that modifies DNA packaging to allow a protein called beta-catenin to enhance its expression. Beta-catenin is known to drive therapy resistance and immunosuppressing genes.</p>



<p>Dr. Rodriguez-Bravo says this discovery offers a possible explanation for prostate cancer growth and spread when treated with standard therapy and poor response to immunotherapy.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A potential key to treatment-resistant prostate cancer</strong></h2>



<p>The study tested whether blocking sPOM121-driven cancer programs like beta-catenin could improve the effectiveness of treatments such as immune checkpoint inhibitors, which help the immune system attack cancer.</p>



<p>"We found that targeting the soluble POM121-beta-catenin pathway really enhances the effect of immune checkpoint inhibitors. The tumors started getting a lot of T-cell infiltration and shrank," says Dr. Rodriguez-Bravo. "Beta-catenin inhibitors are currently being investigated in multiple tumor types, and our results provide the rationale to investigate the efficacy of these inhibitors alone or in combination with immunotherapy for prostate cancer."</p>



<p>Dr. Rodriguez-Bravo also pinpoints the strong unmet need to develop specific nucleoporin inhibitors that could target multiple cancer-driving signal pathways by disrupting these critical logistic centers. The disruption of these logistic centers by targeting sPOM121 would induce a blackout in the cancer cell, increasing the effectiveness of current therapies, but further investigation is needed to directly target sPOM121, says Dr. Rodriguez-Bravo.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Broader impact beyond prostate cancer</strong></h2>



<p>Dr. Rodriguez-Bravo says this study has observed the accumulation of POM121 in multiple tumor types. Her team now hopes to investigate whether the soluble form, sPOM121, is a common cancer driver or plays an earlier role in disease progression.</p>



<p>"If this is really controlling fundamental pathways fueling tumor progression, targeting sPOM121 might potentially benefit more patients in the future," she says.</p>



<p>She also hopes the study will encourage researchers to investigate how cancer might exploit other off-pore nucleoporins.</p>



<p>"We believe sPOM121 is one of many other nucleoporins that orchestrate key transcriptional hubs in the depth of the nucleus. Cancer likes to have a lot of tools on its belt, so we propose these off-pore nucleoporins are selected and used efficiently during tumor evolution," says Dr. Rodriguez-Bravo.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://aacrjournals.org/cancerdiscovery/article/doi/10.1158/2159-8290.CD-25-0629/764547/Off-Pore-Nucleoporin-sPOM121-Transcriptionally" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-uncovers-hidden-driver-fueling-aggressive-prostate-cancer/">Mayo Clinic uncovers hidden driver fueling aggressive prostate cancer&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Header-Prostate-Cancer-Tumor-Tissue-with-soluble-Nucleoporins-fotor-2025101611160-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Prostate-Cancer-Tumor-Tissue-with-soluble-Nucleoporins-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What do you need to know about dense breasts?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-do-you-need-to-know-about-dense-breasts/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[pattymiller]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 13:00:50 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Cameron Leitch]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=406974</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;I just had a mammogram, and I was told that I have dense breast tissue. What does that mean? ANSWER:&nbsp;About half of women are considered to have dense breasts, based on the appearance of their breast tissue on a mammogram. The main concerns about dense breast tissue are that it makes&nbsp;breast cancer screening&nbsp;more […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-do-you-need-to-know-about-dense-breasts/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What do you need to know about dense breasts?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-middle-aged-woman-with-a-neutral-expression-staring-thoughtfully-out-a-window-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a middle aged woman with a neutral expression, staring thoughtfully out a window" class="wp-image-371383" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-middle-aged-woman-with-a-neutral-expression-staring-thoughtfully-out-a-window-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-middle-aged-woman-with-a-neutral-expression-staring-thoughtfully-out-a-window-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-middle-aged-woman-with-a-neutral-expression-staring-thoughtfully-out-a-window-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-middle-aged-woman-with-a-neutral-expression-staring-thoughtfully-out-a-window-16X9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-middle-aged-woman-with-a-neutral-expression-staring-thoughtfully-out-a-window-16X9.jpg 1688w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong>&nbsp;I just had a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mammogram/about/pac-20384806" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">mammogram</a>, and I was told that I have <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mammogram/in-depth/dense-breast-tissue/art-20123968" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dense breast tissue.</a> What does that mean?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:&nbsp;</strong>About half of women are considered to have <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-research-improves-dense-breast-cancer-screening-and-early-detection/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dense breasts,</a> based on the appearance of their breast tissue on a mammogram. The main concerns about dense breast tissue are that it makes&nbsp;breast cancer screening&nbsp;more complex and increases the risk of breast cancer. Here are some answers to questions you might have:<br></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What is dense breast tissue?</strong></h2>



<p>Breast tissue is composed of milk glands, milk ducts and supportive tissue, which make up dense tissue. Breasts also include fatty tissue, which is nondense tissue. When viewed on a mammogram, women with dense breasts have more dense tissue than fatty tissue.</p>



<p>Nondense breast tissue typically appears dark and transparent on a mammogram. In contrast, dense breast tissue appears as a solid white area, which makes it difficult to see through.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>How do doctors determine if you have dense breast tissue?</strong></h2>



<p>The radiologist who analyzes your mammogram determines the ratio of nondense to dense tissue and assigns a level of breast density. These levels are determined by results from the Breast Imaging Reporting and Data System from the American College of Radiology.</p>



<p>The levels of density are designated by letters:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>A.</strong>&nbsp;Breasts are almost entirely composed of fat. About&nbsp;10%&nbsp;of women have this result.</li>



<li><strong>B.</strong>&nbsp;Scattered areas of density, but most breast tissue is nondense. About&nbsp;40%&nbsp;of women have this result.</li>



<li><strong>C.</strong>&nbsp;Heterogeneously dense indicates some areas of nondense tissue, but most breast tissue is dense. About&nbsp;40%&nbsp;of women have this result.</li>



<li><strong>D.</strong>&nbsp;Extremely dense indicates that nearly all breast tissue is dense. About&nbsp;10%&nbsp;of women have this result.</li>
</ul>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="878" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Female-breast-density-1154793_3350944-002-2-1024x878.jpg" alt="Examples of each of the four breast density categories." class="wp-image-407031" style="width:579px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Female-breast-density-1154793_3350944-002-2-1024x878.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Female-breast-density-1154793_3350944-002-2-300x257.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Female-breast-density-1154793_3350944-002-2-768x659.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Female-breast-density-1154793_3350944-002-2.jpg 1312w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What causes dense breast tissue?</strong></h2>



<p>It's not clear why some women have a lot of dense breast tissue and others don't. Dense breasts are more likely if you:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Are younger.</strong>&nbsp;Your breast tissue tends to become less dense as you age, although some women may have dense breast tissue at any age.</li>



<li><strong>Have a lower body mass index.</strong>&nbsp;Women with less body fat are more likely to have more dense breast tissue compared with women who are obese.</li>



<li><strong>Take hormone therapy for menopause.</strong>&nbsp;Women who take combination hormone therapy to relieve signs and symptoms of menopause are more likely to have dense breasts.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Why does breast density matter?</strong></h2>



<p>Having dense breast tissue won't affect your daily life. However, it increases the chance that breast cancer may go undetected by a mammogram, since dense breast tissue can mask a potential cancer. It also increases your risk of breast cancer, though healthcare professionals aren't yet certain why.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Do screening recommendations change for dense breasts?</strong></h2>



<p>Women with dense breasts but no other risk factors for breast cancer are considered to have a higher risk of breast cancer than average. Dense breast tissue makes it more challenging to interpret a mammogram, since cancer and dense breast tissue both appear white on a mammogram. This may increase the risk that cancer won't be detected on a mammogram.</p>



<p>However, mammograms are still effective screening tools. The most common type is a digital mammogram, which is more effective at detecting cancer. It saves images of your breasts as digital files, allowing for more detailed analysis.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Are other tests more effective?</strong></h2>



<p>Other tests carry both risks and benefits, although MRI and molecular breast imaging have demonstrated superior cancer detection in women with dense breasts.</p>



<p>Supplemental tests for breast cancer screening can include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>3D mammogram, also known as breast tomosynthesis</strong><br>Tomosynthesis uses X-rays to collect multiple images of the breast from several angles. A computer synthesizes the images to form a 3D image of the breast. Many mammogram centers are transitioning to incorporate&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/3d-technology-provides-enhanced-breast-cancer-detection">3D mammograms</a>&nbsp;as part of the standard mammogram technology.</li>



<li><strong>Breast MRI</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/breast-mri/about/pac-20384809" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">MRI </a>uses magnets rather than radiation to create images of the breast. This option is recommended for women with a very high risk of breast cancer, such as those with genetic mutations.</li>



<li><strong>Molecular breast imaging</strong><br>This&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/molecular-breast-imaging/about/pac-20394710">imaging</a>&nbsp;uses a gamma camera to record the activity of a radioactive tracer. The tracer is injected into a vein in your arm. Normal tissue and cancerous tissue react differently to the tracer, which can be seen in the images captured by the camera.</li>
</ul>



<p>Every test has pros and cons. Talk with your healthcare professional about your breast cancer risk factors. Together, you can decide whether additional screening tests are right for you.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/cameron-leitch-md"><em>Cameron Leitch, M.D.</em></a><em>, Radiology,&nbsp;Mayo Clinic Health System, Eau Claire, Wisconsin</em></p>



<p><strong>Related posts:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-leads-4-decades-of-advances-in-breast-cancer-care/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic leads 4 decades of advances in breast cancer care</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-research-improves-dense-breast-cancer-screening-and-early-detection/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic research improves dense breast cancer screening and early detection</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/top-10-questions-about-breast-cancer-answered/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Top 10 questions about breast cancer answered</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-treats-first-person-in-the-us-with-a-novel-radiopharmaceutical-therapy-for-breast-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic treats first person in the US with a novel radiopharmaceutical therapy for breast cancer</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-mri-for-dense-breasts-what-to-know/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: MRI for dense breasts — what to know</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-how-to-decide-which-breast-cancer-surgery-is-right-for-you/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: How to decide which breast cancer surgery is right for you</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ready-for-10-13-back-on-the-bench-judges-metastatic-breast-cancer-journey-inspires-hope/">(VIDEO) Back on the bench: Judge’s metastatic breast cancer journey inspires hope</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-do-you-need-to-know-about-dense-breasts/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What do you need to know about dense breasts?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-middle-aged-woman-with-a-neutral-expression-staring-thoughtfully-out-a-window-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-middle-aged-woman-with-a-neutral-expression-staring-thoughtfully-out-a-window-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Cameron Leitch]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>(VIDEO) Back on the bench: Judge’s metastatic breast cancer journey inspires hope</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ready-for-10-13-back-on-the-bench-judges-metastatic-breast-cancer-journey-inspires-hope/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Alex Osiadacz]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 13:04:12 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer Patient Stories]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Florida]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Cycle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Breast Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Pooja Advani]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=406520</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Judge Audrey Moran is known for her strength and fairness in the courtroom in Florida's Duval county. But one of the most difficult cases she's faced is breast cancer that spread to the lining of her brain.&nbsp; With the help of a dedicated care team and precise treatment, Judge Moran is back on the bench, […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ready-for-10-13-back-on-the-bench-judges-metastatic-breast-cancer-journey-inspires-hope/">(VIDEO) Back on the bench: Judge’s metastatic breast cancer journey inspires hope</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-center-align-caption"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran-court-Fl-16-x-9--1024x576.jpg" alt="Judge Audrey Moran, Duval county, Florida, breast cancer patient," class="wp-image-406857" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran-court-Fl-16-x-9--1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran-court-Fl-16-x-9--300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran-court-Fl-16-x-9--768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran-court-Fl-16-x-9--1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran-court-Fl-16-x-9-.jpg 1570w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Judge Audrey Moran</figcaption>



<p>Judge Audrey Moran is known for her strength and fairness in the courtroom in Florida's Duval county. But one of the most difficult cases she's faced is <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a> that spread to the lining of her brain.&nbsp;</p>



<p>With the help of a dedicated <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/breast-clinic/sections/overview/ovc-20459469">care team</a> and precise treatment, Judge Moran is back on the bench, and recent scans show something remarkable.  Alex Osiadacz (oh-SIGH-dus) has her story.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/Vqlk-CKDv4E" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Back on the bench: Judge's metastatic breast cancer journey inspires hope</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeVqlkCKDv4E" title="Back on the bench - Judge's metastatic breast cancer journey inspires hope" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Vqlk-CKDv4E?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>&nbsp;<strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (2:17) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/SCRIPT-_Back_on_the_bench__Judge_s_metastatic_breast_cancer_journey_inspires_hope_Script_NewsNetwork_NewsCenter.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"I work as a county court judge."</p>



<p>Judge Moran doesn't shy away from a challenge, whether in her legal career, solving issues in her community or even her health.<br><br>"We were treating the metastatic breast cancer in my abdomen about two years ago now. I began noticing that my balance wasn't very good, and then I started limping," she says.</p>



<p>Scans in early 2024 showed the cancer had spread to the lining of her brain and spine. Treatment would pose another challenge after Judge Moran developed an infection where a port would deliver <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/chemotherapy/about/pac-20385033" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chemotherapy</a> into the lining of her brain.</p>



<p>"I said, 'We're going to have to figure something else out.' My wonderful oncologist, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/advani-pooja-p-m-b-b-s-m-d/bio-20464247" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Pooja Advani</a>, said she thought she had an idea because a new chemo had come out that she thought might be just the right thing for me," she says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran_treatment-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Judge Audrey Moran, Duval county, Florida, receives treatment for breast cancer" class="wp-image-406860" style="width:703px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran_treatment-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran_treatment-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran_treatment-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran_treatment-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran_treatment-16-x-9.jpg 1824w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Judge Moran receiving treatment</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Instead of delivering treatment directly into the lining of her brain, Judge Moran's care team was able to deliver a newly approved therapy through her arm.&nbsp;The results were better than expected.</p>



<p>"The last scan I got of my brain, the results were that the brain cancer has resolved. And I got to tell you, I couldn't even believe it when I read it on my report," Judge Moran says.</p>



<p>"So many emotions but the biggest of gratitude, you know, to all the people that have worked as a part of her team," says Dr. Advani.</p>



<p>Follow-up appointments have confirmed that the treatment is still working for the metastasis in her abdomen.&nbsp;Beyond her diagnosis, Judge Moran remains active with her family and career.</p>



<p>She says, "You know, my life is back. I am at work. And I'm getting to do that work that I love."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran_Dr.-Advani-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Judge Audrey Moran,with Dr. Pooja Advani" class="wp-image-406859" style="width:726px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran_Dr.-Advani-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran_Dr.-Advani-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran_Dr.-Advani-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran_Dr.-Advani-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran_Dr.-Advani-16-x-9.jpg 1824w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Judge Moran talking with Dr. Pooja Advani</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>In late September, Dr. Advani and Judge Moran had a chance to meet again.</p>



<p>"It almost brought me to tears to have seen how she was in 2024 when she was going through this <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/care-at-mayo-clinic/mac-20352479" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">journey </a>and the remarkable clinical progress that she has made," Dr. Advani says.</p>



<p>Judge Moran adds, "I'd gotten to the point where I almost didn't want to try anything anymore, and she really helped me realize this wasn't the time to give up. It was time to keep going. And boy, I'm glad I did. I'm really, really glad I did."</p>



<p><strong>Related posts:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-leads-4-decades-of-advances-in-breast-cancer-care/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic leads 4 decades of advances in breast cancer care</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-research-improves-dense-breast-cancer-screening-and-early-detection/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic research improves dense breast cancer screening and early detection</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/top-10-questions-about-breast-cancer-answered/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Top 10 questions about breast cancer answered</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-treats-first-person-in-the-us-with-a-novel-radiopharmaceutical-therapy-for-breast-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic treats first person in the US with a novel radiopharmaceutical therapy for breast cancer</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-mri-for-dense-breasts-what-to-know/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: MRI for dense breasts — what to know</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-how-to-decide-which-breast-cancer-surgery-is-right-for-you/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: How to decide which breast cancer surgery is right for you</a></li>
</ul>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/wp-admin/post.php?post=394884&amp;action=edit"></a></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ready-for-10-13-back-on-the-bench-judges-metastatic-breast-cancer-journey-inspires-hope/">(VIDEO) Back on the bench: Judge’s metastatic breast cancer journey inspires hope</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran-court-Fl-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Judge-Moran-court-Fl-16-x-9-.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Breast Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Pooja Advani]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</atom:link></channel>
</rss> 