<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 18:19:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Earlier, more personalized follow-up care through prostate-specific antigen (PSA) monitoring, supported by AI powered by Mayo Clinic Platform</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/earlier-more-personalized-follow-up-care-through-prostate-specific-antigen-psa-monitoring-supported-by-ai-powered-by-mayo-clinic-platform/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jftmayo]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 17:13:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Mark Waddle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=409485</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — To help meet the potentially complex needs of patients after prostate cancer treatment and offer the precision and care necessary in the follow-up journey, Mayo Clinic’s Department of Radiation Oncology developed the PSA Control Tower. This is an intelligent monitoring tool designed to support clinicians in keeping a close, ongoing watch over [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/earlier-more-personalized-follow-up-care-through-prostate-specific-antigen-psa-monitoring-supported-by-ai-powered-by-mayo-clinic-platform/">Earlier, more personalized follow-up care through prostate-specific antigen (PSA) monitoring, supported by AI powered by Mayo Clinic Platform</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Doctor-discusses-health-with-senior-patient-in-hospital_284569472-1024x576.jpg" alt="Doctor sitting next to a senior male patient lying and sitting up in hospital bed, discussing health, treatment, and diagnosis. Doctor using a digital tablet to review health chart with the patient." class="wp-image-409453" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Doctor-discusses-health-with-senior-patient-in-hospital_284569472-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Doctor-discusses-health-with-senior-patient-in-hospital_284569472-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Doctor-discusses-health-with-senior-patient-in-hospital_284569472-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Doctor-discusses-health-with-senior-patient-in-hospital_284569472.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — To help meet the potentially complex needs of patients after prostate cancer treatment and offer the precision and care necessary in the follow-up journey, Mayo Clinic’s Department of Radiation Oncology developed the PSA Control Tower. This is an intelligent monitoring tool designed to support clinicians in keeping a close, ongoing watch over patients after treatment.</p>



<p>Traditionally, the follow-up care for prostate cancer patients follows a standard schedule and relies on manual review. This process can be time-consuming and may delay care due to administrative steps. Subtle but important changes in test results can be missed or recognized too late. Because of this, patients often need faster intervention and a more personalized approach to care.</p>



<p>Prostate cancer follow-up depends on understanding prostate-specific antigen (PSA) trends over time. Each PSA test is important, but spotting early signs of recurrence requires regular contact and ongoing monitoring. As patient numbers grow and care becomes more complex, this process can be difficult to manage. Health systems are under increasing pressure to provide reliable follow-up without adding strain to care teams.</p>



<p>The PSA Control Tower brings together clinical information and PSA trends, using intelligent tools to support care teams in understanding which patients may need attention and when. By bringing potential concerns to light earlier, the system helps teams stay connected to patients. Throughout the process, clinical expertise, thoughtful judgment, and human connection continue to guide every decision.</p>



<p>Behind the scenes, the PSA Control Tower is powered by <a href="https://www.mayoclinicplatform.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Platform</a>, which provides a secure environment where Mayo Clinic staff have access to large amounts of de-identified patient data. This enables teams to study patterns over time and build predictive models using information such as lab results, clinical notes, imaging and pathology.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Dr.-Mark-Waddle_1652626_3911824_0002-200x300.jpg" alt="Portrait of Dr. Mark Waddle" class="wp-image-409486" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Dr.-Mark-Waddle_1652626_3911824_0002-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Dr.-Mark-Waddle_1652626_3911824_0002-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Dr.-Mark-Waddle_1652626_3911824_0002.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mark Waddle, M.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>“Our hope is that the PSA Control Tower will be a rare win-win-win for patients, physicians and hospital systems,” says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/waddle-mark-r-m-d/bio-20532761" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mark Waddle, M.D.</a> “The ‘Control Tower’ will allow each and every patient to be monitored 24/7 — for peace of mind that all patients are being followed per guidelines and that abnormal PSA values are acted upon.”</p>



<p>As new data are introduced, the predictive models continue to learn and improve. Through Mayo Clinic Platform technology, clinicians will be able to easily view PSA trends and recurrence risk through clear dashboards, giving them timely information to support informed conversations and personalized care while keeping clinical expertise and compassion at the center.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A scalable vision for the future</strong></h2>



<p>The PSA Control Tower reflects Mayo Clinic’s Bold. Forward. vision for precision oncology, which includes combining advanced analytics, secure data access, and seamless clinical integration. As this model expands beyond Mayo Clinic, it offers a path toward earlier detection, more efficient workflows, and scalable, data-driven follow-up care for prostate cancer patients nationwide.</p>



<p>“This allows our care providers to see more new patients, treat more complex patients, and focus effort related to prostate cancer follow-up on the patients that truly need their expertise and time,” says Dr. Waddle.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&amp;nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;amp;utm_medium=l&amp;amp;utm_content=content&amp;amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;amp;geo=national&amp;amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;amp;invsrc=other&amp;amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;amp;utm_medium=l&amp;amp;utm_content=content&amp;amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;amp;geo=national&amp;amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;amp;invsrc=other&amp;amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center&amp;nbsp;</strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the <a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs&amp;nbsp;in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong> </p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/earlier-more-personalized-follow-up-care-through-prostate-specific-antigen-psa-monitoring-supported-by-ai-powered-by-mayo-clinic-platform/">Earlier, more personalized follow-up care through prostate-specific antigen (PSA) monitoring, supported by AI powered by Mayo Clinic Platform</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Doctor-discusses-health-with-senior-patient-in-hospital_284569472_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Doctor-discusses-health-with-senior-patient-in-hospital_284569472.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Mark Waddle]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Mayo Clinic study advances personalized prostate cancer education with an EHR-integrated AI agent&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-study-advances-personalized-prostate-cancer-education-with-an-ehr-integrated-ai-agent/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rebeccabromelkamp]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 17:45:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AI and Digital Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Wei Liu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=409383</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>PHOENIX&nbsp;—&nbsp;Mayo Clinic&nbsp;researchers have developed and evaluated MedEduChat, an electronic health record (EHR)&nbsp;that&nbsp;works with&nbsp;a&nbsp;large language model to provide accurate, patient-specific prostate cancer education.&nbsp;&nbsp; The findings are published in&amp;#160;Nature Portfolio Digital Medicine&amp;#160;and highlight&amp;#160;a new approach&amp;#160;to delivering&amp;#160;timely, individualized guidance for people navigating a prostate cancer diagnosis.&amp;#160;&amp;#160; Cancer patients often face uncertainty as they process complex information about their [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-study-advances-personalized-prostate-cancer-education-with-an-ehr-integrated-ai-agent/">New Mayo Clinic study advances personalized prostate cancer education with an EHR-integrated AI agent&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Man-using-computer-tablet-shutterstock_151335656-16x9--1024x576.jpg" alt="Man smiling, using computer tablet" class="wp-image-409385" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Man-using-computer-tablet-shutterstock_151335656-16x9--1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Man-using-computer-tablet-shutterstock_151335656-16x9--300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Man-using-computer-tablet-shutterstock_151335656-16x9--768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Man-using-computer-tablet-shutterstock_151335656-16x9--1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Man-using-computer-tablet-shutterstock_151335656-16x9-.jpg 1604w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>PHOENIX&nbsp;—&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;researchers have developed and evaluated MedEduChat, an electronic health record (EHR)&nbsp;that&nbsp;works with&nbsp;a&nbsp;large language model to provide accurate, patient-specific <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prostate-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353087" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">prostate cancer</a> education.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The findings are published in&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41746-025-02166-0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nature Portfolio Digital Medicine</a>&amp;nbsp;and highlight&amp;nbsp;a new approach&amp;nbsp;to delivering&amp;nbsp;timely, individualized guidance for people navigating a prostate cancer diagnosis.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Cancer patients often face uncertainty as they process complex information about their diagnosis and treatment options. Limited time with clinicians can make it difficult for patients to receive the detailed answers they need to understand decisions that shape their care.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>This&nbsp;MedEduChat&nbsp;study&nbsp;demonstrates&nbsp;how advanced AI, grounded in Mayo-validated clinical data, can help bridge these gaps by delivering clear, conversational explanations based on each patient's own health record.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Understanding the patient experience using&amp;nbsp;AI</strong>&amp;nbsp;</h2>



<p>Fifteen prostate cancer patients interacted with&amp;nbsp;MedEduChat&amp;nbsp;for 20 to 30 minutes as part of a mixed-method usability study conducted at Mayo Clinic campuses in Arizona and Minnesota.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Patients reported higher confidence after using the tool, with Health Confidence Scores increasing from 9.9 to 13.9 on a 16-point scale. Usability scores were also high;&nbsp;average survey responses ranked MedEduChat&nbsp;83.7 out of 100.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Patients noted that&amp;nbsp;MedEduChat&amp;nbsp;helped them understand their diagnosis in a more accessible way. The&amp;nbsp;tool&amp;nbsp;provided relief by explaining unfamiliar or complex terms&amp;nbsp;in a clear and concise manner.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The conversational format&nbsp;helped&nbsp;participants replace incorrect assumptions with medically accurate information derived from their own EHR.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Clinician-evaluated accuracy and safety</strong>&amp;nbsp;</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/liu-wei-ph-d/bio-20055721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Wei Liu, Ph.D.</a>,&nbsp;a radiation oncology medical physicist,&nbsp;and three Mayo Clinic clinicians independently reviewed 85 anonymized question-and-response pairs. They rated MedEduChat's answers as highly correct (2.9 out of 3), complete (2.7 out of 3) and safe (2.7 out of 3).&nbsp;</p>



<p>Clinicians also noted strong patient-readiness and moderate personalization, reflecting&nbsp;MedEduChat's ability to tailor explanations to each person's age, treatment history and cancer stage.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Although&nbsp;MedEduChat&nbsp;delivered&nbsp;accurate&nbsp;and clinically aligned information, clinicians emphasized the importance of ongoing monitoring to prevent errors that could arise from incomplete or inconsistently documented EHR data.</p>



<p>The research team incorporated a&nbsp;multilayer&nbsp;approach&nbsp;to address these concerns and guide future system enhancements.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Combining patient-centered education with AI</strong>&amp;nbsp;</h2>



<p>MedEduChat&nbsp;was designed with a structured educational model that combines closed-domain clinical data, semi-structured guidance and personalized interaction.</p>



<p>Patients can explore diagnosis details, learn about treatment options and side effects, and review lifestyle considerations and follow-up expectations. The tool draws only from validated sources,&nbsp;such as Mayo Clinic materials and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nccn.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Comprehensive Cancer Network</a>&nbsp;guidelines.</p>



<p>"This research demonstrates how large language models can be safely and effectively integrated into real clinical systems to improve cancer education,"&nbsp;according&nbsp;to Dr. Liu.&nbsp;"By combining advanced AI with Mayo Clinic's electronic health records, MedEduChat delivers personalized, accurate and easy-to-understand explanations tailored to each patient's medical history."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Expanding AI&amp;nbsp;cancer research</strong>&amp;nbsp;</h2>



<p>The study team plans to translate this work into clinical use across all three Mayo Clinic campuses&nbsp;in Arizona,&nbsp;Florida&nbsp;and Minnesota. Next steps include expanding MedEduChat beyond radiation oncology to additional cancer specialties. These efforts aim to make personalized AI-assisted education a routine part of cancer care.</p>



<p>This research was funded by the National Cancer Institute, the Eric and Wendy Schmidt Fund for AI Research and Innovation, the Fred C. and Katherine B. Andersen Foundation, and the Kemper Marley Foundation.</p>



<p>###&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</strong>&amp;nbsp;<br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&amp;nbsp;is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection,&amp;nbsp;prevention&amp;nbsp;and treatment to change lives.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo&amp;nbsp;Clinic</strong>&amp;nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion,&amp;nbsp;expertise&amp;nbsp;and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for&amp;nbsp;additional&amp;nbsp;Mayo Clinic news.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-study-advances-personalized-prostate-cancer-education-with-an-ehr-integrated-ai-agent/">New Mayo Clinic study advances personalized prostate cancer education with an EHR-integrated AI agent&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Man-using-computer-tablet-shutterstock_151335656.-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/Man-using-computer-tablet-shutterstock_151335656-16x9-.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Wei Liu]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic integrated care&nbsp;enables treatment for rare, complex cancer&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-integrated-care-enables-treatment-for-rare-complex-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jftmayo]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 13:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Eric Moore]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=408894</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER,&amp;#160;Minn.&amp;#160;—&amp;#160;A&amp;#160;multidisciplinary surgical team&amp;#160;at&amp;#160;Mayo Clinic&amp;#160;has successfully treated an exceptionally rare and life-threatening cancer that&amp;#160;invaded a&amp;#160;patient's&amp;#160;heart and airway. The procedure&amp;#160;combined&amp;#160;advanced cardiac surgery with complex airway reconstruction and&amp;#160;represents&amp;#160;a significant achievement in modern cancer care.&amp;#160; Tami Channel's&nbsp;thyroid cancer&nbsp;was so advanced&nbsp;that&nbsp;her family&nbsp;had begun&nbsp;planning hospice care. The&nbsp;tumor had&nbsp;severely compromised&nbsp;her&nbsp;airway&nbsp;and&nbsp;had encased her carotid artery and jugular vein, two of the body's most [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-integrated-care-enables-treatment-for-rare-complex-cancer/">Mayo Clinic integrated care&nbsp;enables treatment for rare, complex cancer&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-16x9-1-1024x768.jpg" alt="Tami Channel, a Mayo Clinic patient, was treated for a rare cancer" class="wp-image-408920" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-16x9-1-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-16x9-1-300x225.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-16x9-1-768x576.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-16x9-1.jpg 1500w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>
</div>


<p>ROCHESTER,&amp;nbsp;Minn.&amp;nbsp;—&amp;nbsp;A&amp;nbsp;multidisciplinary surgical team&amp;nbsp;at&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;has successfully treated an exceptionally rare and life-threatening cancer that&amp;nbsp;invaded a&amp;nbsp;patient's&amp;nbsp;heart and airway. The procedure&amp;nbsp;combined&amp;nbsp;advanced cardiac surgery with complex airway reconstruction and&amp;nbsp;represents&amp;nbsp;a significant achievement in modern cancer care.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Tami Channel's&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/thyroid-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20354161" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">thyroid cancer</a>&nbsp;was so advanced&nbsp;that&nbsp;her family&nbsp;had begun&nbsp;planning hospice care. The&nbsp;tumor had&nbsp;severely compromised&nbsp;her&nbsp;airway&nbsp;and&nbsp;had encased her carotid artery and jugular vein, two of the body's most vital blood vessels.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Primary cancers&nbsp;of&nbsp;the heart are extremely rare. Most tumors that appear in the heart are benign, and malignant cardiac tumors such as sarcomas account for only a&nbsp;small&nbsp;fraction of all cancers. Airway tumors involving the throat or trachea are also uncommon and often detected late because early symptoms can&nbsp;resemble&nbsp;routine respiratory&nbsp;issues. When&nbsp;a malignant&nbsp;growth extends into both the heart and the airway, the risks multiply quickly because the tumor can narrow or block breathing passages and interfere with the heart's ability to function.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Faced with a tumor that had grown into vital structures and left the patient's airway&nbsp;nearly the&nbsp;width of a toothpick, the care team, including&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/ryder-mabel-m-d/bio-20055734" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mabel Ryder, M.D.</a>,&nbsp;a Mayo Clinic endocrinologist,&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/moore-eric-j-m-d/bio-20053794" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Eric Moore, M.D.</a>,&nbsp;a&nbsp;Mayo Clinic head and neck surgeon,&nbsp;recognized that conventional treatment would not be enough.&nbsp;Tami needed&nbsp;a highly complex&nbsp;surgery — and it needed to happen quickly.&nbsp;As a matter of priority, Tami would undergo an unscheduled thoracotomy and bypass, an emergency open-chest operation that requires opening the chest cavity, supporting circulation through a heart-lung machine, and working around critical airways and blood vessels. Few hospitals could coordinate such a demanding procedure so quickly.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="973" height="547" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-Dr.-Eric-Moore-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-408921" style="aspect-ratio:1.778836609092714;width:613px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-Dr.-Eric-Moore-16x9-1.jpg 973w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-Dr.-Eric-Moore-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-Dr.-Eric-Moore-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 973px) 100vw, 973px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Tami Channel with Dr. Eric Moore</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>"We were able to make it happen because it needed to be done," Dr. Moore says. "That's the Mayo difference."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The operating room reflected Mayo's integrated model: anesthesiology, perfusion, bronchoscopy, cardiothoracic surgery,&amp;nbsp;and head and neck surgery, with each discipline contributing seamlessly.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"It felt like&amp;nbsp;a choreographed&amp;nbsp;ballet," Dr. Moore says. "This kind of multidisciplinary precision doesn't just happen — it's the Mayo model in action."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>During the same operation, specialists reconstructed the airway to restore safe breathing. Procedures of this complexity rely on close coordination among cardiac surgeons, thoracic and airway surgeons, ear, nose and throat&nbsp;specialists, anesthesiologists,&nbsp;oncologists,&nbsp;and critical care teams. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;experts&nbsp;are&nbsp;uniquely positioned to manage these cases because they can move quickly from diagnosis&nbsp;to&nbsp;complex&nbsp;surgery&nbsp;and recovery.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This successful intervention shows what is possible when specialists collaborate on rare cancers that cross organ systems.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>###&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic&nbsp;</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion,&nbsp;expertise&nbsp;and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for&nbsp;additional&nbsp;Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong> &amp;nbsp;<br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the <a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives. &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:&nbsp;</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:Newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-integrated-care-enables-treatment-for-rare-complex-cancer/">Mayo Clinic integrated care&nbsp;enables treatment for rare, complex cancer&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Tami-Channel-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Eric Moore]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic&nbsp;researcher&nbsp;brings new clarity to breast cancer risk through genetics research&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researcher-brings-new-clarity-to-breast-cancer-risk-through-genetics-research/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rebeccabromelkamp]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 17:26:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Fergus Couch]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=409115</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researcher&nbsp;Fergus Couch, Ph.D.,&nbsp;has spent his career studying inherited&nbsp;breast cancer&nbsp;and cancer genetics. Early on, he saw that many families lived with uncertainty of their cancer risk, especially when genetic tests revealed variants no one fully understood.&nbsp; He set out to change that.&amp;#160;&amp;#160; Dr. Couch&amp;#160;is&amp;#160;a&amp;#160;consultant&amp;#160;in&amp;#160;laboratory medicine and pathology&amp;#160;at&amp;#160;the&amp;#160;Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center&amp;#160;and holds the Zbigniew [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researcher-brings-new-clarity-to-breast-cancer-risk-through-genetics-research/">Mayo Clinic&nbsp;researcher&nbsp;brings new clarity to breast cancer risk through genetics research&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/Fergus-Couch-PhD-microscope_16x9.jpg" alt="Dr. Fergus Couch sitting at a microscope" class="wp-image-349652" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/Fergus-Couch-PhD-microscope_16x9.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/Fergus-Couch-PhD-microscope_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/Fergus-Couch-PhD-microscope_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Fergus Couch, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic researcher&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/couch-fergus-j-ph-d/bio-00027515" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Fergus Couch, Ph.D.</a>,&nbsp;has spent his career studying inherited&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a>&nbsp;and cancer genetics. Early on, he saw that many families lived with uncertainty of their cancer risk, especially when genetic tests revealed variants no one fully understood.&nbsp;</p>



<p>He set out to change that.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Couch&amp;nbsp;is&amp;nbsp;a&amp;nbsp;consultant&amp;nbsp;in&amp;nbsp;laboratory medicine and pathology&amp;nbsp;at&amp;nbsp;the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&amp;nbsp;and holds the Zbigniew and Anna M. Scheller Professorship in Medical Research in Honor of Dr. Thomas J. McDonald.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic works with an international network of collaborators, which includes Dr. Couch and his team,&amp;nbsp;who have&amp;nbsp;helped&amp;nbsp;identify&amp;nbsp;many inherited gene alterations that contribute to breast cancer risk.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="857" height="857" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Fergus-Couch-Ph.D.-1554072_3786066_0018-1x1-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-409119" style="width:239px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Fergus-Couch-Ph.D.-1554072_3786066_0018-1x1-1.jpg 857w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Fergus-Couch-Ph.D.-1554072_3786066_0018-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Fergus-Couch-Ph.D.-1554072_3786066_0018-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Fergus-Couch-Ph.D.-1554072_3786066_0018-1x1-1-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 857px) 100vw, 857px" /></figure>
</div>


<p>"We interact on a thematic level — surgeons, oncologists, pathologists, geneticists and biochemists," Dr. Couch shares. "We all work together, focused on improving our knowledge of breast cancer and quickly developing treatments and cures for patients at Mayo Clinic."&nbsp;</p>



<p>Earlier this year,&nbsp;Dr. Couch and other co-authors&nbsp;published&nbsp;a study in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-08388-8" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nature</a>,&nbsp;which&nbsp;included&nbsp;one of the most comprehensive functional maps to date of the BRCA2 cancer risk gene.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>By testing&amp;nbsp;nearly every&amp;nbsp;possible change&amp;nbsp;in this gene, Mayo Clinic researchers can&amp;nbsp;identify&amp;nbsp;which patients are more likely to&amp;nbsp;benefit&amp;nbsp;from targeted cancer therapies.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The work reclassifies previously uncertain genetic test results, helping care teams individualize cancer screening,&amp;nbsp;prevention&amp;nbsp;and treatment. Together, it shows how Mayo Clinic is turning complex genetic data into information clinicians can use now, a central goal of&amp;nbsp;precision medicine.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"It's the extra step that makes the difference, helping people use the findings immediately," Dr. Couch says. "The results of our paper&amp;nbsp;are used to help patients in the clinic. My entire career has been focused on getting information to patients as quickly as possible."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Today, Dr. Couch continues to explore why certain inherited changes lead to cancer, why some families develop breast cancer without known risk&amp;nbsp;genes&amp;nbsp;and how discoveries in the lab can&amp;nbsp;translate&amp;nbsp;to improved&amp;nbsp;care.&amp;nbsp;Just this month,&amp;nbsp;Dr. Couch won the prestigious Komen&amp;nbsp;Brinker Award for Scientific Distinction in Basic Science&amp;nbsp;for his significant work in advancing breast cancer research.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion,&nbsp;expertise&nbsp;and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for&nbsp;additional&nbsp;Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</strong>&amp;nbsp;<br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&amp;nbsp;is defining new boundaries in possibility, focusing on patient-centered care, developing novel treatments, training future generations of cancer experts, and bringing cancer research to communities. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs that are changing approaches to cancer prevention, screening and treatment, and improving the lives of cancer survivors. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center Blog</a>&amp;nbsp;for news,&amp;nbsp;information&amp;nbsp;and stories from Mayo Clinic's cancer experts and patients.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researcher-brings-new-clarity-to-breast-cancer-risk-through-genetics-research/">Mayo Clinic&nbsp;researcher&nbsp;brings new clarity to breast cancer risk through genetics research&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/Fergus-Couch-PhD-microscope_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/Fergus-Couch-PhD-microscope_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Fergus Couch]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers find new hope for toughest myeloma through off-the-shelf immunotherapy&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-find-new-hope-for-toughest-myeloma-through-off-the-shelf-immunotherapy/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jftmayo]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 21:16:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Shaji Kumar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=408813</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A new Mayo Clinic study published in the New England Journal of Medicine has uncovered that an off-the-shelf, dual-antibody therapy can generate deep and durable responses in extramedullary multiple myeloma — one of the most aggressive and treatment-resistant forms of the disease.&amp;#160; "We are seeing powerful responses in a disease that historically [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-find-new-hope-for-toughest-myeloma-through-off-the-shelf-immunotherapy/">Mayo Clinic researchers find new hope for toughest myeloma through off-the-shelf immunotherapy&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/05/Myeloma16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-273595" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/05/Myeloma16x9.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/05/Myeloma16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/05/Myeloma16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><br>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A new Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMoa2514752" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> published in the New England Journal of Medicine has uncovered that an off-the-shelf, dual-antibody therapy can generate deep and durable responses in extramedullary <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/multiple-myeloma/symptoms-causes/syc-20353378" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">multiple myeloma</a> — one of the most aggressive and treatment-resistant forms of the disease.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"We are seeing powerful responses in a disease that historically has resisted every therapy," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/kumar-shaji-m-d/bio-00027411" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Shaji Kumar, M.D.</a>, a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> hematologist and senior author of the study. "By recruiting T cells in two distinct ways at once, this dual-target antibody strategy can generate responses in patients who have had very few effective options."&amp;nbsp; </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="891" height="891" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Kumar-Shaji-K.-MD_12620637_201304290337-1x1-1.jpg" alt="Shaji Kumar, M.D." class="wp-image-408817" style="width:266px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Kumar-Shaji-K.-MD_12620637_201304290337-1x1-1.jpg 891w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Kumar-Shaji-K.-MD_12620637_201304290337-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Kumar-Shaji-K.-MD_12620637_201304290337-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Kumar-Shaji-K.-MD_12620637_201304290337-1x1-1-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 891px) 100vw, 891px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Shaji Kumar, M.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>The approach combines two engineered antibodies, talquetamab and teclistamab, that simultaneously engage T cells and force them to attack myeloma cells through two separate immune pathways. Unlike CAR-T cell therapy, which requires custom manufacturing, this regimen is delivered as a standard infusion-center injection.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>In a trial involving 90 patients, 79% responded to treatment, and 54% achieved no detectable disease by imaging or blood testing. Among responders, nearly two-thirds maintained disease control at one year, a striking improvement for a subtype that typically carries a months-long prognosis.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>This is the first large, prospective study defined specifically by PET/MRI scan and focused exclusively on true extramedullary myeloma, not a mix of para- and extramedullary disease. Serious side effects were common. Infection was one serious side effect and underscores the importance of comprehensive supportive care alongside immunotherapy.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The next big questions are whether this dual-target strategy can be moved earlier in the disease course, how safety can be optimized further through infection monitoring and prevention, and whether similar "two-locks, one-key" immune designs can be applied to other hard-to-treat cancers.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>For a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding, review the <a href="https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMoa2514752" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>###&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic&amp;nbsp;</strong>&amp;nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong>&amp;nbsp;<br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the National Cancer Institute, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo<strong> </strong>Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:&amp;nbsp;</strong>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-find-new-hope-for-toughest-myeloma-through-off-the-shelf-immunotherapy/">Mayo Clinic researchers find new hope for toughest myeloma through off-the-shelf immunotherapy&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Kumar-Shaji-K.-MD_12620637_201304290337-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/05/Myeloma16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Shaji Kumar]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>GE HealthCare and Mayo Clinic unveil GEMINI-RT, a bold research collaboration in radiation therapy and advanced cancer care&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ge-healthcare-and-mayo-clinic-unveil-gemini-rt-a-bold-research-collaboration-in-radiation-therapy-and-advanced-cancer-care/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tom Millikin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 18:24:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Care]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GEMINI-RT]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Radiation Therapy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=408672</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>CHICAGO — GE HealthCare and Mayo Clinic today are announcing the GE HealthCare-Mayo Clinic Initiative in Radiation Therapy, known as GEMINI-RT, an ambitious new collaboration that aims to transform personalized radiation therapy and cancer care. Building on decades of collaboration and the Strategic Radiology Research Collaboration signed in 2023, GEMINI-RT plans to drive innovation in [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ge-healthcare-and-mayo-clinic-unveil-gemini-rt-a-bold-research-collaboration-in-radiation-therapy-and-advanced-cancer-care/">GE HealthCare and Mayo Clinic unveil GEMINI-RT, a bold research collaboration in radiation therapy and advanced cancer care&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Radiation-therapy-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Radiation therapy" class="wp-image-408675" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Radiation-therapy-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Radiation-therapy-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Radiation-therapy-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Radiation-therapy-16x9-1.jpg 1026w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>GE HealthCare and Mayo Clinic launch GEMINI-RT, a strategic initiative to personalize radiation therapy by integrating imaging, artificial intelligence (AI) and patient monitoring across the cancer care continuum.&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>The collaboration focuses on four pillars — automation, predictive oncology, multi-modal therapies and outpatient monitoring — to enhance clinical outcomes, reduce clinician burnout and accelerate innovation in radiation oncology.<br>&nbsp;<br></li>
</ul>



<p>CHICAGO — GE HealthCare and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> today are announcing the GE HealthCare-Mayo Clinic Initiative in Radiation Therapy, known as GEMINI-RT, an ambitious new collaboration that aims to transform personalized radiation therapy and cancer care. Building on decades of collaboration and the Strategic Radiology Research Collaboration <a href="https://www.gehealthcare.com/about/newsroom/press-releases/mayo-clinic-and-ge-healthcare-enter-strategic-collaboration-to-advance-innovation-in-medical-imaging-and-theranostics?npclid=botnpclid&amp;amp;srsltid=AfmBOopLgImTEsmRjcZdV7pKR51qxkmmySmli_s5XFnjp91QSxct9Va3" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">signed in 2023</a>, GEMINI-RT plans to drive innovation in prediction, planning, automation, workflow and monitoring for radiation oncology.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>GEMINI-RT combines Mayo Clinic's world-class clinical and research expertise with GE HealthCare's leading technical and engineering innovation in oncology care and radiation therapy. The initiative aims to deliver comprehensive, personalized care by exploring integrating imaging, advanced therapies, dosimetry and patient monitoring at every step of the patient journey — from detection and diagnosis to treatment and follow-up.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/radiation-therapy/about/pac-20385162" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Radiation therapy</a> is a cornerstone of cancer care, used in more than 50% of cases worldwide and for over 2 million U.S. patients annually<sup>1,2</sup>. The rising rates of new cancer diagnoses worldwide, with 19.3 million new cases in 2022, continues to drive demand for this treatment<sup>3</sup>. Through GEMINI-RT, Mayo Clinic and GE HealthCare aim to make personalized radiation therapy accessible by integrating streamlined, data-driven solutions that will leverage Mayo Clinic's clinical expertise and patient outcomes data.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"GEMINI-RT is grounded in the concept of 'twinning the patient, personalizing the beam' — a transformative approach made possible by Mayo Clinic's extensive clinical expertise and outcomes data," said <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/traughber-bryan-j-m-d/bio-20542149" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bryan Traughber, M.D.</a>, vice chair of innovation for radiation oncology at Mayo Clinic. "The combination of research and technological acumen could allow us to model individual patient journeys with precision, enabling radiation therapy treatments that are truly tailored to each patient."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The collaboration will deepen efforts across four strategic areas:&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Automation: </strong>Collaborating on AI-powered solutions to eliminate repetitive tasks and accelerate treatment planning.&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Predictive oncology: </strong>Harnessing clinical insights to personalize cancer treatment decisions and improve outcomes.&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Multimodal therapies: </strong>Exploring approaches that combine radiation with emerging treatments like targeted drugs and precision heating for more effective care.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Connected care: </strong>Using AI, biomarkers and sensors to monitor patients beyond the clinic — with the aim of predicting side effects early and supporting treatment at home.<strong>&amp;nbsp;</strong>&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>"This effort enables us to collaborate on solutions that are not only leading-edge but also clinically meaningful, helping shape the future of personalized radiation therapy. By integrating innovative technology and AI across the care continuum, we can improve clinician experience, support high-quality patient care and help reduce burnout among care teams," said Dr. Ben Newton, global head of oncology for GE Healthcare.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>GEMINI-RT research and activities will be based at Mayo Clinic's campus in Rochester, Minnesota, leveraging both organizations' strengths in clinical practice, research and product development. This initiative will build on the accomplishments of 2023 Strategic Radiology Research Collaboration in which GE HealthCare and Mayo Clinic are collaborating on projects in advanced magnetic resonance (MR) technologies and techniques, theranostics treatment for cancer, and diagnostic and interventional ultrasound.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>[1] International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC). 2023. “<a href="https://www.iarc.who.int/reference/expanding-global-access-to-radiotherapy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Expanding Global Access to Radiotherapy.</a>”</li>



<li>[2] American Society for Radiation Oncology (ASTRO). 2020. “<a href="https://www.astro.org/ASTRO/media/ASTRO/News%20and%20Publications/Press%20Kits/PDFs/2020/AM20_PressSlidesMaroongroge203.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Geographic Access to Radiation Therapy in the United States.</a>” ASTRO Press Kit.</li>



<li>[3] World Health Organization (WHO). 2024. “<a href="https://www.who.int/news/item/01-02-2024-global-cancer-burden-growing--amidst-mounting-need-for-services" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Global Cancer Burden Growing Amidst Mounting Need for Services.</a>” WHO News Release.</li>
</ul>



<p>###&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About GE HealthCare Technologies Inc.</strong>&amp;nbsp;<br>GE HealthCare is a trusted partner and leading global healthcare solutions provider, innovating medical technology, pharmaceutical diagnostics, and integrated, cloud-first AI-enabled solutions, services and data analytics. It aims to make hospitals and health systems more efficient, clinicians more effective, therapies more precise, and patients healthier and happier. Serving patients and providers for more than 125 years, GE HealthCare is advancing personalized, connected and compassionate care, while simplifying the patient's journey across care pathways. Together, its Imaging, Advanced Visualization Solutions, Patient Care Solutions and Pharmaceutical Diagnostics businesses help improve patient care from screening and diagnosis to therapy and monitoring. GE HealthCare is a $19.7 billion business with approximately 53,000 colleagues working to create a world where healthcare has no limits.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>GE HealthCare is proud to be among <a href="https://nam10.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Ffortune.com%2Franking%2Fworlds-most-admired-companies%2F&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7COCE.SupportTeam%40gehealthcare.com%7C9e0a9aa9f24342bda69f08dd4b827cc0%7C9a309606d6ec4188a28a298812b4bbbf%7C0%7C0%7C638749745988740719%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=lT68MWPeh1hpMIhMmUkjm31bg19GOkqd9j%2BKE8yfioQ%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">2025 </a><a href="https://nam10.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Ffortune.com%2Franking%2Fworlds-most-admired-companies%2F&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7COCE.SupportTeam%40gehealthcare.com%7C9e0a9aa9f24342bda69f08dd4b827cc0%7C9a309606d6ec4188a28a298812b4bbbf%7C0%7C0%7C638749745988772649%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=uYkV37NoqWiLDeSwirRYG6rZMKLFs1BfoSol%2F9%2BBv8g%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Fortune</a><a href="https://nam10.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Ffortune.com%2Franking%2Fworlds-most-admired-companies%2F&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7COCE.SupportTeam%40gehealthcare.com%7C9e0a9aa9f24342bda69f08dd4b827cc0%7C9a309606d6ec4188a28a298812b4bbbf%7C0%7C0%7C638749745988787851%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=zjTYbvmfCecIqa5JO6WoaMvkHHKo0o3iwxmHCgMR4q0%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"> World’s Most Admired Companies</a><a href="https://nam10.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Ffortune.com%2Franking%2Fworlds-most-admired-companies%2F&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7COCE.SupportTeam%40gehealthcare.com%7C9e0a9aa9f24342bda69f08dd4b827cc0%7C9a309606d6ec4188a28a298812b4bbbf%7C0%7C0%7C638749745988803321%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=WUx6%2FHlPwm61Cdggvn84ZTrDX8m%2FupTLSFgrl14VUCA%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">.</a> &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Follow GE HealthCare on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/gehealthcare/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">LinkedIn</a>, <a href="https://x.com/GEHealthCare" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">X</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/GEHealthCare/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/gehealthcare/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Instagram</a>, and <a href="https://www.gehealthcare.com/insights" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Insights</a> for the latest news, or visit its <a href="https://www.gehealthcare.com" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">website </a>or more information.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&amp;nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contacts:</strong>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Caitlin Lamey, GE HealthCare, <a href="mailto:caitlin.lamey@gehealthcare.com" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">caitlin.lamey@gehealthcare.com</a></li>



<li>Tom Millikin, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ge-healthcare-and-mayo-clinic-unveil-gemini-rt-a-bold-research-collaboration-in-radiation-therapy-and-advanced-cancer-care/">GE HealthCare and Mayo Clinic unveil GEMINI-RT, a bold research collaboration in radiation therapy and advanced cancer care&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Radiation-therapy-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Radiation-therapy-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer Care]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[GEMINI-RT]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Radiation Therapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Small team, big impact: Automation helps relieve symptoms to keep cancer patients out of the ER&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/small-team-big-impact-automation-helps-relieve-symptoms-to-keep-cancer-patients-out-of-the-er/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[brandywelvaert]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 17:17:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[remote care]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Telehealth]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=408565</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — For many people living with cancer, symptoms such as pain, anxiety or insomnia can quickly spiral into an emergency room visit. Such visits can be financially costly and take an emotional toll on patients and their caregivers.&amp;#160;&amp;#160; A new study led by Mayo Clinic researchers found that using digital check-ins and a [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/small-team-big-impact-automation-helps-relieve-symptoms-to-keep-cancer-patients-out-of-the-er/">Small team, big impact: Automation helps relieve symptoms to keep cancer patients out of the ER&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1425" height="802" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Woman-using-tablet-virutal-visit-telehealth-WF5002214-16x9-1.jpg" alt="Woman using tablet virutal visit telehealth" class="wp-image-408580" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Woman-using-tablet-virutal-visit-telehealth-WF5002214-16x9-1.jpg 1425w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Woman-using-tablet-virutal-visit-telehealth-WF5002214-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Woman-using-tablet-virutal-visit-telehealth-WF5002214-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Woman-using-tablet-virutal-visit-telehealth-WF5002214-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1425px) 100vw, 1425px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — For many people living with cancer, symptoms such as pain, anxiety or insomnia can quickly spiral into an emergency room visit. Such visits can be financially costly and take an emotional toll on patients and their caregivers.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>A new <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1470204525005261?dgcid=author" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> led by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> researchers found that using digital check-ins and a remote care team can help patients manage symptoms before they reach a crisis point. </p>



<p>"Our goal was simple but ambitious," says study lead <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/cheville-andrea-l-m-d/bio-20054964" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Andrea Cheville, M.D.</a>, professor of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation in the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>. "We wanted to see if automating symptom check-ins and care through the electronic health record could improve patients' lives without adding to the burden on oncology teams. What we found is that this approach not only eased symptoms like anxiety and depression but also kept thousands of patients out of the hospital. That tells us technology can help us successfully extend the reach and efficacy of care."&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Becky-Johnson-1024x1024.jpg" alt="Image of Becky Johnson" class="wp-image-408577" style="width:234px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Becky-Johnson-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Becky-Johnson-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Becky-Johnson-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Becky-Johnson-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Becky-Johnson.jpg 1402w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Becky Johnson</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>For Becky Johnson, participating in the Enhanced EHR-Facilitated Cancer Symptom Control Trial (E2C2) meant better sleep — despite the anxiety she felt about her double breast cancer diagnosis in 2022 at the age of 40.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"I was continually Googling for more information about treatments, prognosis, new terminology and the experiences of others. And the steroid medications I took for treatment prior to chemo messed with my ability to sleep, too. It got to a point where my body's norm was to wake in the middle of the night and not fall back asleep, taking a toll on my ability to heal," says Johnson, program director for the Mayo Clinic School of Health Sciences Sonography Program.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>As part of the trial, Johnson regularly submitted digital surveys about various aspects of her health. Insomnia quickly rose to the top, prompting a phone call from a nurse, who counseled Johnson on ways to get a better night's rest. The nurse also gave Johnson a link to a self-paced online class with sleep strategies based in cognitive behavioral therapy.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"A virtual or phone call visit, especially when I didn't have anything physically wrong, was so convenient and efficient," says Johnson. The intervention helped, and her sleep improved.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>To make such interventions possible, the researchers developed automations in the Plummer Chart, the software system that manages patients' electronic health records (EHRs) and helps Mayo teams coordinate care. Between 2019 and 2023, just over 50,200 patients across 15 cancer specialties at Mayo Clinic enrolled in the E2C2 trial. Like Johnson, they filled out short surveys about pain, fatigue, sleep, anxiety and other symptoms before clinic visits or monthly between visits. The system automatically sorted their responses. Mild scores were simply logged, moderate ones triggered the system to send the patient self-care tips, and severe scores prompted outreach by a remote symptom care manager — a nurse or social worker who could work with patients via phone or video.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Behind the scenes, the software became both an automated traffic controller and safety net. For care teams, it routed information to patients automatically so they could focus on the work that required their expertise. For patients, it made getting support easier, with no additional appointments or travel.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The trial results showed that the automated surveys and responses built into the EHR made care more efficient and, ultimately, improved patients' symptoms.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Patients reported less anxiety and depression, with modest improvements in other symptoms.&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Patients had 40% to 60% fewer acute care encounters, including emergency visits, hospitalizations, and ICU admissions.&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>All of this was achieved with just 2-3 full-time care managers plus 20 percent of one physician's time supporting more than 50,000 study participants.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/E2C2-by-the-numbers-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-408582" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/E2C2-by-the-numbers-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/E2C2-by-the-numbers-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/E2C2-by-the-numbers-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/E2C2-by-the-numbers-16x9-1.jpg 1216w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The E2C2 trial showcases a new approach to using digital tools in cancer care. By automating routine monitoring and triaging of patient symptoms and well-being through the patient's electronic health record, a small care team can support a large patient population.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"The gains we saw are encouraging and point to a scalable way to extend supportive oncology care beyond the clinic walls, meeting patients where they are," says Dr. Cheville. "The next step is to ensure that these tools are available to healthcare teams, enabling them to efficiently reach every patient who needs supportive care."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The E2C2 trial was funded by the National Institutes of Health, National Cancer Institute (NCI) as part of the Cancer Moonshot℠. The study was conducted as part of NCI’s&nbsp;<a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fhealthcaredelivery.cancer.gov%2Fimpact%2F&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7CBalzer.Deborah%40mayo.edu%7C32ad8f9097f44a79dade08de31cf67a4%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C639002964016473569%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=PfYTCOPOQQtlt%2FzAf3hJYhlfoTq9PfsLjZ9kJIhcfOs%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">IMPACT Consortium</a>. Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.sciencedirect.com%2Fscience%2Farticle%2Fpii%2FS1470204525005261%3Fdgcid%3Dauthor&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7CBalzer.Deborah%40mayo.edu%7C32ad8f9097f44a79dade08de31cf67a4%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C639002964016484368%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=WBpwE%2F4Kjpd%2BPhjAnPAKO1hQd9x42DBJZqBVeMBv0Ew%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and additional funding.</p>



<p>###&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> &amp;nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;amp;utm_medium=l&amp;amp;utm_content=content&amp;amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;amp;geo=national&amp;amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;amp;invsrc=other&amp;amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>  is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.  &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong> &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a> &amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/small-team-big-impact-automation-helps-relieve-symptoms-to-keep-cancer-patients-out-of-the-er/">Small team, big impact: Automation helps relieve symptoms to keep cancer patients out of the ER&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Woman-using-tablet-virutal-visit-telehealth-WF5002214-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Woman-using-tablet-virutal-visit-telehealth-WF5002214-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[remote care]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Telehealth]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers identify why some lung tumors respond well to immunotherapy</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-why-some-lung-tumors-respond-well-to-immunotherapy/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kate Ledger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 15:18:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Alan Fields]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lung Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=408439</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. —&amp;#160;For some patients with the most common type of lung cancer, known as lung adenocarcinoma, there's new hope.&amp;#160;In a new study published in Cell Reports,&amp;#160;Mayo Clinic&amp;#160;researchers have found several previously unknown genetic and cellular processes that occur in lung adenocarcinoma tumors that respond well to immunotherapy. A recently approved group of drugs — [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-why-some-lung-tumors-respond-well-to-immunotherapy/">Mayo Clinic researchers identify why some lung tumors respond well to immunotherapy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-left-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Virtual-lung-image-Getty1439259946-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Virtual, digital lung image" class="wp-image-408433" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Virtual-lung-image-Getty1439259946-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Virtual-lung-image-Getty1439259946-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Virtual-lung-image-Getty1439259946-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Virtual-lung-image-Getty1439259946-16X9.jpg 1342w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Getty image</figcaption></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. —&amp;nbsp;For some patients with the most common type of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lung-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20374620" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lung cancer</a>, known as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/in-depth/adenocarcinoma/art-20580469" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lung adenocarcinoma</a>, there's new hope.&amp;nbsp;In a new <a href="https://www.cell.com/cell-reports/fulltext/S2211-1247(25)01378-6" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> published in Cell Reports,&amp;nbsp;Mayo Clinic&amp;nbsp;researchers have found several previously unknown genetic and cellular processes that occur in lung adenocarcinoma tumors that respond well to immunotherapy.</p>



<p>A recently approved group of drugs — immune checkpoint inhibitors — can boost the body's ability to eliminate a tumor and even keep the cancer from coming back. However, while the medications work well for some people, the drugs aren't effective for many other patients with the disease — and researchers are trying to determine why.&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Fields-Alan-P._14202000_20221121-1x1-1-1024x1024.jpg" alt="Alan Fields, Ph.D." class="wp-image-408396" style="width:290px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Fields-Alan-P._14202000_20221121-1x1-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Fields-Alan-P._14202000_20221121-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Fields-Alan-P._14202000_20221121-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Fields-Alan-P._14202000_20221121-1x1-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Fields-Alan-P._14202000_20221121-1x1-1-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Fields-Alan-P._14202000_20221121-1x1-1-2048x2048.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Alan Fields, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>"Our study describes the events that occur when a patient's tumor harbors only one copy of a cancer-causing gene, which occurs in 20% of cases," says&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/fields-alan-p-ph-d/bio-00028181" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alan P. Fields, Ph.D.</a>, a cancer biologist at&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&amp;nbsp;and the principal investigator of the study.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The research team found that the missing tumor-driving gene, known as PRKCI, results in tumors that are less aggressive. The missing gene also cultivates a more powerful immune response to tumors. Surprisingly, the research team found the improved immune response occurs with help from unexpected players: senescent tumor cells, also known as "<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-new-tool-to-find-hidden-zombie-cells/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">zombie cells</a>," which are typically associated with negative consequences of disease and aging.&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1188" height="1188" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Nguyen-Duy-T-Joey-30027902_202008250413-1x1-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-408544" style="width:190px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Nguyen-Duy-T-Joey-30027902_202008250413-1x1-1.jpg 1188w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Nguyen-Duy-T-Joey-30027902_202008250413-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Nguyen-Duy-T-Joey-30027902_202008250413-1x1-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Nguyen-Duy-T-Joey-30027902_202008250413-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Nguyen-Duy-T-Joey-30027902_202008250413-1x1-1-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1188px) 100vw, 1188px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Joey Nguyen</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>The study identified markers that may predict a positive response to immunotherapy and "ultimately may help clinicians stratify patients who are candidates for immune checkpoint inhibitors," says Joey Nguyen, a graduate student at&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/phd-program/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a>&amp;nbsp;and lead author of the publication.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Addressing the nation's leading cause of cancer death</strong></h2>



<p>Lung adenocarcinoma&amp;nbsp;represents 40% of lung cancers in the U.S. and is the leading cause of cancer death. It's strongly associated with smoking, but it's also the most common type of lung cancer to occur in people who have never smoked, likely because of a combination of genetics and other environmental factors.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Fields' lab at Mayo Clinic in Florida has long studied the effect of the PRKCI gene, which drives tumor growth. The gene also suppresses the immune system, keeping cancer-killing immune cells at bay. Because lung tumors depend on the gene to proliferate, Dr. Fields' team was surprised to find that in cases where a copy of the gene is missing, lung adenocarcinoma tumors still occur. Nguyen, who was studying PRKCI in the lab, was inspired to try to learn more about those unusual tumors.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Early experiments found that the tumors without PRKCI grow less aggressively. The team also found that when PRKCI is missing, lung adenocarcinoma cells behave in an unusual way in their very early development, acquiring characteristics of lung cells that regenerate lung tissue after damage.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The team collaborated with the lab of systems biology researcher&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/li-hu-ph-d/bio-20035057" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hu Li, Ph.D.</a>, to examine the process at a single cell level. "We found that the loss of PRKCI forces tumor cells to hijack a lung regeneration process to generate a tumor," Nguyen says.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Tracking the effects of a missing gene</strong></h2>



<p>Nguyen also noticed that the tumors without PRKCI showed elevated levels of organized clusters of immune cells, called tertiary lymphoid structures. The presence of those clumped cells can be a sign that immune checkpoint therapy might work for a patient. But were they a result of the single copy of the PRKCI gene?&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="608" height="608" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Prieto-Luis_20129157_20230508.-1x1-1.jpg" alt="Luis Prieto, Ph.D." class="wp-image-408395" style="width:184px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Prieto-Luis_20129157_20230508.-1x1-1.jpg 608w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Prieto-Luis_20129157_20230508.-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Prieto-Luis_20129157_20230508.-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Luis Prieto, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>Nguyen presented his research at a graduate school seminar where the project caught the attention of postdoctoral fellow Luis Prieto, Ph.D., who had an idea. Dr. Prieto wondered whether the clusters of immune cells might be connected in some way to senescent cells, those that enter a state of arrested development and don't die off. Dr. Prieto works in the lab of researcher&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/baker-darren-j-ph-d-m-s/bio-00027985" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Darren Baker, Ph.D.</a>, who investigates therapies to eliminate senescent cells in various disease processes. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="634" height="634" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Baker-Darren-J.-MS-PhD_13844491_201606011129-1x1-1.jpg" alt="Darren Baker, Ph.D." class="wp-image-408392" style="width:186px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Baker-Darren-J.-MS-PhD_13844491_201606011129-1x1-1.jpg 634w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Baker-Darren-J.-MS-PhD_13844491_201606011129-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Baker-Darren-J.-MS-PhD_13844491_201606011129-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 634px) 100vw, 634px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Darren Baker, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>The collaborating labs were amazed to find that senescent tumor cells actually activate the immune system, leading to the clusters of immune cells that combat the tumor. "The idea that senescent cells may be beneficial in certain settings like this is new to the field, as these 'zombies' are commonly associated with detrimental outcomes," says Dr. Baker, who is a co-corresponding author on the study. </p>



<p>The findings reveal three tumor characteristics that may be used to help clinicians identify candidates for immune checkpoint inhibitors: loss of the PRKCI gene, the presence of senescent tumor cells and an abundance of clustered immune cells.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Further, says Dr. Fields, his team previously identified an approved drug that can inhibit PRKCI signaling, making a tumor that has the PRKCI gene act more like a tumor without it.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"Now that we understand how PRKCI is working in a lung tumor, it may be possible to couple a PRKCI inhibitor with immunotherapy, so a future clinical trial that combines these approaches will certainly be an important avenue to explore," he says.</p>



<p>See the <a href="https://www.cell.com/cell-reports/fulltext/S2211-1247(25)01378-6" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact</strong>:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications,&amp;nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-why-some-lung-tumors-respond-well-to-immunotherapy/">Mayo Clinic researchers identify why some lung tumors respond well to immunotherapy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Virtual-lung-image-Getty1439259946-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Virtual-lung-image-Getty1439259946-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Alan Fields]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Lung Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Minneapolis baker, &amp;#8216;Cake Wars&amp;#8217; winner, defeats &amp;#8216;incurable&amp;#8217; stomach cancer&nbsp;&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/minneapolis-baker-cake-wars-winner-defeats-incurable-stomach-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ltedesco7]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 14:29:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Samir Mardini]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Travis Grotz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stomach cancer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=408314</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>As a "Cake Wars" champion, Ann Alaboud knows that victory takes determination. While facing her biggest foe — stage 4 stomach cancer — she chose Mayo Clinic as her ally.&amp;#160;&amp;#160;&amp;#160;&amp;#160;&amp;#160;&amp;#160;&amp;#160;&amp;#160;&amp;#160;&amp;#160; Although it was February, Ann Alaboud was decked out for Christmas — green apron, bright red lipstick and a sparkly elf hat. She was filming [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/minneapolis-baker-cake-wars-winner-defeats-incurable-stomach-cancer/">Minneapolis baker, &amp;#8216;Cake Wars&amp;#8217; winner, defeats &amp;#8216;incurable&amp;#8217; stomach cancer&nbsp;&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_4-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Photo of Ann Alaboud (middle) with contestants on Cake Wars." class="wp-image-408326" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_4-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_4-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_4-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_4-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_4-16-x-9.jpg 1900w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Ann Alaboud smiles between her teammates, Brie Darling and Julie Jensen, while filming "The Big Bake: Holiday" for the Food Network.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p><em>As a "Cake Wars" champion, Ann Alaboud knows that victory takes determination. While facing her biggest foe — stage 4 stomach cancer — she chose <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> as her ally.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</em>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Although it was February, Ann Alaboud was decked out for Christmas — green apron, bright red lipstick and a sparkly elf hat. She was filming an episode of Food Network's "The Big Bake: Holiday," and her team had just constructed a towering Christmas tree cake.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>As Ann walked off set, she suddenly veered left — her only warning before fainting.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"I woke up to the paramedics trying to figure out what was wrong with me," recalls Ann.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>They chalked it up to fatigue. But Ann had a deepening sense that something wasn't right. For years, she'd been breaking out in hives, and she was perpetually exhausted. Not long after filming ended, she noticed a strange pinching sensation in her stomach.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="683" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_5-683x1024.jpeg" alt="Photo of Ann Alaboud  on Cake Wars." class="wp-image-408327" style="width:349px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_5-683x1024.jpeg 683w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_5-200x300.jpeg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_5-768x1151.jpeg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_5-1025x1536.jpeg 1025w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_5.jpeg 1334w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 683px) 100vw, 683px" /></figure>
</div>


<p>As a Minneapolis baker running two cupcake shops, it'd been easy to blame her symptoms on her busy lifestyle. After fainting, Ann knew she needed to seek care.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Despite multiple hospital visits, the only diagnosis she received was reflux.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>When her 9-year-old daughter asked, "Mommy, do you have cancer?" Ann pushed harder for answers. On April 8, 2022, she woke up from an endoscopy to terrifying news. Her stomach was riddled with tumors. "They said it had already spread, and they couldn't do anything," she says.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>A scan on her birthday confirmed the diagnosis — stage 4 <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stomach-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352443" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stomach cancer</a>.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"It was the shock of a lifetime. I'm a very health-conscious person," says Ann. "My family was like, 'What? <em>You</em> get stomach cancer?'"&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>From ambition to uncertainty&amp;nbsp;</strong>&amp;nbsp;</h2>



<p>Before Ann was a baker, she was a business analyst. Then, in 2011, she made her first artistic cake for her baby shower. As she shaped a pair of sugary booties, she felt inspired to turn her unused culinary degree into a career.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Five years later, Ann had opened her first bakery and won Food Network's "Cake Wars," which led to "The Big Bake: Holiday" in 2022. Shortly after filming, she added another bakery location — just a week before finding out she had cancer.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"That's when everything went downhill," she says.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Instead of investing in her business, Ann found herself fighting for her life.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Moving to Mayo</strong>&amp;nbsp;</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="640" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Grotz_Travis_E._14925036_202207141044.jpg" alt="Dr. Travis Grotz" class="wp-image-385206" style="width:140px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Grotz_Travis_E._14925036_202207141044.jpg 640w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Grotz_Travis_E._14925036_202207141044-240x300.jpg 240w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Travis Grotz</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>Due to the severity of her disease, Ann's local oncologist referred her to Mayo Clinic. While others deemed her stomach cancer inoperable, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/grotz-travis-e-m-d-m-s/bio-20342285" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Travis Grotz</a>, a surgical oncologist at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota, still saw hope.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>With gastric cancer spiking among younger people, his patients are often in the prime of life, facing late-stage disease with little chance of a cure through traditional treatments.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"For stage 4 gastric cancer, it's usually indefinite chemotherapy," he says. "But with research and a multidisciplinary team, I thought we could safely push the envelope."&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>He designed an innovative care plan based on a clinical trial.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Back at home, Ann started chemotherapy and immunotherapy to shrink her tumors. She closed her bakeries as needed and traveled to Mayo for laparoscopic operations to track her progress.&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_1.-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Photo of Ann Alaboud  in a hospital bed, as she's treated for stomach cancer" class="wp-image-408324" style="width:682px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_1.-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_1.-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_1.-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_1.-16-x-9.jpg 1436w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>
</div>


<p>Often arriving with cupcakes for the care team, Ann also brought ample gratitude and positivity — even as her number of procedures climbed into the double digits.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>She was willing to do whatever it took to have a good outcome," says Mary Dorn, one of her nurses.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>At times, Ann was tempted to waver. She recalls writing down account numbers to prepare her husband for her passing. "I started crying and said, 'You know what? I'm going to get better. I can't die young,'" she says. "So I just powered through one surgery after the next."&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/HIPEC-medical-illustration-16x9-1.jpg" alt="HIPEC medical illustration, used to create stomach cancer" class="wp-image-351683" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/HIPEC-medical-illustration-16x9-1.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/HIPEC-medical-illustration-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></figure>
</div>


<p>As one part of her innovative care plan, Dr. Grotz used <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/hyperthermic-intraperitoneal-chemotherapy/about/pac-20583315" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hyperthermic intraperitoneal chemotherapy (HIPEC) </a>to wash her abdomen with heated drugs, destroying lingering cancer cells. He also removed her stomach to prevent a relapse. It was during this surgery that Dr. Grotz made a startling discovery — Ann had new tumors in her esophagus.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>She'd recently begun experiencing crushing chest pain during chemotherapy. Now Ann wondered: Had this been a warning sign? She'd thought treatment was nearly over, but the next day, she'd need surgery to remove her esophagus and add a feeding tube.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>As Ann reeled, Dr. Grotz reassured her that long-term survival was still the goal. "I trusted everything he told me because everything he'd done so far was great," says Ann. "He's phenomenal."&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Restoring normalcy&amp;nbsp;</strong>&amp;nbsp;</h2>



<p>After her esophageal surgery, the focus shifted to restoring Ann's quality of life. Dr. Grotz wanted to give her back as much normalcy as possible. He turned to his colleagues for help.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Two surgeons — one thoracic, the other plastic — created a new esophagus from part of Ann's small intestine, called the jejunum. After severing several attachments in her abdomen, they stretched it to her neck and connected it to her intact upper esophagus. Delicate microsurgery linked the intestinal blood vessels to those in her neck and upper chest.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The complex, several-hour surgery was a success.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Ann now had a working gastrointestinal tract, despite two missing organs, so she no longer needed the feeding tube that made her feel so sick. At last, Ann was able to eat again.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"This kind of care is not possible without collaboration between our teams," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mardini-samir-m-d/bio-20054870" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Samir Mardini</a>, Ann's plastic surgeon. "So many people — surgeons, nutritionists, physical therapists, nurses — worked together to create an outcome that would be hard to achieve any other way."&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>During her two-week stay in Rochester, Ann witnessed this care in action. "All the doctors, all the nurses — everybody — went above and beyond," she says. "I've never said, 'Thank you,' as many times as I did while at Mayo."&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Life beyond stomach cancer</strong>&amp;nbsp;</h2>



<p>Three years later, Ann remains cancer-free. Now a long-term survivor, she's been able to hold onto the identities she cherishes most — mom, wife, baker, small-business owner.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>With her new GI tract, there have been changes. Ann has to slowly eat small portions, often while standing to keep the food moving. It takes effort to remember to chew every bite thoroughly.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>While this can be challenging, her most consistent feeling is gratitude.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Ann is thankful for the prayers and support of loved ones. The customers who contributed to fundraisers. The landlord who gave her grace. The Mayo care team who fought alongside her.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Most of all, she's grateful to be alive.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"Winning 'Cake Wars' validated that I am a pastry chef. I can do anything I want, right?" Ann says. "But having cancer, thinking I wouldn't make it, then coming out OK — that is more victorious than anything."&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/minneapolis-baker-cake-wars-winner-defeats-incurable-stomach-cancer/">Minneapolis baker, &amp;#8216;Cake Wars&amp;#8217; winner, defeats &amp;#8216;incurable&amp;#8217; stomach cancer&nbsp;&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_4-1-x-1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Ann-Alaboud_4-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Samir Mardini]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Travis Grotz]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[stomach cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New genetic biomarker flags aggressive brain tumors</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-genetic-biomarker-flags-aggressive-brain-tumors/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[mbroadfoot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Discovery Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Gelareh Zadeh]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=405928</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Clinicians typically classify meningiomas — the most common type of brain tumor — into three grades, ranging from slow-growing to aggressive. But a new multi-institutional study suggests that appearances may be deceiving. If a tumor shows activity in a gene called telomerase reverse transcriptase (TERT), it tends to recur more quickly, even [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-genetic-biomarker-flags-aggressive-brain-tumors/">New genetic biomarker flags aggressive brain tumors</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/meningioma-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Black and white brain scan image of a meningioma" class="wp-image-405943" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/meningioma-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/meningioma-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/meningioma-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/meningioma-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/meningioma-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><br>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Clinicians typically classify <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/meningioma/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20355648" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">meningiomas</a> — the most common type of brain tumor — into three grades, ranging from slow-growing to aggressive.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="937" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Zadeh-Gelareh-937x1024.jpg" alt="Gelareh Zadeh, M.D., Ph.D." class="wp-image-405939" style="width:203px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Zadeh-Gelareh-937x1024.jpg 937w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Zadeh-Gelareh-274x300.jpg 274w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Zadeh-Gelareh-768x839.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Zadeh-Gelareh-1405x1536.jpg 1405w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/Zadeh-Gelareh-1874x2048.jpg 1874w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 937px) 100vw, 937px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Gelareh Zadeh, M.D., Ph.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>But a new multi-institutional study suggests that appearances may be deceiving. If a tumor shows activity in a gene called telomerase reverse transcriptase (TERT), it tends to recur more quickly, even if it looks low-grade under the microscope. <br><br>The findings, published in <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanonc/article/PIIS1470-2045(25)00267-0/abstract" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lancet Oncology</a>, could significantly change how doctors diagnose and treat meningiomas.</p>



<p>"High TERT expression is strongly linked to faster disease progression," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/zadeh-gelareh-m-d-ph-d/bio-20579723" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gelareh Zadeh, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, a neurosurgeon at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> and senior author of the study. "This makes it a promising new biomarker for identifying patients who may be at greater risk of developing aggressive disease."</p>



<p><strong><em>This research was presented at the <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fvirtual.oxfordabstracts.com%2Fevent%2F74646%2Fsubmission%2F1932&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7CSatake.Alison%40mayo.edu%7Ce56a545b298d43c86c7f08de27bab68a%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C638991880080062919%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=FF19BRxTpQ6iRcANOgH79s4MshKUstvI4VaAkSUVs20%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Society for Neuro-Oncology</a> conference on Nov. 22.</em></strong></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="819" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Aldape-Ken-D._14504812_20250908-819x1024.jpg" alt="Photo of Kenneth Aldape, M.D." class="wp-image-408179" style="width:189px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Aldape-Ken-D._14504812_20250908-819x1024.jpg 819w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Aldape-Ken-D._14504812_20250908-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Aldape-Ken-D._14504812_20250908-768x960.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Aldape-Ken-D._14504812_20250908-1229x1536.jpg 1229w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/Aldape-Ken-D._14504812_20250908-1639x2048.jpg 1639w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 819px) 100vw, 819px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Kenneth Aldape, M.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p><br>"This is one example of how precision diagnostics of cancer may ultimately improve patient outcomes," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/aldape-kenneth-d-m-d/bio-20589565" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kenneth Aldape, M.D.</a>, Mayo Clinic pathologist and study co-author.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>An early warning sign</strong></h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/meningioma/symptoms-causes/syc-20355643" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Meningiomas</a> — tumors of the meninges, the protective tissue that surrounds the brain and spinal cord — are generally considered benign. But a small subset of these tumors has a mutation in the TERT gene, which is linked to faster growth and a shorter time before the tumor returns after treatment.</p>



<p>TERT is the active part of telomerase, an enzyme that maintains telomeres, the protective ends of chromosomes. In most healthy adult cells, TERT is switched off. But if it becomes switched back on, it can fuel cancer development by driving unchecked cell growth.</p>



<p>In this study, the researchers wanted to see whether high TERT expression, even in the absence of the TERT genetic mutation, also predicted worse outcomes. They looked at more than 1,200 meningiomas from patients across Canada, Germany and the U.S., and they found that nearly one-third of them had high TERT expression despite not having the mutation.</p>



<p>These patients had earlier tumor regrowth compared to those without TERT expression, though their outcomes were better than patients with full-blown TERT mutations.</p>



<p>"TERT-positive tumors behaved like they were one grade worse than their official diagnosis," says Dr. Zadeh. "For example, a grade 1 tumor with TERT expression acted more like a grade 2."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Guiding treatment decisions</strong></h2>



<p>The findings suggest that testing for TERT activity could help doctors predict which patients are at higher risk for recurrence and may need closer monitoring or more intensive treatment.</p>



<p>"Because meningiomas are the most common primary brain tumor, this biomarker could influence how thousands of patients are diagnosed and managed worldwide," says Dr. Zadeh.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="819" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/ChloeGuiMayoHeadshot-819x1024.jpg" alt="Photo of Mayo Clinic research collaborator Chloe Gui, M.D." class="wp-image-405944" style="width:204px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/ChloeGuiMayoHeadshot-819x1024.jpg 819w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/ChloeGuiMayoHeadshot-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/ChloeGuiMayoHeadshot-768x960.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/ChloeGuiMayoHeadshot-1229x1536.jpg 1229w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/ChloeGuiMayoHeadshot-1638x2048.jpg 1638w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 819px) 100vw, 819px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Chloe Gui, M.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>"TERT expression can help us more accurately identify patients with aggressive meningiomas," Chloe Gui, M.D., a neurosurgery resident at the University of Toronto, Mayo Clinic research collaborator and the study's lead author, explains on a <a href="https://www.buzzsprout.com/1391338?client_source=large_player&amp;amp;iframe=true&amp;amp;referrer=https://www.buzzsprout.com/1391338.js?container_id=buzzsprout-large-player&amp;amp;player=large#" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">podcast hosted by The Lancet Oncology</a>. "This information allows us to offer treatment tailored to the tumor's behavior."</p>



<p>The team is currently investigating ways to incorporate TERT expression into the clinical workflow. The research is part of a larger effort at Mayo Clinic called the Precure initiative, focused on developing tools that empower clinicians to predict and intercept biological processes before they evolve into disease or progress into complex, hard-to-treat conditions.</p>



<p>Review the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanonc/article/PIIS1470-2045(25)00267-0/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and to providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact: </strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-genetic-biomarker-flags-aggressive-brain-tumors/">New genetic biomarker flags aggressive brain tumors</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/meningioma-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/08/meningioma-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Gelareh Zadeh]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss> 