<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org">

<channel>
	<title>Cardiovascular - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cardiovascular-2/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml">
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cardiovascular-2/
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastbuilddate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 14:23:21 +0000</lastbuilddate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updateperiod>
	hourly	</sy:updateperiod>
	<sy:updatefrequency>
	1	</sy:updatefrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.9.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Is my racing heart an arrhythmia?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-is-my-racing-heart-an-arrhythmia/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[pattymiller]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 14:23:20 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Cycle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[AfFib]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Arrhythmia]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Divya Korpu]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=410134</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;I've noticed that sometimes my heart races or skips a beat. What causes this? Is there treatment for it? ANSWER:&nbsp;What you're experiencing may be an abnormal heart rhythm, also known as an&nbsp;arrhythmia. Arrhythmias fall into two categories: too fast or too slow. A racing heart or a skipped beat typically falls into the […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-is-my-racing-heart-an-arrhythmia/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Is my racing heart an arrhythmia?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/10/a-middle-aged-Asian-woman-sitting-on-a-couch-near-a-window-with-her-hand-on-her-chest-looking-worried-sad-perhaps-in-pain-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="a middle aged Asian woman sitting on a couch near a window with her hand on her chest, heart,  looking worried, sad, perhaps in pain, " class="wp-image-282966" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/10/a-middle-aged-Asian-woman-sitting-on-a-couch-near-a-window-with-her-hand-on-her-chest-looking-worried-sad-perhaps-in-pain-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/10/a-middle-aged-Asian-woman-sitting-on-a-couch-near-a-window-with-her-hand-on-her-chest-looking-worried-sad-perhaps-in-pain-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/10/a-middle-aged-Asian-woman-sitting-on-a-couch-near-a-window-with-her-hand-on-her-chest-looking-worried-sad-perhaps-in-pain-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/10/a-middle-aged-Asian-woman-sitting-on-a-couch-near-a-window-with-her-hand-on-her-chest-looking-worried-sad-perhaps-in-pain-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/10/a-middle-aged-Asian-woman-sitting-on-a-couch-near-a-window-with-her-hand-on-her-chest-looking-worried-sad-perhaps-in-pain-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;</strong>I've noticed that sometimes my heart races or skips a beat. What causes this? Is there treatment for it?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:&nbsp;</strong>What you're experiencing may be an abnormal heart rhythm, also known as an&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-arrhythmia/symptoms-causes/syc-20350668" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">arrhythmia</a>. Arrhythmias fall into two categories: too fast or too slow. A racing heart or a skipped beat typically falls into the "too fast" category. When an abnormal heartbeat interrupts the normal rhythm, you may feel palpitations — sensations that your heart is racing, fluttering, skipping a beat — or a sense of panic. Often these symptoms are more noticeable at night or when lying down.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In younger people, typically those in their 20s to 50s, the heart may suddenly speed up from a normal rate to 180-200 beats per minute. This rapid heartbeat can cause lightheadedness, dizziness, anxiety or, in some cases, fainting.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Fast or skipped heartbeats can originate in either the upper or lower chambers of the heart. Those that begin in the top chamber are called premature atrial contractions (PACs), while those starting in the bottom chambers are&nbsp;<a href="http://premature%20ventricular%20contractions%20(PVCs)" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">premature ventricular contractions (PVCs)</a>. Although they can feel alarming, PACs and PVCs generally aren't dangerous or life-threatening. They don't cause heart attacks, strokes or increase the risk of death.&nbsp;</p>



<p>These irregular heartbeats may be caused by:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>An abnormal electric circuit that people are born with.</li>



<li>Thyroid disorders.</li>



<li>Hormonal changes related to pregnancy or menopause.</li>



<li>Excessive caffeine or alcohol consumption.</li>
</ul>



<p>If symptoms are infrequent and don't interfere with daily activities, people often learn to live with them. However, if they become bothersome, medication may help suppress the extra heartbeats.</p>



<p>One way to slow a sudden racing heart is by performing a vagal maneuver, which can help interrupt the abnormal rhythm. Vagal maneuvers include bearing down like you are having a bowel movement, blowing into a straw with one end closed, clearing your ears as you might on an airplane, dipping your face in ice-cold water or taking a cold shower.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Evaluation</strong></h2>



<p>However, these are temporary fixes. If symptoms persist, patients may be referred for further evaluation, such as an electrophysiology study and possible catheter ablation. During this procedure, catheters are threaded through veins in the groin and guided to the heart. Doctors use specialized wires to find where the arrhythmia is coming from. Then energy is delivered via the catheter to eliminate the abnormal circuit.</p>



<p>Ablation is usually done under twilight sedation and typically is a same-day procedure. Patients need someone with them for 24 hours, should avoid driving for 24 hours and shouldn't lift anything heavy for a week to let the groin incisions heal. After that, they can resume their normal activities.</p>



<p>PACs and PVCs are most common in younger people. For older adults, the most common fast rhythm is&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/atrial-fibrillation/symptoms-causes/syc-20350624" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">atrial fibrillation (AFib)</a>&nbsp;or atrial flutter. These are different types of heart rhythms which become increasingly common with age.</p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-atrial-fibrillation/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">AFib</a>&nbsp;can cause irregular heartbeat, palpitations, chest discomfort, lightheadedness, dizziness, fatigue and sometimes passing out. Some people have no symptoms, and the condition is discovered during routine care or procedures.</p>



<p>Common causes of AFib include untreated sleep apnea, excessive caffeine, binge drinking or overconsumption of alcohol, thyroid disorders, and hormonal changes. In a small group of patients, spicy foods may trigger AFib.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Treatment for AFib</strong></h2>



<p>Treatment options include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Medication to control fast heart rate.</li>



<li>Medication to control heart rhythm.</li>



<li>Catheter ablation.</li>
</ul>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/atrial-fibrillation-ablation/about/pac-20384969" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ablation</a>&nbsp;for AFib is done under general anesthesia. It's a minimally invasive procedure in which doctors access the heart through the groin and target areas on the left side of the heart responsible for triggering or sustaining the abnormal rhythm. Traditionally, two types of energy — radiofrequency (heat) and cryoablation (cold) — have been used for ablation.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Most recently, a new, nonthermal option —&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-offers-new-innovative-therapy-to-treat-atrial-fibrillation/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pulsed field ablation</a>&nbsp;— has been introduced. This energy source selectively targets heart muscle cells. This reduces the risk of serious or life-threatening damage to the surrounding structures, such as the esophagus and the phrenic nerve, which controls the diaphragm and breathing.</p>



<p>Recovery after ablation is similar regardless of the energy source used, including about one week of limited activity.</p>



<p>During AFib, blood can pool in the heart, form clots and cause a stroke. Depending on individual risk factors, patients are often prescribed a blood thinner once they're diagnosed with atrial fibrillation or atrial flutter, even after undergoing ablation. If they're not able to tolerate blood thinners, a permanent device may be implanted in their heart to seal off the left atrial appendage, where most clots form, to reduce the risk of stroke.</p>



<p>If you're experiencing a racing heart, noticing skipped beats or symptoms of an irregular heart rhythm, consult with your&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/heart-rhythm-clinic/overview/ovc-20442477" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">healthcare professional</a>&nbsp;or a cardiologist to determine whether further evaluation or treatment is needed.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/divya-korpu-mbbs" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Divya Korpu, M.B.B.S.</em></a><em>, Cardiovascular Medicine, Mayo Clinic Health System, Eau Claire, Wisconsin</em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-is-my-racing-heart-an-arrhythmia/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Is my racing heart an arrhythmia?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/10/a-middle-aged-Asian-woman-sitting-on-a-couch-near-a-window-with-her-hand-on-her-chest-looking-worried-sad-perhaps-in-pain-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/10/a-middle-aged-Asian-woman-sitting-on-a-couch-near-a-window-with-her-hand-on-her-chest-looking-worried-sad-perhaps-in-pain-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[AfFib]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Arrhythmia]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Divya Korpu]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>3 things to know about cancer and your heart: Mayo Clinic expert shares tips to reduce risk</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/3-things-to-know-about-cancer-and-your-heart-mayo-clinic-expert-shares-tips-to-reduce-risk/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Sharon Theimer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 14:05:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Joerg Herrmann]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=410203</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->February is Heart Month ROCHESTER, Minn. — As cancer therapies improve and increasingly achieve cures or recurring periods of remission, preventing and managing damage to organs from cancer treatment has become a top concern. That includes injury to the heart, says Joerg Herrmann, M.D., a cardiologist and the founder and director of the Cardio-Oncology Clinic […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/3-things-to-know-about-cancer-and-your-heart-mayo-clinic-expert-shares-tips-to-reduce-risk/">3 things to know about cancer and your heart: Mayo Clinic expert shares tips to reduce risk</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/16x9-feat-image-for-Dr-Herrmann-cancer-and-heart-expert-alert-GettyImages-1441981570-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-410122" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/16x9-feat-image-for-Dr-Herrmann-cancer-and-heart-expert-alert-GettyImages-1441981570-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/16x9-feat-image-for-Dr-Herrmann-cancer-and-heart-expert-alert-GettyImages-1441981570-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/16x9-feat-image-for-Dr-Herrmann-cancer-and-heart-expert-alert-GettyImages-1441981570-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/16x9-feat-image-for-Dr-Herrmann-cancer-and-heart-expert-alert-GettyImages-1441981570-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/16x9-feat-image-for-Dr-Herrmann-cancer-and-heart-expert-alert-GettyImages-1441981570-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Physical activity is  important to reduce heart damage risk during cancer treatment, help prevent cancer recurrence and improve cardiovascular outcomes.</figcaption>



<p><em>February is Heart Month</em></p>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — As <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20370594" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer therapies</a> improve and increasingly achieve cures or recurring periods of remission, preventing and managing damage to organs from cancer treatment has become a top concern. That includes injury to the heart, says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/herrmann-joerg-m-d/bio-20143025" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Joerg Herrmann, M.D.</a>, a cardiologist and the founder and director of the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/cardio-oncology-clinic/overview/ovc-20442193" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cardio-Oncology Clinic</a> at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/locations" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> in Minnesota.</p>



<p>As physicians and researchers work to prevent, diagnose and treat heart damage from cancer therapies, they also have learned about connections between cancer and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">the heart</a> that go beyond the cardiac effects of cancer treatments. Dr. Herrmann shares three things to know:</p>



<p><strong>1. There is a "web of risk factors."</strong></p>



<p>Cancer and heart disease have common risk factors, Dr. Herrmann says. Those include lifestyle habits.</p>



<p>"We call it the web of risk factors. Some of the very same lifestyle-related factors can set patients up for both <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20370588" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/in-depth/heart-disease-prevention/art-20046502" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiovascular disease</a>," he explains. "<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/a-smokers-guide-to-quitting" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Smoking</a> is a prime example. It increases the risk of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lung-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20374620" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lung</a> and other cancers and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/coronary-artery-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350613" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">coronary artery disease</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-attack/symptoms-causes/syc-20373106" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart attacks</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/peripheral-artery-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350557" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">peripheral artery disease</a>."</p>



<p>In addition to not smoking, you can reduce your risk of cancer and of heart disease by achieving a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/obesity/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20375749" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">healthy weight</a>; avoiding or moderating alcohol use; controlling <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-cholesterol/symptoms-causes/syc-20350800" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cholesterol</a> (some cancer treatments can worsen cholesterol levels); getting enough <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/adult-health/in-depth/sleep/art-20048379" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">sleep</a>; and adopting a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/basics/nutrition-basics/hlv-20049477" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">healthy diet</a> with fruit and vegetables, he adds.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/in-depth/cancer-survivor/art-20044015" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Physical activity</a> is another important factor. It has been shown to reduce heart damage risk during cancer treatment, help prevent cancer recurrence and improve cardiovascular outcomes, Dr. Herrmann says.</p>



<p>"The more elements of a healthy lifestyle you meet, the better your health projection is for the heart and cancer," he says. "You will reduce the risks of two of the leading killers and increase life expectancy."</p>



<p>Cancer and heart disease can actually be risk factors <a href="https://www.ahajournals.org/doi/10.1161/CIR.0000000000001303?url_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;rfr_id=ori:rid:crossref.org&amp;rfr_dat=cr_pub%20%200pubmed" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">for each other</a>.</p>



<p>"We've realized that the relationship between cancer and heart disease works in both directions," Dr. Herrmann says. "Cancer itself can impact the cardiovascular system apart from cancer therapies, and vice versa. Patients with heart failure or other cardiovascular diseases have a higher risk of cancer."</p>



<p><strong>2.</strong> <strong>A variety of things may be done during cancer treatment to reduce risk to the heart.</strong></p>



<p>Which treatments are given and how can affect the risk of heart damage, Dr. Herrmann says. For example, the medical team may:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Use treatments that minimize harm to healthy tissue, such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/cancer-treatment/about/pac-20393344" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">targeted therapies</a> or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/sections/overview/ovc-20185491" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">proton beam therapy</a>.</li>



<li>Stagger certain chemotherapy drugs to give the heart a chance to heal between treatments.</li>



<li>Use medications that protect the heart during <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/chemotherapy/about/pac-20385033" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chemotherapy</a>.</li>



<li>Use techniques to shield healthy tissue during <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/radiation-therapy/care-at-mayo-clinic/pcc-20385164" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">radiation therapy</a>, such as body positioning and breath-holding to provide greater separation between the tumor and the heart.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>"These shielding efforts have come a long way for adults and children who have cancer," he says.</p>



<p><strong>3</strong>. <strong>Artificial intelligence and wearables are promising innovations.</strong></p>



<p>The goals of Dr. Herrmann's <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials/faculty-search-results?authid=13597311" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">research</a> including developing tools that predict – before treatment – who is at high risk of heart damage from certain cancer therapies. This would enable shared decision making among patients and their care teams about the approach to treatment.</p>



<p>He and his colleagues are also working on therapies to mend hearts broken by chemotherapy and to develop easier and more cost-effective surveillance strategies for cardiovascular side effects of cancer therapies. Early detection and intervention are likely to lead to the best outcomes, Dr. Herrmann says.</p>



<p>The use of <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ai-transforms-smartwatch-ecg-signals-into-a-diagnostic-tool-for-heart-failure/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">wearables</a> and artificial intelligence (AI) can help, he says. Research has found, for example, that <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-study-suggests-ecg-ai-can-detect-cardiovascular-disease-risks-sooner/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">applying AI</a> to an <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ekg/about/pac-20384983" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">electrocardiogram</a>, a test that measures the heart's electrical activity, may help detect a decline in heart function.</p>



<p>"We're interested in going further with AI technologies and developing simulations to show how different therapies would affect a given patient," Dr. Herrmann says.</p>



<p>Some patients remain at risk of heart disease for a lifetime after cancer treatment, but it's impractical to do <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/echocardiogram/about/pac-20393856" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">echocardiograms</a> to look at the heart for the rest of their lives. <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ai-transforms-smartwatch-ecg-signals-into-a-diagnostic-tool-for-heart-failure/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Wearables</a> to alert cancer survivors and their care teams to cardiac abnormalities are another promising area of research, he says.</p>



<p>"We've come a long way in cardio-oncology. We have a much better understanding of what we can do to manage heart risk from cancer therapies," Dr. Herrmann says. "Patients are in much better place now than they were even 10 years ago."</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Sharon Theimer, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/3-things-to-know-about-cancer-and-your-heart-mayo-clinic-expert-shares-tips-to-reduce-risk/">3 things to know about cancer and your heart: Mayo Clinic expert shares tips to reduce risk</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/1x1-feat-image-for-Dr-Herrmann-cancer-and-heart-expert-alert-GettyImages-1441981570.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/16x9-feat-image-for-Dr-Herrmann-cancer-and-heart-expert-alert-GettyImages-1441981570.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Joerg Herrmann]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What is pulsed field ablation?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-is-pulsed-field-ablation/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[pattymiller]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 13:35:18 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[atrial fibrilation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Christopher DeSimone]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=410309</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;I have atrial fibrillation, and I've heard there's a new kind of ablation that could relieve my symptoms. Can you tell me about it? ANSWER:&nbsp;If you have atrial fibrillation (AFib), you're not alone — it's the most common heart rhythm disorder, affecting millions around the world. AFib occurs when the heart's upper chambers […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-is-pulsed-field-ablation/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What is pulsed field ablation?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"--><img decoding="async" width="760" height="428" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/Adult-Black-Woman-Smiling-16-x-9.jpg" alt="photograph of middle-aged Black woman in pink shirt, outside, smiling" class="wp-image-366395" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/Adult-Black-Woman-Smiling-16-x-9.jpg 760w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/Adult-Black-Woman-Smiling-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 760px) 100vw, 760px">



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong>&nbsp;I have <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/atrial-fibrillation/symptoms-causes/syc-20350624" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">atrial fibrillation</a>, and I've heard there's a new kind of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/atrial-fibrillation-ablation/about/pac-20384969" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ablation</a> that could relieve my symptoms. Can you tell me about it?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong>&nbsp;If you have atrial fibrillation (AFib), you're not alone — it's the most common heart rhythm disorder, affecting millions around the world. AFib occurs when the heart's upper chambers beat in a fast, irregular way, which can cause symptoms such as palpitations, fatigue, shortness of breath, dizziness and/or reduced ability to exercise.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For many people, medications can help control symptoms. But when drugs don't work well, cause side effects, or people opt out of that treatment, a procedure called catheter ablation may be another avenue for certain patients.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/12/Atrial-fibrillation-Mayo-16-x-9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Atrial fibrillation can lead to the development of blood clots in the heart that can break off, travel to and block arteries supplying the brain with blood. This can result in the most common type of stroke (ischemic stroke" class="wp-image-398081" style="width:667px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/12/Atrial-fibrillation-Mayo-16-x-9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/12/Atrial-fibrillation-Mayo-16-x-9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/12/Atrial-fibrillation-Mayo-16-x-9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/12/Atrial-fibrillation-Mayo-16-x-9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/12/Atrial-fibrillation-Mayo-16-x-9-1.jpg 1886w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>
</div>


<p>Catheter ablation is a minimally invasive procedure used to treat abnormal heart rhythms such as AFib. During the procedure, doctors guide thin, flexible tubes, called catheters, through blood vessels in the groin up to and into your heart.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>For AFib ablation, patients are put under anesthesia, and depending on the complexity of the rhythms, the procedure can take several hours. The treatment usually focuses on ablation of muscle tissue that can generate electrical signals and trigger AFib.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This muscle tissue is found inside the pulmonary veins, which drain blood from the lungs into the left upper chamber of the heart, called the left atrium. By destroying these small areas of the heart, the main electrical impulses that set off AFib are isolated from the rest of the heart.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Using advanced imaging tools such as X-ray, ultrasound and catheters, doctors can reconstruct a 3D rendering of the heart while it's beating in real time and locate areas of heart tissue that are triggering AFib. This provides a roadmap for pinpointing the areas that are causing AFib. Energy is then delivered through the catheter to disrupt those problem areas, helping the heart maintain a normal rhythm.</p>



<p>For the past 20 years, most AFib ablations have used thermal energy to destroy targeted tissue using:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Heat (radiofrequency ablation).&nbsp;</li>



<li>Extreme cold (cryoablation).&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>These approaches can be effective, but they carry risks because heat or cold can unintentionally cause serious and even life-threatening damage to nearby structures, including:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Injury to the esophagus.</li>



<li>Narrowing of the pulmonary veins.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Damage to the phrenic nerve, which controls the diaphragm and breathing.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>In recent years, a newer form of ablation — called <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-offers-new-innovative-therapy-to-treat-atrial-fibrillation/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pulsed field ablation (PFA)</a> — has emerged and is generating excitement among heart rhythm specialists and patients.<br><br>PFA works in a completely different way. Instead of heat or cold, it uses very brief, high-voltage electrical pulses that last only microseconds. Because PFA is relatively nonthermal, the risks of thermal ablation appear to be dramatically reduced.</p>



<p>The electrical pulses delivered by the catheter create tiny openings in the membranes of heart muscle cells — a process called electroporation. These openings cause targeted cells to stop functioning, eventually die and become scar tissue.&nbsp;</p>



<p>One of the biggest advantages of PFA is the ability to selectively disable cardiac cells.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Another benefit is the efficiency of the procedure. PFA procedures are typically faster, meaning less time under general anesthesia, which may be especially important for older adults or people with other medical conditions.</p>



<p>So far, studies suggest that PFA is as effective as traditional ablation techniques. About 65% to 75% of patients remain free of AFib one year after a single procedure without antiarrhythmic medications. Success rates may improve with repeated procedures, continued medication use and other factors.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Ablation isn't a cure for AFib, and sometimes more ablations aren't always better or the best option. Too much scar tissue in the heart can cause a different set of problems, which is why careful patient selection is essential when weighing the risks and benefits of ablation.</p>



<p>The goal is to relieve symptoms, reduce frequency and duration of episodes, and improve the patient's quality of life.<br><br>While promising, PFA is still relatively new. Rare complications include coronary artery spasm; small bubble formation, which can lead to a stroke; or kidney injury. These events aren't common, and their causes continue to be studied.</p>



<p>PFA may expand treatment options for many people with AFib, particularly those with certain conditions where prolonged anesthesia time poses more risk. Whether it's appropriate depends on your type of AFib, symptoms, overall health, prior treatments, modification of risk factors and the goal for AFib treatment.</p>



<p>Talk with a cardiologist or cardiac electrophysiologist to determine whether PFA fits into your <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/heart-rhythm-clinic/overview/ovc-20442477" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">personalized treatment plan.</a></p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/desimone-christopher-v-m-d-ph-d/bio-20209047" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Christopher DeSimone, M.D., Ph.D.,</em></a><em>&nbsp;Cardiovascular Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota</em><br><br></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-is-pulsed-field-ablation/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What is pulsed field ablation?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/Adult-Black-Woman-Smiling-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/Adult-Black-Woman-Smiling-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[atrial fibrilation]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Christopher DeSimone]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bariatric surgery paves way for heart transplant after end-stage heart failure&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/bariatric-surgery-paves-way-for-heart-transplant-after-end-stage-heart-failure/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[ltedesco7]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 14:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiology Patient Stories]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[bariatric surgery]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Adrian da Silva de Abreu]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Omar Ghanem]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Philip spencer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Heart Transplant]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=410374</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->With a failing heart and little hope of healing, Alan Lewis sunk into depression, gaining 330 pounds. After he came to Mayo, bariatric surgery enabled the transplant he'd sought for so many years. &nbsp;&nbsp; Alan Lewis was lying on the floor — the only position that eased his discomfort — watching a football game. When […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/bariatric-surgery-paves-way-for-heart-transplant-after-end-stage-heart-failure/">Bariatric surgery paves way for heart transplant after end-stage heart failure&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Alan-and-Vida-Lewis-16x9--1024x576.jpg" alt="Alan and VIda Lewis,. Alan, heart transplant patient who underwent bariatric surgery " class="wp-image-410482" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Alan-and-Vida-Lewis-16x9--1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Alan-and-Vida-Lewis-16x9--300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Alan-and-Vida-Lewis-16x9--768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Alan-and-Vida-Lewis-16x9--1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Alan-and-Vida-Lewis-16x9--2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p><strong><em>With a failing heart and little hope of healing, Alan Lewis sunk into depression, gaining 330 pounds. After he came to Mayo, bariatric surgery enabled the transplant he'd sought for so many years. &nbsp;&nbsp;</em></strong></p>



<p>Alan Lewis was lying on the floor — the only position that eased his discomfort — watching a football game. When a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic">Mayo Clinic</a> commercial came on, the tagline seemed to leap off the screen.</p>



<p>"You know where to go."</p>



<p>With heart failure sapping his strength, Alan had begun to doubt there was an "other side" to his condition. At age 41, he'd already lived a decade with a poorly pumping heart, diagnosed during a hospital visit for a broken ankle.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For years, Alan had relied on a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ventricular-assist-device/about/pac-20384529" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">left ventricular assist device</a>, or LVAD, to help his heart circulate blood through his body. After the first one malfunctioned, he received a second device in 2018.</p>



<p>What Alan really needed was a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/heart-transplant/sections/overview/ovc-20212168" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">new heart.</a></p>



<p>Even after <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bariatric-surgery/about/pac-20394258" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bariatric surgery</a> helped him lose weight, he still wasn't added to the transplant list. "When we'd ask about transplant, our care team would just say, 'Oh, he's doing fine. Just keep doing what you're doing,'" says his wife, Vida.</p>



<p>As months became years, Alan's hope of healing waned. His mental health spiraled.</p>



<p>"I was a nervous wreck," he recalls. "What if the LVAD malfunctioned? What if there was a power failure? I was scared to go places, worried about backup batteries. I was in my head 24/7. It was torture."</p>



<p>Deeply depressed, Alan gained 330 pounds during the pandemic, reversing his previous weight loss. Without a clear path forward, he resigned himself to dying.</p>



<p>Then, in 2022, Alan saw the Mayo commercial — and Vida saw an opportunity. She made the decision for them. They were going to Rochester.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A journey toward hope</strong></h2>



<p>After driving from Chicago, weak and rapidly declining, Alan sought help from Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>There, Vida's long-simmering concern was confirmed —a tough-to-kill bacteria had infected the wiring that linked his LVAD to its external battery. The battery for his defibrillator was also dead, leaving him vulnerable to potentially deadly arrhythmias.</p>



<p>Right away, Alan received IV antibiotics, a new defibrillator and an introduction to the transplant team. "Day one, they spoke of transplant," says Vida. "I was shocked."</p>



<p>At his first follow-up visit, Sarah Schettle, a physician assistant on the LVAD team, could see the emotional strain of all that Alan and Vida had been through. "There was a lot of hesitancy — 'Will Mayo accept us?'" she recalls. "I also remember the hopefulness, the desire to know what was possible here."</p>



<p>Recognizing that Alan needed complex, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/multidisciplinary-team-approach/gnc-20203912" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">multidisciplinary care</a>, the team began formulating a plan.</p>



<p>Within two weeks, the couple relocated to Rochester — and just one year into marriage, Vida unflinchingly pivoted to her new role as caregiver.</p>



<p>"It was embedded in me to love as hard and as much as you can," she says.</p>



<p>Vida vowed to do that for Alan.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Alan-and-Vida-Lewis-16-x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Alan and Vida Lewis" class="wp-image-410481" style="width:644px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Alan-and-Vida-Lewis-16-x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Alan-and-Vida-Lewis-16-x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Alan-and-Vida-Lewis-16-x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Alan-and-Vida-Lewis-16-x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Alan-and-Vida-Lewis-16-x9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Throughout Alan's journey, his wife, Vida, advocated for his care.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Preparing for tomorrow</strong></h2>



<p>The team said Alan needed to adopt a healthier lifestyle before a second bariatric surgery — a necessary step toward transplant. So Vida signed them up for a gym. She walked next to him on a treadmill, urging him on. She made healthy meals. She pored over the lengthy care plan, still shocked that they had one. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Back home, no one gave us clear answers. How long would he have the LVAD? Could he ever get a transplant?" she says. "At Mayo, we never experienced that. The focus was always on getting him well enough for a transplant, like he deserved to be transplanted."</p>



<p>Still, there was fear that the new heart wouldn’t happen. Sensing Alan's struggle, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/da-silva-de-abreu-adrian-j-m-d-ph-d/bio-20540178" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Adrian da Silva de Abreu, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, one of his cardiologists, spent an hour at his bedside, mostly listening.</p>



<p>"I'd never seen a doctor take that time," says Alan. "I put it all out there, and I could tell he was hearing me."</p>



<p>Peace replaced his once-crippling anxiety. At last, he knew his team wanted what was best for him. As Vida says, "They had a vision. They had a plan. It was healthcare like I've never seen before."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A risk with great reward</strong></h2>



<p>Alan's first bariatric surgery shrunk his stomach to the size of a banana.</p>



<p>To help him lose the weight he'd regained, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/ghanem-omar-m-m-d/bio-20491179" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Omar Ghanem, M.D.</a>, a bariatric surgeon, planned to reroute part of Alan's small intestine so food would bypass a long segment of his bowel. Known as a modified duodenal switch, this would reduce how many calories and nutrients he absorbed and alter the secretion of hunger-related hormones.</p>



<p>Dr. Ghanem knew the already complex surgery would be even more challenging in Alan's case. &nbsp;</p>



<p>With his heart essentially outside his body, monitoring — and maintaining — his vitals would be difficult. Blood thinners to prevent clots in his LVAD would also elevate his risk of bleeding. Then there was the looming infection, suppressed but still active, only curable if the LVAD was removed. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Seven Mayo Clinic teams — from <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/infectious-diseases/sections/overview/ovc-20456906" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Infectious Diseases</a> to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/anesthesiology-and-perioperative-medicine/home/orc-20507831" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Anesthesiology</a> —&nbsp;worked together to help Alan beat the odds.</p>



<p>"Where else do you have all this expertise in one place? I don't think anything like this can be done outside of a place like Mayo," says Dr. Ghanem. "Here we're able to safely push the limits."</p>



<p>Knowing this path was his best chance at healing, Alan and Vida agreed to go forward.</p>



<p>Despite its complexity, the revision was a success, and so was the recovery.&nbsp;Within months, Alan lost enough weight to qualify for a heart. He was finally on the transplant list. &nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Lifestyle-changes-1-x-1-1024x1024.jpg" alt="Alan Lewis before and after image" class="wp-image-410516" style="width:353px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Lifestyle-changes-1-x-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Lifestyle-changes-1-x-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Lifestyle-changes-1-x-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Lifestyle-changes-1-x-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Lifestyle-changes-1-x-1.jpg 1080w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>
</div>


<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Moving forward at last</strong></h2>



<p>Six weeks later, a middle-of-the-night call brought Alan back to Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>After years of heart failure, two LVADs, two bariatric surgeries, dozens of pounds lost and hundreds of tears shed, Alan was receiving another chance at life. He was receiving a new heart.</p>



<p>Less than five hours after opening his chest, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/spencer-philip-j-m-d/bio-20527536" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Philip Spencer, M.D.</a>, a cardiovascular and transplant surgeon, brought Alan to the "other side" of heart failure — that place he'd once thought didn't exist. &nbsp;</p>



<p>"We had an infection to deal with. And there was scarring within his chest," says Dr. Spencer. "But, once the LVAD was out, it went very well." &nbsp;</p>



<p>IV steroids enabled his body to accept the organ, and with the LVAD out, his infection could finally clear. Even from his hospital bed, Alan felt his confidence returning.</p>



<p>"I'd had this yoke on me. I couldn't move without the LVAD. I couldn't bathe without it. I couldn't eat without it. It was always present," he says. "Mentally, I'd been down so long. Now I had freedom."</p>



<p>For the first time in years, there were no wires to wrestle with. There was no battery to worry about.</p>



<p>Alan could be himself again.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A new life for Alan</strong></h2>



<p>With Alan's heart fully functioning, the couple is now back in Chicago, enjoying a renewed zeal for life.</p>



<p>For Alan, that means showing his gratitude for everyone who supported him — his family, his close friends and, of course, Vida. Every day, he focuses on caring for her in every way possible. &nbsp;</p>



<p>"When I wake up, I start catering to her," he says. "She had to cook and clean. She helped bathe me and put on my shoes and socks. It's a joy for me to be able to do things for her now."</p>



<p>During the night, Alan sometimes reaches across the mattress, making sure Vida is still there, even though he knows she always will be. She is his safe person, and Mayo Clinic is the safe place that showed him what healthcare should be.</p>



<p>Both their hearts remain in Minnesota, where hope first began to beat, strong and steady, in Alan's chest. The tagline from a football game ad — "You know where to go" — still feels like a summons.</p>



<p>"To have so many people involved in your care, and each one be a beautiful experience, is so rare," says Vida. "God has blessed him, and Mayo has been there for him. We want to move back because Rochester feels like home, you know?"</p>



<p><strong>Related story:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-year-new-focus-on-health-mayo-clinic-expert-highlights-effective-treatment-options-for-obesity/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">New year, new focus on health: Mayo Clinic expert highlights effective treatment options for obesity</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/bariatric-surgery-paves-way-for-heart-transplant-after-end-stage-heart-failure/">Bariatric surgery paves way for heart transplant after end-stage heart failure&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Alan-and-VIda-Lewis-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/02/Alan-and-Vida-Lewis-16x9-.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[bariatric surgery]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Adrian da Silva de Abreu]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Omar Ghanem]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Philip spencer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Heart Transplant]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What to know about pregnancy and heart valve disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-to-know-about-pregnancy-and-heart-valve-disease/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[pattymiller]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 11:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Cycle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Katie Young]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Heart Disease]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=410047</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC: I found out during my pregnancy that I have mitral valve stenosis. How common is valve disease, and what should I know about it? ANSWER: Valve disease affects how blood moves through the heart, and pregnancy is often a time when symptoms first appear or become more noticeable. Learning about a heart […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-to-know-about-pregnancy-and-heart-valve-disease/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What to know about pregnancy and heart valve disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="942" height="529" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/02/a-pregnant-woman-with-her-partner-husband-father-of-baby-placing-his-hands-on-her-stomach-in-the-shape-of-a-heart-16x9-1.jpg" alt="a pregnant woman with her partner, husband, father of baby placing his hands on her stomach in the shape of a heart" class="wp-image-262202" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/02/a-pregnant-woman-with-her-partner-husband-father-of-baby-placing-his-hands-on-her-stomach-in-the-shape-of-a-heart-16x9-1.jpg 942w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/02/a-pregnant-woman-with-her-partner-husband-father-of-baby-placing-his-hands-on-her-stomach-in-the-shape-of-a-heart-16x9-1-300x168.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/02/a-pregnant-woman-with-her-partner-husband-father-of-baby-placing-his-hands-on-her-stomach-in-the-shape-of-a-heart-16x9-1-768x431.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 942px) 100vw, 942px">



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: </strong>I found out during my pregnancy that I have <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/mitral-valve-stenosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20353159" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">mitral valve stenosis</a>. How common is valve disease, and what should I know about it?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong> <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-valve-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353727" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Valve disease</a> affects how blood moves through the heart, and pregnancy is often a time when symptoms first appear or become more noticeable. Learning about a heart valve condition during pregnancy can be unexpected and overwhelming. Understanding why this happens and exploring treatment options can bring clarity and calm fears.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/pregnancy-week-by-week/in-depth/pregnancy/art-20045977" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pregnancy</a> is often described as the body's ultimate cardiovascular stress test. The heart works significantly harder to support both the mother and the developing baby. Blood volume expands, vascular resistance drops and heart rate increases. These normal physiological changes begin early in pregnancy and peak in the late second to early third trimester.</p>



<p>These changes can unmask symptoms of previously silent valve disease or intensify those of known valve conditions because the heart is being asked to move more blood through a valve that isn't functioning normally. Known valve conditions include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Narrowed valves (stenosis)</li>



<li>Leaky valves (regurgitation)</li>



<li>Congenital valve abnormalities</li>
</ul>



<p>Other valve conditions may result from infections, such as rheumatic fever, or changes in the valve's structure over time.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Symptoms</h2>



<p>Even women who felt well before pregnancy may begin to notice symptoms around 28 to 30 weeks, when the cardiovascular system reaches its peak workload.</p>



<p>Many common pregnancy symptoms overlap with those of valve disease. Fatigue, shortness of breath, swelling and a faster heart rate can all occur in a healthy pregnancy. It's especially important to evaluate symptoms that begin suddenly or noticeably worsen.</p>



<p>Shortness of breath with activity or when lying flat, unusual fatigue that affects daily routines, swelling in the legs or feet, racing heartbeat, reduced exercise tolerance, or chest pressure should prompt a conversation with a clinician.</p>



<p>Because pregnancy symptoms can mask underlying cardiac issues, clear communication between patients and their care teams is essential. Many patients assume new symptoms are simply part of pregnancy, especially if previous pregnancies were uncomplicated. But when something feels off, listening to that instinct is important.</p>



<p>An assessment of symptoms may include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Physical exam.</li>



<li>Echocardiogram to look at the heart's structure and function.</li>



<li>Electrocardiogram (ECG) to check the heart's rhythm.</li>



<li>Additional imaging or testing.</li>
</ul>



<p>These evaluations help determine whether symptoms are pregnancy-related or caused by cardiac disease.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Treatment</h2>



<p>Once valve disease is identified, coordinated care becomes especially important. Many patients benefit from a pregnancy heart team approach that includes specialists in cardiology and maternal-fetal medicine, with support from cardiac surgery or structural heart experts, if needed. Local obstetric teams may remain involved, particularly if delivery is expected to happen closer to home.</p>



<p>The pregnancy heart team approach helps align medical needs with a patient's goals for pregnancy and family planning. Shared decision-making plays a central role. Every situation is different, and treatment choices are shaped by personal values, risk considerations and long-term planning.</p>



<p>Treatment depends on the severity of the condition and how well a patient tolerates the physiologic demands of pregnancy.</p>



<p>Many women with mild or moderate valve disease can continue pregnancy safely with close monitoring. Medications may be used to help manage fluid retention, control heart rate or reduce symptoms.</p>



<p>When valve disease is more severe or symptoms significantly affect daily life, procedures may be done before or during pregnancy. These include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Catheter-based procedures to widen a narrow valve or improve function.</li>



<li>Valve repair to preserve a person's own valve when possible.</li>



<li>Valve replacement when the disease is advanced or symptoms can't be controlled.</li>
</ul>



<p>For those who need valve replacement, care teams will discuss the choice between a mechanical or tissue valve, especially for women planning future pregnancies.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Mechanical valves are durable but require lifelong anticoagulation, which can add complexity during pregnancy.</li>



<li>Tissue valves typically avoid long-term blood thinners but have a shorter lifespan.</li>
</ul>



<p>Treatment choices can shape both personal health and a family's future. Clear, collaborative discussions about risks and benefits support confident decision-making.</p>



<p>Expert teams across cardiology, maternal-fetal medicine, imaging and surgery help form a comprehensive plan tailored to each patient's needs.</p>



<p>Any expectant mother should reach out to a clinician if symptoms such as shortness of breath, difficulty breathing when lying flat, chest discomfort, palpitations, swelling that increases rapidly or new fatigue begin to interfere with daily life.</p>



<p>When something doesn't feel right, speaking up is one of the most important steps a patient can take. A strong care team is ready to help navigate each stage of pregnancy to safely support the health of both the patient and the baby.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/young-katie-a-m-d/bio-20533690"><em>Katie Young, M.D.</em></a><em>, Cardio-Obstetrics, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota</em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-to-know-about-pregnancy-and-heart-valve-disease/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What to know about pregnancy and heart valve disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/09/a-pregnant-young-woman-standing-by-a-crib-holding-her-belly-and-smiling-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/09/a-pregnant-young-woman-standing-by-a-crib-holding-her-belly-and-smiling-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Katie Young]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Heart Disease]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>(VIDEO) Heart disease in women: 4 things a Mayo Clinic cardiologist wants you to know</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-heart-disease-in-women-4-things-a-mayo-clinic-cardiologist-wants-you-to-know/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Deb Balzer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 14:21:16 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Cycle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Sharonne N. Hayes]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Heart Disease]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=409612</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Editor's note: February is American Heart Month Heart disease affects women differently than men, and understanding those differences can be lifesaving. Dr.&nbsp;Sharonne N. Hayes, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist and leading expert in the field of women’s heart health, says progress in research, treatment and prevention has accelerated but women still need better information. Here are […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-heart-disease-in-women-4-things-a-mayo-clinic-cardiologist-wants-you-to-know/">(VIDEO) Heart disease in women: 4 things a Mayo Clinic cardiologist wants you to know</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<p--><p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/12/shutterstock_486606706_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a diverse group of happy, smiling women standing near a brick wall for a background" class="wp-image-225072" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/12/shutterstock_486606706_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/12/shutterstock_486606706_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/12/shutterstock_486606706_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p><em>Editor's note: February is American Heart Month</em></p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Heart disease</a> affects women differently than men, and understanding those differences can be lifesaving. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/hayes-sharonne-n-m-d/bio-20053532?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr.&nbsp;Sharonne N. Hayes</a>, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist and leading expert in the field of women’s heart health, says progress in research, treatment and prevention has accelerated but women still need better information.</p>



<p>Here are four things Dr. Hayes wants women to know, and do, when it comes to protecting their heart health.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oac3VY87WaM" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Watch: Dr. Sharonne N. Hayes talks about heart disease in women</strong></a></h3>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidoac3VY87WaM" title="Heart disease in women: Four things a Mayo Clinic cardiologist wants you to know" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/oac3VY87WaM?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Video sound bites are available in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Sharonne N. Hayes, M.D./Cardiovascular Medicine/Mayo Clinic"&nbsp;</strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>1. Women get heart disease, and symptoms can be missed.</strong></h2>



<p>Dr.&nbsp;Hayes says there are conditions that disproportionately affect women including heart failure with preserved ejection fraction, microvascular dysfunction and heart attacks due to <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-hope-for-spontaneous-coronary-artery-dissection-scad/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">spontaneous coronary artery dissection (SCAD)</a>. As a result, women with chest pain or shortness of breath were sometimes told their hearts were fine, only to learn later they did have heart disease.</p>



<p>Women were also historically excluded from clinical trials, meaning researchers are still closing evidence gaps today. Dr.&nbsp;Hayes says women should trust their symptoms and continue advocating for answers when something does not feel right.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>2. Knowledge and advocacy can change outcomes.</strong></h2>



<p>One of the most encouraging changes Dr.&nbsp;Hayes has seen is the rise of patient advocacy and access to health information. Women are more engaged, more informed and more willing to ask questions.</p>



<p>That shift is especially visible through advocacy organizations such as <a href="https://www.womenheart.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">WomenHeart: The National Coalition for Women with Heart Disease</a>. Women may arrive at the point of care frightened and unsure how to describe their symptoms, or they may feel alone in dealing with their diagnosis. Education, training and peer support can give them tools to feel more confident and empowered.</p>



<p>Dr.&nbsp;Hayes describes the transformation as powerful, driven by knowledge and by the support women find in one another.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>3. The future of heart care is promising </strong></h2>



<p>Advances in cardiology are moving quickly. Dr.&nbsp;Hayes says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20353124" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">treatments</a> that once required open-heart surgery may now be replaced by less invasive procedures, and emerging therapies offer hope that future outcomes may differ from those of past generations.</p>



<p>Study design is important. Representation in research, including artificial intelligence, can influence how findings apply. Dr. Hayes notes the role of patient data breadth in the development of new tools.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>4. Prevention starts with habits and partnership.</strong></h2>



<p>Dr.&nbsp;Hayes emphasizes that it is never too early or too late to improve heart health. Healthy habits adopted in childhood reduce future risk, and starting an exercise program later in life still improves heart health.</p>



<p>She says prevention comes down to three things: behaviors, choices and knowledge. Staying physically active, avoiding tobacco, and eating a heart-healthy diet that includes fruits, vegetables, whole grains and fewer processed foods all matter. Knowing personal health numbers, such as blood pressure and cholesterol, and understanding family history are also critical.</p>



<p>Equally important is working closely with a healthcare team. Medications should never be stopped without consulting a healthcare professional. If a treatment causes side effects or is not working, there are often other options, says Dr. Hayes, emphasizing the importance of patience and care teams working together to find solutions.</p>



<p><strong>To interview Dr. Sharonne N. Hayes, contact:</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-heart-disease-in-women-4-things-a-mayo-clinic-cardiologist-wants-you-to-know/">(VIDEO) Heart disease in women: 4 things a Mayo Clinic cardiologist wants you to know</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/10/a-diverse-group-of-women-standing-together-and-smiling-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/12/shutterstock_486606706_Fotor-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Sharonne N. Hayes]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Heart Disease]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tomorrow’s Cure: Obesity, behavior and the heart</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-obesity-behavior-and-the-heart/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[jftmayo]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 13:29:11 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[obesity]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=410016</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->This&nbsp;episode&nbsp;of "Tomorrow's Cure"&nbsp;delivers an&nbsp;American Heart Month&nbsp;discussion&nbsp;as&nbsp;the guests talk about&nbsp;heart health and how listeners can make improvements to their cardiovascular&nbsp;well-being&nbsp;at any age.&nbsp;Dr. Andres Acosta,&nbsp;Delaney Family Director, Nutrition Obesity Research Program at&nbsp;Mayo Clinic;&nbsp;Dr. Kevin Volpp, scientific lead for the&nbsp;Food Is Medicine&nbsp;initiative&nbsp;through the American Heart Association (AHA);&nbsp;and&nbsp;Nancy Brown,&nbsp;CEO&nbsp;of the&nbsp;AHA,&nbsp;offer&nbsp;perspectives&nbsp;on both the&nbsp;persistent challenges and emerging opportunities in cardiovascular health.&nbsp;Cardiovascular […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-obesity-behavior-and-the-heart/">Tomorrow’s Cure: Obesity, behavior and the heart</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/TC_Cardio_YT-Thumbnail_1280x720-1024x576.jpg" alt="Graphic: Episode 3 Tomorrow's Cure obesity, behaviors heart" class="wp-image-410021" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/TC_Cardio_YT-Thumbnail_1280x720-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/TC_Cardio_YT-Thumbnail_1280x720-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/TC_Cardio_YT-Thumbnail_1280x720-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/TC_Cardio_YT-Thumbnail_1280x720.jpg 1280w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>This&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rfnq5jc5QSg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">episode</a>&nbsp;of "Tomorrow's Cure"&nbsp;delivers an&nbsp;American Heart Month&nbsp;discussion&nbsp;as&nbsp;the guests talk about&nbsp;heart health and how listeners can make improvements to their cardiovascular&nbsp;well-being&nbsp;at any age.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/acosta-andres-j-m-d-ph-d/bio-20189108" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Andres Acosta</a>,&nbsp;Delaney Family Director, Nutrition Obesity Research Program at&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic;</a>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.healthcarexfood.org/en/about/our-leadership" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Kevin Volpp</a>, scientific lead for the&nbsp;Food Is Medicine&nbsp;initiative&nbsp;through the American Heart Association (AHA);&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.heart.org/en/about-us/nancy-brown" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nancy Brown</a>,&nbsp;CEO&nbsp;of the&nbsp;AHA,&nbsp;offer&nbsp;perspectives&nbsp;on both the&nbsp;persistent challenges and emerging opportunities in cardiovascular health.&nbsp;Cardiovascular disease&nbsp;remains&nbsp;the leading cause of death in the&nbsp;U.S.&nbsp;even as prevention and treatment strategies continue to advance.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Millions of Americans continue to face <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiovascular disease</a> despite significant improvements in mortality&nbsp;rates related to the&nbsp;disease&nbsp;over the past century.&nbsp;Rising rates of obesity,&nbsp;hypertension&nbsp;and diabetes contribute to this burden.&nbsp;Family history&nbsp;remains&nbsp;a critical predictor, underscoring the importance of early awareness and risk assessment.&nbsp;</p>



<p>At the heart&nbsp;of this&nbsp;episode's&nbsp;discussion&nbsp;is&nbsp;the evolving understanding of obesity as a chronic, multifactorial disease. Dr. Acosta emphasizes&nbsp;the need for <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-pave-the-way-for-individualized-obesity-therapy-tailoring-interventions-to-a-persons-needs/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">individualized</a> approaches&nbsp;and notes&nbsp;that people develop obesity for different biological reasons.&nbsp;"Understanding&nbsp;the biology&nbsp;and going down to the root cause of obesity changes the conversation," Dr. Acosta says. "It helps patients see why they struggle and why tailored interventions work."&nbsp;His research&nbsp;demonstrates&nbsp;that phenotype-based treatment strategies produce more effective and sustainable weight loss than standard models, reinforcing the importance of personalized care in addressing one of the most significant contributors to cardiovascular&nbsp;disease.&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidrfnq5jc5QSg" title="Obesity, Behavior, and the Heart: How We Fix It | Tomorrow's Cure Season 4 Episode 3" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rfnq5jc5QSg?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p></p>



<p>The role of nutrition&nbsp;is&nbsp;another focus of this&nbsp;episode. Dr. Volpp&nbsp;points to&nbsp;the AHA's Food Is Medicine initiative, which is building evidence&nbsp;to treat healthy food like a medical therapy, especially for people with conditions such as heart failure,&nbsp;diabetes&nbsp;or obesity. Programs that provide medically tailored meals, produce prescriptions or nutrition coaching have shown promise in improving health and reducing hospital visits, sometimes within just weeks.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The panelists note that improvements in cardiovascular health are achievable at any age. Modest changes, such as increased consumption of&nbsp;nutrient-dense&nbsp;foods and consistent physical activity, can have significant positive&nbsp;effects, particularly among older adults. Research&nbsp;demonstrates&nbsp;that even short-term dietary interventions can yield measurable improvements in stability and quality of life for patients with established cardiovascular&nbsp;conditions.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Looking ahead, precision nutrition&nbsp;represents&nbsp;a promising advancement. Ongoing national research&nbsp;is focused on developing individualized dietary recommendations based on genetics,&nbsp;metabolism&nbsp;and microbiome data. As these tools evolve, they are expected to reduce reliance on&nbsp;trial-and-error&nbsp;approaches&nbsp;and support more effective&nbsp;long-term&nbsp;weight and risk&nbsp;management.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The discussion highlights&nbsp;a clear path forward: advance&nbsp;personalized care, expand access to nutrition-focused&nbsp;interventions&nbsp;and&nbsp;strengthen&nbsp;preventive strategies across populations. Together, these efforts offer significant potential to reduce the burden of cardiovascular disease and improve health outcomes in the years ahead.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Listen to the latest episode of "<a href="https://careinfo.mayoclinic.org/tomorrows-cure-podcast?mc_id=global&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=tcseasonthreeepisodeone&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=global&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=193335" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tomorrow's Cure</a>" wherever you get your podcasts. You can explore the full library of episodes and guests on the&nbsp;show's&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLSWR1ylG_6JZd7nHPPgpIaoq_iRHgXRoF" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">page</a>.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-obesity-behavior-and-the-heart/">Tomorrow’s Cure: Obesity, behavior and the heart</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/TC_Cardio_Episode-Art_3000x3000.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2026/01/TC_Cardio_YT-Thumbnail_1280x720.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[obesity]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What heart-healthy habits should I consider starting in the new year?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-heart-healthy-habits-should-i-consider-starting-in-the-new-year/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[pattymiller]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 13:33:50 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Franciso Lopez-Jimenez]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Heart Health]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=409319</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;Heart disease runs in my family, and I really want to avoid developing it myself if I can. What heart-health habits should I consider starting in the new year? ANSWER:&nbsp;When it comes to heart health, prevention still delivers the greatest return. Taking steps now — no matter how small — provides far greater […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-heart-healthy-habits-should-i-consider-starting-in-the-new-year/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What heart-healthy habits should I consider starting in the new year?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1419981608-1024x683.jpg" alt="a young Black man standing on a city sidewalk, eyes closed and head back, appearing to take a deep breath" class="wp-image-371349" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1419981608-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1419981608-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1419981608-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1419981608-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1419981608.jpg 1687w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Heart disease</a> runs in my family, and I really want to avoid developing it myself if I can. What heart-health habits should I consider starting in the new year?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong>&nbsp;When it comes to <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-tips-for-healthy-heart-from-a-mayo-clinic-cardiologist/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart health</a>, prevention still delivers the greatest return. Taking steps now — no matter how small — provides far greater benefits than managing heart disease later. Fortunately, there are many practical, sustainable ways to lower your risk, even if heart disease is common in your family.</p>



<p>A good place to begin is with the simple, everyday choices that influence your long-term cardiovascular health. To build healthier habits, start gradually. Improving your diet one step at a time, moving your body throughout the day and avoiding long periods of sitting can make a measurable difference. Small changes add up, and consistency matters more than perfection.</p>



<p>Emotional well-being also plays a vital role in heart health. Activities that bring meaning or connection, such as walking with a friend or focusing on purpose in daily life, can lower stress and support healthier behaviors. Caring for your emotional health isn't&nbsp;separate&nbsp;from caring for your heart; both are deeply interconnected.</p>



<p>Taking medications as directed is another key factor in preventing heart attacks or stroke. If you have been prescribed treatment for high blood pressure, high cholesterol or other risk factors, following your clinician's guidance and monitoring your numbers ensures those risks stay under control.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Heart-healthy steps to consider</h2>



<p>Here are eight additional steps that can strengthen your heart-health plan for the year ahead.</p>



<p><strong>1. Avoid tobacco.</strong><br>Smoking or using smokeless tobacco damages the heart and blood vessels, and it lowers the oxygen available to your body, forcing the heart to work harder. The benefits of quitting begin almost immediately, and the risk of heart disease decreases significantly within a year.</p>



<p><strong>2. Get moving every day.</strong><br>Aim for 30 minutes or more of physical activity most days of the week. Brisk walking, cycling, gardening, taking the stairs and even brief movement breaks throughout the day all contribute to better cardiovascular fitness. National guidelines recommend at least 150 minutes of moderate or intense activity weekly, but any amount of movement is better than none. If you've been inactive, increase your activity gradually.</p>



<p><strong>3. Follow a heart-healthy eating plan.</strong><br>Diet affects many major risk factors, including blood pressure, cholesterol and blood sugar. Heart-healthy patterns such as the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/mediterranean-diet/art-20047801" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mediterranean diet</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/dash-diet/art-20048456" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">DASH eating plan</a>&nbsp;emphasize fruits, vegetables, legumes, fish, lean protein, low-fat dairy products, whole grains, and healthy fats like olive oil and avocado. Limiting salt, added sugars, refined carbohydrates, alcohol, saturated fat and processed foods, including processed meat, further protects your heart.</p>



<p><strong>4. Maintain a healthy weight.</strong><br>Excess weight, especially around your belly, raises the risk of high blood pressure, high cholesterol, type 2 diabetes, sleep apnea and heart disease. Even modest weight loss of 3% to 5% can improve blood sugar, triglycerides and overall metabolic health.</p>



<p><strong>5. Prioritize quality sleep.</strong><br>Adults typically need at least seven hours of sleep each night. Poor sleep is linked to obesity, high blood pressure, diabetes and heart disease. Maintain a consistent sleep schedule and a restful environment. If you snore loudly, wake up gasping or feel excessively tired despite adequate sleep, talk to your clinician about screening for obstructive sleep apnea.</p>



<p><strong>6. Manage stress in healthy ways.</strong><br>Chronic stress can elevate blood pressure and affect lifestyle choices. Techniques such as mindfulness, yoga, relaxation exercises, mindful breathing, physical activity and seeking social support can lessen stress and improve overall well-being.</p>



<p><strong>7. Stay up to date with screening tests.</strong><br>High blood pressure, high cholesterol and high blood sugar often develop silently. Regular screenings allow early detection and treatment. Your clinician can recommend how often to check your numbers based on your age and risk profile.</p>



<p><strong>8. Prevent infections.</strong><br>Good dental care and staying up to date on vaccinations reduce risks associated with infections that can harm the heart or worsen existing conditions.</p>



<p>While you can't change your family history, you can adopt many habits that strengthen and protect your heart. Start with small, manageable steps, stay connected emotionally, take medications as prescribed, and partner with your care team to monitor your health.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Prevention is a powerful investment and the new year offers a perfect opportunity to begin.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/lopez-jimenez-francisco-m-d-m-s/bio-20053705" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Francisco Lopez-Jimenez, M.D.</em></a><em>, Cardiovascular Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota</em></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-heart-healthy-habits-should-i-consider-starting-in-the-new-year/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: What heart-healthy habits should I consider starting in the new year?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-young-Black-man-standing-on-a-city-sidewalk-eyes-closed-and-head-back-appearing-to-take-a-deep-breath-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-young-Black-man-standing-on-a-city-sidewalk-eyes-closed-and-head-back-appearing-to-take-a-deep-breath-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Franciso Lopez-Jimenez]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Heart Health]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New heart helps Loren Vinal return to music, life he loves</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-heart-helps-loren-vinal-return-to-music-life-he-loves/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[rebeccabromelkamp]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 14:32:10 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiology Patient Stories]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Daniel Yip]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[lvad]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=409201</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->For Loren Vinal, the holidays have always carried a gentle kind of magic. Loren's hometown of Corning, New York, and his winters on Jekyll Island, Georgia, offered two peaceful places where music and community shaped his daily life. In late 2017, everything changed. After months of worsening shortness of breath and repeated misdiagnoses, Loren — […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-heart-helps-loren-vinal-return-to-music-life-he-loves/">New heart helps Loren Vinal return to music, life he loves</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Loren-Vinal_Patient_AJ-Rodgers_Nurse-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Loren Vinal plays his guitar, heart transplant recipient with AJ Rodgers, nurse" class="wp-image-409276" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Loren-Vinal_Patient_AJ-Rodgers_Nurse-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Loren-Vinal_Patient_AJ-Rodgers_Nurse-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Loren-Vinal_Patient_AJ-Rodgers_Nurse-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Loren-Vinal_Patient_AJ-Rodgers_Nurse-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Loren-Vinal_Patient_AJ-Rodgers_Nurse-16x9-1.jpg 1824w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Loren Vinal plays the guitar with AJ Rodgers,&nbsp;a heart&nbsp;transplant nurse practitioner&nbsp;at Mayo Clinic in Florida.</figcaption></figure>



<p>For Loren Vinal, the holidays have always carried a gentle kind of magic. Loren's hometown of Corning, New York, and his winters on Jekyll Island, Georgia, offered two peaceful places where music and community shaped his daily life.</p>



<p>In late 2017, everything changed. After months of worsening shortness of breath and repeated misdiagnoses, Loren — a guitarist with 40 years of experience — flew to Nashville, Tennessee,&nbsp;to play a show with a friend.&nbsp;Loren&nbsp;ended up in the&nbsp;emergency department&nbsp;before he could play&nbsp;—&nbsp;diagnosed with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/transplant-medicine/news/advanced-heart-failure-complexities-and-when-to-refer-for-specialty-care/mqc-20504989" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">advanced heart failure</a>.&nbsp;He remembers the shock of that moment.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Out of the blue, my life&nbsp;completely&nbsp;shifted,"&nbsp;Loren says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>After&nbsp;receiving that diagnosis, Loren spent&nbsp;13 days&nbsp;in the hospital&nbsp;in Nashville.&nbsp;Once stable,&nbsp;he&nbsp;returned to&nbsp;upstate&nbsp;New York and continued care at&nbsp;a&nbsp;local hospital&nbsp;where specialists determined he needed a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ventricular-assist-device/about/pac-20384529" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">left ventricular assist device (LVAD)</a>. The <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-heart-patients-helped-by-ventricular-assist-devices/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">LVAD&nbsp;</a>is&nbsp;a mechanical pump that supports the heart by helping the left ventricle circulate blood throughout the body.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>After&nbsp;about seven years with the LVAD, new&nbsp;complications&nbsp;in 2024 meant it was time to revisit transplant. By then, Lorena already&nbsp;knew&nbsp;about&nbsp;Mayo&nbsp;Clinic in Florida. Years earlier, he had been transferred there from a nearby hospital while wintering on Jekyll Island because smaller hospitals were not equipped to manage&nbsp;patients&nbsp;with&nbsp;the&nbsp;LVAD.</p>



<p>Loren&nbsp;never&nbsp;forgot&nbsp;the care&nbsp;he received then.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"I was&nbsp;so impressed with the dedication and professionalism at Mayo Clinic,"&nbsp;Loren says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>When he learned he was a strong&nbsp;candidate&nbsp;for heart transplant,&nbsp;he says&nbsp;the decision to pursue care&nbsp;at Mayo Clinic&nbsp;felt right.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Heart transplant</h2>



<p>Loren received his first heart&nbsp;transplant&nbsp;on July 1, 2024.&nbsp;However, due to unforeseen circumstances, Loren would need another new heart, and he was relisted on the transplant waiting list in May 2025.&nbsp;He spent nine and a half weeks&nbsp;waiting in the hospital&nbsp;before receiving his second heart&nbsp;transplant&nbsp;on July 19, 2025.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Waiting was difficult, but he felt supported at every turn.&nbsp;Today,&nbsp;Loren&nbsp;shares that&nbsp;he&nbsp;exercises&nbsp;and&nbsp;plays music again&nbsp;—&nbsp;feeling stronger with each passing day.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Loren-Vinal-heart-transplant-plays-guitar-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Loren Vinal plays his guitar, heart transplant recipient" class="wp-image-409273" style="width:680px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Loren-Vinal-heart-transplant-plays-guitar-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Loren-Vinal-heart-transplant-plays-guitar-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Loren-Vinal-heart-transplant-plays-guitar-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Loren-Vinal-heart-transplant-plays-guitar-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Loren-Vinal-heart-transplant-plays-guitar-16x9-1.jpg 1824w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>
</div>


<p>"A good working heart changes everything,"&nbsp;Loren says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Loren speaks openly about the&nbsp;gratitude he feels toward his&nbsp;donors who&nbsp;gave him the incredible gift of&nbsp;life. "It&nbsp;is the greatest gift you can bestow on another human," he says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Throughout his journey, Loren learned more about the scope of Mayo Clinic's commitment to transplantation.&nbsp;As one of the largest and most comprehensive transplant programs in the world,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/home/orc-20203891" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Transplant Center</a>&nbsp;provides seamless care across&nbsp;heart, lung, liver, kidney, pancreas&nbsp;and&nbsp;bone&nbsp;marrow&nbsp;transplantation&nbsp;for both adults and children.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The transplant center&nbsp;teams in Arizona,&nbsp;Florida&nbsp;and Minnesota work together to advance innovation,&nbsp;research&nbsp;and education, shaping the future of transplantation worldwide.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic also leads research in organ preservation, living donation and regenerative medicine, guided by a vision that no patient should die while waiting for a transplant. These advances have helped expand access for patients with complex needs and support successful outcomes like Loren's.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Loren showed extraordinary resilience,"&nbsp;says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/yip-daniel-s-m-d/bio-20054324" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr.&nbsp;Daniel&nbsp;Yip</a>,&nbsp;transplant&nbsp;cardiologist at Mayo Clinic in Florida.&nbsp;"Even in the face of profound&nbsp;challenges, he&nbsp;remained&nbsp;engaged and hopeful. Our team was committed to walking every step of this with him."&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>As Loren looks toward the&nbsp;new year with a new heart, he feels a deeper joy in the moments he once took for granted:&nbsp;a&nbsp;strong, steady heartbeat;&nbsp;music&nbsp;returning&nbsp;to his fingertips;&nbsp;and time with the people he loves.</p>



<p>"I&nbsp;sincerely thank&nbsp;everyone&nbsp;involved,&nbsp;and&nbsp;I&nbsp;hope to continue to pay it forward,"&nbsp;Loren says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>His story now carries its own quiet holiday light&nbsp;—&nbsp;hope renewed, life restored and gratitude that stretches far beyond the season.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-heart-helps-loren-vinal-return-to-music-life-he-loves/">New heart helps Loren Vinal return to music, life he loves</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Loren-Vinal_Guitar-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Loren-Vinal_Patient_AJ-Rodgers_Nurse-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Daniel Yip]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[lvad]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Transplant]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>VIDEO: Hockey coach back in the game after cardiac event, thanks to teamwork, quality care</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-hockey-coach-back-in-the-game-after-cardiac-event-thanks-to-teamwork-quality-care/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[ajbeltz]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 14:01:12 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiology Patient Stories]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Video]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Gurpreet Sandhu]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jill Colglazier]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Philip spencer]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=409062</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->When a hockey coach and teacher in Minnesota experienced a cardiac event, a multidisciplinary team at Mayo Clinic helped him get back in the game through teamwork and quality care On a winter Sunday in Owatonna, Minnesota, Ryan Harrison, a hockey coach and teacher, was wrapping up a youth game with his son, Justin. As […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-hockey-coach-back-in-the-game-after-cardiac-event-thanks-to-teamwork-quality-care/">VIDEO: Hockey coach back in the game after cardiac event, thanks to teamwork, quality care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Ryan-Harrison-family-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Harrison family" class="wp-image-409092" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Ryan-Harrison-family-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Ryan-Harrison-family-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Ryan-Harrison-family-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Ryan-Harrison-family-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Ryan-Harrison-family-16-x-9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The Harrison family, from left: Justin, Ryan, Chris and Lindsey  </figcaption>



<p><strong>When a hockey coach and teacher in Minnesota experienced a cardiac event, a multidisciplinary team at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-centered-care" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> helped him get back in the game through teamwork and quality care</strong></p>



<p>On a winter Sunday in Owatonna, Minnesota, Ryan Harrison, a hockey coach and teacher, was wrapping up a youth game with his son, Justin. As the family loaded gear into the car and prepared to head home, Ryan pressed the start button and immediately slumped forward, unresponsive.</p>



<p>In an instant, everything changed. Chris, his wife, tried to wake him, pulling on him and calling his name, while their teenage son dialed 911. Justin ran outside the car to flag down help and, in a remarkable stroke of timing, came across a supervising nurse from Owatonna Hospital who had just left the arena.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The nurse began CPR immediately. Her intervention became the first link in a series of lifesaving events that would involve two hospitals, dozens of specialists and some of the most advanced emergency cardiac techniques available.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Somebody was watching over him," Chris says. "The right people were in the right place at exactly the right time."</p>



<p>Paramedics transported Ryan to Owatonna Hospital, where he coded again. Dense fog ruled out airlifting Ryan, and he was rushed to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> in Rochester, Minnesota, by ground ambulance.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Emergency intervention at Mayo Clinic</strong></h2>



<p>The cardiac catheterization laboratory at Mayo was waiting for Ryan when he arrived in critical condition. Specialists quickly uncovered a completely blocked coronary artery and restored blood flow within minutes. But despite their swift action, his heart was still failing.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Ryan-Harrison-hospital-1x1-1-1024x1024.jpg" alt="Ryan Harrison in the hospital" class="wp-image-409093" style="width:433px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Ryan-Harrison-hospital-1x1-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Ryan-Harrison-hospital-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Ryan-Harrison-hospital-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Ryan-Harrison-hospital-1x1-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Ryan-Harrison-hospital-1x1-1-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Ryan-Harrison-hospital-1x1-1.jpg 1883w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>
</div>


<p>The team placed an Impella device&nbsp;—&nbsp;a tiny pump that steps in for the heart when it cannot pump enough blood&nbsp;— in Ryan.&nbsp;When his oxygen levels continued to decline despite the device being in place, the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ecmo/about/pac-20484615" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO)</a> team was called in to provide the highest level of life support.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"This is precisely why our teams prepare the way we do," says&nbsp;<a href="https://quarterly.mayo.edu/directoryui/personDetails/10486500">Dr. Gurpreet Sandhu</a>, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist.&nbsp;"When a patient like Ryan arrives, every link in the chain activates instantly. People from multiple specialties converge without hesitation. That kind of teamwork is what changes outcomes."</p>



<p>Even with the blockage cleared and mechanical support in place, Ryan remained in a fragile state as he was transferred to the intensive care unit (ICU). Early neurological tests offered a quiet but meaningful hope — he could move his fingers and toes.</p>



<p>"That tiny movement meant everything," Chris says. "It told us Ryan was still in there fighting."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A dangerous turn</strong></h2>



<p>Two days later, a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ct-scan/about/pac-20393675" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CT scan</a> revealed a concerning blood clot. The scan also showed that Ryan was born with an unusual arterial configuration: a single shared artery supplying blood to his stomach, liver and bowels. Because of this rare anatomy, the clot created a complete blockage, leaving no alternate pathway for blood flow.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Ryan still needed the Impella for circulatory support, but it was also putting pressure on the artery. Taking the device out could inadvertently move the clot into the aorta, creating the possibility that it might reach his brain or heart.</p>



<p>"His anatomy and the clot location created a perfect storm," says&nbsp;<a href="https://quarterly.mayo.edu/directoryui/personDetails/15546306">Dr. Jill Colglazier</a>, a Mayo Clinic vascular surgeon.&nbsp;"We couldn't move forward without the entire care team planning every step together."</p>



<p>A multispecialty group of cardiologists, vascular surgeons, anesthesiologists, intensivists and ECMO specialists devised a creative plan in which the cardiac catheterization team would establish an alternative circulatory pathway by placing a device in Ryan's upper chest. Following this, the Impella would be removed, allowing vascular surgery to safely restore abdominal blood flow.</p>



<p>"What made this possible was not one specialty, but five or six working simultaneously," Dr. Colglazier says. "Everyone brought their expertise, and everyone trusted one another completely."</p>



<p>The surgery lasted nearly six hours and required careful timing, real-time communication and absolute precision. When it was complete, blood flow had been successfully restored.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Turning the corner in the ICU</strong></h2>



<p>The next morning, Ryan woke up alert and responsive. It was a pivotal moment for both his family and the medical team.</p>



<p>Now the focus shifted to determining whether his heart could function without the use of ECMO. The assessment required a multidisciplinary team at the bedside, including cardiologists, cardiac surgeons, ICU physicians, heart failure specialists, anesthesiologists and echocardiography experts.</p>



<p><a href="https://quarterly.mayo.edu/directoryui/personDetails/30127175">Dr. Philip Spencer</a>, a Mayo Clinic cardiovascular surgeon who leads the ECMO and Mechanical Circulatory Support programs, recalls the moment they tested Ryan's heart function.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"When we slowly reduce <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-teams-with-first-responders-to-improve-care-for-cardiac-arrest-patients/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ECMO</a> flow, we're essentially asking the heart, ‘Can you take over now?'" Dr. Spencer says. "It is a powerful moment when you see it respond. There's a sense of collective relief because every team has been working toward that one goal."</p>



<p>Dr. Spencer credits the seamless teamwork for Ryan's recovery.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"It's not a handoff from one specialty to the next," Dr. Spencer says. "It's multiple teams taking care of the same patient at the same time, each doing what they do best."</p>



<p>Ryan's heart held steady. The ECMO was removed, and for the first time since his collapse, he was breathing, beating and healing completely on his own.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Rebuilding strength and confidence</strong></h2>



<p>With the immediate danger behind him, Ryan began rehabilitation. He tackled small but meaningful steps: sitting up, walking short distances, lifting light weights and completing cognitive exercises. The ICU nurses and therapists encouraged him through each milestone.</p>



<p>One of the things Ryan remembers most was how often staff returned to check on him — even when they were not assigned to his care that day.</p>



<p>"They didn't just keep me alive," Ryan says. "They lifted me up. I felt like I was everyone's patient, not just one person's. Their teamwork made me feel like I wasn't doing this alone."</p>



<p>Chris felt that support too,&nbsp;</p>



<p>"They cared about Ryan as a person," Chris says. "They cared about us as a family. That kind of compassion can't be taught."</p>



<p>Ryan completed <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/cardiac-rehabilitation-program/overview/ovc-20442302" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiac rehabilitation</a>, regained his stamina and later received an <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/implantable-cardioverter-defibrillators/about/pac-20384692" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">implantable cardioverter-defibrillator</a> as a long-term safety measure. Slowly, life returned to the rhythm he recognized.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Life renewed</strong></h2>



<p>Today, Ryan walks several miles a day, has returned to golfing and is coaching hockey again. Everyday moments, such as watching Justin skate, visiting his daughter at college and waking up next to Chris, have taken on deeper meaning. He understands just how close he came to losing them.</p>



<p>When he reflects on his survival, he thinks about the coordinated efforts of people who may never meet one another but were nonetheless part of the same chain: the nurse in the parking lot, first responders, Owatonna clinicians, Mayo's interventional cardiology team, ECMO specialists, vascular and cardiac surgeons, anesthesiologists, ICU nurses, rehabilitation therapists, and many others.</p>



<p>When Ryan tells his players, "We, not me," he now understands the phrase in a way only someone who has relied on an entire community of caregivers can truly understand.</p>



<p>"They gave me my husband back," Chris says. "I will never forget that."</p>



<p>And Ryan, back in the game he loves, simply says, "Every day is a gift."</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/_V8FH-Kg78E">Watch a video of Ryan Harrison's story</a></strong></h3>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeV8FHKg78E" title="Hockey coach back in the game after cardiac arrest event, thanks to teamwork, quality care" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_V8FH-Kg78E?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-hockey-coach-back-in-the-game-after-cardiac-event-thanks-to-teamwork-quality-care/">VIDEO: Hockey coach back in the game after cardiac event, thanks to teamwork, quality care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Ryan-and-Chris-wife-Harrison-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Ryan-Harrison-family-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Gurpreet Sandhu]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jill Colglazier]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Philip spencer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</atom:link></channel>
</rss> 