<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Health &amp;amp; Wellness - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/health-and-wellness/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/health-and-wellness/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 14:25:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;#038;A:  Tips for summer water safety</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-tips-for-summer-water-safety/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pattymiller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health &amp; Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q &amp; A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jason Wray-Raabolle]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=404609</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;We just moved to an area with a lot of opportunities for water recreation and are so excited about our first summer on the water. But we want to make sure everyone stays safe. Can you give us some pointers for water safety? ANSWER:&amp;#160;Nothing beats a day at the lake, river, beach or [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-tips-for-summer-water-safety/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;amp;A:  Tips for summer water safety</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/06/shutterstock_647157832_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a little girl smiling as a woman, perhaps her mother, holds her in the water of a swimming pool" class="wp-image-194661" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/06/shutterstock_647157832_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/06/shutterstock_647157832_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/06/shutterstock_647157832_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;</strong>We just moved to an area with a lot of opportunities for water recreation and are so excited about our first summer on the water. But we want to make sure everyone stays safe. Can you give us some pointers for water safety?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:&amp;nbsp;</strong>Nothing beats a day at the lake, river, beach or pool for fun, fitness, fishing and relaxation. While spending time on and around the water this summer, these tips can ensure that everyone is safe, has fun and enjoys the time together.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Learn to swim</strong></h2>



<p>Every year in the U.S., about 4,000 people die by drowning. Children, men and nonwhite people are at the highest risk.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Learning to swim is one of the most important ways to stay safe on the water. The American Academy of Pediatrics supports swimming lessons for most children ages 4 and older. Lessons for children ages 1 to 4 could be appropriate, depending on how often they're exposed to water. Even infants can be introduced to the water. Check to see what classes are available in your area.</p>



<p>Swimmers of all ages may be more familiar with pools than rivers and may not know what to do if caught in a current. Stay calm, float on your back, and when you come to a calmer area, flip over and swim diagonally toward shore with the flow of the current.</p>



<p>Keep these safety tips in mind too:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Don't swim alone.</li>



<li>Supervise children when they're swimming, and stay close enough to reach out to a child at any time.</li>



<li>Before diving into a body of water, know the water depth and if there are any underwater obstacles.</li>



<li>Keep pool gates closed at all times, and consider an alarm to alert you if the gate is opened.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Wear a personal floatation device</strong></h2>



<p>Even expert swimmers can get into trouble during an emergency. It's important to be sure everyone in a watercraft wears a U.S. Coast Guard-approved personal flotation device. While boating or swimming, remember that arm floaties and inflatable toys aren't a substitute and tend to give kids and families a false sense of security.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Excellent, comfortable, easy-to-put-on models of personal flotation devices are available, so there's really no excuse not to wear one.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Stay safe while boating, no matter your craft</strong></h2>



<p>One of the most popular and fun activities of summer is spending time on the water. Boating creates lifelong memories and gives us the opportunity to unplug, spend time together, learn new skills and explore new areas.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Whether your craft is a power boat, fishing boat, pontoon, personal watercraft, canoe or kayak, you should remember these basic safety rules as you head out for a day on the water:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Be a weather watcher.&amp;nbsp;</strong>Summer weather can change quickly. Check the forecast before heading out and check again frequently while on the water. If you do get caught in a storm, navigate to the shore as quickly as possible.</li>



<li><strong>Tell someone the details of your trip.&amp;nbsp;</strong>Tell your trip plan to a friend who's staying ashore. Share details about who's on the boat, where you'll be and how long you'll be gone.</li>



<li><strong>Always operate your boat at a safe speed.&amp;nbsp;</strong>Waterways can become crowded during the summer. Slow down, stay alert and steer clear of larger vessels. Be sure to follow speed limits in "no wake" areas.</li>



<li><strong>Respect buoys and other navigational aids.&amp;nbsp;</strong>They've been put in place to ensure your safety and the safety of other boaters and swimmers. If you're not familiar with them, the U.S. Coast Guard has a handy&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.uscgboating.org/images/486.PDF" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">water navigation system guide</a>.</li>



<li><strong>Leave alcohol on shore.&amp;nbsp;</strong>The risk of drowning or injury significantly increases when alcohol or drugs are involved. More than 70% of water recreation deaths are related to alcohol use.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Be sun savvy</strong></h2>



<p>The sun's rays can be intense on the open water. Protect everyone with hats, sunglasses and sunscreen. Look for water-resistant, broad-spectrum sunscreen with a sun protection factor (SPF) of at least 30. Apply sunscreen generously and reapply every two hours, or more often if you're swimming or sweating.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Drink plenty of water</strong></h2>



<p>Even when surrounded by water, it's possible to become dehydrated. Sitting in the sun can increase your body's temperature. Pack plenty of water for each person, and drink some water every 15 to 20 minutes to remain properly hydrated.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/jason-wray-raabolle-md"><em>Jason Wray-Raabolle, M.D.</em></a><em>, Family Medicine, Mayo Clinic Health System,&amp;nbsp;Owatonna, Minnesota</em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-tips-for-summer-water-safety/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;amp;A:  Tips for summer water safety</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/06/people-in-lake-water-swimming-and-a-young-child-splashing-through-the-water-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/06/people-in-lake-water-swimming-and-a-young-child-splashing-through-the-water-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jason Wray-Raabolle]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;#038;A: Why some men experience urinary leaks &amp;#8212; or incontinence</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-why-some-men-experience-urinary-leaks-or-incontinence/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pattymiller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 12:21:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health &amp; Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. David Yang]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403645</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&amp;#160;This is kind of embarrassing, but, for a while, I’ve been leaking urine. Can something be done to fix this incontinence problem? ANSWER:&amp;#160;You don’t have to live with this issue. The three main types of&amp;#160;urinary incontinence&amp;#160;are: Incontinence can be treated with behavioral changes, exercises, medications, nerve stimulation and injections. Surgical options are also [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-why-some-men-experience-urinary-leaks-or-incontinence/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;amp;A: Why some men experience urinary leaks &amp;#8212; or incontinence</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Older-man-sitting-on-couch-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Portrait of an older, senior male, man sitting on a couch at home" class="wp-image-403659" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Older-man-sitting-on-couch-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Older-man-sitting-on-couch-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Older-man-sitting-on-couch-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Older-man-sitting-on-couch-16-x-9.jpg 1176w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&amp;nbsp;</strong>This is kind of embarrassing, but, for a while, I’ve been leaking urine. Can something be done to fix this incontinence problem?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:&amp;nbsp;</strong>You don’t have to live with this issue. The three main types of&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/urinary-incontinence/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352814" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">urinary incontinence</a>&amp;nbsp;are:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Stress incontinence</strong>&amp;nbsp;— due to leakage with activities, such as lifting, climbing stairs or strenuous activity.</li>



<li><strong>Urge incontinence</strong>&amp;nbsp;— related to leakage associated with the feeling or urge to urinate.</li>



<li><strong>Mixed incontinence</strong>&amp;nbsp;— a combination of stress and urge incontinence.</li>
</ul>



<p>Incontinence can be treated with behavioral changes, exercises, medications, nerve stimulation and injections. Surgical options are also available.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Stress incontinence in men</strong></h2>



<p>Up to 10% of men may experience stress incontinence after prostate surgery due to multiple factors related to the patient's anatomy, prostate cancer and the surgery performed. Ultimately, this leads to a weakened sphincter muscle and laxity of the pelvic floor. The sphincter muscles control the release of urine, and the urethra is the small tube that empties the bladder.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>A prostatectomy procedure removes some of the control provided by the prostate and bladder, making the patient reliant solely on the external sphincter muscle.</p>



<p>Normally, the sphincter remains closed as the bladder fills with urine until you can reach a restroom. The weakened muscles and relaxed pelvic floor have trouble holding urine, so any movement that exerts a force on the abdominal and pelvic muscles puts pressure on the bladder and can cause leakage. This force could be sneezing, bending over, lifting or even laughing.</p>



<p>Postsurgery stress incontinence symptoms may resolve on their own with time and pelvic physical therapy. Usually, patients can see continued improvement for 12 months after surgery and try nonsurgical treatments, such as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/kegels-are-for-men-too" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">physical therapy</a>, before considering surgical treatment options, such as male urethral slings and artificial urinary sphincters.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Male urethral slings</strong></h2>



<p>Male urethral slings are indicated for men with mild to moderate stress urinary incontinence, which is defined as using one to four pads per day. The surgeon uses a synthetic mesh material to create a sling, or hammock, to support and pull the urethra and pelvic floor back toward their original locations. Some slings also provide compression support for the sphincter muscles.</p>



<p>A cystoscopy test will be needed before the surgery to confirm that the sphincter muscles are working.</p>



<p>Male urethral slings are performed as an outpatient procedure, and patients can go home the same day. Heavy lifting and strenuous exercise are restricted for about six weeks. Patients need to be careful when climbing ladders and squatting for about three months after surgery because significant hip flexing can loosen the sling.</p>



<p>About 80% of men with male urethral slings see an improvement in their symptoms after surgery, with the majority of them no longer needing pads after surgery.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Artificial urinary sphincters</strong></h2>



<p>This surgical procedure is more invasive than male urethral slings and appropriate for men with severe stress incontinence, which is defined as using more than four pads per day. It's also a good option for patients who have damage to sphincter muscles from radiation therapy or a failed male urethral sling.</p>



<p>The placement of artificial urinary sphincters has multiple components. A small cuff is placed around the urethra, replacing the sphincter muscle's function. Tubes connect the cuff to a pressure-regulating balloon placed in the lower pelvic region and a pump in the scrotum. The pump is manually operated to open the cuff on the urethra and allow urine to be released from the body.</p>



<p>Some patients can go home the same day as surgery, while others will require an overnight hospital stay to recover.</p>



<p>After surgery, the artificial urinary sphincter isn't activated for about a month while the body heals. During this time, heavy lifting and exercise are restricted. Patients return to the clinic and are taught how to properly use the device. With proper training and consistent use, artificial urinary sphincters are effective at treating symptoms of severe stress urinary incontinence in men.</p>



<p>Talk with your healthcare team if you're experiencing urinary incontinence symptoms or are concerned about your prostate or urinary health.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/david-yang-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>David Yang, M.D.</em></a><em>, Urology, Mayo Clinic Health System,&amp;nbsp;Mankato, Minnesota</em></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-why-some-men-experience-urinary-leaks-or-incontinence/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;amp;A: Why some men experience urinary leaks &amp;#8212; or incontinence</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Older-man-sitting-on-couch-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Older-man-sitting-on-couch-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. David Yang]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Signs of overtraining</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-signs-of-overtraining/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pattymiller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 12:45:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health &amp; Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q &amp; A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=404616</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&amp;#160;I've taken up running again and decided to enter a half-marathon. I know I have to push myself to get ready for the race, but I don't want to overdo it. What should I watch out for as I train? ANSWER:&amp;#160;We're surrounded by warning signs — on the roads, at work, and on [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-signs-of-overtraining/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Signs of overtraining</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Adult-older-man-running-jogging-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Older man outside running, jogging, exercise" class="wp-image-389069" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Adult-older-man-running-jogging-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Adult-older-man-running-jogging-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Adult-older-man-running-jogging-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Adult-older-man-running-jogging-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Adult-older-man-running-jogging-16-x-9.jpg 1604w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong>&amp;nbsp;I've taken up running again and decided to enter a half-marathon. I know I have to push myself to get ready for the race, but I don't want to overdo it. What should I watch out for as I train?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:&amp;nbsp;</strong>We're surrounded by warning signs — on the roads, at work, and on packaging and equipment. Your body sends warning signs, too. As your race date nears, it's tempting to pull out all the stops. But that makes this a prime time to watch for warning signs of overtraining.</p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ready-to-run-what-are-some-signs-of-overtraining/">Overtraining</a> or overuse injuries are any muscle, joint or bony injuries, such as tendinitis or a stress fracture, that result from repetitive trauma. Overuse injuries typically occur because of training or technique errors.</p>



<p>Runners are tenacious athletes. Pulling back and slowing down may be tough, but while some overtraining issues can be resolved with simple rest, others may evolve into more significant problems.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>How overtraining and overuse injuries occur</strong></h2>



<p>Going too fast, exercising for too long or simply doing too much of one type of activity can strain your muscles and lead to an overuse injury. Improper technique also takes a toll on your body. For example, if you use poor form while running or doing strength-training exercises, you may overload certain areas of the body, which can cause an overuse injury.</p>



<p>Thankfully, most overuse injuries are avoidable. Try these suggestions to prevent them:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Use proper form and gear.</strong><br>Whether you're starting a new activity or have been playing a sport for a long time, taking lessons can help ensure you're using the correct technique. Talk with an expert about proper form, equipment and&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/expert-advice-on-finding-the-best-shoe-fit">gear fit</a>&amp;nbsp;to help ensure success.</li>



<li><strong>Pace yourself.</strong><br>Rely on your training program, which should spread your&amp;nbsp;aerobic activity&amp;nbsp;throughout the week. Take time to warm up before physical activity and cool down afterward.</li>



<li><strong>Gradually increase your activity level.</strong><br>When changing the intensity or duration of physical activity, do so&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-jump-start-your-workout/">gradually</a>. Try not to increase anything by more than about 10% per week. Your body needs time to adapt to the new stress.</li>



<li><strong>Mix up your routine.</strong><br>Instead of focusing on one type of exercise,&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/offseason-sports-training-tips">build variety</a>&amp;nbsp;into your training program. Doing a variety of low-impact activities prevents overuse injuries and allows your body to use different muscle groups.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Overtraining signs and what to do&amp;nbsp;</strong></h2>



<p>It can be hard to know when you’re pushing through your training for continuous improvement and when you’re moving into overtraining. Your feet and legs take a pounding as you run mile after mile, so watch for these issues:&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Callous blistering and broken toenails are common overtraining problems.&amp;nbsp;</li>



<li>Early morning pain on the sole of your foot can be a sign of&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/heel-pain-might-be-plantar-fasciitis">plantar fasciitis</a>.&amp;nbsp;</li>



<li>Tendinitis can leave you with pain in the back of your ankle or in the front of your shins, also called&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/dont-let-shin-splints-stop-your-workout/">shin splints</a>.</li>
</ul>



<p>Typically, these can be treated with rest and medication to relieve pain and inflammation. Slow down your training. Return to the level you were at before the problem or consider cross-training with low- or no-impact exercise, such as a stationary bike, elliptical or swimming. Take an extra day off. These symptoms can be short-term if you treat them early and appropriately.</p>



<p>If pain continues despite rest or gets worse, it could indicate a bone issue, which is potentially serious. Stress reactions or stress fractures are common in the mid-foot, mid-shin or, most concerning, high up in your leg by your hip. Pain that doesn't go away is a symptom, so consult your healthcare team.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What to do if you suspect an overuse injury</strong></h2>



<p>Tell your healthcare practitioner if you've recently changed your workout technique, intensity, duration, frequency or types of exercises. Identifying the cause of your overuse injury will help you correct the problem and avoid repeating it. You can seek further guidance by talking with specialists such as sports medicine physicians, athletic trainers and physical therapists.</p>



<p>Once your injury has healed, ask a specialist to check that you've completely regained strength, motion, flexibility and balance before beginning the activity again. Pay special attention to proper technique to avoid future injuries.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Staying strong</strong></h2>



<p>Don't allow an overuse injury to prevent you from being physically active. By working with a specialist, listening to your body and pacing yourself, you can avoid this common setback and safely increase your activity level.</p>



<p>Knowing you worked hard to prepare will add to your feeling of accomplishment on race day, but don’t overdo it. You’re almost there. Take care of yourself so you can keep going strong all the way to the finish line.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/corey-wencl-lat"><em>Corey Wencl</em></a><em>, Sports Medicine, Mayo Clinic Health System, La Crosse, Wisconsin</em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-signs-of-overtraining/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Signs of overtraining</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Adult-older-man-running-jogging-1-x-1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Adult-older-man-running-jogging-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;#038;A: It&amp;#8217;s a new era for knee replacements and other joint surgeries</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-its-a-new-era-for-knee-replacements-and-other-joint-surgeries/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pattymiller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health &amp; Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Brandon Bukowski]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kree replacement]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedic Surgery]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=404455</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;I know there's a knee replacement in my not too distant future. I'm wondering if there are new techniques or technologies that will give me a good outcome? ANSWER:&nbsp;Not so long ago, undergoing a total hip or knee replacement and recovery was a grueling and often painful ordeal. While these are still major [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-its-a-new-era-for-knee-replacements-and-other-joint-surgeries/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;amp;A: It&amp;#8217;s a new era for knee replacements and other joint surgeries</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="950" height="534" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Sore-knee-16-x-9.jpg" alt="man sitting on chari, holding sore knee, " class="wp-image-404461" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Sore-knee-16-x-9.jpg 950w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Sore-knee-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Sore-knee-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 950px) 100vw, 950px" /></figure></div>


<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;</strong>I know there's a knee replacement in my not too distant future. I'm wondering if there are new techniques or technologies that will give me a good outcome?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:&nbsp;</strong>Not so long ago, undergoing a total hip or <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-advances-in-knee-replacement-surgery/">knee replacement</a> and recovery was a grueling and often painful ordeal. While these are still major surgeries, new techniques and technologies are redefining them — and improving people's outcomes.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Robotic-assisted joint replacement technology has revolutionized hip and knee surgeries. This technology allows the surgeon to:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Perform enhanced,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/anatomic-modeling-laboratories/overview/ovc-20473121" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">three-dimensional preoperative planning and modeling</a>&nbsp;to ensure there's no impingement or pinching of tissues, and to refine implant sizing and positioning for a high degree of accuracy.</li>



<li>Prepare the bone and insert the implants with an unprecedented level of precision.</li>



<li>Produce personalized, patient-specific joint replacements.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p><br>In addition, major advances have been made in anesthesia used for total joint replacement surgery in the past decade. With these advances, patients recover more quickly and get up and move sooner after surgery with less pain, nausea and vomiting.</p>



<p>Another rapidly advancing technology in orthopedic surgery is 3D printing, which allows the designing and creation of custom implants to address challenging problems, including deformities, bone loss, and unusual hip or knee anatomy.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This promising technology needs more long-term data before it becomes widely used. Mayo Clinic is at the forefront of 3D printing and has been integral in advancing its clinical applications.</p>



<p>If a total hip or knee replacement is in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/top-5-reasons-for-joint-replacement" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">your future</a>, here's what you can expect.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Hip replacements&amp;nbsp;</strong></h2>



<p>Any patient who is a candidate for a "conventional" total hip replacement is a candidate for a robotic-assisted total hip replacement.</p>



<p>Hip replacements are no longer a one-technique-fits-all approach. With a "360 degree" approach, your surgeon can tailor the surgery to you, choosing from direct&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/eau-claire/services-and-treatments/orthopedic-surgery/conditions-and-treatments/joint-replacement/hip-replacement" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">anterior, posterior or anterolateral</a>&nbsp;approaches. The surgeon will discuss these options with you during your pre-op consultation.</p>



<p>The surgeon also will review with you the&amp;nbsp;entire surgical experience in detail. You'll also have a standardized patient education session with a specialty nurse and pre-op evaluation by a physical therapist. These sessions will set you up for success beginning immediately after surgery.</p>



<p>When it comes to recovery and rehabilitation:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>For most patients, total hip replacement surgery is either a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/same-day-joint-replacement-surgery-possible">same-day surgery</a>&nbsp;or a one-night hospital stay.</li>



<li>Patients can walk and navigate stairs right after surgery.</li>



<li>The majority of patients will follow a self-directed physical therapy plan at home — no need to go to an outpatient physical therapy facility.<br></li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Knee replacements</strong></h2>



<p>As with hip replacements, any&nbsp;patient who is a candidate&nbsp;for a conventional total knee replacement is a candidate for robotic-assisted total knee replacement. You'll also take part in a comprehensive education experience and physical therapy assessment to review the technique your surgeon will use during surgery. </p>



<p>Like hip replacements, total knee replacements typically are same-day surgeries or may involve a one-night hospital stay.</p>



<p>Once you've awakened from the anesthesia, you can walk and navigate stairs. Within one week after surgery, you'll begin meeting with a physical therapist who specializes in working with knee-replacement patients. For best results with strength and range of motion, you'll also be assigned daily exercises to do at home to supplement your physical therapy sessions at an outpatient facility.</p>



<p>The excellent news for total hip and knee replacement patients is that the techniques and technologies for these surgeries continue to evolve. They have the primary goals of reducing pain, enhancing function, and getting patients back to their day-to-day activities and those they love to do.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/brandon-bukowski-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Brandon Bukowski, M.D.</em></a><em>, Orthopedic Surgery, Mayo Clinic Health System, Mankato, Minnesota</em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-its-a-new-era-for-knee-replacements-and-other-joint-surgeries/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;amp;A: It&amp;#8217;s a new era for knee replacements and other joint surgeries</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Sore-knee-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Sore-knee-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Brandon Bukowski]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Kree replacement]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Orthopedic Surgery]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>(VIDEO) Breathing easy thanks to the gift of life and new Mayo Clinic Lung Transplant Program in Arizona</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-breathing-easy-thanks-to-the-gift-of-life-and-new-mayo-clinic-lung-transplant-program-in-arizona/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 18:26:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health &amp; Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MC Video pkg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[COPD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jonathan D'Cunha]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lung transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=404214</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Craig Scherer takes a deep breath and a bold step into his second chance at life Lung disease is a condition that affects millions of people worldwide. Some of those diseases, like chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, or COPD, are among the top leading causes of death globally. COPD alone affects over 16 million people, like [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-breathing-easy-thanks-to-the-gift-of-life-and-new-mayo-clinic-lung-transplant-program-in-arizona/">(VIDEO) Breathing easy thanks to the gift of life and new Mayo Clinic Lung Transplant Program in Arizona</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="881" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-Scherer-smiles-881x1024.jpg" alt="Craig Scherer takes a deep breath and a bold step into his second chance at life after a lung transplant at Mayo Clinic." class="wp-image-404219" style="width:504px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-Scherer-smiles-881x1024.jpg 881w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-Scherer-smiles-258x300.jpg 258w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-Scherer-smiles-768x893.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-Scherer-smiles.jpg 1320w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 881px) 100vw, 881px" /></figure></div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading has-text-align-center has-medium-font-size"><strong>Craig Scherer takes a deep breath and a bold step into his second chance at life</strong></h3>



<p>Lung disease is a condition that affects millions of people worldwide. Some of those diseases, like chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, or COPD, are among the top leading causes of death globally.</p>



<p>COPD alone affects over 16 million people, like Arizona resident Craig Scherer. Craig got treatments to manage his condition, but there's no cure. The disease is progressive, meaning it gets worse over time, making it harder and harder for a person to breathe.</p>



<p>Craig's disease progressed until treatments no longer worked, leaving him gasping for air and facing death. Doctors said his only hope for survival was a lung transplant.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Craig turned to Mayo Clinic in Phoenix, where doctors just launched a new multidisciplinary, specialized lung transplant program. Craig became the new program's first patient, and today he is breathing easy.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ikub1olZUTw" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Breathing easy thanks to the gift of life and Mayo Clinic's new lung transplant program in Arizona</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidIkub1olZUTw"  title="Breathing easy thanks to gift of life and new Mayo Clinic Lung Transplant Program in Arizona" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ikub1olZUTw?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (2:43) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Breathing-easy___Craig-Scherer-Story.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>It was love at first sight for Craig and Nanci Scherer.</p>



<p>They met at a little league game in the spring of 1992. Eight months later, they were married. This year, Craig and Nanci celebrated their 32nd anniversary.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Their smiles today are just as radiant as on their wedding day.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/IMG_1516-1024x768.png" alt="" class="wp-image-404018" style="width:683px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/IMG_1516-1024x768.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/IMG_1516-300x225.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/IMG_1516-768x576.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/IMG_1516-1536x1152.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/IMG_1516.png 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Nanci and Craig Scherer on their wedding day in 1993. Photo courtesy: Scherer Family</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading has-large-font-size"><strong>Happiness turns to heartache</strong></h2>



<p>The couple raised four children. Their family grew to include 14 grandchildren and six great-grandchildren. They planned for retirement and looked forward to the day when they could travel and enjoy their future together.</p>



<p>But when Craig turned 60, life took a sharp turn. He was diagnosed with&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/copd/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20353685" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</a>.&amp;nbsp;COPD is a progressive disease that causes damage to the lungs, making it hard to breathe. Treatments can help manage the disease, but there's no cure. As the disease continues its silent assault, quality of life often slowly slips away.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"I couldn't do things, and even if I could do things, I didn't have the strength to do it or the stamina because my lungs would wear out," says Craig.</p>



<p>Craig's COPD continued to get worse. Eventually he couldn't breathe, walk or even talk. "It was silent at our house. We didn't talk because he couldn't talk. He didn't have the oxygen," says Nanci. "We lived in silence and isolation."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="613" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-with-breathing-mask-1024x613.jpg" alt="Craig Scherer's lung condition  had frequently landed him in the hospital." class="wp-image-404245" style="width:705px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-with-breathing-mask-1024x613.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-with-breathing-mask-300x180.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-with-breathing-mask-768x460.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-with-breathing-mask.jpg 1067w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Craig's lung condition frequently landed him in the hospital        Photo courtesy: Scherer family</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading has-large-font-size"><strong>Last hope for survival</strong></h2>



<p>Eventually, Craig reached end-stage lung disease. Treatments no longer worked and his health continued to decline. Craig was left with only one last hope for survival, a lung transplant. Craig and Nanci turned to Mayo Clinic in Arizona.</p>



<p>"We see this with patients, when there are no other options, no medical interventions you can do at that point," says&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/d-cunha-jonathan-m-d-ph-d/bio-20471123" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Jonathan&amp;nbsp;D'Cunha</a>, surgical director of the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/lung-transplant/home/orc-20211835?mc_id=us&amp;amp;utm_source=yext&amp;amp;utm_medium=l&amp;amp;utm_content=departmenttransplant&amp;amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;amp;geo=national&amp;amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;amp;invsrc=transplant&amp;amp;cauid=105143&amp;amp;y_source=1_MTA3ODAzNDQwMC03MTUtbG9jYXRpb24ud2Vic2l0ZQ%3D%3D" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo&amp;nbsp;Clinic&amp;nbsp;Lung Transplant Program </a>in Arizona&amp;nbsp;transplant center</p>



<p>For six years, Dr. D'Cunha had been working on building a multidisciplinary team of medical and surgical experts to create a new lung transplant program at Mayo Clinic in Arizona.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/sections/expertise-ranking/orc-20203899" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">transplant center</a>&amp;nbsp;is the largest in the country, performing more adult solid organ transplants than any other center in the U.S. The addition of the lung transplant program establishes Mayo Clinic in Arizona as a comprehensive transplant destination medical center.</p>



<p>The program will provide transplantation for the full range of patients with end-stage lung disease. "This is the beginning of a remarkable new era for lung transplantation in Arizona," says Dr. D'Cunha. "We are excited and honored to offer patients and families renewed hope and a second chance at life through Mayo's unrivaled expertise in comprehensive adult organ transplant care."</p>



<p>Craig became the new program's first patient to receive a lung transplant.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading has-large-font-size"><strong>Giving the gift of life</strong></h2>



<p>On May 30, 2025, Dr. D'Cunha led a team of surgeons in performing Craig's lung transplant. The surgery was a success, and soon after, Craig was slowly starting to breathe with his new lungs.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"It is surreal to be able to breathe and not gasp for air when I talk," says Craig, who was up and walking within days of surgery. "I told the doctors when I got here that I will do whatever it takes. I'm 100% committed. If you want me to walk six times a day, I'll walk seven," says Craig.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-center-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="882" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-beginning-to-walk--882x1024.jpg" alt="Craig Scherer walking two days after his lung transplant" class="wp-image-404246" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-beginning-to-walk--882x1024.jpg 882w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-beginning-to-walk--258x300.jpg 258w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-beginning-to-walk--768x892.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-beginning-to-walk--1323x1536.jpg 1323w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-beginning-to-walk--1764x2048.jpg 1764w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 882px) 100vw, 882px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Craig two days after his lung transplant     Photo courtesy: Scherer family</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>"He did phenomenal," says Dr. D'Cunha. "His optimism and energy he brought with him is absolutely critical because the stronger you are going into these big operations, the better you are on the other side.</p>



<p>"I'm very proud of Craig. He always amazing me throughout the journey of transplant," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/omar-ashraf-m-b-b-ch/bio-20553594" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ashraf Omar, M.B., B.Ch.</a>, medical director of the transplant program. "He is a special person. Motivation is the cornerstone of his success."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading has-large-font-size"><strong>A fighter's farewell</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="610" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/confetti-pom-poms-cheering-discharge-1-1024x610.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-404202" style="width:728px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/confetti-pom-poms-cheering-discharge-1-1024x610.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/confetti-pom-poms-cheering-discharge-1-300x179.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/confetti-pom-poms-cheering-discharge-1-768x457.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/confetti-pom-poms-cheering-discharge-1-1536x915.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/confetti-pom-poms-cheering-discharge-1-2048x1220.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>A joyful farewell from the transplant team as Craig heads home</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Two and a half weeks after his transplant, Craig was heading home. The transplant team bid him farewell with a victory celebration with pom-poms waving and confetti raining down.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fyoutu.be%2FT1A6td-Ci0k&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7CHames.Marty%40mayo.edu%7Cbb19d7b8046c4e8f9d9108ddb4e1ed50%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C638865604618658098%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=f886UYOYKd0oT7m9f2VnORdr20N4%2BIhib0%2FyI1MorkM%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Craig crosses the finish line of his journey with a breathtaking victory celebration from Mayo's transplant team. </a></strong></p>



<p>A few days later, on June 23, Craig returned to Mayo to join his transplant team for a news conference announcing the official launch of the lung transplant program.</p>



<p>It was also Craig's 67th birthday.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote has-medium-font-size"><blockquote><p><strong>"The lungs are my birthday gift, the best birthday gift I could get in the world"</strong></p><cite>Craig Scherer</cite></blockquote></figure>



<p>In honor of his organ donor and the donor family, Craig used his new lungs to blow out the candles on his birthday cake.</p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tCerSoeVehE" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Craig's heartfelt moment in honor of the gift of life</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidtCerSoeVehE"  title="Craig Scherer - Remarks and blowing out his birthday candles" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tCerSoeVehE?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>Craig and Nanci are back at home and looking forward to beginning the next chapter of their story.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"I have a lot of life left to live in me. Everything is a motivator — my wife, my kids, my grandkids, my health," says Craig. "Before, I had no quality of life and couldn't do anything. Now, there's nothing I can't accomplish."&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-and-Nanci-with-pillow-768x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-404244" style="width:624px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-and-Nanci-with-pillow-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-and-Nanci-with-pillow-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-and-Nanci-with-pillow-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-and-Nanci-with-pillow-1536x2048.jpg 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Craig and Nanci holding a lung transplant pillow signed by everyone on the transplant team</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Related stories:</strong></h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-in-arizona-announces-launch-of-new-lung-transplant-program-providing-life-saving-hope-and-restored-function-to-patients-battling-advanced-lung-disease/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Arizona announces launch of new lung transplant program offering hope and restored function to patients facing advanced lung disease</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/lung-transplant/home/orc-20211835" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lung Transplant Program</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/podcast-episode/breathing-easier-with-copd/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Breathing easier with COPD</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-breathing-easy-thanks-to-the-gift-of-life-and-new-mayo-clinic-lung-transplant-program-in-arizona/">(VIDEO) Breathing easy thanks to the gift of life and new Mayo Clinic Lung Transplant Program in Arizona</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-Scherer-smiles.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Craig-and-Nanci-Scherer-16-x-9-.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[COPD]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jonathan D'Cunha]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[lung transplant]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mcthumb >https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Lung-Header-3-150x150.jpg</mayoclinic:mcthumb >	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Dopamine menus: Give your brain some space</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/dopamine-menus-give-your-brain-some-space/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sharon Theimer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 13:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health &amp; Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Robert Wilfahrt]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403961</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. —&amp;#160;You likely are accustomed to encountering a range of menus in daily life, but there is one that may be new to you: a dopamine menu. Dr. Robert Wilfahrt, a family medicine physician at Mayo Clinic and an expert in attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder, or ADHD, explains. “A dopamine menu is a rebranding of what [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/dopamine-menus-give-your-brain-some-space/">Dopamine menus: Give your brain some space</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-feat-image-dopamine-menu-GettyImages-1490275961-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-404071" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-feat-image-dopamine-menu-GettyImages-1490275961-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-feat-image-dopamine-menu-GettyImages-1490275961-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-feat-image-dopamine-menu-GettyImages-1490275961-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-feat-image-dopamine-menu-GettyImages-1490275961-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-feat-image-dopamine-menu-GettyImages-1490275961-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. —&amp;nbsp;You likely are accustomed to encountering a range of menus in daily life, but there is one that may be new to you: a dopamine menu. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/wilfahrt-robert-p-m-d/bio-20208651" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Robert Wilfahrt</a>, a family medicine physician at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> and an expert in <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/adhd/symptoms-causes/syc-20350889" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder</a>, or ADHD, explains.</p>



<p>“A dopamine menu is a rebranding of what psychologists or healthcare professionals previously called behavioral activation — ways to get yourself to do what’s best for you, instead of what you feel like doing in the moment,” Dr. Wilfahrt says.</p>



<p>In this case, the best route to getting that tough task done is to step away from it for a minute, do something else that feeds you energy and then dive back into the task.</p>



<p>The purpose? To stimulate <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/the-art-of-kindness" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dopamine</a> — a hormone and neurotransmitter in the brain involved in mood, attention, reward and motivation. It’s also known as the “feel-good hormone.” Dopamine comes in many forms — reaching for your phone to doomscroll social media is an easy and convenient way to get a bit of a lift, but that’s not the only option. What other accessible activities can bring you joy and a happy brain break?</p>



<p>Examples of healthy “dopamenu” activities include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Going for a brief walk.</li>



<li>Jamming out to your favorite song.</li>



<li>Making a cup of tea.</li>



<li>Petting your dog or cat.</li>



<li>Lighting a candle.</li>



<li>Reaching out to a friend or family member.</li>
</ul>



<p>“The idea is to break up what you’re doing,” says Dr. Wilfahrt. And if the selected menu item is purposeful, you can feel a sense of reward for small progresses.</p>



<p>When are dopamine menus most useful? If we’re not necessarily enthusiastic about the task we’ve been assigned, we struggle to maintain attention or interest. We then risk not meeting the expectation or obligation. We feel bad about it, get flooded with remorse and have an even tougher time completing the task due to that sense of anxiety.</p>



<p>“It can become a vicious cycle,” says Dr. Wilfahrt. “It can be easy to become avoidant when we’re in these sort of doom loops.”</p>



<p>So how can you stop this cycle? Brainstorm. Make a mental or physical list of things you can do to get recentered.</p>



<p>Dr. Wilfahrt says the more recently rebranded concept tends to be targeted to people with ADHD, but anyone would benefit:</p>



<p>“It’s not a bad idea for anybody to know how to best manage energy. Sitting still to labor over one idea isn’t healthy for anyone.”</p>



<p>And while activities on your dopamine menu are meant to be enjoyable, don’t forget to go back to the hard task. A journey to the dopamine menu is meant to provide a burst of enthusiasm, not to be something that sucks you in. Consider setting a timer — perhaps for an unusual interval like 13 minutes and 17 seconds. Enjoy the boost and get back to the (real) to-do list.</p>



<p>For more healthy living tips, visit <a href="https://mcpress.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Press</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">MayoClinic.org</a>.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Sharon Theimer, Mayo Clinic Communications,&amp;nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/dopamine-menus-give-your-brain-some-space/">Dopamine menus: Give your brain some space</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1-image-dopamine-menu-GettyImages-1490275961.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-feat-image-dopamine-menu-GettyImages-1490275961.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Robert Wilfahrt]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Care team&amp;#8217;s persistence saves social worker&amp;#8217;s life</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/care-teams-persistence-saves-social-workers-life/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[briannadipilato]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 12:16:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health &amp; Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cerebral palsy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Cole Cheney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jason Dauffenbach]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403731</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Callie Jones, a social worker for Mayo Clinic Health System (MCHS) in Mankato, Minnesota, spends her days helping patients and their families navigate their healthcare journeys. She takes pride in living by Mayo Clinic's primary value — the needs of the patient come first.&nbsp; In early February, however, Callie's role quickly flipped from social worker [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/care-teams-persistence-saves-social-workers-life/">Care team&amp;#8217;s persistence saves social worker&amp;#8217;s life</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-center-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-hospital-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Callie Jones, a social worker for Mayo Clinic Health System (MCHS) in Mankato, Minnesota, in hospital bed, complications related to her baclofen pump " class="wp-image-403743" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-hospital-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-hospital-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-hospital-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-hospital-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-hospital-16-x-9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Callie Jones experienced complications related to her baclofen pump </figcaption></figure>



<p>Callie Jones, a social worker for <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/mankato" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System (MCHS)</a> in Mankato, Minnesota, spends her days helping patients and their families navigate their healthcare journeys. She takes pride in living by Mayo Clinic's primary value — the needs of the patient come first.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In early February, however, Callie's role quickly flipped from social worker to patient when she began experiencing life-threatening symptoms and complications related to her <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements/baclofen-intrathecal-route/description/drg-20062155#drug-brand-names" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">baclofen</a> pump — the device that helps her to move through life without the spasms or stiffness that often come with having <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cerebral-palsy/symptoms-causes/syc-20353999" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cerebral palsy</a>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Where it all began</strong></h2>



<p>As a child, Callie was diagnosed with spastic cerebral palsy — a neurological condition that can affect movement and posture.</p>



<p>"My muscles were so stiff that it made everyday tasks like diaper changes and eating meals very difficult," Callie says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-4_yrs_Medtronic_Brochure-1-x-1-1024x1024.jpg" alt="Callie Jones, then 4,  was the youngest patient at the time to receive a baclofen pump surgically placed under the skin in front of her abdomen" class="wp-image-403747" style="width:428px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-4_yrs_Medtronic_Brochure-1-x-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-4_yrs_Medtronic_Brochure-1-x-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-4_yrs_Medtronic_Brochure-1-x-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-4_yrs_Medtronic_Brochure-1-x-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-4_yrs_Medtronic_Brochure-1-x-1-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-4_yrs_Medtronic_Brochure-1-x-1.jpg 1846w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Callie Jones at age 4 </figcaption></figure></div>


<p>At just four years old, Callie was the youngest patient at the time to receive a baclofen pump surgically placed under the skin in front of her abdomen. This pump delivers medicine slowly and continuously through a port that connects to a long catheter. The catheter travels around her abdomen and introduces the medicine directly into her spinal canal to help relax her muscles.</p>



<p><a href="https://quarterly.mayo.edu/directory/person/person.htm?per_id=30202779&amp;amp;displaymode=" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Cole Cheney</a>, pain medicine physician at MCHS in Mankato, says that baclofen pumps are normally replaced every six to seven years. In addition, it is often routine to adjust medicine delivery dosages over time as the body's needs change. However, he noted that sometimes, pumps can require troubleshooting.</p>



<p>"If the medication is disrupted, the patient can start feeling sick," Dr. Cheney says. "Receiving too much medicine or too little can be life threatening."</p>



<p>That's why when Callie started to feel strong "itchy and twitchy" symptoms earlier this year, she knew it was serious and quickly sought medical attention in Mankato.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>From social worker to patient</strong></h2>



<p>Following rounds of tests and scans, the Pain Medicine team found that Callie was experiencing severe baclofen withdrawal, thought to be due to a kink in her catheter. The complication can be fatal without quick intervention.</p>



<p>The team quickly performed surgery on Feb. 10 to fix the kink, but Callie's relief was short-lived. Her symptoms continued on and off for the next six weeks. All the while, her care team meticulously tested, explored and exhausted all causes and options to help find the root cause of Callie's symptoms. Her care required extensive involvement from patient access staff, nursing staff, radiation technologists and other healthcare professionals from the Emergency Department, Pain Medicine, Radiology, the Intensive Care Unit, Anesthesiology and Hospitalist teams.</p>



<p>"Callie's pump consistently showed normal medication values, which initially suggested that the pump was functioning correctly," Dr. Cheney says. "For that reason, we avoided intervening at the pump site for as long as we could. It was only after we had ruled out every other potential cause of her symptoms that we determined a pump replacement was the necessary next step."</p>



<p>This would be Callie's most invasive surgery yet, and was particularly high stakes, as Callie has spinal rods that increased the risk of her team failing to re-gain spinal canal access for the device if they lost that during surgery.&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="840" height="840" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-chair-1-x-1.jpg" alt="Callie Jones, a social worker for Mayo Clinic Health System (MCHS) in Mankato, Minnesota, in wheelchair" class="wp-image-403745" style="width:438px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-chair-1-x-1.jpg 840w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-chair-1-x-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-chair-1-x-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-chair-1-x-1-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 840px) 100vw, 840px" /></figure></div>


<p>However, it was a risk that proved worth taking. Six clinic&amp;nbsp;visits,&amp;nbsp;four&amp;nbsp;hospital admissions and three surgeries later, Callie was back to feeling like her old self — and grateful she turned to her workplace back in February when she first sensed something was wrong.</p>



<p>"If it wasn't for the quick actions taken by the Pain Medicine team and the ability for me to access care locally, my situation truly could have had a very different outcome," Callie says.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A story of teamwork, persistence and partnership</strong></h2>



<p><a href="https://quarterly.mayo.edu/directory/person/person.htm?per_id=15218244&amp;amp;displaymode=" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Jason Dauffenbach</a>, MCHS Minnesota Pain Medicine chair, says Callie's successful outcome was the result of a true team effort.</p>



<p>"We utilized the close relationships between our practice in Mankato and the expertise and experience of colleagues across the health system and in Rochester," said Dr. Dauffenbach.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>While the malfunctioning of her device led to a traumatic and emotional time, Callie says she leaned on the positives in her situation — being close to home, near family and colleagues that treated her like family.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"My coworkers would visit me before or after work — they&amp;nbsp;decorated&amp;nbsp;my&amp;nbsp;hospital&amp;nbsp;room for my birthday and they even brought my favorite drink to brighten my day," Callie says.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Now, after more than 10 years of caring for others, Callie has an even deeper appreciation for and understanding of what it means to live by Mayo's RICH TIES values of respect, integrity, compassion, healing, teamwork, innovation, excellence and stewardship.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"With the team's expertise and efforts, I was able to remain in my home community and receive the care and intervention needed from a team that knew me and my medical complexities best," she says. "I had an amazing team."</p>



<p><strong>Related story</strong>:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/dad-walks-daughter-down-the-aisle-despite-als/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dad walks daughter down the aisle despite ALS</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/care-teams-persistence-saves-social-workers-life/">Care team&amp;#8217;s persistence saves social worker&amp;#8217;s life</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-chair-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Callie-Jones-hospital-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cerebral palsy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Cole Cheney]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jason Dauffenbach]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;#038;A: 8 common myths about back pain</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-8-common-myths-about-back-pain/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pattymiller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health &amp; Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Meghan Murphy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403643</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&amp;#160;My back's been bothering me, and everyone seems to have ideas what's causing the pain. Can you help? ANSWER:&amp;#160;Back pain is more common than homeownership in the U.S. While about 65% of adults own a home, nearly 80% of adults will have back pain at some point. Despite how common this type of [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-8-common-myths-about-back-pain/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;amp;A: 8 common myths about back pain</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="432" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/07/a-young-white-man-sitting-on-a-couch-rubbing-his-lower-back-because-it-hurts-perhaps-in-kidney-pain-16x9-1.jpg" alt="a young white man sitting on a couch rubbing his lower back because it hurts, perhaps in kidney pain, sore back, bain pain" class="wp-image-312772" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/07/a-young-white-man-sitting-on-a-couch-rubbing-his-lower-back-because-it-hurts-perhaps-in-kidney-pain-16x9-1.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/07/a-young-white-man-sitting-on-a-couch-rubbing-his-lower-back-because-it-hurts-perhaps-in-kidney-pain-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /></figure></div>


<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&amp;nbsp;</strong>My back's been bothering me, and everyone seems to have ideas what's causing the pain. Can you help?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:&amp;nbsp;</strong>Back pain is more common than homeownership in the U.S. While about 65% of adults own a home, nearly 80% of adults will have back pain at some point. Despite how common this type of pain is, myths about it persist.&amp;nbsp;Here are some facts: &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Myth: Lifting heavy objects is the main cause of back pain.</strong>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Fact: Lifting heavy objects with poor form can contribute to back pain, but the major culprits are a sedentary lifestyle, poor posture, obesity and genetic factors.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Myth: Bed rest will make my back pain better.</strong>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Fact: Probably not, but it depends on the cause of your pain. If it's muscle strain, taking it easy for a few days may help. However, bed rest can also make back pain last longer or even worsen. If your pain is from nerve compression, a disc issue or joint degeneration, inactivity can cause muscles to tighten, pain to worsen, loss of physical condition and more debility.&amp;nbsp;In these cases, you should modify your activities, switch to low-impact exercises like walking and swimming, and avoid movements like bending, twisting or lifting.&amp;nbsp;Maintaining some degree of physical activity can help you heal faster.</p>



<p><strong>Myth: Back pain is caused by sitting on a fat wallet.&amp;nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>Fact: Sitting with a large wallet in your back pocket can cause leg or hip pain and numbness, but typically not back pain. A large wallet can tilt your pelvis and compress your sciatic nerve. This nerve is the largest in your body, branching from the lower back through your hips, buttocks and down each leg. Compressing it causes pain or numbness while sitting or driving. After sitting for a long time, you may find walking difficult or feel pins and needles in your legs.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>First, try removing the wallet and taking over-the-counter anti-inflammatory medications. If the leg pain persists, check with a healthcare professional.</p>



<p><strong>Myth: Back pain is always due to a serious underlying condition.&amp;nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>Fact: Back pain is usually caused by muscle strains or sprains, not by a serious condition like a disc or vertebrae issue. Most back pain resolves on its own,</p>



<p><strong>Myth: Avoid exercise when experiencing back pain.</strong>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Fact: Exercise and physical activity are usually recommended for managing and preventing back pain. Strengthening the core muscles, including your back muscles, improving flexibility, and maintaining a healthy weight can contribute to a healthier back. Depending on your pain, you may need to modify your activity. You know your body best, so listen to it. If something isn't getting better or grows progressively worse, contact a healthcare professional for an evaluation.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Myth: Surgery is the only solution for chronic back pain.</strong>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Fact: Back pain is often caused by issues that aren't relieved with surgery. Non-surgical treatments like physical therapy, medications, injections and lifestyle modifications are often effective in managing and reducing chronic back pain. Surgery may be necessary if your pain:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Intensifies, especially at night or when you lie down.&amp;nbsp;</li>



<li>Spreads down one or both legs.&amp;nbsp;</li>



<li>Causes weakness, numbness or tingling in one or both legs.&amp;nbsp;</li>



<li>Occurs with new bowel or bladder control problems.</li>
</ul>



<p>Seek an immediate medical evaluation if you experience any of these symptoms.</p>



<p><strong>Myth: A firm mattress is the best for alleviating back pain.</strong>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Fact: The ideal mattress firmness varies from person to person. Some people may find relief with a firm mattress, while others may prefer a medium or soft one. When shopping for a new mattress, look for one that provides support and comfort based on your preferences and needs. Also, many companies offer generous return policies so you can try a mattress for a few weeks, or even a few months, before deciding if it's right for you.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Myth: Poor posture doesn't contribute to back pain.</strong>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Fact: Many people spend hours slouching while staring at a computer rather than sitting at attention, or focusing on cellphones that draw the eyes down and curve the neck. These habits can strain muscles and joints, causing body pain over time. Practice good posture habits and take advantage of ergonomic office equipment to help prevent and alleviate back pain.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Preventing back pain</strong>&amp;nbsp;</h2>



<p>Some back issues can't be avoided, like those caused by injuries, arthritis or genetics. Three things you can do to preserve the health of your back are: &amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Maintain an ideal body weight.</strong><br>Excess weight causes increased stress on all joints, including the spine.&amp;nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>Strengthen your core.</strong><br>Stronger core muscles, including abdominal and intrinsic back muscles, can help take the stress off your spine.&amp;nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>Stay active.</strong><br>Regular movement is essential for keeping your body active.&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/meghan-murphy-np" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Meghan E. Murphy, M.D.</em></a><em>, Neurosurgery, Mayo Clinic Health System, Mankato, Minnesota</em></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-8-common-myths-about-back-pain/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;amp;A: 8 common myths about back pain</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/07/a-young-white-man-sitting-on-a-couch-rubbing-his-lower-back-because-it-hurts-perhaps-in-kidney-pain-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/07/a-young-white-man-sitting-on-a-couch-rubbing-his-lower-back-because-it-hurts-perhaps-in-kidney-pain-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Meghan Murphy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: What are your options for managing BPH?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-what-your-options-for-managing-bph/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pattymiller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 12:42:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health &amp; Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q &amp; A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[BPH]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Ross Avant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[prostate]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=399977</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&amp;#160;Recently, I was diagnosed with BPH. This is all new to me, and I hope you can help me better understand the condition and how it's treated.&amp;#160; ANSWER:&amp;#160;Now that you've been diagnosed with benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) — noncancerous tissue growth within the prostate — it's time for you and your healthcare team [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-what-your-options-for-managing-bph/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: What are your options for managing BPH?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="682" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Older-male-alone-16-x9-1024x682.jpg" alt="Older male, alone, isolated, looking outward" class="wp-image-384511" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Older-male-alone-16-x9-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Older-male-alone-16-x9-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Older-male-alone-16-x9-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Older-male-alone-16-x9-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Older-male-alone-16-x9.jpg 1688w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&amp;nbsp;</strong>Recently, I was diagnosed with <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-does-it-mean-to-have-an-enlarged-prostate/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">BPH</a>. This is all new to me, and I hope you can help me better understand the condition and how it's treated.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:&amp;nbsp;</strong>Now that you've been diagnosed with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/benign-prostatic-hyperplasia/symptoms-causes/syc-20370087?mc_id=us&amp;amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;amp;utm_medium=l&amp;amp;utm_content=content&amp;amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;amp;geo=national&amp;amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH)</a> — noncancerous tissue growth within the prostate — it's time for you and your healthcare team to talk about treatment options.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>These options depend on the severity of your symptoms, which can range from having a weak urine stream to not being able to urinate at all. Most treatments are done in the outpatient setting, including your clinician's office, while others may require a hospital stay. Wherever you are on the range of symptoms, there are treatment options that can relieve them, including:&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/a-medical-illustration-of-a-normal-prostate-and-one-with-benign-prostatic-hyperplasia-BPH-16X9.jpg" alt="a medical illustration of a normal prostate and one with benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH)" class="wp-image-221033" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/a-medical-illustration-of-a-normal-prostate-and-one-with-benign-prostatic-hyperplasia-BPH-16X9.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/a-medical-illustration-of-a-normal-prostate-and-one-with-benign-prostatic-hyperplasia-BPH-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">A medical illustration of a normal prostate and one with benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH)</figcaption></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Behavior modifications</strong></h2>



<p>If you're experiencing bothersome, but not severe, symptoms, such as having a weak urine stream or frequently getting up at night to urinate, your treatment may start with:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Changes to your diet</strong><br>Some foods, such as chocolate, citrus, carbonated beverages and caffeine, can irritate your bladder, which can increase your urge to urinate. Cutting back on these foods may ease your symptoms.</li>



<li><strong>Fluid intake</strong><br>Reducing the amount of fluid you drink before bedtime can decrease your need to urinate during the night.</li>



<li><strong>Timed urination (voiding)</strong><br>Holding your urine can also irritate your bladder, so making a point to urinate every hour and a half to two hours can reduce the urge to go "now."</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Medications for BPH</strong></h2>



<p>If these behavior modifications are no longer effective, your clinician may prescribe a medication, which you'll need to take every day. These include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Alpha blockers</strong><br>These drugs relax muscles in the bladder and prostate, and they open up the urinary channel to reduce blockage. Side effects include a decrease in blood pressure, dizziness and lightheadedness. They also can cause semen to go back into the bladder instead of the penis, which may be startling, but is harmless.</li>



<li><strong>5-alpha reductase inhibitors</strong><br>These medications work to shrink the prostate by lowering the production of a specific hormone. There are more side effects, and it may take six to nine months to see any results. Men may have a lower sex drive, and some will experience erectile dysfunction.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Surgical procedures</strong></h2>



<p>You and your healthcare team may decide that in-office therapies or surgery to shrink or remove overgrown prostate tissue would be the best treatment option for you. Some treatments work better than others, depending on your symptoms, treatment goals and the size of your prostate. Most preserve sexual function and have little or no effect on erectile or ejaculatory function.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>These treatments include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Temporarily implanted nitinol device</strong><br>This procedure reshapes the tissue of the prostatic urethra and the bladder neck to create a wider channel through which urine can flow. A narrow, folded nickel titanium device is inserted into the prostatic urethra. As the device expands, gentle pressure reshapes the urethra and bladder opening. After five to seven days, the device is removed.</li>



<li><strong>Prostatic urethral lift (PUL)</strong><br>This procedure reshapes the prostate using a small, permanent implant to compress and lift the side of the enlarged prostate to increase the urethra opening.</li>



<li><strong>Steam therapy</strong><br>During the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-steam-treatment-for-enlarged-prostate/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">treatment</a>, a tiny needle is inserted into the urethra and positioned in the prostate gland. In nine seconds, the needle produces a 2-centimeter-wide steam ball that shrinks the surrounding prostate tissue.</li>



<li><strong>Transurethral resection of the prostate (TURP) and photo-selective vaporization (PVP)</strong><br>During a TURP, a lighted scope is inserted into the urethra and the surgeon uses an electric loop to remove all but the outer part of the prostate. TURP generally relieves symptoms quickly, and most men have a stronger urine flow soon after the procedure.&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>PVP is laser therapy performed in an operating room under anesthesia. A surgeon inserts a thin, tube-like instrument into the urethra. This instrument has a lens, light and tool that sends out an electrical current to destroy prostate tissue. Heat from the current seals small blood vessels, reducing the risk of bleeding. This procedure destroys or removes overgrown prostate tissue and is a good choice if you need to stay on blood thinners.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Prostate enucleation (<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/treatment-for-enlarged-prostate" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">BipoLEP</a>&amp;nbsp;or&amp;nbsp;</strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/laser-based-prostate-procedure-treats-bph" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>HoLEP</strong></a><strong>)</strong><br>This procedure removes nearly the entire prostate without an incision. It is often a good option for patients with especially large prostates, the inability to stop blood thinners or in significant urinary retention. A thin instrument is inserted into the urethra. Then, a laser cuts the prostate tissue into small, removable pieces.&amp;nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>Simple prostatectomy</strong><br>This minimally invasive surgery removes tissue blocking the flow of urine. It usually requires a one-night stay in the hospital and is done laparoscopically through a small incision in your side, most often using a surgical robot.</li>
</ul>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/ross-avant-md"><em>Ross Avant, M.D.</em></a><em>, Urology, Mayo Clinic Health System, Austin and Red Wing, Minnesota; Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota</em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-what-your-options-for-managing-bph/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: What are your options for managing BPH?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Older-male-alone-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Older-male-alone-16-x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[BPH]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Ross Avant]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[prostate]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>(VIDEO) Superhero window washers brighten day at Mayo Clinic Children&amp;#8217;s</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-superhero-window-washers-brighten-day-at-mayo-clinic-childrens/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kristy Jacobson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 19:40:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Children's Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health &amp; Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Children's]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403406</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Superheroes took a short break from fighting crime (and grime) to bring joy and smiles to young patients at&amp;#160;Mayo Clinic Children's. The team of window washers from the Squeegee Squad in Rochester, Minnesota, dressed up as Batman, Superman and Spider-Man while demonstrating their superpower rappelling skills for children and their families. Afterward, kids had a [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-superhero-window-washers-brighten-day-at-mayo-clinic-childrens/">(VIDEO) Superhero window washers brighten day at Mayo Clinic Children&amp;#8217;s</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Children-watch-superhero-window-washers-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-403453" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Children-watch-superhero-window-washers-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Children-watch-superhero-window-washers-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Children-watch-superhero-window-washers-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Children-watch-superhero-window-washers-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Children-watch-superhero-window-washers-16-x-9.jpg 1824w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p>Superheroes took a short break from fighting crime (and grime) to bring joy and smiles to young patients at&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/childrens-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Children's</a>. The team of window washers from the Squeegee Squad in Rochester, Minnesota, dressed up as Batman, Superman and Spider-Man while demonstrating their superpower rappelling skills for children and their families. Afterward, kids had a chance to meet the team of superhero window washers and take photos with their favorite superhero.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/9fATXXXx8-I" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Superhero window washers brighten day at Mayo Clinic Children's</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutube9fATXXXx8I"  title="Superhero window washers brighten day at Mayo Clinic Children&amp;#039;s" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/9fATXXXx8-I?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network."</strong></p>



<p>Check out these images:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" data-id="403427" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Window-washer-superhero-fotor-20250605134933-1024x1024.jpg" alt="Superhero window washers visit Mayo Clinic Children's" class="wp-image-403427" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Window-washer-superhero-fotor-20250605134933-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Window-washer-superhero-fotor-20250605134933-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Window-washer-superhero-fotor-20250605134933-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Window-washer-superhero-fotor-20250605134933-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Window-washer-superhero-fotor-20250605134933-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Window-washer-superhero-fotor-20250605134933.jpg 2031w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="403438" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Superhero-window-washers-pose-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-403438" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Superhero-window-washers-pose-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Superhero-window-washers-pose-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Superhero-window-washers-pose-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Superhero-window-washers-pose-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Superhero-window-washers-pose-16-x-9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="403430" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Superhero-indow-washers-exterior-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-403430" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Superhero-indow-washers-exterior-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Superhero-indow-washers-exterior-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Superhero-indow-washers-exterior-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Superhero-indow-washers-exterior-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Superhero-indow-washers-exterior-16-x-9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" data-id="403425" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/little-spidey-big-spidey-superheroes-1024x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-403425" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/little-spidey-big-spidey-superheroes-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/little-spidey-big-spidey-superheroes-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/little-spidey-big-spidey-superheroes-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/little-spidey-big-spidey-superheroes-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/little-spidey-big-spidey-superheroes-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/little-spidey-big-spidey-superheroes-2048x2048.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>
</figure>



<p></p>



<p>For Cory and his family, it is a gift to be able to give back in a meaningful way and bring joy to young patients currently fighting their own health battles.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>This is a full circle moment for Cory Simonson, who now owns and manages the Squeegee Squad in Rochester, and his son, Carter Simonson.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="860" height="484" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Carter-Simonson-in-2014-16-x-9.jpg" alt="Carter Simonson in 2014 visited by superheroes while a patient at Mayo Clinic Children's" class="wp-image-403417" style="width:596px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Carter-Simonson-in-2014-16-x-9.jpg 860w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Carter-Simonson-in-2014-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Carter-Simonson-in-2014-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 860px) 100vw, 860px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Carter Simonson in 2014 visited by superheroes while a patient at Mayo Clinic Children's</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>At the age of 5, Carter was diagnosed with <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/3-facts-about-acute-lymphocytic-leukemia-in-children/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">T-cell leukemia</a> and was treated Mayo Clinic Children's. Carter is now 17 years old and remembers the 2014 visit from superheroes when he was hospitalized.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-superhero-window-washers-brighten-day-at-mayo-clinic-childrens/">(VIDEO) Superhero window washers brighten day at Mayo Clinic Children&amp;#8217;s</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Kids-watch-superheroes-wash-windows-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Children-watch-superhero-window-washers-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Children's]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss> 