<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Research - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 22:28:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers identify a new stem cell patch to gently heal damaged hearts</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-a-new-stem-cell-patch-to-gently-heal-damaged-hearts/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[mbroadfoot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 16:17:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Wugiang Zhu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stem Cells]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407550</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>PHOENIX&nbsp;—&nbsp;Mayo Clinic&nbsp;researchers have developed a pioneering method to mend damaged hearts without open-heart surgery, an advance that could one day transform the treatment of heart failure.&nbsp; The new approach uses lab-grown heart tissue made from reprogrammed adult stem cells, delivered through a tiny incision rather than a surgically opened chest cavity. In preclinical testing, the [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-a-new-stem-cell-patch-to-gently-heal-damaged-hearts/">Mayo Clinic researchers identify a new stem cell patch to gently heal damaged hearts</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-center-align-caption"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Stem-cell-pipette-GettyImages-1150965935-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="A researcher uses a pipette to place stem cells into a multiwell plate, with an image of the cells shown beneath." class="wp-image-407637" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Stem-cell-pipette-GettyImages-1150965935-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Stem-cell-pipette-GettyImages-1150965935-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Stem-cell-pipette-GettyImages-1150965935-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Stem-cell-pipette-GettyImages-1150965935-16-x-9.jpg 1425w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">A researcher uses a pipette to place stem cells into a multiwell plate, with an image of the cells shown beneath.</figcaption></figure>



<p>PHOENIX&nbsp;—&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;researchers have developed a pioneering method to mend damaged hearts without open-heart surgery, an advance that could one day transform the treatment of heart failure.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The new approach uses lab-grown heart tissue made from reprogrammed adult stem cells, delivered through a tiny incision rather than a surgically opened chest cavity. In preclinical testing, the stem cell patch restored heart function and improved healing.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="855" height="855" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Zhu-Wuqiang_21415234_202406271049-1-x-1.jpg" alt="Wuqiang Zhu, Ph.D." class="wp-image-407638" style="width:154px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Zhu-Wuqiang_21415234_202406271049-1-x-1.jpg 855w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Zhu-Wuqiang_21415234_202406271049-1-x-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Zhu-Wuqiang_21415234_202406271049-1-x-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Zhu-Wuqiang_21415234_202406271049-1-x-1-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 855px) 100vw, 855px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Wuqiang Zhu, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"For patients with severe heart failure, there are very few options beyond mechanical pumps or transplants. We hope this approach will offer a new way to repair their own hearts," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/zhu-wuqiang-m-d-ph-d/bio-20465805" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Wuqiang Zhu, Ph.D.</a>, senior author of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S174270612500649X?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;published in Acta Biomaterialia and a cardiovascular researcher at&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/arizona" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Arizona</a>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Reversing the irreversible</strong></h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-attack/symptoms-causes/syc-20373106" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Heart attacks</a> remain one of the leading causes of death worldwide. When blood flow to the heart is blocked, oxygen-starved cells die and are replaced by scar tissue that cannot contract or conduct electrical signals — weakening the heart’s ability to pump blood.</p>



<p>"The adult human heart doesn't regenerate once those cells are lost," Dr. Zhu explains. "That's why heart failure, especially chronic heart failure due to the loss of functional cardiac muscle, is often difficult to treat; the muscle simply can't repair itself."</p>



<p>For years, scientists have been working on ways to replace damaged tissue with healthy heart cells derived from stem cells. Early efforts showed promise, but most required open-heart surgery<a>&amp;nbsp;—&amp;nbsp;</a>a procedure too risky for many patients already struggling with severe&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-failure/symptoms-causes/syc-20373142" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart failure</a>.</p>



<p>Scientists have long hoped that stem cells could provide a way to rebuild what the body cannot. By reprogramming ordinary adult cells such as skin or blood cells into induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs), researchers can coax them into becoming replacement heart cells.</p>



<p>But safely and effectively delivering engineered heart tissues made from these cells has remained a major challenge.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Innovation at heart</strong></h2>



<p>In collaboration with engineers at the University of Nebraska Medical Center, Mayo researchers developed a flexible, paper-thin patch made of nano- and microfibers coated with gelatin. This hybrid scaffold supports a blend of human heart muscle cells, blood vessel cells and fibroblasts—cells that form the tissue’s structural framework—to create a living, beating piece of heart tissue. Before transplantation, the tissue is infused with bioactive factors such as fibroblast growth factor 1 and CHIR99021 that encourage the growth of new blood vessels and help the cells survive once they are in place.</p>



<p>"The beauty of this design," says Dr. Zhu, "is that it can be folded like a piece of paper, loaded into a slender tube, and delivered precisely where it's needed through a small incision in the chest. Once in place, it unfolds and adheres naturally to the heart's surface."</p>



<p>Instead of using stitches, the team used a biocompatible surgical adhesive that holds the patch in place while minimizing additional trauma to the surrounding tissue.</p>



<p>Testing in preclinical models showed that the minimally invasive method improved heart function, reduced scarring, enhanced vascular growth and lessened inflammation compared with conventional approaches.</p>



<p>"Our results show that these engineered tissues not only survive but actually help the heart heal itself," says Dr. Zhu. "That's the ultimate goal: to replace what's lost and restore function."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A step toward regeneration</strong></h2>



<p>The research aligns closely with Mayo Clinic's Genesis Initiative, which aims to accelerate discoveries that restore or regenerate human organs and tissues.</p>



<p>"Genesis is about pioneering new ways to repair and rebuild the human body," Dr. Zhu says. "What we're doing here is exactly that — using regenerative science and minimally invasive delivery to give the heart a chance to recover."</p>



<p>Currently, more than 4,000 <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/heart-transplant/about/pac-20384750" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart transplants</a> are performed in the United States each year, while thousands more patients die waiting for a donor organ. Dr. Zhu hopes this technology could eventually offer another option.</p>



<p>"Our vision," he says, "is that patients could one day receive engineered heart tissue made from their own reprogrammed cells, delivered through a minimally invasive procedure — no donor organ, no long recovery, just a repaired heart."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Next steps</strong></h2>



<p>The Mayo Clinic team plans to advance this work through larger-scale preclinical testing to ensure the therapy's safety and effectiveness before moving to human clinical trials, a process that Dr. Zhu estimates could take five years or more.</p>



<p>"Heart failure remains a devastating condition," he says. "If we can make stem cell treatment accessible to more patients, especially those too fragile for open-heart surgery, we could save lives."</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-a-new-stem-cell-patch-to-gently-heal-damaged-hearts/">Mayo Clinic researchers identify a new stem cell patch to gently heal damaged hearts</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Stem-cell-pipette-GettyImages-1150965935-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Stem-cell-pipette-GettyImages-1150965935-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Wugiang Zhu]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Stem Cells]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>How Mayo Clinic experts are using AI to better detect sleep apnea, especially in women</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-mayo-clinic-experts-are-using-ai-to-better-detect-sleep-apnea-especially-in-women/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Vincent Jacobbi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AI and Digital Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health &amp; Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rochester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI ECG]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Virend Somers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sleep apnea]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407501</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic researchers have developed an artificial intelligence (AI) algorithm that can identify obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) using the results from an electrocardiogram (ECG) – a common heart test. The innovation could make it faster, cheaper, and easier to spot sleep apnea, particularly in women, who are often underdiagnosed. A common but [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-mayo-clinic-experts-are-using-ai-to-better-detect-sleep-apnea-especially-in-women/">How Mayo Clinic experts are using AI to better detect sleep apnea, especially in women</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" width="800" height="533" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/shutterstock_283528316.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-407502" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/shutterstock_283528316.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/shutterstock_283528316-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/shutterstock_283528316-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure></div>


<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> researchers have developed an artificial intelligence (AI) algorithm that can identify <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/obstructive-sleep-apnea/symptoms-causes/syc-20352090" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">obstructive sleep apnea (OSA)</a> using the results from an electrocardiogram (ECG) – a common heart test. The innovation could make it faster, cheaper, and easier to spot sleep apnea, particularly in women, who are often underdiagnosed.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A common but underrecognized condition</strong></h2>



<p>OSA affects more than 936 million adults ages 30-69 worldwide and poses significant cardiovascular risks. People with <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-happens-to-your-body-when-you-have-obstructive-sleep-apnea/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">OSA</a> experience repeated episodes of upper airway collapse or blockage during sleep. This collapse causes breathing to stop or become shallow repeatedly, which often leads to loud snoring and gasping. Despite its prevalence, it often goes undiagnosed.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/09/sleep-apnea-16x9-1.jpg" alt="Medical illustration of sleep apnea" class="wp-image-249304" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/09/sleep-apnea-16x9-1.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/09/sleep-apnea-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></figure></div>


<p></p>



<p>"Obstructive sleep apnea or OSA is a highly prevalent disease with important cardiovascular consequences," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/somers-virend-m-d-ph-d/bio-00027756" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Virend Somers, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, Alice Sheets Marriott Professor of Cardiovascular Medicine and senior author of the <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/40961733/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> published in JACC: Advances. "OSA affects the heart to the point where AI algorithms can detect the OSA signature from the ECG, which in essence is a representation of the electrical activity of the heart muscle cells," Dr. Somers adds.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>AI model shows strong performance — especially for women</strong></h2>



<p>In the study, the researchers used AI algorithms to review the 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) test results of 11,299 patients at Mayo Clinic who had undergone the test along with sleep evaluations. More than 7,000 of them had a known diagnosis of OSA, and 4,000 were controls.</p>



<p>"The most surprising finding was the increased visibility on the ECG of OSA in the females compared to the males, even though the OSA severity was less in the females," says Dr. Somers.</p>



<p>"This is relevant since emerging data consistently suggest that females have a greater relative likelihood of suffering the cardiovascular consequences of OSA, even if their OSA may be considered 'milder' by standard diagnostic criteria," he adds.</p>



<p>The test also strongly suggests women may suffer more damage to their heart muscle cells from OSA, Dr. Somers says.</p>



<p>Dr. Somers underscores that this approach may have the potential to evaluate whether a given OSA treatment may be able to reduce a patient's cardiovascular risk.</p>



<p>Review the <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/40961733/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong> </p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-mayo-clinic-experts-are-using-ai-to-better-detect-sleep-apnea-especially-in-women/">How Mayo Clinic experts are using AI to better detect sleep apnea, especially in women</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Woman-sleeping-GettyImages-2226499363-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/shutterstock_283528316.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[AI ECG]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Virend Somers]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[sleep apnea]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers find enhancing the body&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8216;first responder&amp;#8217; cells may boost immune therapy for cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-find-enhancing-the-bodys-first-responder-cells-may-boost-immune-therapy-for-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kate Ledger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 17:14:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Haidong Dong]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jessica Lancaster]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407363</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic researchers have identified a specific immune cell that can be targeted to give a boost to standard immunotherapies for cancer. Two research teams, working collaboratively but using distinct approaches, found that "first-responder" immune cells known as myeloid cells can be manipulated to enhance the activity of tumor-killing T cells. The [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-find-enhancing-the-bodys-first-responder-cells-may-boost-immune-therapy-for-cancer/">Mayo Clinic researchers find enhancing the body&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8216;first responder&amp;#8217; cells may boost immune therapy for cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image is-style-left-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="562" height="316" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/TcellsANDmacrophages-16-x-9.jpg" alt="A live cell microscopy image of a tumor’s environment shows the interaction of tumor-killing T-cells (magenta) and macrophages (green round cells). They are surrounded by stiff tumor tissue (green fibers) and non-fluorescent tumor cells (black areas). Image captured by Tina Kwok." class="wp-image-407397" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/TcellsANDmacrophages-16-x-9.jpg 562w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/TcellsANDmacrophages-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 562px) 100vw, 562px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Live cell microscopy image of a tumor’s environment shows the interaction of tumor-killing T-cells (magenta) and macrophages (green round cells),  surrounded by stiff tumor tissue (green fibers) and non-fluorescent tumor cells (black areas). Image captured: Tina Kwok.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> researchers have identified a specific immune cell that can be targeted to give a boost to standard immunotherapies for cancer. Two research teams, working collaboratively but using distinct approaches, found that "first-responder" immune cells known as myeloid cells can be manipulated to enhance the activity of tumor-killing T cells.</p>



<p>The finding suggests that enhanced myeloid cells may boost certain immune checkpoint therapies, which are the standard of care for some cancers but may not have lasting effects. A clinical trial is now being developed at Mayo Clinic to test the enhanced cells in patients.</p>



<p></p>



<p>In a study in <a href="https://jitc.bmj.com/content/13/10/e012164" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Journal for ImmunoTherapy of Cancer</a>, Mayo Clinic researchers detailed how they found a way to boost cancer-killing T cells. The goal was to improve treatments that interfere with immunosuppressive proteins, PD-1 and PD-L1, which together suppress T cells' ability to fight cancer. Even though PD-L1 immunotherapies aim to block PD-L1, the researchers found that the molecule can persist through a natural recycling process that puts it back in play.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dong-Haidong_12985848_20220816-240x300.jpg" alt="Portrait of Dr. Haidong Dong" class="wp-image-407368" style="width:204px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dong-Haidong_12985848_20220816-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dong-Haidong_12985848_20220816.jpg 640w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Haidong Dong, M.D., Ph.D</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Our study found the importance of the recycling process, and we present a way to address it," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/dong-haidong-m-d-ph-d/bio-00027557" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Haidong Dong, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, a cancer immunology researcher at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center/cancer-care" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> and principal investigator of the study.</p>



<p>The research team developed an antibody, H1A, which they found can reduce PD-L1 in human myeloid cells and keep it from recycling. The protein PD-L1 is present in abundance on the surface of myeloid cells. When the protein was prevented from recycling on myeloid cells, the cells then boosted the action of cancer-killing T cells.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Hsu-Michelle-A._30026716_202509162045-240x300.jpg" alt="Portrait of Michelle Hsu" class="wp-image-407367" style="width:200px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Hsu-Michelle-A._30026716_202509162045-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Hsu-Michelle-A._30026716_202509162045.jpg 640w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Michelle Hsu</figcaption></figure></div>


<p></p>



<p>"We now have a tool that can completely remove PD-L1 and in doing so we have more myeloid cell activation," says lead author of the study, Michelle Hsu, who conducted the research as her graduate thesis at <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a>. "Identifying the myeloid cell was an unexpected discovery," she says. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Lancaster-Jessica-N._21667098_202502181545-240x300.jpg" alt="Portrait of Dr. Jessica Lancaster" class="wp-image-407369" style="width:186px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Lancaster-Jessica-N._21667098_202502181545-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Lancaster-Jessica-N._21667098_202502181545.jpg 640w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Jessica Lancaster, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Another Mayo Clinic team took a different approach and arrived at a similar conclusion about the importance of myeloid cells. A research team led by immunology researcher <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/lancaster-jessica-n-ph-d/bio-20482482" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jessica Lancaster, Ph.D.</a>, at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/arizona" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Arizona</a>, reported in <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2589004225017997" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">iScience</a> that macrophages, a type of myeloid cell, play a role in activating the cancer-killing T cells.</p>



<p></p>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-CcIVENx1zI"><br>Watch animation</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidCcIVENx1zI"  title="Tcell and macrophage" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-CcIVENx1zI?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><em><strong>Animation available in the downloads:</strong>  Live cell microscopy shows a cancer-killing T cell (magenta) as it migrates and interacts with macrophages (blue) in the tumor microenvironment. Black spaces are packed with non-fluorescent tumor cells. Image captured by Tina Kwok, Mayo Clinic.</em><br></p>



<p>Using the complex approach of live-cell microscopy, the team found that in mice, T cells interact closely with the macrophages and create a molecular environment that has greater capacity to kill a tumor.</p>



<p>"This is a paradigm shift for PD-L1 immunotherapy, which has traditionally focused on the interaction of the tumor and the T cells," says Dr. Lancaster. "We found that it’s important to co-opt the macrophage, which acts as another immune cell partner."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Kwok-Tina_30026717_202506271753-240x300.jpg" alt="Portrait of Tina Kwok" class="wp-image-407366" style="width:179px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Kwok-Tina_30026717_202506271753-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Kwok-Tina_30026717_202506271753.jpg 640w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Tina Kwok</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><br>Further, says lead author Tina Kwok, who completed the studies during her Ph.D. research at Mayo Clinic, "We can directly reprogram tumor macrophages to be more pro-inflammatory. They can become better T-cell activators and drive better tumor control. Reprogramming of the macrophage may be key to being able to prevent therapy resistance and change outcomes for patients."</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p>Based on the findings from both labs, a phase 1 clinical trial of H1A is being planned. The research could ultimately better address resistance to immunotherapy and expand treatment options for people with cancer.</p>



<p>Review the studies in <a href="https://jitc.bmj.com/content/13/10/e012164" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Journal for ImmunoTherapy of Cancer</a> and <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2589004225017997" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">iScience</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center <br></strong>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact</strong>: </p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-find-enhancing-the-bodys-first-responder-cells-may-boost-immune-therapy-for-cancer/">Mayo Clinic researchers find enhancing the body&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8216;first responder&amp;#8217; cells may boost immune therapy for cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/TcellsANDmacrophages-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/TcellsANDmacrophages-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Haidong Dong]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jessica Lancaster]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic study finds majority of midlife women with menopause symptoms do not seek care</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-finds-majority-of-midlife-women-with-menopause-symptoms-do-not-seek-care/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sharon Theimer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Ekta Kapoor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407252</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A new study from Mayo Clinic underscores the widespread impact of menopause symptoms on midlife women — and raises concern that most are navigating this stage of life without medical care to help manage those challenges. The study, published in Mayo Clinic Proceedings, was based on responses from nearly 5,000 women ages [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-finds-majority-of-midlife-women-with-menopause-symptoms-do-not-seek-care/">Mayo Clinic study finds majority of midlife women with menopause symptoms do not seek care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9-feat-image-Kapoor-study-Proceedings-shutterstock_1428227687-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-407253" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9-feat-image-Kapoor-study-Proceedings-shutterstock_1428227687-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9-feat-image-Kapoor-study-Proceedings-shutterstock_1428227687-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9-feat-image-Kapoor-study-Proceedings-shutterstock_1428227687-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9-feat-image-Kapoor-study-Proceedings-shutterstock_1428227687-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9-feat-image-Kapoor-study-Proceedings-shutterstock_1428227687-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.mayoclinicproceedings.org%2Fpb-assets%2FHealth%2520Advance%2Fjournals%2Fjmcp%2FJMCP4762.pdf&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7CFurst.Justin%40mayo.edu%7C96006f986b5a48bf500c08de08248578%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C638957150871831386%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=zaP8jQgwJ12UEaFVekeNDuQSVbmxuVVLvIwDBREoZPw%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">new study</a> from <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> underscores the widespread impact of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/menopause/symptoms-causes/syc-20353397" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">menopause</a> symptoms on midlife women — and raises concern that most are navigating this stage of life without medical care to help manage those challenges.</p>



<p>The study, published in <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a>, was based on responses from nearly 5,000 women ages 45-60 who were surveyed across four Mayo Clinic primary care locations. More than 3 out of 4 respondents experienced menopause symptoms, with many reporting substantial effects on daily life, work productivity and overall well-being.</p>



<p>Despite the availability of safe and effective <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/menopause/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20353401" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">treatment options</a>, Mayo Clinic researchers found that menopause symptoms remain underrecognized, undertreated and inadequately addressed in the health care system.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Severe symptoms affect daily life, yet few women seek care or receive treatment</strong></h2>



<p>More than one-third (34%) of women who were surveyed reported moderate to very severe symptoms. <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-managing-sleep-during-menopause/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sleep</a> disturbances and <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-combating-weight-gain-during-menopause/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">weight gain</a> were among the most common issues reported by more than half of participants.</p>



<p>The most striking finding was that more than 80% of the women who responded to the survey did not seek medical care for their menopause symptoms. While many women said they preferred to manage symptoms on their own, others said that they were too busy or unaware that effective treatments exist. Only about 1 in 4 women were receiving any treatment for menopause symptoms at the time of the survey.</p>



<p>"Menopause is universal for women at midlife, the symptoms are common and disruptive, and yet, few women are receiving care that could help them," says lead author <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/kapoor-ekta-m-b-b-s/bio-20090811" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ekta Kapoor, M.B.B.S.</a>, an <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/endocrinology/sections/overview/ovc-20392506" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">endocrinologist</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/menopause-womens-sexual-health/overview/ovc-20487915" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">menopause specialist</a> at Mayo Clinic in Rochester. "This gap has real consequences for women's health and quality of life, and it's time we address it more proactively."</p>



<p>Without proper treatment, menopause symptoms can negatively affect sleep, mood, <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-does-menopause-cause-brain-fog/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cognition</a>, and <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-puts-price-tag-on-cost-of-menopause-symptoms-for-women-in-the-workplace/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">productivity</a> at work and at home. The findings underscore the importance of healthcare professionals proactively identifying and managing menopause symptoms in patients who may be struggling with them, the authors said.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Researchers call for proactive care strategies and new tools to close the treatment gap</strong></h2>



<p>The study noted that women often do not voluntarily mention concerns about menopause symptoms to their healthcare professional. Mayo Clinic researchers emphasize the need for strategies that destigmatize menopause care and make it more visible and accessible. Efforts are underway to develop questionnaires, digital tools and smartphone apps that help women identify symptoms, learn about treatment options and have more productive discussions with their primary care professionals.</p>



<p>"Our goal is to educate women and healthcare professionals about menopause," Dr. Kapoor says. "By making it easier to recognize and understand symptoms, we can close the gap between need and care — and help midlife women live healthier, more fulfilling lives."</p>



<p>Review the study for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&amp;nbsp; A <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=31WDB0JRpVI" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">video</a> of Dr. Kapoor discussing the findings is available.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Proceedings</strong> <br>One of the premier peer-reviewed clinical journals in general and internal medicine, <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a><em> </em>is among the most widely read and highly cited scientific publications for physicians. Continuously published since 1926 and celebrating its <a href="https://www.elsevier.com/en-in/subject/medicine/mayo-clinic-family-of-journals/mcp-100-years" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">centennial next year</a>, <em>Mayo Clinic Proceedings</em> is sponsored by Mayo Clinic, guided by its Bold. Forward. vision to transform medicine as the global authority in the care of serious or complex disease. The journal publishes original research, articles and commentary from authors worldwide and has an Impact Factor of 6.7, placing it in the top 10% among general and internal medicine journals.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> <br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact</strong>:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Sharon Theimer, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-finds-majority-of-midlife-women-with-menopause-symptoms-do-not-seek-care/">Mayo Clinic study finds majority of midlife women with menopause symptoms do not seek care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/1x1-feat-image-Kapoor-study-Proceedings-shutterstock_1428227687.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9-feat-image-Kapoor-study-Proceedings-shutterstock_1428227687.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Ekta Kapoor]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic discovery of breast cancer treatment resistance can lead to new hope for some</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-discovery-of-breast-cancer-treatment-resistance-can-lead-to-new-hope-for-some/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Vincent Jacobbi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 17:08:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rochester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407323</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. —&amp;#160;Mayo Clinic researchers have discovered a key reason why certain breast cancers might not respond to an important new class of therapeutics called antibody drug conjugates (ADCs). These treatments pair an antibody that targets cancer cells with a strong chemotherapy drug. For many patients with human epidermal growth factor receptor 2-positive (HER2+) breast [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-discovery-of-breast-cancer-treatment-resistance-can-lead-to-new-hope-for-some/">Mayo Clinic discovery of breast cancer treatment resistance can lead to new hope for some</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="682" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/A-breast-cancer-patient-sits-on-the-examination-table-and-shares-her-symptoms-with-her-physician_GettyImages-2148188847-1024x682.jpg" alt="A breast cancer patient sits on the examination table and shares her symptoms with her physician." class="wp-image-407381" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/A-breast-cancer-patient-sits-on-the-examination-table-and-shares-her-symptoms-with-her-physician_GettyImages-2148188847-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/A-breast-cancer-patient-sits-on-the-examination-table-and-shares-her-symptoms-with-her-physician_GettyImages-2148188847-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/A-breast-cancer-patient-sits-on-the-examination-table-and-shares-her-symptoms-with-her-physician_GettyImages-2148188847-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/A-breast-cancer-patient-sits-on-the-examination-table-and-shares-her-symptoms-with-her-physician_GettyImages-2148188847-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/A-breast-cancer-patient-sits-on-the-examination-table-and-shares-her-symptoms-with-her-physician_GettyImages-2148188847.jpg 1688w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. —&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> researchers have discovered a key reason why certain breast cancers might not respond to an important new class of therapeutics called antibody drug conjugates (ADCs). These treatments pair an antibody that targets cancer cells with a strong chemotherapy drug. For many patients with human epidermal growth factor receptor 2-positive (<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/expert-answers/breast-cancer/faq-20058066" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">HER2+</a>) breast cancers, ADCs such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements/fam-trastuzumab-deruxtecan-nxki-intravenous-route/description/drg-20481655" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">trastuzumab deruxtecan (T-DXd)</a> have dramatically improved outcomes.</p>



<p>"While T-DXd has shown remarkable results for many patients, it hasn't worked for everyone with advanced HER2+ breast cancer," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/lucas-peter-c-m-d-ph-d/bio-20571057" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Peter Lucas, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, vice chair for research in the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/laboratory-medicine-pathology/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathology</a> at Mayo Clinic and co-senior author of the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s43018-025-00969-4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>, published in Nature Cancer. "This indicates that some tumors have built-in resistant mechanisms that prevent the drug from doing its job."</p>



<p>In the study, researchers in the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/oncoimmune-signaling-therapeutics/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Oncoimmune Signaling and Therapeutics Laboratory</a> at Mayo Clinic discovered that a shortened version of the HER2 protein, called p95HER2, that is produced by a subset of HER2+ breast cancers can alter treatment response. The protein p95HER2 "signals differently" from the full HER2 oncoprotein — which proved to be the key to how it drives therapy resistance.</p>



<p>"Our discovery that p95HER2 has the unique ability to induce signals that produce an immune-protected microenvironment strongly suggested that p95HER2 could function within cancer cells to actively resist T-DXd," says Dr. Lucas.</p>



<p>The study also revealed that a drug called <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements/neratinib-oral-route/description/drg-20406380" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">neratinib</a> is highly effective at blocking the action of p95HER2, even causing the protein to be degraded.</p>



<p>"In fact, treatment with neratinib results in complete p95HER2 degradation, abolishing the protein from the cancer cells in our preclinical models," says Dong Hu, Ph.D., a research scientist in Laboratory Medicine and Pathology at Mayo Clinic and lead author of the manuscript.</p>



<p>Based on these findings, the research team believes the next step is a clinical trial to evaluate the combination of neratinib with T-DXd in patients with HER2+ early breast cancer. The goal is to determine if this combination therapy can improve the response in cancers that co-express p95HER2 along with full HER2.</p>



<p>They note that this is just one of many therapeutic combinations being considered.</p>



<p>"No single, one-size-fits-all approach to treatment will work for every patient with HER2+ breast cancer," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/mcallister-linda-m-m-d-ph-d/bio-20568725" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Linda McAllister, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, a pediatric hematologist/oncologist at Mayo Clinic and co-senior author of the study.</p>



<p>However, with the discovery of p95HER2's role, a clear roadmap for future treatment is in sight.</p>



<p>"Having this new understanding of why T-DXd does not always work helps us to envision next steps toward customized therapies and more cures," says Dr. Lucas. "It's all about staying one step ahead of cancer."</p>



<p>For a complete list of authors, disclosures and findings, review the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s43018-025-00969-4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>. The work was supported by the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/specialized-programs-research-excellence-spore-grants/breast-cancer/research-projects/p95her2-antitumor-immunity-efficacy-her2-directed-antibody-drug-conjugates" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Breast Cancer SPORE</a>.</p>



<p>####</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the <a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-discovery-of-breast-cancer-treatment-resistance-can-lead-to-new-hope-for-some/">Mayo Clinic discovery of breast cancer treatment resistance can lead to new hope for some</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/A-breast-cancer-patient-sits-on-the-examination-table-and-shares-her-symptoms-with-her-physician_GettyImages-2148188847_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/A-breast-cancer-patient-sits-on-the-examination-table-and-shares-her-symptoms-with-her-physician_GettyImages-2148188847_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>A new tool to find hidden &amp;#8216;zombie cells&amp;#8217;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-new-tool-to-find-hidden-zombie-cells/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kate Ledger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 13:59:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Aging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Discovery Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Darren Baker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. L. James Maher III]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nathan LeBrasseur]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407191</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researchers report finding a new technique to tag senescent cells. </p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-new-tool-to-find-hidden-zombie-cells/">A new tool to find hidden &amp;#8216;zombie cells&amp;#8217;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-left-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Pearson-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="A confocal microscopy image shows senescent cells (red) tagged with molecules known as aptamers (blue). Image reproduced from the article in Aging Cell." class="wp-image-407195" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Pearson-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Pearson-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Pearson-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Pearson-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Pearson-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">A confocal microscopy image shows senescent cells (red) tagged with molecules known as aptamers (blue). Image reproduced from the article in Aging Cell.</figcaption></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. —&amp;nbsp;When it comes to treating disease, one promising avenue is addressing the presence of senescent cells. These cells — also known as "zombie cells" — stop dividing but don't die off as cells typically do. They turn up in numerous diseases, including cancer and Alzheimer's disease, and in the process of aging. While potential treatments aim to remove or repair the cells, one hurdle has been finding a way to identify them among healthy cells in living tissue.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>In the journal <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/acel.70245" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Aging Cell</a>, Mayo Clinic researchers report finding a new technique to tag senescent cells. The team used molecules known as "aptamers" — small segments of synthetic DNA that fold into three-dimensional shapes. Aptamers have the ability to attach themselves to proteins on the surfaces of cells. In mouse cells, the team found several rare aptamers, identified from among more than 100 trillion random DNA sequences, that can latch onto specific cell surface proteins and flag senescent cells.</p>



<p>"This approach established the principle that aptamers are a technology that can be used to distinguish senescent cells from healthy ones," says biochemist and molecular biologist <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/maher-jim-iii-ph-d/bio-00027304" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jim Maher, III, Ph.D.</a>, a principal investigator of the study. "Though this study is a first step, the results suggest the approach could eventually apply to human cells."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>From a quirky idea to collaboration &amp;nbsp;</strong></h2>



<p>The project began with the quirky idea of a Mayo Clinic graduate student who had a chance conversation with a classmate.</p>



<p>Keenan Pearson, Ph.D. — who recently received his degree from <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/phd-program/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a> — was working under the mentorship of Dr. Maher, studying how aptamers might address neurodegenerative diseases or brain cancer.</p>



<p>A few floors away, Sarah Jachim, Ph.D., — who was also then conducting her graduate research — was working in the lab of researcher <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/lebrasseur-nathan-k-ph-d-m-s/bio-00055041" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nathan LeBrasseur, Ph.D.</a>, Director, Mayo Clinic Robert and Arlene Kogod Center on Aging, who studies senescent cells and aging.</p>



<p>At a scientific event, the two happened to chat about their graduate thesis projects. Dr. Pearson thought aptamer technology might be able to identify senescent cells. "I thought the idea was a good one, but I didn't know about the process of preparing senescent cells to test them, and that was Sarah's expertise," says Dr. Pearson, who became lead author of the publication. &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>They pitched the idea to their mentors and to researcher <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/baker-darren-j-ph-d-m-s/bio-00027985" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Darren Baker, Ph.D.</a>, who investigates therapies to treat senescent cells. At first, Dr. Maher acknowledges, the students' idea seemed "crazy" but worth pursuing. The three mentors were excited about the plan. "We frankly loved that it was the students' idea and a real synergy of two research areas," says Dr. Maher.</p>



<p>The students obtained compelling results sooner than they expected and quickly recruited other student participants from the labs. Then-graduate students Brandon Wilbanks, Ph.D., Luis Prieto, Ph.D., and M.D.-Ph.D. student Caroline Doherty, each contributed additional approaches, including special microscopy techniques and more varied tissue samples. "It became encouraging to expend more effort," Dr. Jachim says, "because we could tell it was a project that was going to succeed."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Identifying attributes of senescent cells</strong></h2>



<p>&amp;nbsp;The study has provided new information about senescent cells beyond a way to tag them. "To date, there aren't universal markers that characterize senescent cells," says Dr. Maher. "Our study was set up to be open-ended about the target surface molecules on senescent cells. The beauty of this approach is that we let the aptamers choose the molecules to bind to."</p>



<p>The study found several aptamers latched onto a variant of a specific molecule on the surface of mouse cells, a protein called fibronectin. The role of this variant fibronectin in senescence is not yet understood. The finding means that aptamers may be a tool to further define unique characteristics of senescent cells.</p>



<p>Additional studies will be necessary to find aptamers that can identify senescent cells in humans. Aptamers with the ability to latch onto senescent cells could potentially deliver a therapy directly to those cells. Dr. Pearson notes aptamer technology is less expensive and more versatile than conventional antibodies, proteins that are typically used to differentiate cells from one another.</p>



<p>"This project demonstrated a novel concept," says Dr. Maher. "Future studies may extend the approach to applications related to senescent cells in human disease."</p>



<p>See the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/acel.70245" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&amp;nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact</strong>:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-new-tool-to-find-hidden-zombie-cells/">A new tool to find hidden &amp;#8216;zombie cells&amp;#8217;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Pearson-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Pearson-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Darren Baker]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. L. James Maher III]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nathan LeBrasseur]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic study sheds light on colorectal cancer risk in overlooked group</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-sheds-light-on-colorectal-cancer-risk-in-overlooked-group/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jessica Saenz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 15:57:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nicholas LaRusso]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[research Dr. Saqr Alsakarneh]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407172</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Primary sclerosing cholangitis (PSC) causes inflammation and scarring of the bile ducts. This rare liver disease is often accompanied by inflammatory bowel disease (IBD). Together, these diseases increase the risk of colorectal cancer by more than sixfold compared to the general population. Until recently, it&amp;#160;wasn't&amp;#160;clear whether that increased colorectal cancer risk extended to people with [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-sheds-light-on-colorectal-cancer-risk-in-overlooked-group/">Mayo Clinic study sheds light on colorectal cancer risk in overlooked group</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image is-style-left-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Gastro-researcher-WF3829116_0189-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Gastroenterology researchers look at screen" class="wp-image-407268" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Gastro-researcher-WF3829116_0189-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Gastro-researcher-WF3829116_0189-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Gastro-researcher-WF3829116_0189-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Gastro-researcher-WF3829116_0189-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Gastro-researcher-WF3829116_0189-16-x-9.jpg 1900w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Gastroenterology researchers look at screen</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Primary sclerosing cholangitis (PSC) causes inflammation and scarring of the bile ducts. This rare liver disease is often accompanied by inflammatory bowel disease (IBD). Together, these diseases increase the risk of colorectal cancer by more than sixfold compared to the general population.</p>



<p>Until recently, it&amp;nbsp;<a>wasn't</a>&amp;nbsp;clear whether that increased colorectal cancer risk extended to people with PSC alone, but Mayo Clinic researchers have helped answer this question. Their findings could help open the door to earlier colorectal cancer screening and better prevention for people with PSC.</p>



<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="608" height="608" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr.-Saqr-Alsakarneh-30425105_20250701-1-x-1.jpg" alt="Photo of Dr. Saqr Alsakarneh" class="wp-image-407174" style="width:166px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr.-Saqr-Alsakarneh-30425105_20250701-1-x-1.jpg 608w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr.-Saqr-Alsakarneh-30425105_20250701-1-x-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Dr.-Saqr-Alsakarneh-30425105_20250701-1-x-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Saqr Alsakarneh</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We wanted to answer something that was overlooked in the guidelines because these patients are a smaller group and have been understudied in research," says Dr.&nbsp;Saqr Alsakarneh, a fellow in the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/gastroenterology-hepatology-digestive-care/sections/overview/ovc-20348241?customer_id=919-955-2329&amp;amp;mc_id=google&amp;amp;campaign=8927988164&amp;amp;geo=9199032&amp;amp;kw=mayo%20clinic%20gastroenterology&amp;amp;ad=458309235531&amp;amp;network=g&amp;amp;sitetarget=&amp;amp;adgroup=111165104350&amp;amp;extension=&amp;amp;target=kwd-367650091164&amp;amp;matchtype=e&amp;amp;device=c&amp;amp;account=9199552329&amp;amp;invsrc=arizona&amp;amp;placementsite=arizona&amp;amp;gad_source=1&amp;amp;gad_campaignid=8927988164&amp;amp;gbraid=0AAAAAD8Qu28LZ_ykDEhzwUdztX41xIe9R&amp;amp;gclid=Cj0KCQjw58PGBhCkARIsADbDilxBHSas-T8H9QdFt0dNSntXtQI6tzhJ5Pej5p9tpWeYJda5z2MOamwaAuh3EALw_wcB">Department of Gastroenterology at Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;and lead author of the study,&nbsp;published in&nbsp;<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/apt.70303">Alimentary Pharmacology and Therapeutics</a>. </p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><br><strong>Searching data for cancer prevention blind spots</strong></h2>



<p>In the largest population-based analysis of its kind, Dr. Alsakarneh and his co-authors analyzed data from 115 million de-identified health records from 65 healthcare organizations across the U.S. Their goal was to understand long-term risk of colorectal and other gastrointestinal cancers in people with PSC.</p>



<p>The researchers found that&amp;nbsp;people with PSC without IBD have&amp;nbsp;<a>nearly three</a>&amp;nbsp;times the risk of developing colorectal cancer compared to the general population.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"This is important because it challenges the current assumption that only&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/primary-sclerosing-cholangitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20355797">primary sclerosing cholangitis</a>&amp;nbsp;with IBD causes colorectal cancer," says&amp;nbsp;Dr.&amp;nbsp;<a>Alsakarneh</a>.</p>



<p>While colorectal cancer prevention guidelines recommend annual screening and increased surveillance for people who have PSC and IBD, no specific guidelines exist for people with only PSC. Dr. Alsakarneh says this is a missed opportunity for early detection of colorectal cancer, which is highly preventable with proper screening.</p>



<p>In addition to discovering an increased risk for colorectal cancer, the study&amp;nbsp;confirmed an association between PSC alone and higher rates of bile duct,&amp;nbsp;<a>liver</a>&amp;nbsp;and pancreatic cancers. While previous research has suggested this connection, the study provides large-scale data to support the need for continued vigilance and screening strategies tailored to people with PSC.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Translating discovery to better care</strong></h2>



<p>Dr. Alsakarneh says these findings are an important first step toward a better understanding of PSC and cancer risk, although more studies are needed to confirm how this information should be incorporated into healthcare guidelines.</p>



<p>"Before anything is put into guidelines, the first step is always to validate the findings," says Dr. Alsakarneh. "Colleagues from the gastrointestinal community have reached out and are interested, so this is something we are working on."</p>



<p>As researchers investigate further, Dr. Alsakarneh says&amp;nbsp;<a>it's</a>&amp;nbsp;important that clinicians with PSC patients be aware of this association, tune into emerging evidence and keep their patients informed as findings develop.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Continuing a legacy of PSC discovery at Mayo Clinic</strong></h2>



<p>Dr. Alsakarneh's research continues a legacy of PSC discovery at Mayo Clinic that&nbsp;dates back to&nbsp;the '70s. That was when&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/larusso-nicholas-f-m-d/bio-20053658" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Nicholas LaRusso</a>, a gastroenterologist at Mayo Clinic, first began studying the cluster of symptoms that he eventually helped describe and define as PSC in a 1980&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/7399227/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>.  </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="819" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/LaRusso-Nicholas-F._10157514_20220913-819x1024.jpg" alt="Dr. Nicholas LaRusso" class="wp-image-407260" style="width:159px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/LaRusso-Nicholas-F._10157514_20220913-819x1024.jpg 819w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/LaRusso-Nicholas-F._10157514_20220913-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/LaRusso-Nicholas-F._10157514_20220913-768x960.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/LaRusso-Nicholas-F._10157514_20220913.jpg 900w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 819px) 100vw, 819px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Nicholas LaRusso</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"It's important to me that this study comes from Mayo Clinic because Dr. LaRusso, who still has a lab here, made so much progress in this disease. He is the reason I came to Mayo Clinic to do my training," says Dr. Alsakarneh.</p>



<p>Alongside Dr. LaRusso, Dr. Alsakarneh next plans to lead Mayo Clinic research investigating why and how PSC increases cancer risk.</p>



<p></p>



<p>Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/apt.70303" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-sheds-light-on-colorectal-cancer-risk-in-overlooked-group/">Mayo Clinic study sheds light on colorectal cancer risk in overlooked group</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Gastro-researcher-WF3829116_0189-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Gastro-researcher-WF3829116_0189-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nicholas LaRusso]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[research Dr. Saqr Alsakarneh]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New genomic test could spare some people with melanoma from lymph node biopsy surgery&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-genomic-test-could-spare-some-people-with-melanoma-from-lymph-node-biopsy-surgery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 14:55:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Discovery Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individualized Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Alexander Meves]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Tina Hieken]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407092</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A genomic test co-developed by Mayo Clinic and SkylineDx can identify whether people with melanoma are at low or high risk for cancer in their lymph nodes — a finding that could guide treatment decisions and help some people avoid lymph node biopsy surgery. The study results are published in JAMA Surgery. [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-genomic-test-could-spare-some-people-with-melanoma-from-lymph-node-biopsy-surgery/">New genomic test could spare some people with melanoma from lymph node biopsy surgery&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9MELANOMA1-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-407094" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9MELANOMA1-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9MELANOMA1-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9MELANOMA1-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9MELANOMA1-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9MELANOMA1.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">A 3D illustration shows a cross-section of skin with melanoma spreading into the bloodstream and lymphatic system. (Getty Images)</figcaption></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A genomic test co-developed by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> and <a href="https://www.skylinedx.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">SkylineDx</a> can identify whether people with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/melanoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20374884" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">melanoma</a> are at low or high risk for cancer in their <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/swollen-lymph-nodes/symptoms-causes/syc-20353902%C2%A0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymph nodes</a> — a finding that could guide treatment decisions and help some people avoid lymph node biopsy surgery. The study results are <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamasurgery/fullarticle/2840207" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">published</a> in JAMA Surgery.</p>



<p>In the largest prospective study of its kind, about 93% of people classified as low risk had no cancer in their lymph nodes, while about 25% in the high-risk group did. The multicenter clinical trial enrolled 1,761 people with early- or intermediate-stage melanoma at nine U.S. cancer centers between 2021 and 2024.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Decoding the tumor’s genomic blueprint</strong></h2>



<p>The test measures the activity of eight genes in a melanoma tumor and combines that data with a person's age and tumor thickness to estimate the chance that cancer has reached the lymph nodes. The Merlin CP-GEP Test analyzes tissue from the tumor already collected during an initial biopsy, so no additional procedure or visit is required for the test.</p>



<p>Sentinel lymph node biopsy is performed under anesthesia to remove one or a few lymph nodes and check for microscopic cancer. The procedure usually requires a second incision and can have side effects, yet nearly 80% of people who undergo the surgery have no cancer in their lymph nodes.</p>



<p>"Surgery will always be central to cancer care, but this study shows that sentinel lymph node surgery might be avoided for selected patients with melanoma," says first author <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/hieken-tina-j-m-d/bio-20089011" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tina Hieken, M.D.</a>, a surgical <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/oncology/sections/overview/ovc-20198225" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">oncologist</a> at the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> and co-principal investigator of the study. "This test lets us use a patient's own tumor biology to guide care with true precision."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Turning molecular insight into clinical impact</strong></h2>



<p>Melanoma is the deadliest form of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/skin-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20377605" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">skin cancer</a>. While early-stage disease can often be treated successfully, once melanoma spreads to the lymph nodes, the risk of recurrence increases. Determining whether the cancer has reached the lymph nodes is a key step in guiding treatment.</p>



<p>"Melanoma progression is driven by subtle molecular processes that we're only beginning to understand," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/meves-alexander-m-d-m-b-a/bio-00027476" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alexander Meves, M.D.</a>, a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/dermatology/sections/overview/ovc-20420526" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dermatologist</a> at the Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center who led earlier validation studies of the test. "This work translates that biology into tools that can improve care."</p>



<p>Researchers are now studying how incorporating the test into melanoma care might help healthcare professionals understand the risk of recurrence and guide follow-up care.</p>



<p>For a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding information, review the <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamasurgery/fullarticle/2840207" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong> </p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-genomic-test-could-spare-some-people-with-melanoma-from-lymph-node-biopsy-surgery/">New genomic test could spare some people with melanoma from lymph node biopsy surgery&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/1x1MELANOMA.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/16x9MELANOMA1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Alexander Meves]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Tina Hieken]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Breast cancer survivors find relief for debilitating menopause symptom</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breast-cancer-survivors-find-relief-for-debilitating-menopause-symptom/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alison Satake]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Anita Chen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Emanuel Trabuco]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407122</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic gynecologists have found a potential solution for a bothersome menopause condition affecting a majority of breast cancer survivors.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breast-cancer-survivors-find-relief-for-debilitating-menopause-symptom/">Breast cancer survivors find relief for debilitating menopause symptom</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-left-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/GettyImages-1700833462-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Photo of woman with short hair looks into distance." class="wp-image-407158" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/GettyImages-1700833462-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/GettyImages-1700833462-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/GettyImages-1700833462-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/GettyImages-1700833462-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/GettyImages-1700833462-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Getty Images</figcaption></figure>



<p>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. — About 50% of menopausal women experience <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/vaginal-atrophy/symptoms-causes/syc-20352288#symptoms" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">genitourinary syndrome of menopause (GSM)</a> that involves changes to the genitals, including the vagina, urethra and bladder. When estrogen levels drop during <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/menopause/symptoms-causes/syc-20353397?mc_id=us&amp;amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;amp;utm_medium=l&amp;amp;utm_content=content&amp;amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;amp;geo=national&amp;amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">menopause</a>, it can cause the GSM symptoms of <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/vaginal-dryness-symptoms-causes-and-remedies" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">vaginal dryness</a>, itching, burning, frequent <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/urinary-tract-infection/symptoms-causes/syc-20353447" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">urinary tract infections</a> and pain during sex. Replenishing the hormone through vaginal estrogen is an effective GSM treatment. But many <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a> survivors either can't or don't want to use estrogen.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>More than 4 million people in the U.S. are breast <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer</a> survivors. GSM affects up to 70% of these survivors. Medications that stop the body from producing estrogen can prevent or stop the spread of breast cancer. However, these antiestrogen therapies, called <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/hormone-therapy-for-breast-cancer/about/pac-20384943#:~:text=Medicines%20that%20stop%20the%20body%20from%20making%20estrogen" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">aromatase inhibitors</a>, also can exacerbate GSM symptoms.&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="320" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/AHC-Head-Shot.jpg" alt="Headshot photo of Dr. Anita Chen" class="wp-image-407125" style="width:238px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/AHC-Head-Shot.jpg 320w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/AHC-Head-Shot-300x281.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 320px) 100vw, 320px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Anita Chen, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Our data shows that as many as 20% of breast cancer survivors on aromatase inhibitors will stop taking their medication prematurely because they cause severe GSM symptoms. This early discontinuation of their breast cancer therapy can lead to worse outcomes in breast cancer survivorship. So, clearly, nonhormonal treatment options for GSM are needed," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/chen-anita-h-m-d/bio-20053260" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Anita Chen, M.D.</a>, a gynecologist at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a>. Dr. Chen is the lead author of a <a href="https://journals.lww.com/greenjournal/fulltext/9900/platelet_rich_plasma_for_genitourinary_syndrome_of.1369.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> published in Obstetrics &amp;amp; Gynecology. &amp;nbsp;<br>&amp;nbsp;<br>This need drove Dr. Chen to search for another option. Her team conducted a phase 1 clinical trial with 20 breast cancer survivors with GSM to test the efficacy of platelet-rich plasma (PRP), the part of the blood that holds healing properties, to see if it could help. Blood was drawn from each participant and then spun in a centrifuge to obtain platelets and plasma that have self-healing and regenerative effects. PRP was then injected diffusely once into the opening of the vagina and the vaginal canal in each participant.&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="683" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Trabuco-Emanuel-WF6590801_0007-683x1024.jpg" alt="Headshot photo of Dr. Emanuel Trabuco" class="wp-image-407130" style="width:193px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Trabuco-Emanuel-WF6590801_0007-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Trabuco-Emanuel-WF6590801_0007-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Trabuco-Emanuel-WF6590801_0007-768x1151.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Trabuco-Emanuel-WF6590801_0007-1025x1536.jpg 1025w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Trabuco-Emanuel-WF6590801_0007-1366x2048.jpg 1366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 683px) 100vw, 683px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Emanuel Trabuco, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"After six months, the breast cancer patients' GSM symptoms had significantly improved, including sexual function, urinary symptoms and overall quality of life, even amongst those taking estrogen blockers," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/trabuco-emanuel-c-m-d/bio-00028202" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Emanuel Trabuco, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic researcher and co-author of the study.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>While vasomotor symptoms of menopause, such as hot flashes and night sweats, can improve over time, GSM does not improve without treatment and worsens over time.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"All of our participants completed the injection protocol and rigorous follow-up, which suggests that this population desires treatment for a bothersome condition, one that is likely underreported, underestimated and undertreated," says Dr. Chen. "Most importantly, none of the participants stopped their breast cancer treatment or experienced cancer recurrence during the study."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>PRP has been used for years in orthopedics and dermatology, and gynecologists have started looking into it to treat <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stress-incontinence/symptoms-causes/syc-20355727" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stress urinary incontinence</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/infertility/care-at-mayo-clinic/mac-20354325" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">reproductive medicine</a> and GSM.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The next step in this research includes pursuing a phase 2 randomized controlled clinical trial to compare PRP injection with a placebo to treat GSM in breast cancer survivors and further evaluate its efficacy.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Review the <a href="https://journals.lww.com/greenjournal/fulltext/9900/platelet_rich_plasma_for_genitourinary_syndrome_of.1369.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding. &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>###&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&amp;nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breast-cancer-survivors-find-relief-for-debilitating-menopause-symptom/">Breast cancer survivors find relief for debilitating menopause symptom</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/GettyImages-1700833462-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/GettyImages-1700833462-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Anita Chen]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Emanuel Trabuco]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-radiation-therapy-for-patients-with-breast-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 12:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health &amp; Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Laura Vallow]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395065</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Radiation therapy is a common component of breast cancer treatment for patients. The high-powered beams of intense energy kill cancer cells and reduce the risk of the cancer recurring. Dr. Laura Vallow, chair of the Radiation Oncology Department at Mayo Clinic in Florida, explains how innovation is transforming radiation treatments. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-radiation-therapy-for-patients-with-breast-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Patient-with-radiation-tech-1461606_3648465_0034-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Patient with radiation technician, radiation therapy" class="wp-image-407114" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Patient-with-radiation-tech-1461606_3648465_0034-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Patient-with-radiation-tech-1461606_3648465_0034-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Patient-with-radiation-tech-1461606_3648465_0034-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Patient-with-radiation-tech-1461606_3648465_0034-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Patient-with-radiation-tech-1461606_3648465_0034-16-x-9.jpg 1604w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/radiation-therapy/about/pac-20385162" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Radiation therapy</a> is a common component of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352475" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer treatment</a> for patients. The high-powered beams of intense energy kill cancer cells and reduce the risk of the cancer recurring.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/vallow-laura-a-m-d/bio-20054004">Dr. Laura Vallow</a>, chair of the Radiation Oncology Department at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a>, explains how innovation is transforming radiation treatments.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=me4OE84cerE" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidme4OE84cerE"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/me4OE84cerE?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:05) is in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/SCRIPT-MCM-Radiation-therapy-for-breast-cancer.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Patients with breast cancer now have more options when it comes to radiation treatments. The goal is to remove any remaining cancer cells following chemotherapy or surgery.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"In other situations, we use radiation if the cancer is more advanced, or spread to the lymph nodes," says Dr. Vallow.</p>



<p>Advancements in technology allow healthcare professionals to treat patients more safely. One technique called "prone positioning" reduces the chance of beams targeting other organs. For this procedure, patients lie on their stomachs.</p>



<p>"We take advantage of gravity, the breast pulls away from the body, and we can treat the breast without exposing the underlying lung and heart to unnecessary radiation," explains Dr. Vallow.</p>



<p>Intensity-modulated radiation therapy is cutting-edge. Unlike traditional radiation, this procedure delivers X-rays directly to the targeted area from multiple angles, allowing for higher, more effective doses.</p>



<p>"Before intensity-modulated radiation therapy, we were not able to conform the dose around the chest wall," says Dr. Vallow.</p>



<p>For patients undergoing radiation therapy, it's crucial to stay hydrated and try to sleep well to fight fatigue. It's also important to use sunscreen after treatment.</p>



<p><strong>Related Posts:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-leads-4-decades-of-advances-in-breast-cancer-care/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic leads 4 decades of advances in breast cancer care</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-research-improves-dense-breast-cancer-screening-and-early-detection/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic research improves dense breast cancer screening and early detection</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/top-10-questions-about-breast-cancer-answered/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Top 10 questions about breast cancer answered</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-treats-first-person-in-the-us-with-a-novel-radiopharmaceutical-therapy-for-breast-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic treats first person in the US with a novel radiopharmaceutical therapy for breast cancer</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-mri-for-dense-breasts-what-to-know/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: MRI for dense breasts — what to know</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-how-to-decide-which-breast-cancer-surgery-is-right-for-you/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;amp;A: How to decide which breast cancer surgery is right for you</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ready-for-10-13-back-on-the-bench-judges-metastatic-breast-cancer-journey-inspires-hope/">(VIDEO) Back on the bench: Judge’s metastatic breast cancer journey inspires hope</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-do-you-need-to-know-about-dense-breasts/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;amp;A: What do you need to know about dense breasts?</a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/wp-admin/post.php?post=406974&amp;amp;action=edit"></a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-radiation-therapy-for-patients-with-breast-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Patient-with-radiation-tech-1461606_3648465_0034.-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/10/Patient-with-radiation-tech-1461606_3648465_0034-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Laura Vallow]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss> 