<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org">

<channel>
	<title>Research - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml">
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research/
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastbuilddate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 21:01:50 +0000</lastbuilddate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updateperiod>
	hourly	</sy:updateperiod>
	<sy:updatefrequency>
	1	</sy:updatefrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>New Mayo-led study establishes practical definition for rapidly progressive dementia</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-led-study-establishes-practical-definition-for-rapidly-progressive-dementia/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Lynda De Widt]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 21:01:49 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Florida]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Neurosciences]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#medical research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Gregg Day]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Florida News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[rapidly progressive dementia]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=408144</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->JACKSONVILLE, Fla. — A new multicenter study led by Mayo Clinic researchers has established a practical, evidence-based definition for rapidly progressive dementia (RPD), a rare but devastating form of cognitive decline that develops over months instead of years. The findings, published in Neurology, the medical journal of the American Academy of Neurology, may help clinicians […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-led-study-establishes-practical-definition-for-rapidly-progressive-dementia/">New Mayo-led study establishes practical definition for rapidly progressive dementia</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Arms-reaching-around-mans-neck_GettyImages-1576851402-1024x576.jpg" alt="A cropped view of a pair of hands reaching around a man's neck and resting their hands on his chest as he holds onto them." class="wp-image-408412" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Arms-reaching-around-mans-neck_GettyImages-1576851402-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Arms-reaching-around-mans-neck_GettyImages-1576851402-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Arms-reaching-around-mans-neck_GettyImages-1576851402-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Arms-reaching-around-mans-neck_GettyImages-1576851402-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Arms-reaching-around-mans-neck_GettyImages-1576851402.jpg 1999w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Getty Images</figcaption>



<p>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. — A new multicenter study led by Mayo Clinic researchers has established a practical, evidence-based definition for <a href="https://news.mayocliniclabs.com/neurology/dementia/rapidly-progressive-dementia/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">rapidly progressive dementia (RPD)</a>, a rare but devastating form of cognitive decline that develops over months instead of years. The findings, <a href="https://www.neurology.org/doi/10.1212/WNL.0000000000214439" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">published in Neurology</a>, the medical journal of the American Academy of Neurology, may help clinicians recognize and treat RPD earlier, and enable researchers to work from a shared framework when studying the condition.</p>



<p>While most types of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/dementia/symptoms-causes/syc-20352013" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dementia</a> progress gradually, RPD advances with alarming speed, often leading to significant cognitive decline or death within one to two years. Although it accounts for around 4% of dementia cases, RPD is difficult to diagnose. Symptoms can stem from numerous causes, including autoimmune disease, infections, neurodegenerative disorders such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/alzheimers-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350447" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alzheimer's disease</a> and rare conditions like <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/creutzfeldt-jakob-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20371226" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease</a>. This makes it challenging to consistently define the disorder across different settings.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Gregg-Day-WF430770_0001-300x200.jpg" alt="Portrait of Dr. Gregg Day" class="wp-image-408151" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Gregg-Day-WF430770_0001-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Gregg-Day-WF430770_0001-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Gregg-Day-WF430770_0001-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Gregg-Day-WF430770_0001-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Gregg-Day-WF430770_0001-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Gregg Day, M.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>"Clinicians need a clear, standardized way to identify patients whose decline is unusually fast," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/day-gregg-s-m-d/bio-20545897" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gregg Day, M.D.</a>, a behavioral neurologist at Mayo Clinic and senior author of the study. "This helps ensure that those with potentially treatable causes are recognized quickly, wherever they are seen. Furthermore, this is a necessary step before launching multicenter studies aimed at understanding why a small subset of dementia patients progresses rapidly and how to address this through clinical trials and treatments."</p>



<p>The new definition proposed by Dr. Day and his colleagues uses the <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/neuroscience/clinical-dementia-rating" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR)</a> scale, a well-established tool for assessing dementia severity. Criteria are based on the level of functional impairment involving memory, orientation, judgment, problem-solving, community affairs, home and hobbies, and personal care. Under the new framework, a person is considered to have rapidly progressive dementia if they develop mild dementia (CDR score of 1 or higher) within one year of symptom onset, or moderate-to-severe dementia (CDR score of 2 or higher) within two years. Researchers refer to this as the "1-in-1 or 2-in-2" rule.</p>



<p>To test this definition, the research team applied it to two large datasets. The first, known as the RaPID cohort, included 248 patients evaluated for suspected RPD at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a> and Washington University in St. Louis. The second used data from the <a href="https://naccdata.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Alzheimer's Coordinating Center</a>, representing more than 19,000 participants across 46 research centers in the United States.</p>



<p>In the RaPID group, about 75% of patients met the new criteria. Nearly 1 in 3 had autoimmune or inflammatory causes — many of which are potentially reversible. In the broader national dataset, about 4% met the definition for RPD, with Alzheimer's disease being the most common underlying cause. Across both groups, people who met the RPD definition declined 3 to 4 times faster than those with typical dementia, based on changes measured using the CDR scale.</p>



<p>The new definition proved reliable across clinical and research settings, identifying both rare and common causes of RPD. It can be applied using a patient's clinical history instead of specialized testing, making it adaptable in diverse healthcare settings, including those with limited medical resources.</p>



<p>"By uniformly defining rapid progression, we can better identify patients who might benefit from treatment, improve consistency in research, and ultimately enhance care for people facing one of the most challenging forms of dementia," Dr. Day says.</p>



<p>For a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding, <a href="https://www.neurology.org/doi/10.1212/WNL.0000000000214439" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">see the paper</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Related:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-to-study-causes-of-rapidly-progressive-dementia/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic researchers to study causes of rapidly progressive dementia</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/researchers-identify-new-criteria-to-detect-rapidly-progressive-dementia/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Researchers identify new criteria to detect rapidly progressive dementia</a></li>
</ul>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> <br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Tia Ford, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-led-study-establishes-practical-definition-for-rapidly-progressive-dementia/">New Mayo-led study establishes practical definition for rapidly progressive dementia</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Arms-reaching-around-mans-neck_GettyImages-1576851402_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Arms-reaching-around-mans-neck_GettyImages-1576851402.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#medical research]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Gregg Day]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Florida News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[rapidly progressive dementia]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic smartwatch system helps parents shorten and defuse children’s severe tantrums early&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-smartwatch-system-helps-parents-shorten-and-defuse-childrens-severe-tantrums-early/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Susan Murphy]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 16:06:24 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Arjun Athreya]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Julia Shekunov]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Magdalena Romanowicz]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Paul Croarkin]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=408467</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn.&nbsp;—&nbsp;Mayo Clinic&nbsp;researchers have developed a smartwatch-based alert system that signals parents at the earliest signs of a tantrum in children with emotional and behavioral disorders — prompting them to intervene before it intensifies.&nbsp;&nbsp; In a new study published&nbsp;in&nbsp;JAMA&nbsp;Network Open, these alerts helped parents intervene within four seconds and shortened severe tantrums by an average […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-smartwatch-system-helps-parents-shorten-and-defuse-childrens-severe-tantrums-early/">Mayo Clinic smartwatch system helps parents shorten and defuse children’s severe tantrums early&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/16x9-TANTRUMS-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-408857" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/16x9-TANTRUMS-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/16x9-TANTRUMS-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/16x9-TANTRUMS-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/16x9-TANTRUMS-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/16x9-TANTRUMS.png 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn.&nbsp;—&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;researchers have developed a smartwatch-based alert system that signals parents at the earliest signs of a tantrum in children with emotional and behavioral disorders — prompting them to intervene before it intensifies.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>In a new study <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/2842819" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">published</a>&nbsp;in&nbsp;JAMA&nbsp;Network Open, these alerts helped parents intervene within four seconds and shortened severe tantrums by an average of 11 minutes — about half the duration seen with standard therapy.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>In this system, a smartwatch worn by the child detects physiological stress signals, such as rising heart rate, or changes in movement or sleep, and sends them to an artificial intelligence (AI)-enabled app on the parent's smartphone. The app analyzes the data in real time and sends an alert as a cue for the parent to connect with their child.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The findings&nbsp;demonstrate&nbsp;how smartwatch technology can help bridge a gap in pediatric mental healthcare by giving parents actionable support when professional help isn't immediately available. That need is widespread —&nbsp;nearly 1&nbsp;in 5 U.S. children has a mental,&nbsp;behavioral&nbsp;or emotional health disorder, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The approach&nbsp;shows&nbsp;how wearable technology, paired with patient-centric AI design, can support families beyond the clinic.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Study design and results</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p>In the randomized clinical trial, 50 children aged 3 to 7 receiving Parent-Child Interaction Therapy at Mayo Clinic&nbsp;participated&nbsp;over&nbsp;16 weeks. Half were assigned to use the smartwatch system, and half continued standard therapy. The study evaluated whether families would use the technology as intended and whether immediate alerts could measurably change parent response times and children's behavior.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Notably, children&nbsp;wore the smartwatch&nbsp;for about 75% of the study period, demonstrating&nbsp;feasibility and family engagement.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"This study shows that even small, well-timed interventions can change the trajectory of a child's emotional dysregulation episode," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/romanowicz-magdalena-m-d/bio-20306747" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Magdalena Romanowicz, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic child psychiatrist who co-led the study. "These moments give parents a chance to step in with supportive actions — moving closer, offering reassurance, labeling emotions and redirecting attention before a tantrum intensifies."&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Building on earlier research</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p>This work builds on the team's earlier study, which used a machine learning algorithm to analyze smartwatch data&nbsp;—&nbsp;including heart rate,&nbsp;sleep&nbsp;and movement&nbsp;—&nbsp;to predict disruptive behaviors in hospitalized children receiving psychiatric care.&nbsp;</p>



<p>That study,&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37966360/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">published</a>&nbsp;in the Journal of Child and Adolescent Psychopharmacology, showed the algorithm could predict a child's behavioral state with 81% accuracy and provided a&nbsp;30- to 60-minute&nbsp;advance warning of an impending outburst.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"This work shows how basic science and clinical research can come together to transform patient care," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/athreya-arjun-p-ph-d-m-s/bio-20473903" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Arjun Athreya, Ph.D.</a>, who co-led the study and serves on the engineering faculty in Mayo Clinic's Department of Molecular Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. "We've translated inpatient findings to outpatient care, and the results show how data from everyday smart devices can help families in real time."&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Empowering families with data-driven care</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/croarkin-paul-e-d-o-m-s/bio-00027440" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Paul Croarkin, D.O.</a>, a Mayo Clinic child and adolescent psychiatrist and study co-author, says the findings highlight the power of data-driven care. "A smartwatch may seem simple, but when it's backed by evidence-based treatments and advanced analytics, it becomes a lifeline for families trying to manage severe behavioral symptoms at home."&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/shekunov-julia-m-d/bio-20359665" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Julia Shekunov, M.D.</a>,&nbsp;medical&nbsp;director of Mayo Clinic's Child and Adolescent Psychiatry Inpatient Unit&nbsp;and also&nbsp;a study co-author, says the work addresses an urgent need. "We're seeing more children in crisis, and&nbsp;the severity&nbsp;is increasing. This system gives parents tools they can use immediately, even outside the clinic, to help their child regain control."&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Next steps</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p>Future studies will refine the system's predictive accuracy, test it in larger&nbsp;groups&nbsp;and assess its long-term benefits in routine outpatient care.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This study was funded in part by&nbsp;a Mayo&nbsp;Clinic Clinical Trial Stimulus Fund and Mayo Clinic's Center for Individualized Medicine. For a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding, review the&nbsp;<a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/2842819" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>###&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo&nbsp;Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion,&nbsp;expertise&nbsp;and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for&nbsp;additional&nbsp;Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:&nbsp;</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-smartwatch-system-helps-parents-shorten-and-defuse-childrens-severe-tantrums-early/">Mayo Clinic smartwatch system helps parents shorten and defuse children’s severe tantrums early&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/1x1-tantrums.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/16x9-TANTRUMS.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Arjun Athreya]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Julia Shekunov]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Magdalena Romanowicz]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Paul Croarkin]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>‘Zombie’ cells spark inflammation in severe fatty liver disease, Mayo Clinic researchers find&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/zombie-cells-spark-inflammation-in-severe-fatty-liver-disease-mayo-clinic-researchers-find/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Alison Satake]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 10:03:49 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Aging]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Discovery Science]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Gastroenterology]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. João Passos]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Stella Victorelli]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=408757</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic researchers have uncovered how aging "zombie cells" trigger harmful inflammation that accelerates a severe and increasingly common form of fatty liver disease called metabolic dysfunction-associated steatohepatitis (MASH). As obesity rates rise worldwide, MASH is projected to increase and is already one of the leading causes of liver transplantation.&nbsp; "Liver scarring […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/zombie-cells-spark-inflammation-in-severe-fatty-liver-disease-mayo-clinic-researchers-find/">‘Zombie’ cells spark inflammation in severe fatty liver disease, Mayo Clinic researchers find&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/senescent-cell-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="A microscopy image of a senescent cell and its mitochondrial network shown in red (nucleus is shown in gray). " class="wp-image-408763" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/senescent-cell-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/senescent-cell-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/senescent-cell-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/senescent-cell-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/senescent-cell-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">A microscopy image of a senescent cell and its mitochondrial network shown in red (nucleus is shown in gray).</figcaption>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> researchers have uncovered how aging "zombie cells" trigger harmful inflammation that accelerates a severe and increasingly common form of fatty liver disease called <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/nonalcoholic-fatty-liver-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20354567" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">metabolic dysfunction-associated steatohepatitis (MASH)</a>. As obesity rates rise worldwide, MASH is projected to increase and is already one of the leading causes of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/liver-transplant/about/pac-20384842" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">liver transplantation</a>.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7368400_0043-1024x683.jpg" alt="Photo of Stella Victorelli, Ph.D." class="wp-image-408758" style="aspect-ratio:1.4993160054719563;width:308px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7368400_0043-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7368400_0043-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7368400_0043-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7368400_0043-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7368400_0043-2048x1366.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Stella Victorelli, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>"Liver scarring and inflammation are hallmarks of MASH. If left untreated, it can progress to liver cancer. This is why it's so important to understand the mechanisms driving the disease so that we can prevent it or develop more effective treatments," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/cell-molecular-aging/faculty-staff" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stella Victorelli, Ph.D.</a>, who is the lead author of the <a href="https://www.doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66159-z" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> published in Nature Communications. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Victorelli and colleagues, who study aged or senescent "zombie" cells, identified a mechanism by which these cells drive liver scarring and inflammation. They found that small molecules called mitochondrial RNA, typically found within the cell's energy-producing mitochondria, can leak into the main part of the cell, where they mistakenly activate antiviral sensors called RIG-I and MDA5 — normally triggered when a virus infects a cell. In this case, the danger signal comes from the cell's own mitochondria, prompting a wave of inflammation that can damage nearby healthy tissue.&nbsp;</p>



<p>When the researchers blocked the sensors, inflammation dropped sharply. The study also found that proteins BAX and BAK, which help open pores in the mitochondrial membrane, enable mitochondrial RNA to escape. In a preclinical MASH model, inhibiting BAX and BAK prevented RNA from escaping and was associated with less inflammation and healthier liver tissue.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What are 'zombie' cells?</strong></h2>



<p>As we age, some cells enter senescence — a state in which they stop dividing but continue releasing inflammatory and tissue‑damaging molecules. When people are young, the immune system typically eliminates these senescent, or "zombie," cells. With age, however, they can persist and contribute to a range of age‑related health problems and diseases.&nbsp;</p>



<p>While some research focuses on removing these cells, this team investigated how to quiet their harmful signals.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="683" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7368400_0253-683x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-408759" style="aspect-ratio:0.6669972838526567;width:229px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7368400_0253-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7368400_0253-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7368400_0253-768x1151.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7368400_0253-1025x1536.jpg 1025w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7368400_0253-1366x2048.jpg 1366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 683px) 100vw, 683px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">João Passos, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>"With age, we accumulate 'zombie' cells, which can lead to more disease," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/passos-joao-ph-d/bio-20454365" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">João Passos, Ph.D.</a>, senior author of the study. "Our idea is that if we can quiet these cells earlier, we can prevent runaway inflammation and the development of many age‑related conditions, including liver disease. Understanding the mechanisms that drive disease allows us to target and delay those processes — potentially benefiting more than one condition."&nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Passos and colleagues also are developing new technology to <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1038/s44318-025-00601-2" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">spatially map senescent cells</a> throughout the body during aging.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This research was conducted in partnership between the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-arlene-kogod-center-aging" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Robert and Arlene Kogod Center on Aging</a> and the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-cell-signaling-gastroenterology-c-sig/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Cell Signaling in Gastroenterology (C-SiG)</a> at Mayo Clinic.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The research is part of a larger effort at Mayo Clinic called the Precure initiative, which is focused on developing tools that empower clinicians to predict and intercept biological processes before they evolve into disease or progress into complex, hard-to-treat conditions.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Review the <a href="https://www.doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66159-z" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>###&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic </strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/zombie-cells-spark-inflammation-in-severe-fatty-liver-disease-mayo-clinic-researchers-find/">‘Zombie’ cells spark inflammation in severe fatty liver disease, Mayo Clinic researchers find&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/woman-diptych-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/woman-diptych-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. João Passos]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Stella Victorelli]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Joint study finds proton beam therapy helps patients with throat cancer live longer with fewer side effects&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/joint-study-finds-proton-beam-therapy-helps-patients-with-throat-cancer-live-longer-with-fewer-side-effects/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Jessica Saenz]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 23:35:32 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Daniel Ma]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Robert Foote]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Proton Beam]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Throat Cancer]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=408774</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — Photon therapy offers strong outcomes in treating oropharyngeal cancers; however, some radiation can reach and damage nearby healthy tissue. The damage can lead to side effects that may be severe for some patients. In a new nationwide&nbsp;study&nbsp;published in The Lancet that included&nbsp;Mayo Clinic, investigators found that patients with oropharyngeal cancer can live […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/joint-study-finds-proton-beam-therapy-helps-patients-with-throat-cancer-live-longer-with-fewer-side-effects/">Joint study finds proton beam therapy helps patients with throat cancer live longer with fewer side effects&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="760" height="428" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Man-hiking-16-x-9.jpg" alt="Man with beard hiking" class="wp-image-408783" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Man-hiking-16-x-9.jpg 760w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Man-hiking-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 760px) 100vw, 760px">



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Photon therapy offers strong outcomes in treating oropharyngeal cancers; however, some radiation can reach and damage nearby healthy tissue. The damage can lead to side effects that may be severe for some patients. In a new nationwide&nbsp;<a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Furldefense.com%2Fv3%2F__https%3A%2F%2Fwww.thelancet.com%2Fjournals%2Flancet%2Farticle%2FPIIS0140-6736(25)01962-2%2Ffulltext__%3B!!PfbeBCCAmug!jnDZq-pUjzQbsU5dlBmAFEpCwre9G6iFA1VaUkmQGF1z5ncSfRCv0pMiz3zX2Uj5lZojXc2yfYftch8KpgvHnohk%24&amp;data=05%7C02%7CSaenz.Jessica%40mayo.edu%7C1071c402bd224fc3ef3908de3807aafd%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C639009802789540389%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=CSlDfEksVRnYlx%2FFQH9GEhjTXFn%2F2lVdPKTdypNVMnk%3D&amp;reserved=0">study</a>&nbsp;published in The Lancet that included&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/">Mayo Clinic</a>, investigators found that patients with oropharyngeal cancer can live longer with fewer side effects if treated with&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/sections/overview/ovc-20185491">proton beam radiation therapy</a>.</p>



<p>Photon radiation therapy, which uses X-rays to cure cancers, is a standard treatment for a type of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/throat-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20366462">throat cancer</a>&nbsp;called oropharyngeal cancer. Rates of oropharyngeal cancers are increasing in the U.S., mainly driven by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hpv-infection/symptoms-causes/syc-20351596">HPV infection</a>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Reducing the toll of treatment</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p>Proton beam therapy has been used for years in children, where research shows it lowers both short- and long-term treatment-related side effects. "Protons have been studied extensively in pediatric populations and consistently demonstrate reduced short- and long-term toxicity," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/laack-nadia-n-m-d/bio-20054933" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nadia Laack, M.D.</a>, chair of the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/radiation-oncology/home/orc-20188588" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Radiation Oncology</a> at Mayo Clinic in Rochester. "It has been more difficult to prove the benefits in adult cancer because many adult studies have not measured side effects as carefully or as long."&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="891" height="891" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Laack-Nadia-N._13569252_202107200920-1x1-1.jpg" alt="Nadia N. Laack, M.D." class="wp-image-408870" style="width:351px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Laack-Nadia-N._13569252_202107200920-1x1-1.jpg 891w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Laack-Nadia-N._13569252_202107200920-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Laack-Nadia-N._13569252_202107200920-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Laack-Nadia-N._13569252_202107200920-1x1-1-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 891px) 100vw, 891px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Nadia Laack, M.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>To explore whether the same advantages apply to adults, investigators directly compared proton beam therapy with modern photon radiation called intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT), which precisely targets tumors while limiting exposure to nearby healthy tissue. "It is effective as an oropharyngeal cancer treatment, but there's always some incidental dose to surrounding tissues because of the physical nature of X-rays," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/ma-daniel-j-m-d/bio-10031781">Daniel Ma, M.D.</a>, radiation oncologist at Mayo Clinic and the Mayo site primary investigator of the study. This incidental dose of radiation can sometimes cause long-term complications, including pain, problems with&nbsp;<a>swallowing</a>&nbsp;and a weakened jawbone.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="418" height="418" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Dr.-Daniel-J.-Ma-1x1-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-408779" style="width:364px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Dr.-Daniel-J.-Ma-1x1-1.jpg 418w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Dr.-Daniel-J.-Ma-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Dr.-Daniel-J.-Ma-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 418px) 100vw, 418px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Daniel Ma, M.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>To alleviate these unwanted side effects, investigators studied proton beam radiation therapy as a treatment option. "Protons are charged particles that can stop at a certain depth, so the delivery is more focused," says Dr. Ma. "If you set up your proton fields thoughtfully, you can avoid irradiating critical structures like the mouth, voice box and swallowing muscles. That's the advantage of proton therapy and why we decided to investigate it within a clinical trial."</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic was one of 18 participating institutions around the U.S. that enrolled patients in the first-ever phase 3 randomized trial comparing the two types of radiation for&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/throat-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20366462">oropharyngeal cancer</a>. Dr. Ma collaborated with Robert Foote, M.D., emeritus professor of radiation oncology at Mayo Clinic and senior author of the study, and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/patel-samir-h-m-d/bio-20588749">Samir Patel, M.D.</a>, radiation oncologist at Mayo Clinic, to help lead Mayo Clinic’s involvement in the study.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-gallery aligncenter has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="506" height="506" data-id="408922" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Samir-Patel-M.D.-.jpg" alt="Samir H. Patel, M.D." class="wp-image-408922" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Samir-Patel-M.D.-.jpg 506w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Samir-Patel-M.D.--300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Samir-Patel-M.D.--150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 506px) 100vw, 506px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Samir H. Patel, M.D.</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="634" height="634" data-id="408780" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Robert_L.-Foote-MD_10345060_201805080927-1x1-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-408780" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Robert_L.-Foote-MD_10345060_201805080927-1x1-1.jpg 634w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Robert_L.-Foote-MD_10345060_201805080927-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Robert_L.-Foote-MD_10345060_201805080927-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 634px) 100vw, 634px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Robert Foote, M.D.</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p><br>Study results found that proton beam therapy weakened the immune system by 15% less than photon therapy. It also lowered the risk of severe swallowing problems by 13% and reduced the need for feeding tubes by more than 13%.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>An unexpected outcome</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p>The treatments were similar in effectiveness in controlling cancer growth and spread, so Dr. Ma expected survival to be approximately the same, but the survival results were surprising.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Unexpectedly, we found that the overall survival at five years was 91% with proton therapy and 81% with photon therapy," he says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>These results weren't immediately apparent. "The survival benefit in our study didn't start separating out until three years and wasn't apparent until five years, so longer follow-up with patients was key," he says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Ma says this result is likely due to a variety of factors, including less toxicity and immune suppression. He adds, "Because of this, we feel strongly that proton therapy should be a standard treatment for oropharyngeal cancer patients who can tolerate and receive it."&nbsp;</p>



<p>"This study is important because it confirms what we believe to be true in many adult cancer cases: reducing toxicity has a meaningful impact on quality of life and long-term outcomes," says Dr. Laack. "As our treatments improve and our patients live longer, reducing toxicity and improving quality of life is more important than ever."&nbsp;</p>



<p>The study was led by The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center. Review the <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Furldefense.com%2Fv3%2F__https%3A%2F%2Fwww.thelancet.com%2Fjournals%2Flancet%2Farticle%2FPIIS0140-6736(25)01962-2%2Ffulltext__%3B!!PfbeBCCAmug!jnDZq-pUjzQbsU5dlBmAFEpCwre9G6iFA1VaUkmQGF1z5ncSfRCv0pMiz3zX2Uj5lZojXc2yfYftch8KpgvHnohk%24&amp;data=05%7C02%7CSaenz.Jessica%40mayo.edu%7C1071c402bd224fc3ef3908de3807aafd%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C639009802789540389%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=CSlDfEksVRnYlx%2FFQH9GEhjTXFn%2F2lVdPKTdypNVMnk%3D&amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&nbsp;</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D.,  Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/joint-study-finds-proton-beam-therapy-helps-patients-with-throat-cancer-live-longer-with-fewer-side-effects/">Joint study finds proton beam therapy helps patients with throat cancer live longer with fewer side effects&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/man-hiking-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Man-hiking-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Daniel Ma]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Robert Foote]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Proton Beam]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Throat Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researcher redefines the brain’s immune connection</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researcher-redefines-the-brains-immune-connection/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[mbroadfoot]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 23:31:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Neurosciences]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Translational Science]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Sarosh Irani]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=408450</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Early in his medical training, Sarosh Irani, B.M., B.Ch., D.Phil., met a patient who would change the course of his career. The woman, in her mid-30s, arrived at the hospital confused, trembling and wracked by seizures. She was losing her memory and her ability to walk. Yet unlike many with such severe neurological decline, she […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researcher-redefines-the-brains-immune-connection/">Mayo Clinic researcher redefines the brain’s immune connection</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Sarosh-Irani16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Photo of Dr. Sarosh Irani" class="wp-image-408538" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Sarosh-Irani16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Sarosh-Irani16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Sarosh-Irani16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Sarosh-Irani16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Sarosh-Irani16x9.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Sarosh Irani, B.M., B.Ch., D.Phil.</figcaption>



<p>Early in his medical training, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/irani-sarosh-r-b-m-b-ch-d-phil/bio-20557862" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sarosh Irani, B.M., B.Ch., D.Phil.</a>, met a patient who would change the course of his career. The woman, in her mid-30s, arrived at the hospital confused, trembling and wracked by seizures. She was losing her memory and her ability to walk. Yet unlike many with such severe neurological decline, she recovered completely.</p>



<p><a id="_msocom_1"></a>Her turnaround came after the clinical team discovered a particular antibody in her blood — proof that her immune system had attacked her brain. When they suppressed that immune response, her symptoms disappeared. The discovery not only changed that woman's life but also opened a window into a new, potentially reversible, facet of medicine — one in which the immune system itself could explain devastating brain diseases.</p>



<p>That revelation propelled Dr. Irani into a field that bridges neurology and immunology, one that continues to expand today from <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/irani-sarosh-r-b-m-b-ch-d-phil/bio-20557862" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">his laboratory at Mayo Clinic in Florida</a>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A burgeoning field</strong></h2>



<p>Dr. Irani's first passion was psychiatry. <a>"</a>I wanted to understand disorders of the mind," he recalls. But he found that the field lacked the molecular footholds that could make its mysteries scientifically tractable. “You couldn't put your hands on the biology,” he says. "There were too many inferences and not enough mechanisms."</p>



<p>He turned to neurology just as scientists were discovering that neurological conditions could, in fact, be autoimmune diseases.</p>



<p>Dr. Irani joined, and subsequently led, the University of Oxford's autoimmune neurology lab, where he helped identify several antibodies that define distinct syndromes — including the antibodies LGI1 and CASPR2, now standard diagnostic markers for treatable forms of various <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/autoimmune-encephalitis/doctors-departments/ddc-20576425?cjdata=MXxOfDB8WXww&amp;cjevent=37d20a1cc42311f0800404300a82b836&amp;cm_mmc=CJ-_-100357191-_-5250933-_-Evergreen+Link+for+Mayo+Clinic+Diet&amp;utm_source=cj&amp;utm_content=100357191&amp;utm_capaign=3-months" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">autoimmune neurological conditions</a>.</p>



<p>"What was once a medical curiosity has become a thriving field," says Dr. Irani, who came to Mayo Clinic in 2023. "Twenty years ago, there were no known antibodies affecting the brain. Now we know 20 or 30 such antibodies, and each one represents a potential cure."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Toward Precure</strong></h2>



<p>For Irani, these discoveries connect directly to Mayo Clinic's Precure initiative, which aims to predict and prevent disease before symptoms appear. "There are very few examples in medicine where we have a tractable handle on what's causing the disease," he explains. "Here we know the antibodies cause the disease. So the question is simple: How and why are they made? If we can work out causation, we can get close to pre-cure."</p>



<p>His lab is tackling that question through two complementary approaches: exploring patients' genetic predispositions and studying their immune cells. One variant, for example — in an HLA gene involved in presenting proteins to the immune system — <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/39454566/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">appears in more than 90 percent of patients</a> with a particular autoimmune neurological condition.</p>



<p>But genes alone do not tell the whole story. Irani suspects that environmental triggers, such as infections or even medications, act as the final push. "It's likely a multi-hit process," he says. "You need the gene, a misbehaving immune cell and an environmental spark."</p>



<p>His lab is studying patients' own immune cells to trace where this autoimmune process begins. Evidence increasingly points to the periphery, not the brain, as the starting point. That idea is supported by emerging research on the brain's lymphatic drainage system, which helps clear waste and immune molecules.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Early clues to autoimmunity</strong></h2>



<p>Recently, Dr. Irani and colleagues showed that biomarkers of neurodegeneration <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/39432679/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">can be detected in the lymph nodes</a> of the neck. These lymph nodes drain byproducts and proteins resulting from brain activity via a network of tiny lymphatic vessels.</p>



<p>Using ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration — a quick sampling technique similar to drawing blood — the team measured several proteins including amyloid beta and tau, proteins that build up in <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/alzheimers-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350447" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alzheimer's disease</a>, as well as other markers of brain cell health. They found that almost all of these proteins were found in much higher quantities in the lymph nodes than in the blood, especially one called phosphorylated tau (pTau181), which was 266 times more concentrated.</p>



<p>Strikingly, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/39432679/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pTau181 levels in lymph nodes decreased with age</a>, suggesting that the brain's ability to clear toxic proteins through lymphatic drainage declines over time — potentially contributing to diseases like Alzheimer's. The discovery also challenges one of medicine's oldest assumptions: that the brain is "immune-privileged" and largely sealed off from the body's immune system.</p>



<p>"This is the first direct evidence that brain proteins accumulate in cervical lymph nodes in living people," says Dr. Irani. "It opens up a minimally invasive way to study how the brain clears waste — and how that process falters with age."</p>



<p>Lymph node aspiration is far less invasive than spinal taps, yet it could offer powerful insight into brain health, aging, and disease progression.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Brain on fire</strong></h2>



<p>Dr. Irani's research has come full circle with a new <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanpsy/article/PIIS2215-0366(25)00305-0/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> in The Lancet Psychiatry. The research focuses on patients with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/autoimmune-encephalitis/doctors-departments/ddc-20576425?cjdata=MXxOfDB8WXww&amp;cjevent=37d20a1cc42311f0800404300a82b836&amp;cm_mmc=CJ-_-100357191-_-5250933-_-Evergreen+Link+for+Mayo+Clinic+Diet&amp;utm_source=cj&amp;utm_content=100357191&amp;utm_capaign=3-months" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">autoimmune encephalitis</a> — a condition popularized by the book and movie "Brain on Fire"— whose illnesses often first appear to be psychiatric. The work shows that these patients can be distinguished from others by a simple scoring system based on how rapidly symptoms appear and how they evolve.</p>



<p>"It's a mixture of symptoms — depression, anxiety, psychosis, sleep and eating disturbances — all unfolding over days," he says. "If clinicians recognize that pattern early, we can treat it before irreversible brain injury occurs."</p>



<p>Current therapies for <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/autoimmune-encephalitis/doctors-departments/ddc-20576425?cjdata=MXxOfDB8WXww&amp;cjevent=37d20a1cc42311f0800404300a82b836&amp;cm_mmc=CJ-_-100357191-_-5250933-_-Evergreen+Link+for+Mayo+Clinic+Diet&amp;utm_source=cj&amp;utm_content=100357191&amp;utm_capaign=3-months" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">autoimmune encephalitis</a> rely on broad immunosuppression — powerful drugs that quiet the entire immune system and leave patients vulnerable to infection. Dr. Irani envisions a more refined approach that involves the selective silencing of only the harmful immune cells while preserving the rest.</p>



<p>"We want to pick off just the bits causing trouble," he says. "If we can identify exactly what the immune system is attacking, we can teach it tolerance only to that target."</p>



<p>That vision, he believes, could extend to other conditions where the immune system plays a role, potentially informing treatments for dementia, cancer and even common psychiatric disorders. "We're trying to translate these observations to more widespread diseases," he says. "There's enormous potential."</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity">



<p><a id="_msocom_1"></a></p>



<p><a id="_msocom_2"></a></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researcher-redefines-the-brains-immune-connection/">Mayo Clinic researcher redefines the brain’s immune connection</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Sarosh-Irani1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Sarosh-Irani16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Sarosh Irani]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers find new hope for toughest myeloma through off-the-shelf immunotherapy&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-find-new-hope-for-toughest-myeloma-through-off-the-shelf-immunotherapy/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[jftmayo]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 21:16:18 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Shaji Kumar]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=408813</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — A new Mayo Clinic study published in the New England Journal of Medicine has uncovered that an off-the-shelf, dual-antibody therapy can generate deep and durable responses in extramedullary multiple myeloma — one of the most aggressive and treatment-resistant forms of the disease.&nbsp; "We are seeing powerful responses in a disease that historically […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-find-new-hope-for-toughest-myeloma-through-off-the-shelf-immunotherapy/">Mayo Clinic researchers find new hope for toughest myeloma through off-the-shelf immunotherapy&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/05/Myeloma16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-273595" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/05/Myeloma16x9.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/05/Myeloma16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/05/Myeloma16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p><br>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A new Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMoa2514752" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> published in the New England Journal of Medicine has uncovered that an off-the-shelf, dual-antibody therapy can generate deep and durable responses in extramedullary <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/multiple-myeloma/symptoms-causes/syc-20353378" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">multiple myeloma</a> — one of the most aggressive and treatment-resistant forms of the disease.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"We are seeing powerful responses in a disease that historically has resisted every therapy," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/kumar-shaji-m-d/bio-00027411" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Shaji Kumar, M.D.</a>, a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> hematologist and senior author of the study. "By recruiting T cells in two distinct ways at once, this dual-target antibody strategy can generate responses in patients who have had very few effective options."&nbsp; </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="891" height="891" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Kumar-Shaji-K.-MD_12620637_201304290337-1x1-1.jpg" alt="Shaji Kumar, M.D." class="wp-image-408817" style="width:266px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Kumar-Shaji-K.-MD_12620637_201304290337-1x1-1.jpg 891w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Kumar-Shaji-K.-MD_12620637_201304290337-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Kumar-Shaji-K.-MD_12620637_201304290337-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Kumar-Shaji-K.-MD_12620637_201304290337-1x1-1-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 891px) 100vw, 891px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Shaji Kumar, M.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>The approach combines two engineered antibodies, talquetamab and teclistamab, that simultaneously engage T cells and force them to attack myeloma cells through two separate immune pathways. Unlike CAR-T cell therapy, which requires custom manufacturing, this regimen is delivered as a standard infusion-center injection.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In a trial involving 90 patients, 79% responded to treatment, and 54% achieved no detectable disease by imaging or blood testing. Among responders, nearly two-thirds maintained disease control at one year, a striking improvement for a subtype that typically carries a months-long prognosis.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This is the first large, prospective study defined specifically by PET/MRI scan and focused exclusively on true extramedullary myeloma, not a mix of para- and extramedullary disease. Serious side effects were common. Infection was one serious side effect and underscores the importance of comprehensive supportive care alongside immunotherapy.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The next big questions are whether this dual-target strategy can be moved earlier in the disease course, how safety can be optimized further through infection monitoring and prevention, and whether similar "two-locks, one-key" immune designs can be applied to other hard-to-treat cancers.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding, review the <a href="https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMoa2514752" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>###&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic&nbsp;</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong>&nbsp;<br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the National Cancer Institute, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo<strong> </strong>Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:&nbsp;</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-find-new-hope-for-toughest-myeloma-through-off-the-shelf-immunotherapy/">Mayo Clinic researchers find new hope for toughest myeloma through off-the-shelf immunotherapy&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Kumar-Shaji-K.-MD_12620637_201304290337-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/05/Myeloma16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Shaji Kumar]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic scientist uses AI, wearables and implants to decode brain rhythms and forecast seizures&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-scientist-uses-ai-wearables-and-implants-to-decode-brain-rhythms-and-forecast-seizures/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Susan Murphy]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 11:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[AI and Digital Health]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Discovery Science]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Benjamin Brinkmann]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Epilepsy seizures]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=407767</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->At Mayo Clinic, biomedical engineer Benjamin Brinkmann, Ph.D., is developing tools and technologies that help reveal brain patterns — making epileptic seizures more predictable and, one day, preventable.&nbsp; In a neurology lab at Mayo Clinic, Dr. Benjamin Brinkmann studies the brain's electrical rhythms across days, weeks and months — searching for patterns that reveal when […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-scientist-uses-ai-wearables-and-implants-to-decode-brain-rhythms-and-forecast-seizures/">Mayo Clinic scientist uses AI, wearables and implants to decode brain rhythms and forecast seizures&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/16x9-Dr.Brinkmann3-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-407903" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/16x9-Dr.Brinkmann3-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/16x9-Dr.Brinkmann3-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/16x9-Dr.Brinkmann3-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/16x9-Dr.Brinkmann3-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/16x9-Dr.Brinkmann3.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">At Mayo Clinic, biomedical engineer Benjamin Brinkmann, Ph.D., is developing tools and technologies that help reveal brain patterns — making epileptic seizures more predictable and, one day, preventable.&nbsp;</h2>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>In a neurology lab at Mayo Clinic, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/brinkmann-benjamin-h-ph-d/bio-20482796" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Benjamin Brinkmann</a> studies the brain's electrical rhythms across days, weeks and months — searching for patterns that reveal when seizures are most likely to occur. Working with neuroscientists and clinicians, he combines data from brain waves, vital signs and imaging to develop tools that interpret those signals and help guide patient care.&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/epilepsy/symptoms-causes/syc-20350093" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Epilepsy</a> is a brain disorder that causes recurring seizures — sudden bursts of electrical activity that can interrupt movement, speech or awareness. About 3.4 million people in the U.S. live with the condition. For many, medication keeps seizures under control. But for those with drug-resistant epilepsy, the episodes can occur without warning — disrupting routines and independence.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Brinkmann, a biomedical engineer, has dedicated his career to improving care for people with epilepsy. Working with Mayo Clinic's epilepsy team, he helps identify where seizures begin in the brain — essential information&nbsp;for those whose epilepsy is difficult to control. His long-term goal is to move from forecasting seizures to stopping them before they start.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A clearer picture of epilepsy, one signal at a time</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0001-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-407907" style="width:362px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0001-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0001-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0001-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0001-1536x1025.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0001-2048x1366.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Brinkmann holds one of the small implant devices used to record brain activity.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>One example of that work is a <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/epi.18566" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> Dr. Brinkmann led with international collaborators. They tested a small implant that sits just under the skin behind the ear, recording brain activity as people go about their day. The device helps provide a more accurate picture than seizure diaries, which can miss or misclassify episodes.&nbsp;Accurate and continuous monitoring helps doctors track seizure patterns and adjust treatment. </p>



<p>Over 15 months, the team collected more than 72,000 hours of brainwave data from people with epilepsy. They recorded 754 seizures — nearly twice as many as were reported in diaries. About half of the study participants wore the device more than 20 hours a day and reported it did not interfere with daily life. The findings suggest that long-term, at-home brain monitoring can uncover seizure patterns missed in short clinic visits.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Smartwatch uses AI to forecast seizures</strong>&nbsp;</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0040-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-407909" style="width:374px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0040-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0040-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0040-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0040-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0040-2048x1366.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Brinkmann holds a smartwatch used to study patterns that may signal when a seizure is likely to occur.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>Dr. Brinkmann also led a study on wearable technology — a smartwatch that uses artificial intelligence to help forecast seizures before they happen.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The watch tracks heart rate, movement, skin conductance and temperature, using machine learning to help clinicians find patterns that may signal a seizure. In findings <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/40411751/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">published</a> in Epilepsia, the team correctly predicted about 75% of seizures, with few false alarms.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Brinkmann says the idea is simple: to give people a warning. A few minutes' notice can mean calling a caregiver, sitting down or avoiding a risky activity. In the future, those alerts could even trigger treatments automatically, using medication or gentle brain stimulation when seizure risk is high.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Building the future of epilepsy care</strong></h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0019-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-407912" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0019-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0019-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0019-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0019-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/WF8005050_0019-2048x1366.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>Together, the implant and smartwatch studies show what's possible when brain activity can be tracked continuously. The research is opening a new window into how seizures develop and helping shape the next generation of neurotechnology at Mayo Clinic.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Brinkmann's work contributes to Mayo's BIONIC program — short for Bioelectronics Neuromodulation Innovation to Cure — which unites scientists and clinicians to develop smarter, more responsive technologies and therapeutics for the brain, spine and nervous system. The goal is ambitious: systems that can sense trouble and respond instantly to stop it.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In Dr. Brinkmann's lab, every signal adds to that future — each one bringing a clearer picture of epilepsy and what care might look like in the years ahead.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-scientist-uses-ai-wearables-and-implants-to-decode-brain-rhythms-and-forecast-seizures/">Mayo Clinic scientist uses AI, wearables and implants to decode brain rhythms and forecast seizures&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/1x1-Dr.Brinkmann.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/16x9-Dr.Brinkmann3.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Benjamin Brinkmann]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Epilepsy seizures]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Small team, big impact: Automation helps relieve symptoms to keep cancer patients out of the ER&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/small-team-big-impact-automation-helps-relieve-symptoms-to-keep-cancer-patients-out-of-the-er/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[brandywelvaert]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 17:17:52 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[remote care]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Telehealth]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=408565</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — For many people living with cancer, symptoms such as pain, anxiety or insomnia can quickly spiral into an emergency room visit. Such visits can be financially costly and take an emotional toll on patients and their caregivers.&nbsp;&nbsp; A new study led by Mayo Clinic researchers found that using digital check-ins and a […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/small-team-big-impact-automation-helps-relieve-symptoms-to-keep-cancer-patients-out-of-the-er/">Small team, big impact: Automation helps relieve symptoms to keep cancer patients out of the ER&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1425" height="802" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Woman-using-tablet-virutal-visit-telehealth-WF5002214-16x9-1.jpg" alt="Woman using tablet virutal visit telehealth" class="wp-image-408580" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Woman-using-tablet-virutal-visit-telehealth-WF5002214-16x9-1.jpg 1425w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Woman-using-tablet-virutal-visit-telehealth-WF5002214-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Woman-using-tablet-virutal-visit-telehealth-WF5002214-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Woman-using-tablet-virutal-visit-telehealth-WF5002214-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1425px) 100vw, 1425px">



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — For many people living with cancer, symptoms such as pain, anxiety or insomnia can quickly spiral into an emergency room visit. Such visits can be financially costly and take an emotional toll on patients and their caregivers.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>A new <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1470204525005261?dgcid=author" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> led by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> researchers found that using digital check-ins and a remote care team can help patients manage symptoms before they reach a crisis point. </p>



<p>"Our goal was simple but ambitious," says study lead <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/cheville-andrea-l-m-d/bio-20054964" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Andrea Cheville, M.D.</a>, professor of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation in the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>. "We wanted to see if automating symptom check-ins and care through the electronic health record could improve patients' lives without adding to the burden on oncology teams. What we found is that this approach not only eased symptoms like anxiety and depression but also kept thousands of patients out of the hospital. That tells us technology can help us successfully extend the reach and efficacy of care."&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Becky-Johnson-1024x1024.jpg" alt="Image of Becky Johnson" class="wp-image-408577" style="width:234px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Becky-Johnson-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Becky-Johnson-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Becky-Johnson-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Becky-Johnson-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Becky-Johnson.jpg 1402w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Becky Johnson</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>For Becky Johnson, participating in the Enhanced EHR-Facilitated Cancer Symptom Control Trial (E2C2) meant better sleep — despite the anxiety she felt about her double breast cancer diagnosis in 2022 at the age of 40.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"I was continually Googling for more information about treatments, prognosis, new terminology and the experiences of others. And the steroid medications I took for treatment prior to chemo messed with my ability to sleep, too. It got to a point where my body's norm was to wake in the middle of the night and not fall back asleep, taking a toll on my ability to heal," says Johnson, program director for the Mayo Clinic School of Health Sciences Sonography Program.&nbsp;</p>



<p>As part of the trial, Johnson regularly submitted digital surveys about various aspects of her health. Insomnia quickly rose to the top, prompting a phone call from a nurse, who counseled Johnson on ways to get a better night's rest. The nurse also gave Johnson a link to a self-paced online class with sleep strategies based in cognitive behavioral therapy.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>"A virtual or phone call visit, especially when I didn't have anything physically wrong, was so convenient and efficient," says Johnson. The intervention helped, and her sleep improved.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>To make such interventions possible, the researchers developed automations in the Plummer Chart, the software system that manages patients' electronic health records (EHRs) and helps Mayo teams coordinate care. Between 2019 and 2023, just over 50,200 patients across 15 cancer specialties at Mayo Clinic enrolled in the E2C2 trial. Like Johnson, they filled out short surveys about pain, fatigue, sleep, anxiety and other symptoms before clinic visits or monthly between visits. The system automatically sorted their responses. Mild scores were simply logged, moderate ones triggered the system to send the patient self-care tips, and severe scores prompted outreach by a remote symptom care manager — a nurse or social worker who could work with patients via phone or video.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Behind the scenes, the software became both an automated traffic controller and safety net. For care teams, it routed information to patients automatically so they could focus on the work that required their expertise. For patients, it made getting support easier, with no additional appointments or travel.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The trial results showed that the automated surveys and responses built into the EHR made care more efficient and, ultimately, improved patients' symptoms.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Patients reported less anxiety and depression, with modest improvements in other symptoms.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Patients had 40% to 60% fewer acute care encounters, including emergency visits, hospitalizations, and ICU admissions.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>All of this was achieved with just 2-3 full-time care managers plus 20 percent of one physician's time supporting more than 50,000 study participants.&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/E2C2-by-the-numbers-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-408582" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/E2C2-by-the-numbers-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/E2C2-by-the-numbers-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/E2C2-by-the-numbers-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/E2C2-by-the-numbers-16x9-1.jpg 1216w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>The E2C2 trial showcases a new approach to using digital tools in cancer care. By automating routine monitoring and triaging of patient symptoms and well-being through the patient's electronic health record, a small care team can support a large patient population.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"The gains we saw are encouraging and point to a scalable way to extend supportive oncology care beyond the clinic walls, meeting patients where they are," says Dr. Cheville. "The next step is to ensure that these tools are available to healthcare teams, enabling them to efficiently reach every patient who needs supportive care."&nbsp;</p>



<p>The E2C2 trial was funded by the National Institutes of Health, National Cancer Institute (NCI) as part of the Cancer Moonshot℠. The study was conducted as part of NCI’s&nbsp;<a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fhealthcaredelivery.cancer.gov%2Fimpact%2F&amp;data=05%7C02%7CBalzer.Deborah%40mayo.edu%7C32ad8f9097f44a79dade08de31cf67a4%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C639002964016473569%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=PfYTCOPOQQtlt%2FzAf3hJYhlfoTq9PfsLjZ9kJIhcfOs%3D&amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">IMPACT Consortium</a>. Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.sciencedirect.com%2Fscience%2Farticle%2Fpii%2FS1470204525005261%3Fdgcid%3Dauthor&amp;data=05%7C02%7CBalzer.Deborah%40mayo.edu%7C32ad8f9097f44a79dade08de31cf67a4%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C639002964016484368%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=WBpwE%2F4Kjpd%2BPhjAnPAKO1hQd9x42DBJZqBVeMBv0Ew%3D&amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and additional funding.</p>



<p>###&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> &nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>  is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.  &nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong> &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a> &nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/small-team-big-impact-automation-helps-relieve-symptoms-to-keep-cancer-patients-out-of-the-er/">Small team, big impact: Automation helps relieve symptoms to keep cancer patients out of the ER&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Woman-using-tablet-virutal-visit-telehealth-WF5002214-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Woman-using-tablet-virutal-visit-telehealth-WF5002214-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[remote care]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Telehealth]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers develop 3D scanning approach for ultra-precise brain surgery&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-3d-scanning-tool-for-ultra-precise-brain-surgery/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Susan Murphy]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 14:30:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Neurosciences]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jaeyun Sung]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Kendall Lee]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=405460</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. —&nbsp;Mayo Clinic&nbsp;researchers&nbsp;have developed and tested a new 3D surface scanning approach that gives neurosurgeons even greater precision when&nbsp;operating&nbsp;deep inside the brain.&nbsp;&nbsp; The system aligns a patient's head, facial&nbsp;features&nbsp;and surgical head frame with brain images, achieving sub-millimeter accuracy — a level of precision that can make a critical difference in delicate procedures.&nbsp; In a […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-3d-scanning-tool-for-ultra-precise-brain-surgery/">Mayo Clinic researchers develop 3D scanning approach for ultra-precise brain surgery&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/16x93d-surface-scanning-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-405462" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/16x93d-surface-scanning-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/16x93d-surface-scanning-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/16x93d-surface-scanning-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/16x93d-surface-scanning-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/16x93d-surface-scanning.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. —&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;researchers&nbsp;have developed and tested a new 3D surface scanning approach that gives neurosurgeons even greater precision when&nbsp;operating&nbsp;deep inside the brain.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The system aligns a patient's head, facial&nbsp;features&nbsp;and surgical head frame with brain images, achieving sub-millimeter accuracy — a level of precision that can make a critical difference in delicate procedures.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In a feasibility study&nbsp;<a href="https://thejns.org/view/journals/j-neurosurg/aop/article-10.3171-2025.7.JNS25870/article-10.3171-2025.7.JNS25870.xml" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">published</a>&nbsp;in the Journal of Neurosurgery, the 3D scanning method proved more&nbsp;accurate&nbsp;than the CT scan typically used during neurosurgery, all while eliminating&nbsp;exposure to radiation.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Researchers say the approach could make complex procedures, such as deep brain stimulation, drainage and biopsies safer and more efficient, while enhancing patient comfort. Because it&nbsp;integrates with&nbsp;most surgical navigation systems, it may also bring high-precision guidance to operating rooms that&nbsp;don't&nbsp;have a CT scanner.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>How the new 3D approach works</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p>Using cameras and structured-light scanning, the new system creates high-resolution 3D models of the patient's face and the surgical frame that keeps the head still. It merges these images into a detailed spatial “map” of the patient's position in the operating room. That map is then matched with pre-surgery brain scans, such as MRI or CT images, giving surgeons precise, real-time guidance to reach the exact target in the brain.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>In the study, the system's computer analysis aligned images with an average precision of&nbsp;0.14 millimeters&nbsp;— compared with about&nbsp;0.20 millimeters&nbsp;typically achieved with CT scans. The difference is&nbsp;roughly the&nbsp;width of a pencil tip, but in delicate brain surgery, that fraction can be enough to affect accuracy.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Teamwork behind the breakthrough</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-core-columns-is-layout-28f84493 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="683" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF4998388_0352-2-683x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-408511" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF4998388_0352-2-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF4998388_0352-2-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF4998388_0352-2-768x1151.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF4998388_0352-2-1025x1536.jpg 1025w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF4998388_0352-2-1366x2048.jpg 1366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 683px) 100vw, 683px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Jaeyun Sung</figcaption></figure>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="683" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7460775_0016-683x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-408510" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7460775_0016-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7460775_0016-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7460775_0016-768x1151.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7460775_0016-1025x1536.jpg 1025w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF7460775_0016-1366x2048.jpg 1366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 683px) 100vw, 683px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Kendall Lee</figcaption></figure>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="682" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF3617753_0156-1-682x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-408513" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF3617753_0156-1-682x1024.jpg 682w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF3617753_0156-1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF3617753_0156-1-768x1154.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF3617753_0156-1-1023x1536.jpg 1023w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/WF3617753_0156-1-1364x2048.jpg 1364w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 682px) 100vw, 682px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Basel Sharaf</figcaption></figure>
</div>
</div>



<p>The project combined Mayo Clinic's engineering and surgical expertise.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/sung-jaeyun-ph-d/bio-20320110" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jaeyun Sung, Ph.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic computational biologist, clinical AI researcher and corresponding author, led the engineering and computational work. Dr. Sung focuses on using engineering and computer science to develop advanced precision medicine tools for patient care.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>"When engineers and neurosurgeons look at the same challenge, we see different details, and that's where breakthroughs can happen," Dr. Sung says. "This is about building the next generation of surgical tools that bring engineering-level, sub-millimeter precision directly into the operating room."&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/lee-kendall-h-m-d-ph-d/bio-00027489" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kendall Lee, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic neurosurgeon, led the surgical integration of the technology and said it could make a real difference for patients and improve his practice.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Some of the most important steps in neurosurgery happen before we even begin the operation," Dr. Lee says. "This new 3D scanning method is safe, quick and cost-effective, and it can help us hit the right target more accurately, improving how we care for patients."&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/sharaf-basel-a-m-d-d-d-s/bio-20575285" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Basel Sharaf, M.D., D.D.S.</a>, a Mayo Clinic surgeon and lead author of the study, sees even greater possibilities ahead&nbsp;for&nbsp;the technology.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>"In the future, 3D surface scanning could be as simple as using a smartphone," Dr. Sharaf says. "With advanced AI, the system could adapt in real time, even predicting small shifts in the brain to help surgeons work with greater accuracy and a smoother workflow."&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Next Steps: Advancing automation,&nbsp;AI&nbsp;and clinical validation</strong></h2>



<p>The team is now working to add automation and artificial intelligence to help make the process faster and easier to use. They are also testing new hardware and running a larger clinical trial to further evaluate the technique's effectiveness in brain surgery.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://thejns.org/view/journals/j-neurosurg/aop/article-10.3171-2025.7.JNS25870/article-10.3171-2025.7.JNS25870.xml" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors,&nbsp;disclosures&nbsp;and funding.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact</strong>:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Tia Ford, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-3d-scanning-tool-for-ultra-precise-brain-surgery/">Mayo Clinic researchers develop 3D scanning approach for ultra-precise brain surgery&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/1x1-3D-surface-scanning.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/16x93d-surface-scanning.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jaeyun Sung]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Kendall Lee]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers identify why some lung tumors respond well to immunotherapy</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-why-some-lung-tumors-respond-well-to-immunotherapy/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Kate Ledger]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 15:18:48 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Education]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Cycle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Alan Fields]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Lung Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=408439</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. —&nbsp;For some patients with the most common type of lung cancer, known as lung adenocarcinoma, there's new hope.&nbsp;In a new study published in Cell Reports,&nbsp;Mayo Clinic&nbsp;researchers have found several previously unknown genetic and cellular processes that occur in lung adenocarcinoma tumors that respond well to immunotherapy. A recently approved group of drugs — […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-why-some-lung-tumors-respond-well-to-immunotherapy/">Mayo Clinic researchers identify why some lung tumors respond well to immunotherapy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-left-align-caption"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Virtual-lung-image-Getty1439259946-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Virtual, digital lung image" class="wp-image-408433" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Virtual-lung-image-Getty1439259946-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Virtual-lung-image-Getty1439259946-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Virtual-lung-image-Getty1439259946-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Virtual-lung-image-Getty1439259946-16X9.jpg 1342w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Getty image</figcaption>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. —&nbsp;For some patients with the most common type of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lung-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20374620" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lung cancer</a>, known as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/in-depth/adenocarcinoma/art-20580469" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lung adenocarcinoma</a>, there's new hope.&nbsp;In a new <a href="https://www.cell.com/cell-reports/fulltext/S2211-1247(25)01378-6" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> published in Cell Reports,&nbsp;Mayo Clinic&nbsp;researchers have found several previously unknown genetic and cellular processes that occur in lung adenocarcinoma tumors that respond well to immunotherapy.</p>



<p>A recently approved group of drugs — immune checkpoint inhibitors — can boost the body's ability to eliminate a tumor and even keep the cancer from coming back. However, while the medications work well for some people, the drugs aren't effective for many other patients with the disease — and researchers are trying to determine why.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Fields-Alan-P._14202000_20221121-1x1-1-1024x1024.jpg" alt="Alan Fields, Ph.D." class="wp-image-408396" style="width:290px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Fields-Alan-P._14202000_20221121-1x1-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Fields-Alan-P._14202000_20221121-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Fields-Alan-P._14202000_20221121-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Fields-Alan-P._14202000_20221121-1x1-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Fields-Alan-P._14202000_20221121-1x1-1-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Fields-Alan-P._14202000_20221121-1x1-1-2048x2048.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Alan Fields, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>"Our study describes the events that occur when a patient's tumor harbors only one copy of a cancer-causing gene, which occurs in 20% of cases," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/fields-alan-p-ph-d/bio-00028181" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alan P. Fields, Ph.D.</a>, a cancer biologist at&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;and the principal investigator of the study.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The research team found that the missing tumor-driving gene, known as PRKCI, results in tumors that are less aggressive. The missing gene also cultivates a more powerful immune response to tumors. Surprisingly, the research team found the improved immune response occurs with help from unexpected players: senescent tumor cells, also known as "<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-new-tool-to-find-hidden-zombie-cells/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">zombie cells</a>," which are typically associated with negative consequences of disease and aging.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1188" height="1188" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Nguyen-Duy-T-Joey-30027902_202008250413-1x1-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-408544" style="width:190px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Nguyen-Duy-T-Joey-30027902_202008250413-1x1-1.jpg 1188w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Nguyen-Duy-T-Joey-30027902_202008250413-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Nguyen-Duy-T-Joey-30027902_202008250413-1x1-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Nguyen-Duy-T-Joey-30027902_202008250413-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/12/Nguyen-Duy-T-Joey-30027902_202008250413-1x1-1-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1188px) 100vw, 1188px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Joey Nguyen</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>The study identified markers that may predict a positive response to immunotherapy and "ultimately may help clinicians stratify patients who are candidates for immune checkpoint inhibitors," says Joey Nguyen, a graduate student at&nbsp;<a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/phd-program/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a>&nbsp;and lead author of the publication.&nbsp;</p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Addressing the nation's leading cause of cancer death</strong></h2>



<p>Lung adenocarcinoma&nbsp;represents 40% of lung cancers in the U.S. and is the leading cause of cancer death. It's strongly associated with smoking, but it's also the most common type of lung cancer to occur in people who have never smoked, likely because of a combination of genetics and other environmental factors.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Fields' lab at Mayo Clinic in Florida has long studied the effect of the PRKCI gene, which drives tumor growth. The gene also suppresses the immune system, keeping cancer-killing immune cells at bay. Because lung tumors depend on the gene to proliferate, Dr. Fields' team was surprised to find that in cases where a copy of the gene is missing, lung adenocarcinoma tumors still occur. Nguyen, who was studying PRKCI in the lab, was inspired to try to learn more about those unusual tumors.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Early experiments found that the tumors without PRKCI grow less aggressively. The team also found that when PRKCI is missing, lung adenocarcinoma cells behave in an unusual way in their very early development, acquiring characteristics of lung cells that regenerate lung tissue after damage.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The team collaborated with the lab of systems biology researcher&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/li-hu-ph-d/bio-20035057" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hu Li, Ph.D.</a>, to examine the process at a single cell level. "We found that the loss of PRKCI forces tumor cells to hijack a lung regeneration process to generate a tumor," Nguyen says.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Tracking the effects of a missing gene</strong></h2>



<p>Nguyen also noticed that the tumors without PRKCI showed elevated levels of organized clusters of immune cells, called tertiary lymphoid structures. The presence of those clumped cells can be a sign that immune checkpoint therapy might work for a patient. But were they a result of the single copy of the PRKCI gene?&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="608" height="608" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Prieto-Luis_20129157_20230508.-1x1-1.jpg" alt="Luis Prieto, Ph.D." class="wp-image-408395" style="width:184px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Prieto-Luis_20129157_20230508.-1x1-1.jpg 608w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Prieto-Luis_20129157_20230508.-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Prieto-Luis_20129157_20230508.-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Luis Prieto, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>Nguyen presented his research at a graduate school seminar where the project caught the attention of postdoctoral fellow Luis Prieto, Ph.D., who had an idea. Dr. Prieto wondered whether the clusters of immune cells might be connected in some way to senescent cells, those that enter a state of arrested development and don't die off. Dr. Prieto works in the lab of researcher&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/baker-darren-j-ph-d-m-s/bio-00027985" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Darren Baker, Ph.D.</a>, who investigates therapies to eliminate senescent cells in various disease processes. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="634" height="634" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Baker-Darren-J.-MS-PhD_13844491_201606011129-1x1-1.jpg" alt="Darren Baker, Ph.D." class="wp-image-408392" style="width:186px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Baker-Darren-J.-MS-PhD_13844491_201606011129-1x1-1.jpg 634w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Baker-Darren-J.-MS-PhD_13844491_201606011129-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Baker-Darren-J.-MS-PhD_13844491_201606011129-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 634px) 100vw, 634px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Darren Baker, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>The collaborating labs were amazed to find that senescent tumor cells actually activate the immune system, leading to the clusters of immune cells that combat the tumor. "The idea that senescent cells may be beneficial in certain settings like this is new to the field, as these 'zombies' are commonly associated with detrimental outcomes," says Dr. Baker, who is a co-corresponding author on the study. </p>



<p>The findings reveal three tumor characteristics that may be used to help clinicians identify candidates for immune checkpoint inhibitors: loss of the PRKCI gene, the presence of senescent tumor cells and an abundance of clustered immune cells.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Further, says Dr. Fields, his team previously identified an approved drug that can inhibit PRKCI signaling, making a tumor that has the PRKCI gene act more like a tumor without it.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Now that we understand how PRKCI is working in a lung tumor, it may be possible to couple a PRKCI inhibitor with immunotherapy, so a future clinical trial that combines these approaches will certainly be an important avenue to explore," he says.</p>



<p>See the <a href="https://www.cell.com/cell-reports/fulltext/S2211-1247(25)01378-6" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact</strong>:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Julie Ferris-Tillman, Ph.D., Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-why-some-lung-tumors-respond-well-to-immunotherapy/">Mayo Clinic researchers identify why some lung tumors respond well to immunotherapy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Virtual-lung-image-Getty1439259946-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/11/Virtual-lung-image-Getty1439259946-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Alan Fields]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Lung Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</atom:link></channel>
</rss> 