<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Research - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 13:08:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers link CAR-T cell aging to cancer relapse&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-link-car-t-cell-aging-to-cancer-relapse/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Discovery Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individualized Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Ismail Can]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Saad Kendarian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=404713</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic researchers have discovered a key reason some cancer patients relapse after receiving chimeric antigen receptor T-cell therapy, or CAR-T cell therapy. Over time, the engineered immune cells age and lose their ability to fight cancer. &amp;#160; Published in Molecular Cancer, the study identifies this aging process, known as senescence, as [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-link-car-t-cell-aging-to-cancer-relapse/">Mayo Clinic researchers link CAR-T cell aging to cancer relapse&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-video"><video autoplay controls loop muted src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/GettyImages-1808335875.mp4" playsinline></video></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> researchers have discovered a key reason some cancer patients relapse after receiving chimeric antigen receptor T-cell therapy, or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/car-t-cell-therapy/about/pac-20585020" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CAR-T cell therapy</a>. Over time, the engineered immune cells age and lose their ability to fight cancer. &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://molecular-cancer.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12943-025-02371-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Published</a> in Molecular Cancer, the study identifies this aging process, known as senescence, as a previously unrecognized mechanism of CAR-T failure.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The researchers also showed that senescence is influenced by how CAR-T cells are engineered. Certain intracellular features — such as how the cell recognizes cancer and how strongly it activates — can overwork the cells. The researchers found that if the activation signal is too intense or prolonged, it can push CAR-T cells into premature aging. &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The discovery may guide the development of next-generation CAR-T therapies that last longer and are more effective across a broader range of cancers. &amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF5259875_0007-1-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-404717" style="width:431px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF5259875_0007-1-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF5259875_0007-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF5259875_0007-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF5259875_0007-1-1536x1025.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF5259875_0007-1-2048x1366.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Saad Kenderian, MB, ChB, Hematology consultant, and Chimeric Antigen Receptor (CAR) T Cell Engineering Laboratory lead, poses in the CAR T Cell Engineering Laboratory.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"This is one of the most clinically relevant discoveries we've made because it doesn't just explain the cause of relapse, it gives us a biological target to possibly prevent it," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/kenderian-saad-j-m-b-ch-b/bio-20206512" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Saad Kenderian, M.B., Ch.B.</a>, a principal investigator and hematologist at Mayo Clinic. &nbsp;</p>



<p>CAR-T therapy reprograms a patient's own immune cells to recognize and destroy cancer. It has led to long-term remission for patients, including some with aggressive or treatment-resistant diseases. But many patients eventually relapse, and the causes have remained poorly understood.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Modeling CAR-T cell stress over time</strong>&amp;nbsp;</h2>



<p>To investigate why CAR-T therapy can fail, the Mayo team developed a novel lab model that simulates long-term biological stress, offering a clearer view of how the engineered cells behave after infusion. Over time, some CAR-T cells lost their ability to multiply and attack cancer. Specifically, they showed hallmark signs of senescence, including distinct genetic changes. &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The researchers found that senescence occurred more often in CAR-T cells built with a signaling feature, known as 4-1BB, which affects how the cells respond to cancer. In comparison, cells designed with an alternative domain, called CD28, were less affected by aging. These cells activate more quickly and persist for a shorter time, reducing the cumulative stress that drives senescence. </p>



<p>The researchers confirmed the results in multiple laboratory models and validated them in patient samples.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Engineering CAR-T cells for longevity</strong>&amp;nbsp;</h2>



<p>That discovery was driven in part by the work of Ismail Can, Ph.D., who helped lead the molecular analysis behind the finding.&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="683" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/DR.CAN_-683x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-404740" style="width:222px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/DR.CAN_-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/DR.CAN_-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/DR.CAN_-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/DR.CAN_-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/DR.CAN_-1365x2048.jpg 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 683px) 100vw, 683px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Ismail Can, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Efforts to make CAR-T cell therapy more durable will likely fail without fully understanding the reasons behind CAR-T cell failure. This study represents a significant step toward understanding why CAR-T cells fail," says Dr. Can, first author of the study and a senior research fellow at Mayo Clinic’s T&amp;nbsp;Cell Engineering Laboratory. "By identifying the early molecular triggers of senescence, we can begin to refine CAR-T design to potentially improve long-term function and reduce relapse."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The findings highlight a new direction for CAR-T research, with potential implications not only for blood cancers but also for expanding cell therapy into solid tumors. &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The study builds on Dr. Kenderian's broader efforts to identify resistance mechanisms and design more durable and personalized immunotherapies. &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>This work was supported in part by Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, the Eagles 5th District Cancer Telethon Funds for Cancer Research, the State of Minnesota, and benefactors Georgia and Michael Michelson. For a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding information, review the <a href="https://molecular-cancer.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12943-025-02371-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>. &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>###&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&amp;nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact: </strong>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Sharon Theimer, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-link-car-t-cell-aging-to-cancer-relapse/">Mayo Clinic researchers link CAR-T cell aging to cancer relapse&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/1x1-Kenderian.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/16x9-KENDERIEAN.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Ismail Can]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Saad Kendarian]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Pioneering change: The inception and potential of Mayo Clinic&amp;#8217;s Nursing Research Scholars</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/7-11-pioneering-change-the-inception-and-potential-of-mayo-clinics-nursing-research-scholars/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Carey Stanton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 13:12:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=404710</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic’s Department of Nursing welcomes its first&nbsp;Nursing Research Scholars. As an Academic Medical Center, Mayo integrates clinical practice with research and education to deliver the best possible care. In its inaugural year, three scholars were accepted into the unique Nursing Research Scholar program. Under the guidance of nurse scientists in the Division of Nursing [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/7-11-pioneering-change-the-inception-and-potential-of-mayo-clinics-nursing-research-scholars/">Pioneering change: The inception and potential of Mayo Clinic&amp;#8217;s Nursing Research Scholars</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-center-align-caption"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Nursing-Research-Scholars-1024x576.jpg" alt="Nursing research scholars" class="wp-image-404728" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Nursing-Research-Scholars-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Nursing-Research-Scholars-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Nursing-Research-Scholars-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Nursing-Research-Scholars.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Jeanine Gangeness, Ph.D., Amanda Rossley, Ph.D. and Savannah Zins, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic’s Department of Nursing welcomes its first&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/departments-divisions/department-nursing/nursing-research-division/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nursing Research Scholars</a>. As an Academic Medical Center, Mayo integrates clinical practice with research and education to deliver the best possible care. In its inaugural year, three scholars were accepted into the unique Nursing Research Scholar program. Under the guidance of nurse scientists in the Division of Nursing Research, the Nursing Research Scholars are Ph.D.-prepared nurses who will now dedicate one day a week to research that improves patient care.&nbsp;</p>



<div class="wp-block-media-text is-stacked-on-mobile is-vertically-aligned-center"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="820" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/res-research-model-1-1-768x820-1.png" alt="Nursing research graphic" class="wp-image-404731 size-full" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/res-research-model-1-1-768x820-1.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/res-research-model-1-1-768x820-1-281x300.png 281w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p></p>



<p>Research at Mayo Clinic begins with the unmet needs of the patient. As a patient or a loved one, you want to be sure you are receiving the best care from the best-trained staff who follow evidence-based care. Nurses provide direct care to patients daily, so they know which approaches work well and which need adjusting. A key characteristic of an effective practitioner is the ability to evaluate standard procedures and identify opportunities for improvement. The concept of refining nursing practices and procedures is at the heart of nursing research.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p></p>
</div></div>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p>Education and training are ongoing in medicine, and nurses are frequently tasked with updating their knowledge.&amp;nbsp;Amanda Rossley, Ph.D.,&amp;nbsp;a&amp;nbsp;nurse manager in nursing professional development, hopes to study the latest in training pedagogy by using gamification to improve learning among nurses. “Gaming is an active learning strategy that improves concentration, creativity, memory and engagement,” she says.&amp;nbsp;She hopes her research will contribute to data-driven insights that lead to the practical translation for gamification-based nursing and patient education that improves patient care. For patients, this means the possibility of playing a game to learn more about managing conditions, instead of reading about it.</p>



<p>The clinical performance of a nursing student is influenced by their mental health, social support, the learning environment and self-efficacy, or the belief in one's capacity to perform.&amp;nbsp;Jeanine Gangeness, Ph.D.,&amp;nbsp;a&amp;nbsp;program director in Nursing Academic Affairs, is on a mission to enhance the existing training environment for nursing students by pinpointing which interventions increase student self-efficacy and sense of belonging. “This research is an investment in the future workforce of Mayo Clinic,” she explains. “Nursing students with high self-efficacy are more likely to work hard, complete their tasks and be more resilient in the face of failures, leading to better patient outcomes and more competent and confident nurses.”</p>



<p>For patients with adverse symptoms, relief cannot come soon enough. Despite monumental advances in medical practice and technology, many questions remain regarding symptom management in complex patients.&amp;nbsp;Savannah Zins, Ph.D.,&amp;nbsp;a nursing education specialist in nursing professional development, says, “Understanding the biological and behavioral aspects of adverse symptoms through symptom science can improve patients’ quality of life, reduce chronic symptoms and burden, and lower healthcare costs.” Through her research, Zins hopes to identify non-pharmacologic and nursing interventions to make patients more comfortable.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Because Mayo Clinic is highly collaborative, discoveries from one area are quickly translated to other areas. Within this scholarly environment, staff at Mayo continually seek new medical knowledge and ways to rapidly and responsibly validate and apply it. The Nursing Research Scholar program is one example of how the organization empowers nurses to integrate their clinical expertise with guided research opportunities, applying their findings to drive change. These research initiatives will have a positive impact, enabling the organization to share discoveries that lead to improved healthcare beyond its walls.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/7-11-pioneering-change-the-inception-and-potential-of-mayo-clinics-nursing-research-scholars/">Pioneering change: The inception and potential of Mayo Clinic&amp;#8217;s Nursing Research Scholars</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/res-research-model-1-1-768x820-1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Nursing-Research-Scholars.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers develop AI tool to detect surgical site infections from patient-submitted photos</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-ai-tool-to-detect-surgical-site-infections-from-patient-submitted-photos/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chloe Corey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 13:46:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AI and Digital Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Cornelius Thiels]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Hala Muaddi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=404641</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn.&amp;#160;— A team of Mayo Clinic researchers has developed an artificial intelligence (AI) system that can detect surgical site infections (SSIs) with high accuracy from patient-submitted postoperative wound photos, potentially transforming how postoperative care is delivered. Published in the&amp;#160;Annals of Surgery, the study introduces an AI-based pipeline the researchers created that can automatically identify [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-ai-tool-to-detect-surgical-site-infections-from-patient-submitted-photos/">Mayo Clinic researchers develop AI tool to detect surgical site infections from patient-submitted photos</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-style-center-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1603" height="902" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-in-surgery-16-x-9.jpg" alt="Dr. Hala Muaddi in surgery" class="wp-image-404654" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-in-surgery-16-x-9.jpg 1603w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-in-surgery-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-in-surgery-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-in-surgery-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-in-surgery-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1603px) 100vw, 1603px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Hala Muaddi in surgery</figcaption></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn.&amp;nbsp;— A team of Mayo Clinic researchers has developed an artificial intelligence (AI) system that can detect surgical site infections (SSIs) with high accuracy from patient-submitted postoperative wound photos, potentially transforming how postoperative care is delivered.</p>



<p>Published in the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://journals.lww.com/annalsofsurgery/abstract/9900/imaging_based_surgical_site_infection_detection.1357.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Annals of Surgery</a>, the study introduces an AI-based pipeline the researchers created that can automatically identify surgical incisions, assess image quality and flag signs of infection in photos submitted by patients through online portals. The system was trained on over 20,000 images from more than 6,000 patients across nine Mayo Clinic hospitals.<br><br>"We were motivated by the increasing need for outpatient monitoring of surgical incisions in a timely manner," says&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/thiels-cornelius-a-d-o-m-b-a/bio-20519744" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cornelius Thiels, D.O.</a>, a hepatobiliary and pancreatic surgical oncologist at Mayo Clinic and co-senior author of the study. "This process, currently done by clinicians, is time-consuming and can delay care. Our AI model can help triage these images automatically, improving early detection and streamlining communication between patients and their care teams."</p>



<p>The AI system uses a two-stage model. First, it detects whether an image contains a surgical incision and then evaluates whether that incision shows signs of infection. The model, Vision Transformer, achieved a 94% accuracy in detecting incisions and an 81% area under the curve (AUC) in identifying infections.</p>



<p></p>



<div class="wp-block-media-text is-stacked-on-mobile" style="grid-template-columns:38% auto"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="855" height="855" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-1-x-1.jpg" alt="Dr. Hala Muaddi" class="wp-image-404653 size-full" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-1-x-1.jpg 855w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-1-x-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-1-x-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-1-x-1-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 855px) 100vw, 855px" /></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p>"This work lays the foundation for AI-assisted postoperative wound care, which can transform how postoperative patients are monitored," says Hala Muaddi, M.D., Ph.D., a hepatopancreatobiliary fellow at Mayo Clinic and first author. "It’s especially relevant as outpatient operations and virtual follow-ups become more common."</p>
</div></div>



<p></p>



<p>The researchers are hopeful that this technology could help patients receive faster responses, reduce delays in diagnosing infections and support better care for those recovering from surgery at home. With further validation, it could function as a frontline screening tool that alerts clinicians to concerning incisions. This AI tool also paves the way for developing algorithms capable of detecting subtle signs of infection, potentially before they become visually apparent to the care team. This would allow for earlier treatment, decreased morbidity and reduced costs.</p>



<p>"For patients, this could mean faster reassurance or earlier identification of a problem," says Dr. Muaddi. "For clinicians, it offers a way to prioritize attention to cases that need it most, especially in rural or resource-limited settings."</p>



<p>Importantly, the model demonstrated consistent performance across diverse groups, addressing concerns about algorithmic bias.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>While the results are promising, the team says that further validation is needed.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"Our hope is that the AI models we developed — and the large dataset they were trained on — have the potential to fundamentally reshape how surgical follow-up is delivered," says&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/salehinejad-hojjat-ph-d/bio-20547448" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hojjat Salehinejad, Ph.D.</a>, a senior associate consultant of health care delivery research within the Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery and co-senior author. "Prospective studies are underway to evaluate how well this tool integrates into day-to-day surgical care."</p>



<p>This research was supported by the Dalio Philanthropies Artificial Intelligence/Machine Learning Enablement Award and the Simons Family Career Development Award in Surgical Innovation.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Chloe Corey, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-ai-tool-to-detect-surgical-site-infections-from-patient-submitted-photos/">Mayo Clinic researchers develop AI tool to detect surgical site infections from patient-submitted photos</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-surgery-1-x-1-.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-in-surgery-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Cornelius Thiels]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Hala Muaddi]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>(VIDEO) A rare cancer. A rare weapon. Curtis Jackson&amp;#8217;s inspiring story of survival</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-a-rare-cancer-a-rare-weapon-curtis-jacksons-inspiring-story-of-survival/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 17:33:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MC Video pkg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cholangiocarcinoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Liver Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Liver Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403352</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Curtis Jackson was living his dream life — a loving and supportive wife, three wonderful kids, and a future that looked as bright as could be. Then, one day, without warning, the dream was shattered. At only 46, Curtis was diagnosed with&amp;#160;cholangiocarcinoma, one of the deadliest and most aggressive forms of cancer. It's a silent [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-a-rare-cancer-a-rare-weapon-curtis-jacksons-inspiring-story-of-survival/">(VIDEO) A rare cancer. A rare weapon. Curtis Jackson&amp;#8217;s inspiring story of survival</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-and-Kim-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-404539" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-and-Kim-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-and-Kim-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-and-Kim-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-and-Kim-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-and-Kim-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Curtis and Kim Jackson</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Curtis Jackson was living his dream life — a loving and supportive wife, three wonderful kids, and a future that looked as bright as could be.</p>



<p>Then, one day, without warning, the dream was shattered.</p>



<p>At only 46, Curtis was diagnosed with&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cholangiocarcinoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20352408">cholangiocarcinoma</a>, one of the deadliest and most aggressive forms of cancer. It's a silent killer that strikes the liver. It is often diagnosed in later stages, leaving patients with few treatment options and little time to live.</p>



<p>The Jackson family turned to Mayo Clinic, where a team of experts fought the cancer with a weapon rarely used in the battle against this aggressive form of cancer.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/7TZSj_T0CHQ" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: A rare cancer. A rare weapon. Curtis Jackson's inspiring story of survival.</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutube7TZSjT0CHQ"  title="A rare cancer. A rare weapon. Curtis Jackson&amp;#039;s inspiring story of survival." width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/7TZSj_T0CHQ?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (2:17) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/A-rare-cancer.-A-rare-weapon.-Curtis-Jacksons-inspiring-story-of-survival-.pdf">script</a>.</strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The rare cancer</strong></h2>



<p>Years before his cancer diagnosis, Curtis was diagnosed with <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-primary-sclerosing-cholangitis/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">primary sclerosing cholangitis (PSC)</a>. PSC is a chronic liver disease that causes inflammation and scarring to the bile ducts, which work with the liver to help with digestion.</p>



<p>PSC put the Arizona man at higher risk for liver cancer, requiring him to get regular diagnostic screenings. As with most forms of cancer, but particularly cholangiocarcinoma, doctors say early detection is key to improving patient outcomes.</p>



<p>However, with cholangiocarcinoma, there are often no warning signs or symptoms alerting patients of the need to consult with their doctor about getting screened, until it's too late. In Curtis' case, the cholangiocarcinoma was detected in one of his routine screenings at Mayo Clinic, which doctors say likely helped save his life.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-center-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-with-Dr.-Aqel-Bashar-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Curtis and Kim Jackson consulting with Dr. Aqel Bashar;cholangiocarcinoma,  a rare cancer led to a treatment at Mayo Clinic." class="wp-image-404534" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-with-Dr.-Aqel-Bashar-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-with-Dr.-Aqel-Bashar-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-with-Dr.-Aqel-Bashar-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-with-Dr.-Aqel-Bashar-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-with-Dr.-Aqel-Bashar-16-x-9.jpg 1993w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Curtis and Kim consulting with Dr. Bashar Aqel, director, Mayo Clinic Transplant Center in Arizona</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>"It's a very rare cancer that tends to grow unnoticed," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/bekaii-saab-tanios-s-m-d/bio-20413464">Dr. Tanios Bekaii-Saab</a>, an oncologist with the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center/cancer-care/arizona" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center in Arizona</a>. "If the cancer gets to the point where it's too advanced for surgery or transplantation, universally this is a noncurative or noncurable cancer."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The rare weapon</strong></h2>



<p>Doctors say a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/liver-transplant/home/orc-20211818" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">liver transplant </a>can sometimes be an option for some patients. However, not many transplant centers perform liver transplants on patients diagnosed with cholangiocarcinoma. Mayo Clinic is one of the few centers that do offer liver transplantation for some patients who meet certain criteria.</p>



<p>In Curtis' case, doctors at Mayo Clinic determined a liver transplant was his best chance for survival.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p>"We're not just here treating the cancer. We're also treating the disease that led to the cancer."</p><cite>Dr. Tanios Bekaii-Saab, Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center in Arizona</cite></blockquote></figure>



<p>"It is a unique form of therapy that is based on research that started at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/aqel-bashar-a-m-d/bio-20055093">Dr. Bashar Aqel</a>, director of the Mayo Clinic Transplant Center in Arizona.</p>



<p>"We developed some protocols that helped us improve the outcome of transplant in these patients, and without these protocols, a lot of patients with this type of cancer would not make it to transplant," says Dr. Aqel.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p>"Mayo Clinic's ability to offer this curative option for rare cancers like this has differentiated us from many other transplant centers."</p><cite>Dr. Bashar Aqel, Director, Mayo Clinic Transplant Center in Arizona</cite></blockquote></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The treatment</strong></h2>



<p>Curtis first underwent <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/chemotherapy/about/pac-20385033" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chemotherapy</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/radiation-therapy/about/pac-20385162" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">radiation</a> at Mayo Clinic. He was then placed on the liver transplant waiting list for a donor organ. While waiting, Curtis says he kept his focus on his family.</p>



<p>"I spent all the time I could with my wife and kids, like basketball practices, homework, anything we could do to help our kids," says Curtis.</p>



<p>When Curtis got the call a donor organ was found, he immediately reported to Mayo Clinic to undergo his lifesaving liver transplant. The surgery was a success. Four weeks later, Curtis was back at home with family recovering well and feeling a deep sense of gratitude for his organ donor and his team at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized is-style-center-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-Jackson-Stetson-Rooney-Gwyn-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Curtis with his children following his successful liver transplant, due to his rare cancer." class="wp-image-404531" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-Jackson-Stetson-Rooney-Gwyn-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-Jackson-Stetson-Rooney-Gwyn-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-Jackson-Stetson-Rooney-Gwyn-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-Jackson-Stetson-Rooney-Gwyn-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-Jackson-Stetson-Rooney-Gwyn-16-x-9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Curtis with his children following his successful liver transplant    Photo courtesy: Jackson family</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>"Thank you because now I get to see my daughters get married, go to college, I get to see my son live his dreams and go to college and get married," says Curtis. "I get to live and grow old with my wife. I can't say this enough to everyone, 'thank you.'"</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p>"What Mayo has done to make these transplants happen is a miracle."</p><cite>Curtis Jackson, liver transplant recipient and cancer survivor</cite></blockquote></figure>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-4-days-post-1-x-1-1024x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-404533" style="width:570px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-4-days-post-1-x-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-4-days-post-1-x-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-4-days-post-1-x-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-4-days-post-1-x-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-4-days-post-1-x-1.jpg 1427w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Curtis and Kim following his liver transplant    Photo courtesy: Jackson family</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We're already observing excellent function from Curtis' new liver, with the majority of his liver tests returning normal results," says Dr. Aqel. "His recovery has been remarkably swift and impressive."</p>



<p>"A lot of love goes out to the people in that family," says Gwyn Jackson, Curtis' oldest daughter in reference to the organ donor's family. "They allowed us to have our dad back and we're so grateful because we love him so much."</p>



<p>Doctors at Mayo Clinic are monitoring Curtis' progress closely. Meanwhile, Curtis' future is back to looking bright, only now with even deeper gratitude in his heart.</p>



<p>"This truly is the gift of life," says Curtis.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Related stories:</strong></h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-breathing-easy-thanks-to-the-gift-of-life-and-new-mayo-clinic-lung-transplant-program-in-arizona/">(VIDEO) Breathing easy thanks to the gift of life and new Mayo Clinic Lung Transplant Program in Arizona</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-barriers-helping-native-americans-in-need-get-the-gift-of-life/">Breaking barriers: Helping Native Americans in need get the gift of life</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-jessies-journey/">Jessie’s Journey</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/videoharnessing-the-power-of-innovation-and-a-patients-will-to-survive/">(VIDEO) Harnessing the power of innovation and a patient’s will to survive</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-a-rare-cancer-a-rare-weapon-curtis-jacksons-inspiring-story-of-survival/">(VIDEO) A rare cancer. A rare weapon. Curtis Jackson&amp;#8217;s inspiring story of survival</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-and-Kim-Jackson-at-window-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-and-Kim-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cholangiocarcinoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Liver Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Liver Transplant]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mcthumb >https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-CANCER-CELLS-150x150.png</mayoclinic:mcthumb >	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researcher harnesses uniqueness of space to advance medicine on Earth</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researcher-harnesses-uniqueness-of-space-to-advance-medicine-on-earth/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sharon Theimer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 13:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Abba Zubair]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=404367</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Cancer, stroke, bone loss among diseases and conditions studied in microgravity JACKSONVILLE, Florida — Mayo Clinic physician and researcher Dr. Abba Zubair’s work combines two passions — medicine and space — for the benefit of astronauts and people on Earth. His research in space is yielding discoveries in cancer, stroke, bone loss and more. In [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researcher-harnesses-uniqueness-of-space-to-advance-medicine-on-earth/">Mayo Clinic researcher harnesses uniqueness of space to advance medicine on Earth</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Abba-Zubair-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-404368" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Abba-Zubair-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Abba-Zubair-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Abba-Zubair-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Abba-Zubair-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Abba-Zubair-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><em>Cancer, stroke, bone loss among diseases and conditions studied in microgravity</em></p>



<p>JACKSONVILLE, Florida — Mayo Clinic physician and researcher <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/zubair-abba-c-m-d-ph-d/bio-00092417" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Abba Zubair’s</a> work combines two passions — medicine and space — for the benefit of astronauts and people on Earth. His research in space is yielding discoveries in <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20370588" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stroke/symptoms-causes/syc-20350113" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stroke</a>, bone loss and more. In this expert alert, Dr. Zubair answers five questions about his studies in <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/centers-and-facilities/glenn/what-is-microgravity/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">microgravity</a>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What are you hoping to accomplish through your research?</h2>



<p>"The goal is to harness the uniqueness of the space environment for the betterment of humanity, be it on Earth or in space," Dr. Zubair says."We wanted to take advantage of the environment at the International Space Station to study how it affects human physiology."</p>



<p>The absence of gravity and the impacts of radiation and vacuum are three fundamental aspects of the uniqueness of space, adds Dr. Zubair, who has sent three research projects to the International Space Station (ISS) since 2017, with more to come.</p>



<p>As a <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">regenerative biotherapeutics</a> specialist, Dr. Zubair's work focuses in part on adult&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bone-marrow-transplant/in-depth/stem-cells/art-20048117?mc_id=us&amp;amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;amp;utm_medium=l&amp;amp;utm_content=content&amp;amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;amp;geo=national&amp;amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;amp;invsrc=other&amp;amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stem cells</a>&amp;nbsp;— known as mesenchymal stem cells —and their use in future treatments for stroke. He noted that he uses stem cells in regenerative medicine and in supporting Mayo's <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bone-marrow-transplant/about/pac-20384854" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bone marrow transplant program</a>.</p>



<p>"I also know how challenging it is to grow them in the lab. One of the first fundamentals is to see how the absence of gravity influences how stem cells divide and the growth rate," Dr. Zubair explains. "We wanted to see whether cells grown in space are any better or grow faster than cells grown in the lab. When we did our first space flight, we had a really interesting finding, because we realized that the absence of gravity affects stem cells, but it depends on the type of stem cells." &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>That led Dr. Zubair to another project on the ISS: studying how mesenchymal stem cells, the precursor for bone-forming cells, play a role in bone formation or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/osteoporosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20351968" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">osteoporosis</a>, bone loss. He notes that astronauts tend to lose bone density despite rigorous exercise.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How might your research benefit people with cancer?</h2>



<p>Dr. Zubair is also studying how <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/leukemia/symptoms-causes/syc-20374373" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">leukemia</a> stem cells, the cells that form the seed of this blood cancer, respond to the space environment.</p>



<p>"We are also working to understand the impact of space radiation, from the angle of how we can mitigate the effect of radiation and prevent cancer," Dr. Zubair says. "In the long run, we really want to protect astronauts, especially during long-term space travel, such as to Mars, where they would be deep in space and away from any magnetic field protection that we get from Earth."</p>



<p>The research also may benefit people on Earth by revealing how to protect stem cells or cells in general when there is radiation exposure, such as nuclear accidents, he adds.</p>



<p>In addition, Dr. Zubair's space research could have implications for CAR-T treatment, bone marrow transplants or other therapies for cancer patients.</p>



<p>"If we can understand how stem cells in space, especially <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bone-marrow-transplant/in-depth/stem-cells/art-20048117" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hematopoietic&nbsp;stem cells</a> (cells that live in the bone marrow and produce cells that function in the blood), expand and differentiate to make immune cells like T cells, microphages, we will learn how to make them more efficiently," Dr. Zubair says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">You've remarked that you can envision a time when people might go into space to receive certain medical treatments. How would that work, and might it be possible to simulate microgravity for those treatments on Earth?</h2>



<p>If cells proliferate more in space, for example if cancer cells go into what is called cell cycle and multiply abnormally when they proliferate, then chemotherapy will be more effective, Dr. Zubair says.</p>



<p>"If that is the case, that absence of gravity can induce leukemia cells or other cancer cells to go into cell cycle, that makes them susceptible to chemotherapy," he explains. "So instead of giving the chemo on Earth, you might go into space where the absence of gravity makes the cancer cells more vulnerable to chemotherapy. That would be one more reason to go to space. That is definitely something that I would love to explore."</p>



<p>It would be difficult to create a comparable microgravity environment on Earth, but technically, it could be done, Dr. Zubair adds.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Dr.-Zubair-Childhood-love-of-space.mp4"></video></figure>


<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network."</strong></p>
<p>"Microgravity on Earth is basically like going into a swimming pool, a state of buoyancy where you are kind of in suspension; the gravity is canceled out by the effect of the water," he says. "Now, obviously it wouldn't be pleasant to be in water for quite some time. In the lab, we use a microgravity simulator where cells are suspended. It would be interesting if you could do the same for a human being."</p>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What attracted you to space research?</h2>



<p>Dr. Zubair grew up in Kano, Nigeria, and remembers gazing at the night sky as a child.</p>



<p>"As far back as I can remember, I was always fascinated by what is out there in space. Looking at the moon and all the stars, and really that ignites my passion for space and space exploration," Dr. Zubair says.</p>



<p>Dr. Zubair's first dream was to become an astronaut, but an adviser in high school counseled him to find a more practical career, and he pursued medicine.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What's next?</h2>



<p>One of Dr. Zubair's next two payloads to the International Space Station, not yet scheduled for launch, will examine whether umbilical cord blood cells, rich in stem cells and potential therapeutic value, can be expanded. Another study will explore different cell types that participate in bone formation and whether the problem of bone loss in space can be alleviated through use of a special compound.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"If it works, then definitely we will see how we can treat patients with osteoporosis, particularly women, cancer patients, or people who are bedridden for a long time and are not weight-bearing, which affects their bone," Dr. Zubair says.</p>



<p>Dr. Zubair notes that all of his space experiments are done in parallel on Earth with identical cells to compare the two results and validate the findings from space.</p>



<p>&amp;nbsp;"I really think there is a lot out there that is just waiting for us to explore and use," he says. "And that's why I do what I do."</p>



<p>Dr. Zubair has been honored by NASA with the Exceptional Scientific Achievement Medal for demonstrating that human-derived mesenchymal stem cells grown aboard the International Space Station could be used for potential clinical applications.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Sharon Theimer, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researcher-harnesses-uniqueness-of-space-to-advance-medicine-on-earth/">Mayo Clinic researcher harnesses uniqueness of space to advance medicine on Earth</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1-Dr-Zubair.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Abba-Zubair.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Abba Zubair]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>How a Mayo Clinic neurologist used AI to help restore a patient&amp;#8217;s health</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-mayo-clinics-ai-helped-a-neurologist-give-a-patient-his-life-back/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Discovery Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurology Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. David Jones]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403848</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Just one day after undergoing brain shunt surgery at Mayo Clinic, 75-year-old Minoo Press put his wheelchair aside and walked out of the hospital on his own. For the first time in two years, his mind was clear. His balance had returned. He was no longer losing control of his bladder.&amp;#160; The significant turnaround followed [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-mayo-clinics-ai-helped-a-neurologist-give-a-patient-his-life-back/">How a Mayo Clinic neurologist used AI to help restore a patient&amp;#8217;s health</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Minoo-Press1-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-403965" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Minoo-Press1-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Minoo-Press1-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Minoo-Press1-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Minoo-Press1-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Minoo-Press1.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Minoo Press (right) and his wife, Zarin Press. <em>Photo courtesy of Minoo Press</em></figcaption></figure>



<p>Just one day after undergoing brain shunt surgery at Mayo Clinic, 75-year-old Minoo Press put his wheelchair aside and walked out of the hospital on his own. For the first time in two years, his mind was clear. His balance had returned. He was no longer losing control of his bladder.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The significant turnaround followed two years of steady cognitive and physical decline. A retired engineer known for his sharp mind and independence, Press gradually withdrew from daily life. Even simple routines became impossible.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>He visited leading medical centers across the country, undergoing spinal taps, surgical procedures and advanced imaging to evaluate for conditions ranging from Alzheimer's disease to Parkinson's.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Some clinicians at those institutions also considered <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hydrocephalus/symptoms-causes/syc-20373604" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">normal pressure hydrocephalus</a>, a condition in which excess fluid builds up in the brain. But because Mr. Press' symptoms overlapped with signs of neurodegenerative disease, the doctors could not confirm the diagnosis or recommend surgery. They told him there was nothing more they could do.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>From rapid diagnosis to life-changing care</strong></h2>



<p>After an exhaustive search for answers, Press' family brought him to Mayo Clinic where he was evaluated by <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/jones-david-t-m-d/bio-20200690" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. David Jones</a>, a neurologist and director of Mayo Clinic's Neurology Artificial Intelligence Program.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="684" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Minoo-Press3-684x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-404118" style="width:455px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Minoo-Press3-684x1024.jpg 684w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Minoo-Press3-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Minoo-Press3.jpg 711w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 684px) 100vw, 684px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Minoo Press (center) is pictured with his sons, Carl and Cyrus, and his wife, Zarin, before undergoing a stent procedure at Mayo Clinic. At the time, he was unable to walk and used a wheelchair. <em>Photo courtesy of Minoo Press</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Dr. Jones used an innovative artificial intelligence tool developed by his team, called <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-tool-identifies-9-dementia-types-including-alzheimers-with-one-scan/">StateViewer</a>. The tool works with a widely available brain scan known as fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography, or FDG-PET, comparing a patient's brain activity to thousands of confirmed dementia cases. It highlights patterns linked to nine types of the disease — from Alzheimer's and frontotemporal dementia to less common forms with overlapping symptoms.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>In a recent <a href="https://n.neurology.org/lookup/doi/10.1212/WNL.0000000000213831">study</a> published in Neurology, the tool identified the correct dementia type in 88% of cases and helped clinicians interpret scans up to three times more accurately and twice as fast as standard methods.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>In Press' case, the tool helped Dr. Jones rule out Alzheimer's and other types of dementia. That was the turning point.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>With neurodegenerative disease ruled out, Dr. Jones diagnosed Press with normal pressure hydrocephalus and confirmed that he was a candidate for a shunt procedure to relieve the pressure on his brain and potentially reverse the symptoms.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>A last-minute surgical cancellation&amp;nbsp;made it possible for Press to have the procedure that same week. </p>



<p>Within three days at Mayo Clinic, he had a clear diagnosis, a treatment plan and underwent brain surgery to place a shunt that would drain excess fluid from his brain.&amp;nbsp;The procedure was performed by <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/elder-benjamin-d-m-d-ph-d/bio-20406877" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Ben Elder</a>, a neurosurgeon and clinician-scientist. &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Press, who traveled from Chicago, noticed immediate improvements. His thinking was sharper, his steps steadier and he felt like himself again.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A clear mind, steady steps and hope</strong></h2>



<p>Dr. Jones says Press' case highlights the promise of combining AI with clinical care to accelerate diagnosis, scale expert clinical knowledge and help guide treatment planning.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>"When you're looking at overlapping symptoms, it's easy to miss the underlying cause," Dr. Jones says. "StateViewer gave us the clarity we needed to make an informed diagnosis and take action."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Press continues physical therapy and says he's improving every day.&amp;nbsp;He hopes his story can help others who are navigating the same often misdiagnosed and debilitating condition.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"I can enjoy time with my family again and I can go out with my friends. I can even do my own taxes. These are the moments I thought I had lost forever," Mr. Press says. "Mayo Clinic gave me my life back."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Related article:</strong></h2>



<div class="wp-block-columns has-background is-layout-flex wp-container-core-columns-is-layout-28f84493 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex" style="background-color:#d4d4d9">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-tool-identifies-9-dementia-types-including-alzheimers-with-one-scan/">Mayo Clinic's AI tool identifies 9 dementia types, including Alzheimer's, with one scan</a></strong></h2>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">Mayo Clinic researchers have developed a new artificial intelligence (AI) tool that helps clinicians identify brain activity patterns linked to nine types of dementia, including Alzheimer's disease, using a single, widely available scan — a transformative advance in early, accurate diagnosis. <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-tool-identifies-9-dementia-types-including-alzheimers-with-one-scan/">Read more</a>.</p>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="600" height="600" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1DR.DAVID-JONES1.png" alt="" class="wp-image-404080" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1DR.DAVID-JONES1.png 600w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1DR.DAVID-JONES1-300x300.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1DR.DAVID-JONES1-150x150.png 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></figure>
</div>
</div>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-mayo-clinics-ai-helped-a-neurologist-give-a-patient-his-life-back/">How a Mayo Clinic neurologist used AI to help restore a patient&amp;#8217;s health</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1-MinooPress.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Minoo-Press1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. David Jones]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic&amp;#8217;s AI tool identifies 9 dementia types, including Alzheimer&amp;#8217;s, with one scan&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-tool-identifies-9-dementia-types-including-alzheimers-with-one-scan/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 20:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Discovery Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Translational Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. David Jones]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403846</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic researchers have developed a new artificial intelligence (AI) tool that helps clinicians identify brain activity patterns linked to nine types of dementia, including Alzheimer's disease, using a single, widely available scan — a transformative advance in early, accurate diagnosis.&amp;#160; The tool, StateViewer, helped researchers identify the dementia type in 88% [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-tool-identifies-9-dementia-types-including-alzheimers-with-one-scan/">Mayo Clinic&amp;#8217;s AI tool identifies 9 dementia types, including Alzheimer&amp;#8217;s, with one scan&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-DAVID-JONES1-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-404078" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-DAVID-JONES1-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-DAVID-JONES1-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-DAVID-JONES1-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-DAVID-JONES1-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-DAVID-JONES1.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. David Jones reviews brain scans on a computer at Mayo Clinic.</figcaption></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic researchers have developed a new artificial intelligence (AI) tool that helps clinicians identify brain activity patterns linked to nine types of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/dementia/symptoms-causes/syc-20352013" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dementia</a>, including <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/alzheimers-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350447" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alzheimer's disease</a>, using a single, widely available scan — a transformative advance in early, accurate diagnosis.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The tool, StateViewer, helped researchers identify the dementia type in 88% of cases, according to research <a href="https://n.neurology.org/lookup/doi/10.1212/WNL.0000000000213831" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">published</a> online on June 27, 2025, in Neurology, the medical journal of the American Academy of Neurology. It also enabled clinicians to interpret brain scans nearly twice as fast and with up to three times greater accuracy than standard workflows. Researchers trained and tested the AI on more than 3,600 scans, including images from patients with dementia and people without cognitive impairment.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>This innovation addresses a core challenge in dementia care: identifying the disease early and precisely, even when multiple conditions are present. As new treatments emerge, timely diagnosis helps match patients with the most appropriate care when it can have the greatest impact. The tool could bring advanced diagnostic support to clinics that lack neurology expertise.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The rising toll of dementia</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p>Dementia affects more than 55 million people worldwide, with nearly 10 million new cases each year. Alzheimer's disease, the most common form, is now the fifth-leading cause of death globally. Diagnosing dementia typically requires cognitive tests, blood draws, imaging, clinical interviews and specialist referrals. Even with extensive testing, distinguishing conditions such as Alzheimer's, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lewy-body-dementia/symptoms-causes/syc-20352025">Lewy body dementia</a> and <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-is-frontotemporal-degeneration/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">frontotemporal dementia</a> remains challenging, including for highly experienced specialists.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>StateViewer was developed under the direction of <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/jones-david-t-m-d/bio-20200690" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">David Jones, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic neurologist and director of the Mayo Clinic Neurology Artificial Intelligence Program.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"Every patient who walks into my clinic carries a unique story shaped by the brain's complexity," Dr. Jones says. "That complexity drew me to neurology and continues to drive my commitment to clearer answers. StateViewer reflects that commitment — a step toward earlier understanding, more precise treatment and, one day, changing the course of these diseases."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>To bring that vision to life, Dr. Jones worked alongside Leland Barnard, Ph.D., a data scientist who leads the AI engineering behind StateViewer.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"As we were designing StateViewer, we never lost sight of the fact that behind every data point and brain scan was a person facing a difficult diagnosis and urgent questions," Dr. Barnard says. "Seeing how this tool could assist physicians with real-time, precise insights and guidance highlights the potential of machine learning for clinical medicine."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Turning brain patterns into clinical insight&nbsp;</strong></h2>



<p>The tool analyzes a fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (FDG-PET) scan, which shows how the brain uses glucose for energy. It then compares the scan to a large database of scans from people with confirmed dementia diagnoses and identifies patterns that match specific types, or combinations, of dementia.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Alzheimer's typically affects memory and processing regions, Lewy body dementia involves areas tied to attention and movement, and frontotemporal dementia alters regions responsible for language and behavior. StateViewer displays these patterns through color-coded brain maps that highlight key areas of brain activity, giving all clinicians, even those without neurology training, a visual explanation of what the AI sees and how it supports the diagnosis.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers plan to expand the tool's use and will continue evaluating its performance in a variety of clinical settings.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>For a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding,&amp;nbsp;review the <a href="https://n.neurology.org/lookup/doi/10.1212/WNL.0000000000213831">study</a>.</p>



<p>###&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&amp;nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:&amp;nbsp;</strong>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Tia Ford, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-tool-identifies-9-dementia-types-including-alzheimers-with-one-scan/">Mayo Clinic&amp;#8217;s AI tool identifies 9 dementia types, including Alzheimer&amp;#8217;s, with one scan&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1DR.DAVID-JONES1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-DAVID-JONES1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. David Jones]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers capture first signs of ovarian cancer risk</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-capture-first-signs-of-ovarian-cancer-risk/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alison Satake]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 20:14:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Discovery Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jamie Bakkum-Gamez]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nagarajan Kannan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403806</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A Mayo discovery could lead to future strategies for detecting the disease in its earliest, precancerous stages.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-capture-first-signs-of-ovarian-cancer-risk/">Mayo Clinic researchers capture first signs of ovarian cancer risk</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Female-reproductive-system-Shutterstock16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Illustration of female reproductive system. Credit: Shutterstock" class="wp-image-403810" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Female-reproductive-system-Shutterstock16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Female-reproductive-system-Shutterstock16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Female-reproductive-system-Shutterstock16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Female-reproductive-system-Shutterstock16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Female-reproductive-system-Shutterstock16x9.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Shutterstock</figcaption></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. —&amp;nbsp;Little is known about what causes <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/ovarian-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20375941" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ovarian cancer</a>, and there is no way to detect it early yet. About 75% of the time when someone is diagnosed with ovarian cancer, it has already progressed to stage 3 or stage 4, which means it has spread to other parts of the body. Mayo Clinic physicians, researchers and patients had been working together to learn more about this devastating disease when a 22-year-old patient, who has two rare genetic conditions that dramatically elevate lifetime cancer risk, came to Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>The patient carries a hereditary BRCA2 mutation, which is one of the genes that causes hereditary breast and ovarian cancer (HBOC) syndrome, and a hereditary TP53 mutation, which causes Li-Fraumeni syndrome.</p>



<p>At Mayo Clinic, she was diagnosed with breast cancer. Imaging also revealed she had an ovarian cyst. Although the cyst was benign, she chose to have a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mastectomy/about/pac-20394670" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">mastectomy</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/abdominal-hysterectomy/multimedia/types-of-hysterectomy-surgery/img-20007786" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hysterectomy</a> with removal of her ovaries and fallopian tubes, a procedure called a bilateral salpingo-<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/oophorectomy/about/pac-20385030" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">oophorectomy</a>, because of her elevated cancer risk. Upon further examination, her Mayo Clinic physician and research team detected early, hidden changes in the cells lining her fallopian tubes, revealing signals that may point to the first signs of ovarian cancer before symptoms or visible lesions appear.</p>



<p>"Our team glimpsed a rare and revealing phenomenon in epithelial biology, uncovered through the cells of a young patient living with profoundly high-risk genetic conditions. Using cutting-edge, single-cell technologies, we traced how her epithelial cells were developmentally altered in ways that signaled a high risk for lethal ovarian cancer. These insights could pave the way for future strategies to detect the disease in its earliest, precancerous stages when prevention is still possible," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/kannan-nagarajan-ph-d-m-s/bio-20233074" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nagarajan Kannan, Ph.D.</a>, director of the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/stem-cell-and-cancer-biology/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stem Cell and Cancer Biology Laboratory</a> at Mayo Clinic and co-lead author of this <a href="https://doi.org/10.1200/PO-24-00589" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> published in JCO Precision Oncology.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="819" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Bakkum-Gamez-Jamie-N._13871561_20240708-819x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-403808" style="width:241px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Bakkum-Gamez-Jamie-N._13871561_20240708-819x1024.jpg 819w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Bakkum-Gamez-Jamie-N._13871561_20240708-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Bakkum-Gamez-Jamie-N._13871561_20240708-768x960.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Bakkum-Gamez-Jamie-N._13871561_20240708.jpg 900w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 819px) 100vw, 819px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Jamie Bakkum-Gamez, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/bakkum-gamez-jamie-n-m-d/bio-20055230" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jamie Bakkum-Gamez, M.D.</a>, the patient's gynecologic oncology surgeon at Mayo Clinic, says she is determined to find a way to detect ovarian cancer earlier to help save more patients' lives.</p>



<p>"We know that the most aggressive and common form of ovarian cancer often actually starts in the fallopian tube. However, why the fallopian tube and how it starts are not yet known. Knowing how ovarian cancer begins and forms could not only lead to the development of earlier screening tools, but also more personalized risk-reduction strategies and improved guidance around the timing of preventive surgeries and fertility planning," says Dr. Bakkum-Gamez, who is a co-lead author of this study.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/4Qo_XmxrrLA">Watch: Dr. Jamie Bakkum-Gamez on revealing hidden signs of ovarian cancer risk</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutube4QoXmxrrLA"  title="Dr. Jamie Bakkum-Gamez - Revealing hidden signs of ovarian cancer risk" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4Qo_XmxrrLA?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites are available in the downloads. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Name super/CG: Jamie Bakkum-Gamez, M.D./&amp;nbsp;Gynecologic Oncology/Mayo Clinic</strong></p>



<p>Together, Dr. Kannan and Dr. Bakkum-Gamez have established a living fallopian tube biobank at Mayo Clinic. The cells and tissues donated by patients help scientists study how ovarian cancer begins — cell by cell — directly in human tissue. From the patient specimens, organoids, or small versions of the fallopian tubes, can be grown. The biobank includes organoids from patients with average-to-high ovarian cancer risk and specializes in inherited cancer mutations like the ones associated with HBOC syndrome and Li-Fraumeni syndrome.</p>



<div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-core-columns-is-layout-28f84493 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow" style="flex-basis:75%">
<figure class="wp-block-pullquote has-medium-font-size" style="margin-top:0;margin-bottom:0;padding-top:var(--wp--preset--spacing--30);padding-right:var(--wp--preset--spacing--30);padding-bottom:var(--wp--preset--spacing--30);padding-left:var(--wp--preset--spacing--30)"><blockquote><p>"The precise cellular origin of ovarian cancer remains one of the greatest unanswered questions in cancer prevention — limiting our ability to intervene early and save lives. This work lays the foundation for a new era of early detection and precision prevention for ovarian cancer, especially for patients with inherited risk such as BRCA mutations."</p><cite>Nagarajan Kannan, Ph.D.</cite></blockquote></figure>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow" style="flex-basis:50%"><div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="683" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1716990_WF81191_0007-resized-683x1024.jpg" alt="Nagarajan Kannan, Ph.D." class="wp-image-403807" style="width:243px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1716990_WF81191_0007-resized-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1716990_WF81191_0007-resized-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1716990_WF81191_0007-resized-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1716990_WF81191_0007-resized.jpg 988w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 683px) 100vw, 683px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Nagarajan Kannan, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div></div>
</div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Ovarian cancer precursor</strong></h2>



<p>A healthy fallopian tube consists of two main types of epithelial cells: multiciliated cells that have hundreds of cilia, or hairlike appendages, that help move the fertilized egg through the fallopian tube and secretory cells that secrete fluids to nourish and protect the developing embryo. But in the fallopian tube cells collected from the patient with HBOC syndrome and Li-Fraumeni syndrome, the scientists saw something they had never seen before. Instead of the two types of epithelial cells, the secretory cells vastly outnumbered the multiciliated cells across the fallopian tube. They also found that secretory cells were driving chronic inflammation — an established contributor to cancer development.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="854" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Ritting-Megan-L._30081932_202106231044-854x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-403809" style="width:222px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Ritting-Megan-L._30081932_202106231044-854x1024.jpg 854w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Ritting-Megan-L._30081932_202106231044-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Ritting-Megan-L._30081932_202106231044-768x921.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Ritting-Megan-L._30081932_202106231044.jpg 938w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 854px) 100vw, 854px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Megan Ritting</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Through single-cell RNA sequencing, we could see the disruptions in the development of cells lining the fallopian tube lumen — findings that could help reshape how we understand and ultimately prevent ovarian cancer," says Megan Ritting, co-lead author and <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a> doctoral candidate. Ritting spearheaded the use of cutting-edge genomic technology in this study.</p>



<p>Furthermore, oral contraceptives containing progestins, or synthetic analogs of the hormone progesterone that is produced by the ovaries, can be used to reduce ovarian cancer risk by up to 50%. However, Ritting and the research team were surprised to see that this patient's fallopian tube cells did not have any progesterone receptor proteins, which suggests oral contraceptives may not have been effective in reducing the patient's risk for ovarian cancer.</p>



<p>"With the generous partnership of patients who allow their cells to be studied using advanced technologies, including organoid models, we are making critical progress in understanding how these cancers develop. This work represents an important step toward identifying opportunities to develop preventive strategies, treatments and approaches that could reduce the risk of fallopian tube and ovarian cancers," says Dr. Bakkum-Gamez.</p>



<p>In the next steps of this research, using the living fallopian tube biobank, the scientists are investigating how and where earliest origins of ovarian cancer take root.</p>



<p>Review the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1200/PO-24-00589" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&amp;nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-capture-first-signs-of-ovarian-cancer-risk/">Mayo Clinic researchers capture first signs of ovarian cancer risk</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Female-reproductive-system-Shutterstock1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Female-reproductive-system-Shutterstock16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jamie Bakkum-Gamez]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nagarajan Kannan]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Mayo Clinic tool exposes hidden cancer DNA changes that may drive treatment resistance</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-tool-exposes-hidden-cancer-dna-changes-that-may-drive-treatment-resistance/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individualized Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. George Vasmatzis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403614</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Some of the most harmful genetic changes in cancer are also the hardest to see. These structural alterations, deep within a tumor's DNA, can fuel aggressive growth and evade standard testing, especially when tissue samples are small or degraded.&amp;#160; To address this challenge, Mayo Clinic researchers have developed a new computational tool called BACDAC that [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-tool-exposes-hidden-cancer-dna-changes-that-may-drive-treatment-resistance/">New Mayo Clinic tool exposes hidden cancer DNA changes that may drive treatment resistance</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-CANCER-CELLS-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-403617" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-CANCER-CELLS-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-CANCER-CELLS-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-CANCER-CELLS-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-CANCER-CELLS-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-CANCER-CELLS.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">3D rendering of cancer cells. (Getty Images)</figcaption></figure>



<p>Some of the most harmful genetic changes in cancer are also the hardest to see. These structural alterations, deep within a tumor's DNA, can fuel aggressive growth and evade standard testing, especially when tissue samples are small or degraded.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>To address this challenge, Mayo Clinic researchers have developed a new computational tool called BACDAC that shines a light on these elusive genomic patterns. The tool helps researchers identify signs of genomic instability using DNA sequencing that reads the entire genome, even in low-purity or low-coverage samples.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The tool could help clinicians better predict how a tumor will behave and guide more personalized treatment choices.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Detecting chromosome changes</strong></h2>



<p>At the core of BACDAC's approach is the concept of ploidy, which refers to the number of complete sets of chromosomes in a cell. While normal human cells have two sets (46 chromosomes total), cancer cells often show large-scale gains or losses, disrupting this balance and enabling unchecked growth.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<div style="height:25px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-core-columns-is-layout-28f84493 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized is-style-center-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="853" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Vasmatzis-George_13527509_201912200302-1-853x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-403620" style="width:280px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Vasmatzis-George_13527509_201912200302-1-853x1024.jpg 853w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Vasmatzis-George_13527509_201912200302-1-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Vasmatzis-George_13527509_201912200302-1-768x922.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Vasmatzis-George_13527509_201912200302-1.jpg 1250w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 853px) 100vw, 853px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">George Vasmatzis, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-pullquote" style="padding-top:0;padding-bottom:0"><blockquote><p>"This tool lets us see a layer of the genome that's been invisible until now. We've spent decades studying the biology of genomic instability. This is the first time we've been able to translate that knowledge into a tool that works at scale."&amp;nbsp;</p><cite>George Vasmatzis, Ph.d.</cite></blockquote></figure>
</div>
</div>



<div style="height:25px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>In a study <a href="https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-025-03599-2" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">published</a> in Genome Biology, the research team used BACDAC to analyze more than 650 tumors across 12 cancer types. The tool helped researchers detect signs of whole-genome doubling, where a tumor duplicates all of its DNA. This type of abnormal ploidy is often linked to aggressive behavior and treatment resistance.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"This tool lets us see a layer of the genome that's been invisible until now," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/vasmatzis-george-ph-d/bio-00027811" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">George Vasmatzis, Ph.D.</a>, a lead author of the study and co-director of Mayo Clinic's Biomarker Discovery Program. "We've spent decades studying the biology of genomic instability. This is the first time we've been able to translate that knowledge into a tool that works at scale."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>BACDAC also provides a visual summary of a tumor's genomic landscape. A custom output called the Constellation Plot offers an intuitive view of whether the tumor's chromosomes are stable or disrupted. This may help researchers and pathologists interpret results more easily.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Next, the Mayo Clinic team plans to further validate BACDAC and develop it into a clinically deployable diagnostic tool. It may help inform treatment decisions by providing a clearer view of a tumor’s structural changes.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The study was supported in part by the Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine and the Mayo Clinic Center for Digital Health. For a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding, <a href="https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-025-03599-2" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">review the study</a>.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading has-black-color has-text-color has-link-color wp-elements-df8571fc8e3ef97780c06235715addce"><strong>More recent research from Dr. Vasmatzis</strong></h2>



<div style="height:25px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-columns has-background is-layout-flex wp-container-core-columns-is-layout-28f84493 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex" style="background-color:#d4d4d9">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-reveal-personalized-approach-to-brain-cancer-monitoring/"><strong>Mayo Clinic researchers reveal personalized approach to brain cancer monitoring</strong></a></h2>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">Mayo Clinic researchers have developed a personalized blood test that detects tumor DNA to help track the progression of high-grade gliomas more quickly and less invasively. <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-reveal-personalized-approach-to-brain-cancer-monitoring/">Read more</a>.</p>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1brain-cancer.png" alt="" class="wp-image-403767" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1brain-cancer.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1brain-cancer-150x150.png 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure>
</div>
</div>



<div style="height:5px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading has-medium-font-size"></h3>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-tool-exposes-hidden-cancer-dna-changes-that-may-drive-treatment-resistance/">New Mayo Clinic tool exposes hidden cancer DNA changes that may drive treatment resistance</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1CANCER-CELLS.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-CANCER-CELLS.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. George Vasmatzis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers validate blood test to diagnose Alzheimer&amp;#8217;s disease in outpatient memory clinics</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-validate-blood-test-to-diagnose-alzheimers-disease-in-outpatient-memory-clinics/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lynda De Widt]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 11:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Laboratories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Alzheimer’s disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Gregg Day]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403324</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. —&amp;#160;Alzheimer's disease, marked by memory loss, trouble concentrating and thinking, and changes in personality and behavior, devastates patients, their families and loved ones. With new treatments available for people with early signs of Alzheimer's disease, there is a growing need for accessible and cost-effective tests to diagnose Alzheimer's disease sooner. In a new [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-validate-blood-test-to-diagnose-alzheimers-disease-in-outpatient-memory-clinics/">Mayo Clinic researchers validate blood test to diagnose Alzheimer&amp;#8217;s disease in outpatient memory clinics</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Aging-hands-GettyImages-1802990110-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Photo of aging hands. Getty Images" class="wp-image-398491" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Aging-hands-GettyImages-1802990110-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Aging-hands-GettyImages-1802990110-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Aging-hands-GettyImages-1802990110-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Aging-hands-GettyImages-1802990110-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Aging-hands-GettyImages-1802990110-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. —&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/alzheimers-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350447" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alzheimer's disease</a>, marked by memory loss, trouble concentrating and thinking, and changes in personality and behavior, devastates patients, their families and loved ones. With new treatments available for people with early signs of Alzheimer's disease, there is a growing need for accessible and cost-effective tests to diagnose Alzheimer's disease sooner. In a new study, Mayo Clinic researchers confirmed the accuracy of an&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.fda.gov/news-events/press-announcements/fda-clears-first-blood-test-used-diagnosing-alzheimers-disease" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">FDA-approved blood test</a>&amp;nbsp;that can be used at outpatient memory clinics to diagnose the disease in patients with a range of cognitive impairment. The findings are&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://alz-journals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/alz.70316" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">published in Alzheimer's and Dementia: The Journal of the Alzheimer's Association</a>.</p>



<p>Standard ways of measuring the buildup of toxic proteins in the brain that indicate Alzheimer's disease include positron emission tomography, or PET scans, and spinal taps. But these tests can be expensive and invasive. More accessible, non-invasive and cost-effective biomarkers&amp;nbsp;—&amp;nbsp;measurable indicators of a disease&amp;nbsp;—&amp;nbsp;are needed to improve diagnoses broadly in clinical settings.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<div class="wp-block-media-text is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Gregg-S-Day-MD-neurology-FL-1-x-1-1-1024x1024.jpg" alt="Portrait of Gregg Day, M.D.. He says Mayo Clinic researchers validate blood test to diagnose Alzheimer's disease in outpatient memory clinics" class="wp-image-403332 size-full" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Gregg-S-Day-MD-neurology-FL-1-x-1-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Gregg-S-Day-MD-neurology-FL-1-x-1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Gregg-S-Day-MD-neurology-FL-1-x-1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Gregg-S-Day-MD-neurology-FL-1-x-1-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Gregg-S-Day-MD-neurology-FL-1-x-1-1-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Gregg-S-Day-MD-neurology-FL-1-x-1-1.jpg 2031w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p></p>



<p>"Our study found that blood testing affirmed the diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease with 95% sensitivity and 82% specificity,” says corresponding author&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/day-gregg-s-m-d/bio-20545897" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gregg Day, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic neurologist, dementia specialist and clinical researcher. "When performed in the outpatient clinical setting, this is similar to the accuracy of cerebrospinal fluid biomarkers of the disease and is much more convenient and cost-effective."</p>
</div></div>



<p></p>



<p>The research team says their findings show promise in:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Better identifying research participants with Alzheimer's disease brain changes.</li>



<li>Screening and selecting patients with Alzheimer's disease for clinical trials.</li>



<li>Assessing how patients respond to therapy in clinical trials.<br></li>
</ul>



<p>More than 500 patients receiving treatment for a range of memory issues at the outpatient&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/memory-disorder-clinic-florida/overview/ovc-20556902" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Memory Disorder Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;at&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a>&amp;nbsp;participated in the study. They included patients with early- and late-onset cognitive impairment, typical and atypical Alzheimer's disease,&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lewy-body-dementia/symptoms-causes/syc-20352025" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lewy body dementia</a>&amp;nbsp;and vascular cognitive impairment.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Patients ranged from 32 to 89 years old, with the average age of symptom onset being 66. Alzheimer's disease was determined to be the underlying cause of the symptoms in 56% of the patients. The team also conducted serum tests to measure kidney disease, which can influence plasma biomarker concentrations.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayocliniclabs.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Laboratories</a>&amp;nbsp;tested for two proteins in blood plasma that are associated with amyloid plaque buildup, the hallmark of Alzheimer's disease:&amp;nbsp;Aβ42/40 and p-tau217. The researchers found that p-tau217 levels were higher in patients with Alzheimer's disease versus those without the disease. Higher plasma p-tau217 concentrations were also associated with impaired kidney function, which researchers say should be taken into account when performing the blood test.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Plasma p-tau217 concentrations were positive in 267 out of 509 patients, including 233 of 246 patients (95%) with cognitive impairment attributed to Alzheimer's disease.</p>



<p>The study was featured at the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.aan.com/events/annual-meeting" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Academy of Neurology Annual Meeting</a>&amp;nbsp;in April.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>In a&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/39030981/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">previous study</a>, researchers from the Mayo Clinic Laboratories team showed the utility of these blood tests compared to amyloid PET scans in research participants.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Day says the next steps in this research are to evaluate blood-based testing in more diverse patient populations and people with early Alzheimer's disease who show no cognitive symptoms. The team also wants to evaluate disease-specific factors that may alter biomarker accuracy in clinical trials.</p>



<p>Other Mayo Clinic authors include Yoav Piura, M.D.,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/lachner-christian-m-d/bio-20149778" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Christian Lachner, M.D.</a>, Joshua Bornhorst, Ph.D.,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/algeciras-schimnich-alicia-ph-d/bio-00086617" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alicia Algeciras Schimnich, Ph.D.</a>, and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/graff-radford-neill-r-m-d/bio-00083030" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Neill Graff-Radford, M.D.</a>&nbsp;For a full list of authors, funding and disclosures, see the&nbsp;<a href="https://alz-journals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/alz.70316" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">paper</a>.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> <br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Tia Ford, Mayo Clinic Communications,&amp;nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-validate-blood-test-to-diagnose-alzheimers-disease-in-outpatient-memory-clinics/">Mayo Clinic researchers validate blood test to diagnose Alzheimer&amp;#8217;s disease in outpatient memory clinics</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Aging-hands-GettyImages-1802990110-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Aging-hands-GettyImages-1802990110-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Alzheimer’s disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Gregg Day]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss> 