<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Research - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 12:22:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic AI tool finds early signs of blood mutations linked to cancer&nbsp;and heart disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-ai-tool-finds-early-signs-of-blood-mutations-linked-to-cancer-and-heart-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AI and Digital Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individualized Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Eric Klee]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Shulan Tian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403209</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>(Video animation shows blood stem cells dividing and multiplying. Getty Images). Deep inside the body, a slow-growing cluster of mutated blood cells can form. This cluster, found in 1 in 5 older adults, can raise the risk of leukemia and heart disease, often without warning.&amp;#160; To better understand this hidden risk, Mayo Clinic researchers have [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-ai-tool-finds-early-signs-of-blood-mutations-linked-to-cancer-and-heart-disease/">Mayo Clinic AI tool finds early signs of blood mutations linked to cancer&nbsp;and heart disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-video"><video autoplay controls loop muted src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/09/GettyImages-1757724395.mp4" playsinline></video></figure>



<p class="has-text-align-center has-text-color has-link-color wp-elements-0a381724fd8a6321f7f32360329589e7" style="color:#4e526d"><em>(Video animation shows blood stem cells dividing and multiplying. Getty Images).</em></p>



<div style="height:25px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Deep inside the body, a slow-growing cluster of mutated blood cells can form. This cluster, found in 1 in 5 older adults, can raise the risk of leukemia and heart disease, often without warning.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>To better understand this hidden risk, Mayo Clinic researchers have developed an artificial intelligence (AI) tool to help investigators uncover how it contributes to disease risk and progression. </p>



<p>In a study <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Facademic.oup.com%2Fgpb%2Fadvance-article%2Fdoi%2F10.1093%2Fgpbjnl%2Fqzaf040%2F8121950&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7CMurphy.Susan%40mayo.edu%7C05f57239f813422ca87008ddc97a7be3%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C638888250101337358%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=EEqrric0Eslg1ajqpP60TW69EXgCPyIzcLJp5GRxa4Q%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0">published</a> in Genomics, Proteomics &amp;amp; Bioinformatics, the tool showed promising results in identifying early signs of this condition, known as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/cancer/news/clonal-hematopoiesis-clinic-stratifies-risk-for-patients-with-cancer/mac-20543180" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">clonal hematopoiesis of indeterminate potential</a>, or CHIP.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>When blood cells mutate</strong></h2>



<p>CHIP starts in the bone marrow, where blood stem cells make the cells that keep organs working, oxygen flowing and the immune system strong. But if one of those cells acquires a mutation in a gene linked to blood cancer, it can multiply abnormally, forming a cluster of mutated cells that gradually expands.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>This can cause CHIP, a condition with no symptoms that researchers link to higher rates of death, especially from heart disease. Because its effects vary, CHIP is hard to track and often goes undetected for years.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>CHIP makes leukemia more than 10 times more likely and raises the risk of heart disease up to four times, even in healthy adults. Finding it earlier could help guide proactive monitoring or preventive care.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A new tool for early detection</strong>&amp;nbsp;</h2>



<p>The new tool, called UNISOM — short for UNIfied SOmatic calling and Machine learning — was developed by <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/tian-shulan-ph-d-m-s/bio-20524328" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Shulan Tian, Ph.D.</a>, under the leadership of <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/klee-eric-w-ph-d/bio-00077293" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Eric Klee, Ph.D.</a>, co-senior author of the study and the Everett J. and Jane M. Hauck Midwest Associate Director of Research and Innovation.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>UNISOM helps clinicians identify CHIP-related mutations in standard genetic datasets, opening new avenues for research and discovery. In the past, that level of detection required more complex and advanced sequencing methods.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"Detecting disease at its earliest molecular roots is one of the most meaningful advances we can make in medicine," says Dr. Klee. "UNISOM is just one of many examples of how we're translating genomic science into innovative tools that support timely and informed care."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>UNISOM helped researchers detect nearly 80% of CHIP mutations using whole-exome sequencing, which analyzes the protein-coding regions of DNA.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The team also tested UNISOM on whole-genome sequencing data from the Mayo Clinic Biobank, which captures nearly all of a person's genetic code. In that data, it detected early signs of CHIP, including mutations present in fewer than 5% of blood cells. Standard techniques often miss these small but important changes.</p>



<p>"We're engineering a path from genomic discovery to clinical decision-making," says Dr. Tian, the co-senior author and a bioinformatician at Mayo Clinic. "It's rewarding to help bring these discoveries closer to clinical care, where they can inform decisions and support more precise treatment."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Next, the team plans to apply UNISOM to larger and more diverse datasets to support research and expand its use in clinical practice.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Review the <a href="https://academic.oup.com/gpb/article/23/2/qzaf040/8121950" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-ai-tool-finds-early-signs-of-blood-mutations-linked-to-cancer-and-heart-disease/">Mayo Clinic AI tool finds early signs of blood mutations linked to cancer&nbsp;and heart disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1-leukemia.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9leukemia.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Eric Klee]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Shulan Tian]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Progress in gene therapy offers hope for long-term knee pain relief</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/progress-in-gene-therapy-offers-hope-for-long-term-knee-pain-relief/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[mbroadfoot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Clinical Trials]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Discovery Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Christopher Evans]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=404948</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researchers aim to engineer knees that are more resistant to arthritis.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/progress-in-gene-therapy-offers-hope-for-long-term-knee-pain-relief/">Progress in gene therapy offers hope for long-term knee pain relief</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="683" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF1320397_0002-683x1024.jpg" alt="Christopher Evans, Ph.D, Professor of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation (PMR), and Consultant-Research in PMR. " class="wp-image-404953" style="width:275px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF1320397_0002-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF1320397_0002-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF1320397_0002-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF1320397_0002-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF1320397_0002-1365x2048.jpg 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 683px) 100vw, 683px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Christopher Evans, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>For nearly <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34437305/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">three decades</a>, Mayo Clinic researcher <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/evans-christopher-h-ph-d/bio-20086893" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Christopher Evans, Ph.D.</a>, has pushed to expand gene therapy beyond its original scope of fixing rare, single-gene defects. That has meant systematically advancing the field through laboratory experiments, pre-clinical studies and clinical trials.</p>



<p>Several gene therapies have already received approval from the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA), and experts predict that <a href="https://newdigs.tuftsmedicalcenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/NEWDIGS-Research-Brief-2020F207v51-PipelineAnalysis.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">40 to 60 more</a> could be approved over the next decade for a range of conditions. Dr. Evans hopes a gene therapy for osteoarthritis — a form of arthritis affecting more than <a href="https://oaaction.unc.edu/oa-module/oa-prevalence-and-burden/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">32.5 million</a> U.S. adults — will be one of them.</p>



<p>Recently, Dr. Evans and a team of 18 researchers and clinicians reported the results of a first-in-human, phase 1 clinical trial of a novel gene therapy for osteoarthritis. The findings, published in <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/40465688/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Science Translational Advances</a>, demonstrated that the therapy is safe, achieved sustained expression of a therapeutic gene inside the joint and offered early evidence of clinical benefit.</p>



<p>"This could revolutionize the treatment of osteoarthritis," says Dr. Evans, who directs the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/musculoskeletal-gene-therapy-research" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Musculoskeletal Gene Therapy Research</a> lab at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>In <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/osteoarthritis/symptoms-causes/syc-20351925" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">osteoarthritis</a>, the cartilage that cushions the ends of bones — and sometimes the underlying bone itself — degenerates over time. It is a leading cause of disability, and notoriously difficult to treat. "Any medications you inject into the affected joint will seep right back out in a few hours," says Dr. Evans. "As far as I know, gene therapy is the only reasonable way to overcome this pharmacologic barrier, and it's a huge barrier." By genetically modifying cells in the joint to produce their own pharmacy of anti-inflammatory molecules, Evans aims to engineer knees that are more resistant to arthritis.</p>



<p>The Evans laboratory found that a molecule called interleukin-1 (IL-1) plays an important role in fueling inflammation, pain and cartilage loss in osteoarthritis. As luck would have it, the molecule had a natural inhibitor, aptly named the IL-1 receptor antagonist (IL-1Ra), that could form the basis of the first gene therapy for the disease. In 2000, Dr. Evans and his team <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/10853185/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">packaged the IL-1Ra gene into a harmless virus called AAV</a>, which they tested in cells and then pre-clinical models. The results were encouraging.</p>



<p>In pre-clinical testing, his collaborators at the University of Florida demonstrated that the gene therapy successfully infiltrated the cells that make up the synovial lining of the joint as well as the neighboring cartilage. The therapy <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/11850718/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">protected the cartilage</a> from breakdown. In 2015, the team got investigational new drug approval to start human testing. But regulatory hurdles and manufacturing challenges kept them from injecting their first patient for another four years. Mayo Clinic has since established a&nbsp;new process for accelerating clinical trial&nbsp;activation that could help researchers launch studies more quickly.</p>



<p>In the <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/40465688/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">recent study</a>, Dr. Evans and his team gave the experimental gene therapy to nine patients with osteoarthritis, delivering it directly into the knee joint. They found that the levels of the anti-inflammatory IL-1Ra increased and remained elevated in the joint for at least a year. Participants also reported reduced pain and improved joint function, with no serious safety issues. Dr. Evans says the findings suggest the treatment is safe and may offer long-lasting relief from osteoarthritis symptoms. "This study provides a highly promising, novel way to attack the disease," he says.</p>



<p>Dr. Evans has co-founded an arthritis gene therapy company called <a href="https://genascence.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Genascence </a>to drive the project forward. The company just completed a larger phase Ib study and is in discussions with the FDA about launching a pivotal phase IIb/III clinical trial&nbsp;to evaluate the therapy's effectiveness, the next step before FDA approval for the therapy.</p>



<p>Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/40465688/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Additional resources: </strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/pushing-the-limits-of-gene-therapy-for-osteoarthritis/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pushing the limits of gene therapy for osteoarthritis</a></li>
</ul>



<p><a id="_msocom_1"></a></p>



<p>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/progress-in-gene-therapy-offers-hope-for-long-term-knee-pain-relief/">Progress in gene therapy offers hope for long-term knee pain relief</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/osteoarthritis-illo1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/osteoarthritis-illo16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Christopher Evans]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic deploys NVIDIA Blackwell infrastructure to drive generative AI solutions in medicine</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-deploys-nvidia-blackwell-infrastructure-to-drive-generative-ai-solutions-in-medicine/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[criley]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AI and Digital Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=405155</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic took a pivotal step toward integrating AI solutions in the clinical setting with the deployment of NVIDIA DGX SuperPOD with NVIDIA DGX B200 systems, an advanced infrastructure that provides state-of-the-art AI compute capabilities. Mayo Clinic and NVIDIA collaborated to enable the rapid innovation and development of foundation models in support [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-deploys-nvidia-blackwell-infrastructure-to-drive-generative-ai-solutions-in-medicine/">Mayo Clinic deploys NVIDIA Blackwell infrastructure to drive generative AI solutions in medicine</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-center-align-caption"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Discussing-a-digital-pathology-image_WF2205754_0440-1024x683.jpg" alt="A group of consultants discuss and review a colorful digital pathology image on a wall monitor." class="wp-image-405164" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Discussing-a-digital-pathology-image_WF2205754_0440-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Discussing-a-digital-pathology-image_WF2205754_0440-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Discussing-a-digital-pathology-image_WF2205754_0440-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Discussing-a-digital-pathology-image_WF2205754_0440-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Discussing-a-digital-pathology-image_WF2205754_0440.jpg 1687w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><sup>A group of consultants discuss and review a digital pathology image on a wall monitor.</sup></figcaption></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> took a pivotal step toward integrating AI solutions in the clinical setting with the deployment of <a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/data-center/dgx-superpod/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">NVIDIA DGX SuperPOD</a> with NVIDIA DGX B200 systems, an advanced infrastructure that provides state-of-the-art AI compute capabilities.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic and NVIDIA collaborated to enable the rapid innovation and development of foundation models in support of Mayo’s platform approach to healthcare, contributing to Mayo Clinic’s Bold. Forward. strategy and new innovations for generative AI solutions and digital pathology. These innovations are delivering new insights as Mayo is driving to improve patient outcomes and transform healthcare.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Callstrom.WF1447844_0012-200x300.jpg" alt="Headshot of Dr. Matthew Callstrom" class="wp-image-405148" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Callstrom.WF1447844_0012-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Callstrom.WF1447844_0012-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Callstrom.WF1447844_0012.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><sup>Matthew Callstrom, M.D., Ph.D.</sup></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Our aspiration for AI is to meaningfully improve patient outcomes by detecting disease early enough to intervene. What was once a hypothetical — 'If only we had the right data' — is now becoming reality thanks to AI and advanced computing," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/callstrom-matthew-r-m-d-ph-d/bio-00085927" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Matthew Callstrom, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, medical director of the Department of Strategy and leader of Mayo Clinic’s Generative Artificial Intelligence Program.</p>



<p>The advanced computing infrastructure will initially support foundation model development for pathomics, drug discovery and precision medicine.</p>



<p>The NVIDIA Blackwell-powered <a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/data-center/dgx-b200/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">DGX SuperPOD</a> is built to efficiently process large, high-resolution imaging essential for AI foundation model training. Designed for speed and scalability, the Blackwell infrastructure enables Mayo Clinic to accelerate pathology slide analysis and foundation model development — reducing four weeks of work to just one, ultimately improving patient outcomes. This advanced computing infrastructure will also advance Mayo Clinic’s generative AI and multimodal digital pathology foundation model development.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoid6qfRLnhGAk"  title="Mayo Clinic DGX B200 SuperPOD for Generative AI | Launch | Summer 2025" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/6qfRLnhG_Ak?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic, in partnership with Aignostics, developed a leading pathology foundation model called Atlas, trained on more than 1.2 million histopathology whole-slide images. With Atlas, Mayo Clinic clinicians and researchers can improve accuracy and reduce administrative tasks. The new computing capabilities will accelerate and improve clinical model development.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/A-RogersWF5636492_0005-1024x768.jpg" alt="Portrait of Jim Rogers" class="wp-image-405170" style="width:381px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/A-RogersWF5636492_0005-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/A-RogersWF5636492_0005-300x225.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/A-RogersWF5636492_0005-768x576.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/A-RogersWF5636492_0005-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/A-RogersWF5636492_0005-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p>"This compute power, coupled with Mayo’s unparalleled clinical expertise and platform data of over 20 million digitized pathology slides, will allow Mayo to build on its existing foundation models. We’re transforming healthcare by quickly and safely developing innovative AI solutions that can improve patient outcomes and enable clinicians to dedicate more time to patient care while also accelerating commercial affiliations with other industry leaders," says Jim Rogers, CEO of Mayo Clinic Digital Pathology.</p>



<p><strong>Journalists:</strong> Media kit with images for download available <a href="https://mcmedia.mayo.edu/Share/871b647n73p1b11u4jw8yys7voanethw?FR_=1&amp;amp;W=1620&amp;amp;H=976">here</a>.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Digital Pathology</strong><br>Mayo Clinic Digital Pathology facilitates the global scaling of digital pathology solutions to benefit clinicians and patients, advancing key areas such as scanning, storage, foundation model development and the creation and deployment of cutting-edge algorithms. Working with Mayo Clinic innovators and external collaborators, Mayo Clinic Digital Pathology is wholly owned by Mayo Clinic and seeks to incubate and start impactful companies while investing in and acquiring existing companies, spurring innovation across pathology.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications,&amp;nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-deploys-nvidia-blackwell-infrastructure-to-drive-generative-ai-solutions-in-medicine/">Mayo Clinic deploys NVIDIA Blackwell infrastructure to drive generative AI solutions in medicine</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Discussing-a-digital-pathology-image_WF2205754_0440_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Discussing-a-digital-pathology-image_WF2205754_0440_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers link CAR-T cell aging to cancer relapse&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-link-car-t-cell-aging-to-cancer-relapse/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Discovery Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individualized Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Ismail Can]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Saad Kendarian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=404713</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic researchers have discovered a key reason some cancer patients relapse after receiving chimeric antigen receptor T-cell therapy, or CAR-T cell therapy. Over time, the engineered immune cells age and lose their ability to fight cancer. &amp;#160; Published in Molecular Cancer, the study identifies this aging process, known as senescence, as [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-link-car-t-cell-aging-to-cancer-relapse/">Mayo Clinic researchers link CAR-T cell aging to cancer relapse&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-video"><video autoplay controls loop muted src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/GettyImages-1808335875.mp4" playsinline></video></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> researchers have discovered a key reason some cancer patients relapse after receiving chimeric antigen receptor T-cell therapy, or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/car-t-cell-therapy/about/pac-20585020" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CAR-T cell therapy</a>. Over time, the engineered immune cells age and lose their ability to fight cancer. &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://molecular-cancer.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12943-025-02371-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Published</a> in Molecular Cancer, the study identifies this aging process, known as senescence, as a previously unrecognized mechanism of CAR-T failure.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The researchers also showed that senescence is influenced by how CAR-T cells are engineered. Certain intracellular features — such as how the cell recognizes cancer and how strongly it activates — can overwork the cells. The researchers found that if the activation signal is too intense or prolonged, it can push CAR-T cells into premature aging. &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The discovery may guide the development of next-generation CAR-T therapies that last longer and are more effective across a broader range of cancers. &amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF5259875_0007-1-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-404717" style="width:431px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF5259875_0007-1-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF5259875_0007-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF5259875_0007-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF5259875_0007-1-1536x1025.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/WF5259875_0007-1-2048x1366.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Saad Kenderian, MB, ChB, Hematology consultant, and Chimeric Antigen Receptor (CAR) T Cell Engineering Laboratory lead, poses in the CAR T Cell Engineering Laboratory.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"This is one of the most clinically relevant discoveries we've made because it doesn't just explain the cause of relapse, it gives us a biological target to possibly prevent it," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/kenderian-saad-j-m-b-ch-b/bio-20206512" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Saad Kenderian, M.B., Ch.B.</a>, a principal investigator and hematologist at Mayo Clinic. &nbsp;</p>



<p>CAR-T therapy reprograms a patient's own immune cells to recognize and destroy cancer. It has led to long-term remission for patients, including some with aggressive or treatment-resistant diseases. But many patients eventually relapse, and the causes have remained poorly understood.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Modeling CAR-T cell stress over time</strong>&amp;nbsp;</h2>



<p>To investigate why CAR-T therapy can fail, the Mayo team developed a novel lab model that simulates long-term biological stress, offering a clearer view of how the engineered cells behave after infusion. Over time, some CAR-T cells lost their ability to multiply and attack cancer. Specifically, they showed hallmark signs of senescence, including distinct genetic changes. &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The researchers found that senescence occurred more often in CAR-T cells built with a signaling feature, known as 4-1BB, which affects how the cells respond to cancer. In comparison, cells designed with an alternative domain, called CD28, were less affected by aging. These cells activate more quickly and persist for a shorter time, reducing the cumulative stress that drives senescence. </p>



<p>The researchers confirmed the results in multiple laboratory models and validated them in patient samples.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Engineering CAR-T cells for longevity</strong>&amp;nbsp;</h2>



<p>That discovery was driven in part by the work of Ismail Can, Ph.D., who helped lead the molecular analysis behind the finding.&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="683" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/DR.CAN_-683x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-404740" style="width:222px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/DR.CAN_-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/DR.CAN_-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/DR.CAN_-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/DR.CAN_-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/DR.CAN_-1365x2048.jpg 1365w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 683px) 100vw, 683px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Ismail Can, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Efforts to make CAR-T cell therapy more durable will likely fail without fully understanding the reasons behind CAR-T cell failure. This study represents a significant step toward understanding why CAR-T cells fail," says Dr. Can, first author of the study and a senior research fellow at Mayo Clinic’s T&amp;nbsp;Cell Engineering Laboratory. "By identifying the early molecular triggers of senescence, we can begin to refine CAR-T design to potentially improve long-term function and reduce relapse."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The findings highlight a new direction for CAR-T research, with potential implications not only for blood cancers but also for expanding cell therapy into solid tumors. &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The study builds on Dr. Kenderian's broader efforts to identify resistance mechanisms and design more durable and personalized immunotherapies. &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>This work was supported in part by Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, the Eagles 5th District Cancer Telethon Funds for Cancer Research, the State of Minnesota, and benefactors Georgia and Michael Michelson. For a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding information, review the <a href="https://molecular-cancer.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12943-025-02371-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>. &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>###&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&amp;nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact: </strong>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Sharon Theimer, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-link-car-t-cell-aging-to-cancer-relapse/">Mayo Clinic researchers link CAR-T cell aging to cancer relapse&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/1x1-Kenderian.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/16x9-KENDERIEAN.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Ismail Can]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Saad Kendarian]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Pioneering change: The inception and potential of Mayo Clinic&amp;#8217;s Nursing Research Scholars</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/7-11-pioneering-change-the-inception-and-potential-of-mayo-clinics-nursing-research-scholars/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Carey Stanton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 13:12:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=404710</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic’s Department of Nursing welcomes its first&nbsp;Nursing Research Scholars. As an Academic Medical Center, Mayo integrates clinical practice with research and education to deliver the best possible care. In its inaugural year, three scholars were accepted into the unique Nursing Research Scholar program. Under the guidance of nurse scientists in the Division of Nursing [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/7-11-pioneering-change-the-inception-and-potential-of-mayo-clinics-nursing-research-scholars/">Pioneering change: The inception and potential of Mayo Clinic&amp;#8217;s Nursing Research Scholars</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-center-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Nursing-Research-Scholars-1024x576.jpg" alt="Nursing research scholars" class="wp-image-404728" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Nursing-Research-Scholars-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Nursing-Research-Scholars-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Nursing-Research-Scholars-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Nursing-Research-Scholars.jpg 1080w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Jeanine Gangeness, Ph.D., Amanda Rossley, Ph.D. and Savannah Zins, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic’s Department of Nursing welcomes its first&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/departments-divisions/department-nursing/nursing-research-division/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nursing Research Scholars</a>. As an Academic Medical Center, Mayo integrates clinical practice with research and education to deliver the best possible care. In its inaugural year, three scholars were accepted into the unique Nursing Research Scholar program. Under the guidance of nurse scientists in the Division of Nursing Research, the Nursing Research Scholars are Ph.D.-prepared nurses who will now dedicate one day a week to research that improves patient care.&nbsp;</p>



<div class="wp-block-media-text is-stacked-on-mobile is-vertically-aligned-center"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="820" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/res-research-model-1-1-768x820-1.png" alt="Nursing research graphic" class="wp-image-404731 size-full" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/res-research-model-1-1-768x820-1.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/res-research-model-1-1-768x820-1-281x300.png 281w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p></p>



<p>Research at Mayo Clinic begins with the unmet needs of the patient. As a patient or a loved one, you want to be sure you are receiving the best care from the best-trained staff who follow evidence-based care. Nurses provide direct care to patients daily, so they know which approaches work well and which need adjusting. A key characteristic of an effective practitioner is the ability to evaluate standard procedures and identify opportunities for improvement. The concept of refining nursing practices and procedures is at the heart of nursing research.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p></p>
</div></div>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p>Education and training are ongoing in medicine, and nurses are frequently tasked with updating their knowledge.&amp;nbsp;Amanda Rossley, Ph.D.,&amp;nbsp;a&amp;nbsp;nurse manager in nursing professional development, hopes to study the latest in training pedagogy by using gamification to improve learning among nurses. “Gaming is an active learning strategy that improves concentration, creativity, memory and engagement,” she says.&amp;nbsp;She hopes her research will contribute to data-driven insights that lead to the practical translation for gamification-based nursing and patient education that improves patient care. For patients, this means the possibility of playing a game to learn more about managing conditions, instead of reading about it.</p>



<p>The clinical performance of a nursing student is influenced by their mental health, social support, the learning environment and self-efficacy, or the belief in one's capacity to perform.&amp;nbsp;Jeanine Gangeness, Ph.D.,&amp;nbsp;a&amp;nbsp;program director in Nursing Academic Affairs, is on a mission to enhance the existing training environment for nursing students by pinpointing which interventions increase student self-efficacy and sense of belonging. “This research is an investment in the future workforce of Mayo Clinic,” she explains. “Nursing students with high self-efficacy are more likely to work hard, complete their tasks and be more resilient in the face of failures, leading to better patient outcomes and more competent and confident nurses.”</p>



<p>For patients with adverse symptoms, relief cannot come soon enough. Despite monumental advances in medical practice and technology, many questions remain regarding symptom management in complex patients.&amp;nbsp;Savannah Zins, Ph.D.,&amp;nbsp;a nursing education specialist in nursing professional development, says, “Understanding the biological and behavioral aspects of adverse symptoms through symptom science can improve patients’ quality of life, reduce chronic symptoms and burden, and lower healthcare costs.” Through her research, Zins hopes to identify non-pharmacologic and nursing interventions to make patients more comfortable.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Because Mayo Clinic is highly collaborative, discoveries from one area are quickly translated to other areas. Within this scholarly environment, staff at Mayo continually seek new medical knowledge and ways to rapidly and responsibly validate and apply it. The Nursing Research Scholar program is one example of how the organization empowers nurses to integrate their clinical expertise with guided research opportunities, applying their findings to drive change. These research initiatives will have a positive impact, enabling the organization to share discoveries that lead to improved healthcare beyond its walls.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/7-11-pioneering-change-the-inception-and-potential-of-mayo-clinics-nursing-research-scholars/">Pioneering change: The inception and potential of Mayo Clinic&amp;#8217;s Nursing Research Scholars</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/res-research-model-1-1-768x820-1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Nursing-Research-Scholars.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers develop AI tool to detect surgical site infections from patient-submitted photos</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-ai-tool-to-detect-surgical-site-infections-from-patient-submitted-photos/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chloe Corey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 13:46:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AI and Digital Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Cornelius Thiels]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Hala Muaddi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=404641</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn.&amp;#160;— A team of Mayo Clinic researchers has developed an artificial intelligence (AI) system that can detect surgical site infections (SSIs) with high accuracy from patient-submitted postoperative wound photos, potentially transforming how postoperative care is delivered. Published in the&amp;#160;Annals of Surgery, the study introduces an AI-based pipeline the researchers created that can automatically identify [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-ai-tool-to-detect-surgical-site-infections-from-patient-submitted-photos/">Mayo Clinic researchers develop AI tool to detect surgical site infections from patient-submitted photos</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-style-center-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1603" height="902" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-in-surgery-16-x-9.jpg" alt="Dr. Hala Muaddi in surgery" class="wp-image-404654" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-in-surgery-16-x-9.jpg 1603w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-in-surgery-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-in-surgery-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-in-surgery-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-in-surgery-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1603px) 100vw, 1603px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Hala Muaddi in surgery</figcaption></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn.&amp;nbsp;— A team of Mayo Clinic researchers has developed an artificial intelligence (AI) system that can detect surgical site infections (SSIs) with high accuracy from patient-submitted postoperative wound photos, potentially transforming how postoperative care is delivered.</p>



<p>Published in the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://journals.lww.com/annalsofsurgery/abstract/9900/imaging_based_surgical_site_infection_detection.1357.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Annals of Surgery</a>, the study introduces an AI-based pipeline the researchers created that can automatically identify surgical incisions, assess image quality and flag signs of infection in photos submitted by patients through online portals. The system was trained on over 20,000 images from more than 6,000 patients across nine Mayo Clinic hospitals.<br><br>"We were motivated by the increasing need for outpatient monitoring of surgical incisions in a timely manner," says&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/thiels-cornelius-a-d-o-m-b-a/bio-20519744" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cornelius Thiels, D.O.</a>, a hepatobiliary and pancreatic surgical oncologist at Mayo Clinic and co-senior author of the study. "This process, currently done by clinicians, is time-consuming and can delay care. Our AI model can help triage these images automatically, improving early detection and streamlining communication between patients and their care teams."</p>



<p>The AI system uses a two-stage model. First, it detects whether an image contains a surgical incision and then evaluates whether that incision shows signs of infection. The model, Vision Transformer, achieved a 94% accuracy in detecting incisions and an 81% area under the curve (AUC) in identifying infections.</p>



<p></p>



<div class="wp-block-media-text is-stacked-on-mobile" style="grid-template-columns:38% auto"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="855" height="855" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-1-x-1.jpg" alt="Dr. Hala Muaddi" class="wp-image-404653 size-full" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-1-x-1.jpg 855w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-1-x-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-1-x-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-1-x-1-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 855px) 100vw, 855px" /></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p>"This work lays the foundation for AI-assisted postoperative wound care, which can transform how postoperative patients are monitored," says Hala Muaddi, M.D., Ph.D., a hepatopancreatobiliary fellow at Mayo Clinic and first author. "It’s especially relevant as outpatient operations and virtual follow-ups become more common."</p>
</div></div>



<p></p>



<p>The researchers are hopeful that this technology could help patients receive faster responses, reduce delays in diagnosing infections and support better care for those recovering from surgery at home. With further validation, it could function as a frontline screening tool that alerts clinicians to concerning incisions. This AI tool also paves the way for developing algorithms capable of detecting subtle signs of infection, potentially before they become visually apparent to the care team. This would allow for earlier treatment, decreased morbidity and reduced costs.</p>



<p>"For patients, this could mean faster reassurance or earlier identification of a problem," says Dr. Muaddi. "For clinicians, it offers a way to prioritize attention to cases that need it most, especially in rural or resource-limited settings."</p>



<p>Importantly, the model demonstrated consistent performance across diverse groups, addressing concerns about algorithmic bias.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>While the results are promising, the team says that further validation is needed.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"Our hope is that the AI models we developed — and the large dataset they were trained on — have the potential to fundamentally reshape how surgical follow-up is delivered," says&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/salehinejad-hojjat-ph-d/bio-20547448" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hojjat Salehinejad, Ph.D.</a>, a senior associate consultant of health care delivery research within the Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery and co-senior author. "Prospective studies are underway to evaluate how well this tool integrates into day-to-day surgical care."</p>



<p>This research was supported by the Dalio Philanthropies Artificial Intelligence/Machine Learning Enablement Award and the Simons Family Career Development Award in Surgical Innovation.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Chloe Corey, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-ai-tool-to-detect-surgical-site-infections-from-patient-submitted-photos/">Mayo Clinic researchers develop AI tool to detect surgical site infections from patient-submitted photos</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-surgery-1-x-1-.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Dr.-Hala-Muaddi-in-surgery-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Cornelius Thiels]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Hala Muaddi]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>(VIDEO) A rare cancer. A rare weapon. Curtis Jackson&amp;#8217;s inspiring story of survival</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-a-rare-cancer-a-rare-weapon-curtis-jacksons-inspiring-story-of-survival/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 17:33:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MC Video pkg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cholangiocarcinoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Liver Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Liver Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403352</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Curtis Jackson was living his dream life — a loving and supportive wife, three wonderful kids, and a future that looked as bright as could be. Then, one day, without warning, the dream was shattered. At only 46, Curtis was diagnosed with&amp;#160;cholangiocarcinoma, one of the deadliest and most aggressive forms of cancer. It's a silent [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-a-rare-cancer-a-rare-weapon-curtis-jacksons-inspiring-story-of-survival/">(VIDEO) A rare cancer. A rare weapon. Curtis Jackson&amp;#8217;s inspiring story of survival</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-and-Kim-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-404539" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-and-Kim-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-and-Kim-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-and-Kim-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-and-Kim-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-and-Kim-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Curtis and Kim Jackson</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Curtis Jackson was living his dream life — a loving and supportive wife, three wonderful kids, and a future that looked as bright as could be.</p>



<p>Then, one day, without warning, the dream was shattered.</p>



<p>At only 46, Curtis was diagnosed with&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cholangiocarcinoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20352408">cholangiocarcinoma</a>, one of the deadliest and most aggressive forms of cancer. It's a silent killer that strikes the liver. It is often diagnosed in later stages, leaving patients with few treatment options and little time to live.</p>



<p>The Jackson family turned to Mayo Clinic, where a team of experts fought the cancer with a weapon rarely used in the battle against this aggressive form of cancer.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/7TZSj_T0CHQ" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: A rare cancer. A rare weapon. Curtis Jackson's inspiring story of survival.</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutube7TZSjT0CHQ"  title="A rare cancer. A rare weapon. Curtis Jackson&amp;#039;s inspiring story of survival." width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/7TZSj_T0CHQ?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (2:17) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/A-rare-cancer.-A-rare-weapon.-Curtis-Jacksons-inspiring-story-of-survival-.pdf">script</a>.</strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The rare cancer</strong></h2>



<p>Years before his cancer diagnosis, Curtis was diagnosed with <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-primary-sclerosing-cholangitis/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">primary sclerosing cholangitis (PSC)</a>. PSC is a chronic liver disease that causes inflammation and scarring to the bile ducts, which work with the liver to help with digestion.</p>



<p>PSC put the Arizona man at higher risk for liver cancer, requiring him to get regular diagnostic screenings. As with most forms of cancer, but particularly cholangiocarcinoma, doctors say early detection is key to improving patient outcomes.</p>



<p>However, with cholangiocarcinoma, there are often no warning signs or symptoms alerting patients of the need to consult with their doctor about getting screened, until it's too late. In Curtis' case, the cholangiocarcinoma was detected in one of his routine screenings at Mayo Clinic, which doctors say likely helped save his life.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-center-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-with-Dr.-Aqel-Bashar-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Curtis and Kim Jackson consulting with Dr. Aqel Bashar;cholangiocarcinoma,  a rare cancer led to a treatment at Mayo Clinic." class="wp-image-404534" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-with-Dr.-Aqel-Bashar-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-with-Dr.-Aqel-Bashar-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-with-Dr.-Aqel-Bashar-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-with-Dr.-Aqel-Bashar-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-with-Dr.-Aqel-Bashar-16-x-9.jpg 1993w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Curtis and Kim consulting with Dr. Bashar Aqel, director, Mayo Clinic Transplant Center in Arizona</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>"It's a very rare cancer that tends to grow unnoticed," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/bekaii-saab-tanios-s-m-d/bio-20413464">Dr. Tanios Bekaii-Saab</a>, an oncologist with the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center/cancer-care/arizona" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center in Arizona</a>. "If the cancer gets to the point where it's too advanced for surgery or transplantation, universally this is a noncurative or noncurable cancer."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The rare weapon</strong></h2>



<p>Doctors say a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/liver-transplant/home/orc-20211818" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">liver transplant </a>can sometimes be an option for some patients. However, not many transplant centers perform liver transplants on patients diagnosed with cholangiocarcinoma. Mayo Clinic is one of the few centers that do offer liver transplantation for some patients who meet certain criteria.</p>



<p>In Curtis' case, doctors at Mayo Clinic determined a liver transplant was his best chance for survival.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p>"We're not just here treating the cancer. We're also treating the disease that led to the cancer."</p><cite>Dr. Tanios Bekaii-Saab, Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center in Arizona</cite></blockquote></figure>



<p>"It is a unique form of therapy that is based on research that started at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/aqel-bashar-a-m-d/bio-20055093">Dr. Bashar Aqel</a>, director of the Mayo Clinic Transplant Center in Arizona.</p>



<p>"We developed some protocols that helped us improve the outcome of transplant in these patients, and without these protocols, a lot of patients with this type of cancer would not make it to transplant," says Dr. Aqel.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p>"Mayo Clinic's ability to offer this curative option for rare cancers like this has differentiated us from many other transplant centers."</p><cite>Dr. Bashar Aqel, Director, Mayo Clinic Transplant Center in Arizona</cite></blockquote></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The treatment</strong></h2>



<p>Curtis first underwent <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/chemotherapy/about/pac-20385033" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chemotherapy</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/radiation-therapy/about/pac-20385162" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">radiation</a> at Mayo Clinic. He was then placed on the liver transplant waiting list for a donor organ. While waiting, Curtis says he kept his focus on his family.</p>



<p>"I spent all the time I could with my wife and kids, like basketball practices, homework, anything we could do to help our kids," says Curtis.</p>



<p>When Curtis got the call a donor organ was found, he immediately reported to Mayo Clinic to undergo his lifesaving liver transplant. The surgery was a success. Four weeks later, Curtis was back at home with family recovering well and feeling a deep sense of gratitude for his organ donor and his team at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized is-style-center-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-Jackson-Stetson-Rooney-Gwyn-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Curtis with his children following his successful liver transplant, due to his rare cancer." class="wp-image-404531" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-Jackson-Stetson-Rooney-Gwyn-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-Jackson-Stetson-Rooney-Gwyn-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-Jackson-Stetson-Rooney-Gwyn-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-Jackson-Stetson-Rooney-Gwyn-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-Jackson-Stetson-Rooney-Gwyn-16-x-9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Curtis with his children following his successful liver transplant    Photo courtesy: Jackson family</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>"Thank you because now I get to see my daughters get married, go to college, I get to see my son live his dreams and go to college and get married," says Curtis. "I get to live and grow old with my wife. I can't say this enough to everyone, 'thank you.'"</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p>"What Mayo has done to make these transplants happen is a miracle."</p><cite>Curtis Jackson, liver transplant recipient and cancer survivor</cite></blockquote></figure>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-4-days-post-1-x-1-1024x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-404533" style="width:570px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-4-days-post-1-x-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-4-days-post-1-x-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-4-days-post-1-x-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-4-days-post-1-x-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Kim-and-Curtis-Jackson-4-days-post-1-x-1.jpg 1427w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Curtis and Kim following his liver transplant    Photo courtesy: Jackson family</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We're already observing excellent function from Curtis' new liver, with the majority of his liver tests returning normal results," says Dr. Aqel. "His recovery has been remarkably swift and impressive."</p>



<p>"A lot of love goes out to the people in that family," says Gwyn Jackson, Curtis' oldest daughter in reference to the organ donor's family. "They allowed us to have our dad back and we're so grateful because we love him so much."</p>



<p>Doctors at Mayo Clinic are monitoring Curtis' progress closely. Meanwhile, Curtis' future is back to looking bright, only now with even deeper gratitude in his heart.</p>



<p>"This truly is the gift of life," says Curtis.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Related stories:</strong></h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-breathing-easy-thanks-to-the-gift-of-life-and-new-mayo-clinic-lung-transplant-program-in-arizona/">(VIDEO) Breathing easy thanks to the gift of life and new Mayo Clinic Lung Transplant Program in Arizona</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-barriers-helping-native-americans-in-need-get-the-gift-of-life/">Breaking barriers: Helping Native Americans in need get the gift of life</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-jessies-journey/">Jessie’s Journey</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/videoharnessing-the-power-of-innovation-and-a-patients-will-to-survive/">(VIDEO) Harnessing the power of innovation and a patient’s will to survive</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-a-rare-cancer-a-rare-weapon-curtis-jacksons-inspiring-story-of-survival/">(VIDEO) A rare cancer. A rare weapon. Curtis Jackson&amp;#8217;s inspiring story of survival</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-and-Kim-Jackson-at-window-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/07/Curtis-and-Kim-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cholangiocarcinoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Liver Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Liver Transplant]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mcthumb >https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-CANCER-CELLS-150x150.png</mayoclinic:mcthumb >	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researcher harnesses uniqueness of space to advance medicine on Earth</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researcher-harnesses-uniqueness-of-space-to-advance-medicine-on-earth/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sharon Theimer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 13:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Abba Zubair]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=404367</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Cancer, stroke, bone loss among diseases and conditions studied in microgravity JACKSONVILLE, Florida — Mayo Clinic physician and researcher Dr. Abba Zubair’s work combines two passions — medicine and space — for the benefit of astronauts and people on Earth. His research in space is yielding discoveries in cancer, stroke, bone loss and more. In [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researcher-harnesses-uniqueness-of-space-to-advance-medicine-on-earth/">Mayo Clinic researcher harnesses uniqueness of space to advance medicine on Earth</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Abba-Zubair-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-404368" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Abba-Zubair-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Abba-Zubair-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Abba-Zubair-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Abba-Zubair-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Abba-Zubair-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><em>Cancer, stroke, bone loss among diseases and conditions studied in microgravity</em></p>



<p>JACKSONVILLE, Florida — Mayo Clinic physician and researcher <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/zubair-abba-c-m-d-ph-d/bio-00092417" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Abba Zubair’s</a> work combines two passions — medicine and space — for the benefit of astronauts and people on Earth. His research in space is yielding discoveries in <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20370588" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stroke/symptoms-causes/syc-20350113" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stroke</a>, bone loss and more. In this expert alert, Dr. Zubair answers five questions about his studies in <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/centers-and-facilities/glenn/what-is-microgravity/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">microgravity</a>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What are you hoping to accomplish through your research?</h2>



<p>"The goal is to harness the uniqueness of the space environment for the betterment of humanity, be it on Earth or in space," Dr. Zubair says."We wanted to take advantage of the environment at the International Space Station to study how it affects human physiology."</p>



<p>The absence of gravity and the impacts of radiation and vacuum are three fundamental aspects of the uniqueness of space, adds Dr. Zubair, who has sent three research projects to the International Space Station (ISS) since 2017, with more to come.</p>



<p>As a <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">regenerative biotherapeutics</a> specialist, Dr. Zubair's work focuses in part on adult&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bone-marrow-transplant/in-depth/stem-cells/art-20048117?mc_id=us&amp;amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;amp;utm_medium=l&amp;amp;utm_content=content&amp;amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;amp;geo=national&amp;amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;amp;invsrc=other&amp;amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stem cells</a>&amp;nbsp;— known as mesenchymal stem cells —and their use in future treatments for stroke. He noted that he uses stem cells in regenerative medicine and in supporting Mayo's <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bone-marrow-transplant/about/pac-20384854" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bone marrow transplant program</a>.</p>



<p>"I also know how challenging it is to grow them in the lab. One of the first fundamentals is to see how the absence of gravity influences how stem cells divide and the growth rate," Dr. Zubair explains. "We wanted to see whether cells grown in space are any better or grow faster than cells grown in the lab. When we did our first space flight, we had a really interesting finding, because we realized that the absence of gravity affects stem cells, but it depends on the type of stem cells." &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>That led Dr. Zubair to another project on the ISS: studying how mesenchymal stem cells, the precursor for bone-forming cells, play a role in bone formation or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/osteoporosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20351968" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">osteoporosis</a>, bone loss. He notes that astronauts tend to lose bone density despite rigorous exercise.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How might your research benefit people with cancer?</h2>



<p>Dr. Zubair is also studying how <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/leukemia/symptoms-causes/syc-20374373" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">leukemia</a> stem cells, the cells that form the seed of this blood cancer, respond to the space environment.</p>



<p>"We are also working to understand the impact of space radiation, from the angle of how we can mitigate the effect of radiation and prevent cancer," Dr. Zubair says. "In the long run, we really want to protect astronauts, especially during long-term space travel, such as to Mars, where they would be deep in space and away from any magnetic field protection that we get from Earth."</p>



<p>The research also may benefit people on Earth by revealing how to protect stem cells or cells in general when there is radiation exposure, such as nuclear accidents, he adds.</p>



<p>In addition, Dr. Zubair's space research could have implications for CAR-T treatment, bone marrow transplants or other therapies for cancer patients.</p>



<p>"If we can understand how stem cells in space, especially <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bone-marrow-transplant/in-depth/stem-cells/art-20048117" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hematopoietic&nbsp;stem cells</a> (cells that live in the bone marrow and produce cells that function in the blood), expand and differentiate to make immune cells like T cells, microphages, we will learn how to make them more efficiently," Dr. Zubair says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">You've remarked that you can envision a time when people might go into space to receive certain medical treatments. How would that work, and might it be possible to simulate microgravity for those treatments on Earth?</h2>



<p>If cells proliferate more in space, for example if cancer cells go into what is called cell cycle and multiply abnormally when they proliferate, then chemotherapy will be more effective, Dr. Zubair says.</p>



<p>"If that is the case, that absence of gravity can induce leukemia cells or other cancer cells to go into cell cycle, that makes them susceptible to chemotherapy," he explains. "So instead of giving the chemo on Earth, you might go into space where the absence of gravity makes the cancer cells more vulnerable to chemotherapy. That would be one more reason to go to space. That is definitely something that I would love to explore."</p>



<p>It would be difficult to create a comparable microgravity environment on Earth, but technically, it could be done, Dr. Zubair adds.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Dr.-Zubair-Childhood-love-of-space.mp4"></video></figure>


<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network."</strong></p>
<p>"Microgravity on Earth is basically like going into a swimming pool, a state of buoyancy where you are kind of in suspension; the gravity is canceled out by the effect of the water," he says. "Now, obviously it wouldn't be pleasant to be in water for quite some time. In the lab, we use a microgravity simulator where cells are suspended. It would be interesting if you could do the same for a human being."</p>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What attracted you to space research?</h2>



<p>Dr. Zubair grew up in Kano, Nigeria, and remembers gazing at the night sky as a child.</p>



<p>"As far back as I can remember, I was always fascinated by what is out there in space. Looking at the moon and all the stars, and really that ignites my passion for space and space exploration," Dr. Zubair says.</p>



<p>Dr. Zubair's first dream was to become an astronaut, but an adviser in high school counseled him to find a more practical career, and he pursued medicine.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What's next?</h2>



<p>One of Dr. Zubair's next two payloads to the International Space Station, not yet scheduled for launch, will examine whether umbilical cord blood cells, rich in stem cells and potential therapeutic value, can be expanded. Another study will explore different cell types that participate in bone formation and whether the problem of bone loss in space can be alleviated through use of a special compound.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"If it works, then definitely we will see how we can treat patients with osteoporosis, particularly women, cancer patients, or people who are bedridden for a long time and are not weight-bearing, which affects their bone," Dr. Zubair says.</p>



<p>Dr. Zubair notes that all of his space experiments are done in parallel on Earth with identical cells to compare the two results and validate the findings from space.</p>



<p>&amp;nbsp;"I really think there is a lot out there that is just waiting for us to explore and use," he says. "And that's why I do what I do."</p>



<p>Dr. Zubair has been honored by NASA with the Exceptional Scientific Achievement Medal for demonstrating that human-derived mesenchymal stem cells grown aboard the International Space Station could be used for potential clinical applications.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Sharon Theimer, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researcher-harnesses-uniqueness-of-space-to-advance-medicine-on-earth/">Mayo Clinic researcher harnesses uniqueness of space to advance medicine on Earth</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1-Dr-Zubair.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Dr-Abba-Zubair.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Abba Zubair]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>How a Mayo Clinic neurologist used AI to help restore a patient&amp;#8217;s health</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-mayo-clinics-ai-helped-a-neurologist-give-a-patient-his-life-back/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Discovery Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurology Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. David Jones]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403848</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Just one day after undergoing brain shunt surgery at Mayo Clinic, 75-year-old Minoo Press put his wheelchair aside and walked out of the hospital on his own. For the first time in two years, his mind was clear. His balance had returned. He was no longer losing control of his bladder.&amp;#160; The significant turnaround followed [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-mayo-clinics-ai-helped-a-neurologist-give-a-patient-his-life-back/">How a Mayo Clinic neurologist used AI to help restore a patient&amp;#8217;s health</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Minoo-Press1-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-403965" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Minoo-Press1-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Minoo-Press1-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Minoo-Press1-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Minoo-Press1-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Minoo-Press1.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Minoo Press (right) and his wife, Zarin Press. <em>Photo courtesy of Minoo Press</em></figcaption></figure>



<p>Just one day after undergoing brain shunt surgery at Mayo Clinic, 75-year-old Minoo Press put his wheelchair aside and walked out of the hospital on his own. For the first time in two years, his mind was clear. His balance had returned. He was no longer losing control of his bladder.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The significant turnaround followed two years of steady cognitive and physical decline. A retired engineer known for his sharp mind and independence, Press gradually withdrew from daily life. Even simple routines became impossible.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>He visited leading medical centers across the country, undergoing spinal taps, surgical procedures and advanced imaging to evaluate for conditions ranging from Alzheimer's disease to Parkinson's.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Some clinicians at those institutions also considered <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hydrocephalus/symptoms-causes/syc-20373604" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">normal pressure hydrocephalus</a>, a condition in which excess fluid builds up in the brain. But because Mr. Press' symptoms overlapped with signs of neurodegenerative disease, the doctors could not confirm the diagnosis or recommend surgery. They told him there was nothing more they could do.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>From rapid diagnosis to life-changing care</strong></h2>



<p>After an exhaustive search for answers, Press' family brought him to Mayo Clinic where he was evaluated by <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/jones-david-t-m-d/bio-20200690" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. David Jones</a>, a neurologist and director of Mayo Clinic's Neurology Artificial Intelligence Program.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="684" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Minoo-Press3-684x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-404118" style="width:455px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Minoo-Press3-684x1024.jpg 684w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Minoo-Press3-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/Minoo-Press3.jpg 711w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 684px) 100vw, 684px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Minoo Press (center) is pictured with his sons, Carl and Cyrus, and his wife, Zarin, before undergoing a stent procedure at Mayo Clinic. At the time, he was unable to walk and used a wheelchair. <em>Photo courtesy of Minoo Press</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Dr. Jones used an innovative artificial intelligence tool developed by his team, called <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-tool-identifies-9-dementia-types-including-alzheimers-with-one-scan/">StateViewer</a>. The tool works with a widely available brain scan known as fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography, or FDG-PET, comparing a patient's brain activity to thousands of confirmed dementia cases. It highlights patterns linked to nine types of the disease — from Alzheimer's and frontotemporal dementia to less common forms with overlapping symptoms.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>In a recent <a href="https://n.neurology.org/lookup/doi/10.1212/WNL.0000000000213831">study</a> published in Neurology, the tool identified the correct dementia type in 88% of cases and helped clinicians interpret scans up to three times more accurately and twice as fast as standard methods.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>In Press' case, the tool helped Dr. Jones rule out Alzheimer's and other types of dementia. That was the turning point.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>With neurodegenerative disease ruled out, Dr. Jones diagnosed Press with normal pressure hydrocephalus and confirmed that he was a candidate for a shunt procedure to relieve the pressure on his brain and potentially reverse the symptoms.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>A last-minute surgical cancellation&amp;nbsp;made it possible for Press to have the procedure that same week. </p>



<p>Within three days at Mayo Clinic, he had a clear diagnosis, a treatment plan and underwent brain surgery to place a shunt that would drain excess fluid from his brain.&amp;nbsp;The procedure was performed by <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/elder-benjamin-d-m-d-ph-d/bio-20406877" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Ben Elder</a>, a neurosurgeon and clinician-scientist. &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Press, who traveled from Chicago, noticed immediate improvements. His thinking was sharper, his steps steadier and he felt like himself again.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A clear mind, steady steps and hope</strong></h2>



<p>Dr. Jones says Press' case highlights the promise of combining AI with clinical care to accelerate diagnosis, scale expert clinical knowledge and help guide treatment planning.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>"When you're looking at overlapping symptoms, it's easy to miss the underlying cause," Dr. Jones says. "StateViewer gave us the clarity we needed to make an informed diagnosis and take action."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Press continues physical therapy and says he's improving every day.&amp;nbsp;He hopes his story can help others who are navigating the same often misdiagnosed and debilitating condition.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"I can enjoy time with my family again and I can go out with my friends. I can even do my own taxes. These are the moments I thought I had lost forever," Mr. Press says. "Mayo Clinic gave me my life back."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Related article:</strong></h2>



<div class="wp-block-columns has-background is-layout-flex wp-container-core-columns-is-layout-28f84493 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex" style="background-color:#d4d4d9">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-tool-identifies-9-dementia-types-including-alzheimers-with-one-scan/">Mayo Clinic's AI tool identifies 9 dementia types, including Alzheimer's, with one scan</a></strong></h2>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">Mayo Clinic researchers have developed a new artificial intelligence (AI) tool that helps clinicians identify brain activity patterns linked to nine types of dementia, including Alzheimer's disease, using a single, widely available scan — a transformative advance in early, accurate diagnosis. <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-tool-identifies-9-dementia-types-including-alzheimers-with-one-scan/">Read more</a>.</p>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="600" height="600" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1DR.DAVID-JONES1.png" alt="" class="wp-image-404080" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1DR.DAVID-JONES1.png 600w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1DR.DAVID-JONES1-300x300.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1DR.DAVID-JONES1-150x150.png 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></figure>
</div>
</div>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-mayo-clinics-ai-helped-a-neurologist-give-a-patient-his-life-back/">How a Mayo Clinic neurologist used AI to help restore a patient&amp;#8217;s health</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1-MinooPress.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-Minoo-Press1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. David Jones]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic&amp;#8217;s AI tool identifies 9 dementia types, including Alzheimer&amp;#8217;s, with one scan&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-tool-identifies-9-dementia-types-including-alzheimers-with-one-scan/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 20:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Discovery Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Translational Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. David Jones]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=403846</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic researchers have developed a new artificial intelligence (AI) tool that helps clinicians identify brain activity patterns linked to nine types of dementia, including Alzheimer's disease, using a single, widely available scan — a transformative advance in early, accurate diagnosis.&amp;#160; The tool, StateViewer, helped researchers identify the dementia type in 88% [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-tool-identifies-9-dementia-types-including-alzheimers-with-one-scan/">Mayo Clinic&amp;#8217;s AI tool identifies 9 dementia types, including Alzheimer&amp;#8217;s, with one scan&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-DAVID-JONES1-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-404078" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-DAVID-JONES1-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-DAVID-JONES1-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-DAVID-JONES1-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-DAVID-JONES1-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-DAVID-JONES1.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. David Jones reviews brain scans on a computer at Mayo Clinic.</figcaption></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic researchers have developed a new artificial intelligence (AI) tool that helps clinicians identify brain activity patterns linked to nine types of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/dementia/symptoms-causes/syc-20352013" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dementia</a>, including <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/alzheimers-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350447" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alzheimer's disease</a>, using a single, widely available scan — a transformative advance in early, accurate diagnosis.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The tool, StateViewer, helped researchers identify the dementia type in 88% of cases, according to research <a href="https://n.neurology.org/lookup/doi/10.1212/WNL.0000000000213831" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">published</a> online on June 27, 2025, in Neurology, the medical journal of the American Academy of Neurology. It also enabled clinicians to interpret brain scans nearly twice as fast and with up to three times greater accuracy than standard workflows. Researchers trained and tested the AI on more than 3,600 scans, including images from patients with dementia and people without cognitive impairment.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>This innovation addresses a core challenge in dementia care: identifying the disease early and precisely, even when multiple conditions are present. As new treatments emerge, timely diagnosis helps match patients with the most appropriate care when it can have the greatest impact. The tool could bring advanced diagnostic support to clinics that lack neurology expertise.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The rising toll of dementia</strong>&nbsp;</h2>



<p>Dementia affects more than 55 million people worldwide, with nearly 10 million new cases each year. Alzheimer's disease, the most common form, is now the fifth-leading cause of death globally. Diagnosing dementia typically requires cognitive tests, blood draws, imaging, clinical interviews and specialist referrals. Even with extensive testing, distinguishing conditions such as Alzheimer's, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lewy-body-dementia/symptoms-causes/syc-20352025">Lewy body dementia</a> and <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-is-frontotemporal-degeneration/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">frontotemporal dementia</a> remains challenging, including for highly experienced specialists.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>StateViewer was developed under the direction of <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/jones-david-t-m-d/bio-20200690" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">David Jones, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic neurologist and director of the Mayo Clinic Neurology Artificial Intelligence Program.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"Every patient who walks into my clinic carries a unique story shaped by the brain's complexity," Dr. Jones says. "That complexity drew me to neurology and continues to drive my commitment to clearer answers. StateViewer reflects that commitment — a step toward earlier understanding, more precise treatment and, one day, changing the course of these diseases."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>To bring that vision to life, Dr. Jones worked alongside Leland Barnard, Ph.D., a data scientist who leads the AI engineering behind StateViewer.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"As we were designing StateViewer, we never lost sight of the fact that behind every data point and brain scan was a person facing a difficult diagnosis and urgent questions," Dr. Barnard says. "Seeing how this tool could assist physicians with real-time, precise insights and guidance highlights the potential of machine learning for clinical medicine."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Turning brain patterns into clinical insight&nbsp;</strong></h2>



<p>The tool analyzes a fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (FDG-PET) scan, which shows how the brain uses glucose for energy. It then compares the scan to a large database of scans from people with confirmed dementia diagnoses and identifies patterns that match specific types, or combinations, of dementia.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Alzheimer's typically affects memory and processing regions, Lewy body dementia involves areas tied to attention and movement, and frontotemporal dementia alters regions responsible for language and behavior. StateViewer displays these patterns through color-coded brain maps that highlight key areas of brain activity, giving all clinicians, even those without neurology training, a visual explanation of what the AI sees and how it supports the diagnosis.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers plan to expand the tool's use and will continue evaluating its performance in a variety of clinical settings.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>For a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding,&amp;nbsp;review the <a href="https://n.neurology.org/lookup/doi/10.1212/WNL.0000000000213831">study</a>.</p>



<p>###&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&amp;nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:&amp;nbsp;</strong>&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Tia Ford, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-tool-identifies-9-dementia-types-including-alzheimers-with-one-scan/">Mayo Clinic&amp;#8217;s AI tool identifies 9 dementia types, including Alzheimer&amp;#8217;s, with one scan&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/1x1DR.DAVID-JONES1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/06/16x9-DAVID-JONES1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. David Jones]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss> 