<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 12:16:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Goldilocks surgery: Finding the perfect balance in breast cancer reconstruction</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/goldilocks-surgery-finding-the-perfect-balance-in-breast-cancer-reconstruction/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Kathleen Christian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Steven Perkins]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Goldilocks surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kathleen Stewart]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374385</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Kathleen Stewart was used to waiting for test results. She'd been called back for additional mammogram images many times and had already undergone two biopsies of suspicious areas in her breasts. In March 2022, as she waited for a call about the results of a breast biopsy, the resident of La Crosse, Wisconsin, felt she [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/goldilocks-surgery-finding-the-perfect-balance-in-breast-cancer-reconstruction/">Goldilocks surgery: Finding the perfect balance in breast cancer reconstruction</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/kathleen-stewart-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374387" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/kathleen-stewart-16x9-1.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/kathleen-stewart-16x9-1-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></figure>



<p>Kathleen Stewart was used to waiting for test results. She'd been called back for additional <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mammogram/about/pac-20384806" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">mammogram</a> images many times and had already undergone two biopsies of suspicious areas in her breasts.</p>



<p>In March 2022, as she waited for a call about the results of a breast biopsy, the resident of La Crosse, Wisconsin, felt she already knew what they would be.</p>



<p>"I had already had that internal conversation that if I was diagnosed, I knew what I would do," Kathleen says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Not-so-surprising diagnosis</h2>



<p>Kathleen's experience with breast cancer started long before that afternoon. She was raised in a close-knit family and witnessed 11 family members diagnosed with breast cancer firsthand. She remembers how each responded to chemotherapy, radiation and surgery.</p>



<p>Kathleen contemplated having a prophylactic mastectomy due to her family history of breast cancer. This surgery removes breast tissue to lower the chances of getting breast cancer in the future.</p>



<p>While considering this option, the then 52-year-old scheduled a routine mammogram. It came back clear, but she wasn't convinced. At the urging of her sister, Kathleen discussed her concerns and family history with <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/steven-perkins-do" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Steven Perkins, D.O.</a>, her primary care physician. Together they decided that a follow-up <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/breast-mri/about/pac-20384809" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">MRI scan</a> would be necessary to give her peace of mind.</p>



<p>Kathleen's suspicions were correct. The MRI showed a small lump and swollen lymph nodes, leading to a sonogram and another biopsy. Kathleen was at work when she got the phone call from surgeon <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/m-kathleen-christian-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">M. Kathleen Christian, M.D.</a>, who explained the biopsy confirmed that she had early stage 1A <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470">breast cancer</a>.</p>



<p>"When you get breast cancer, it's hard to understand the complexity of it. Dr. Christian did a really good job explaining it to me," says Kathleen. "I took a deep breath, but I already knew I was going to be as aggressive as I needed to be because I have kids."</p>



<p>Kathleen learned that she had a "well-behaved tumor," but an invasive one, so treatment would be required.</p>



<p>"Thankfully, Kathleen had been diligent about regular breast cancer screenings. Due to her obtaining recommended breast imaging, the cancer was caught early," says Dr. Christian. "She had several options on how to best treat her cancer based on her desires and risks related to her family history. She has an excellent prognosis, and that's what we want for our patients."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Taking an aggressive approach</h2>



<p>Dr. Christian explained different treatment approaches to Kathleen, including a lumpectomy to surgically remove only the concerning areas in her breast.</p>



<p>"We talked about a lumpectomy, but I knew that wouldn't give me peace of mind," says Kathleen. "I was a high risk, and I knew that a mastectomy was the way I needed to go.</p>



<p>A bilateral mastectomy would remove the cancer and both of Kathleen's breasts. She wasn't interested in reconstruction with implants or a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/eau-claire/services-and-treatments/plastic-and-reconstructive-surgery/breast-services/breast-reconstruction">flap procedure</a>&nbsp;but didn't like the idea of being completely flat-chested after surgery. She says she feared a drastically changed profile would be a constant cancer reminder for her and her family.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Goldilocks: Not too little or too much</h2>



<p>That's why Kathleen was relieved when Dr. Christian explained she might be a good candidate for a new option: a Goldilocks procedure.</p>



<p>"Even with hearing and watching so many family members on their cancer journeys, I'd never heard of this option before," Kathleen says.</p>



<p>The Goldilocks procedure is performed after a mastectomy to remove unhealthy breast tissue. Then, the remaining fatty tissue and skin are formed into a breast mound that gives some shape and definition to the breast. The operation is typically used in patients with larger and heavier breasts, but it can be used in some patients with smaller breasts.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full"><img decoding="async" width="325" height="400" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/goldlilocks-procedure-illustration.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374386" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/goldlilocks-procedure-illustration.jpg 325w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/goldlilocks-procedure-illustration-244x300.jpg 244w" sizes="(max-width: 325px) 100vw, 325px" /></figure></div>


<p>It's called Goldilocks because it represents a middle-of-the-road option for patients, explains plastic surgeon&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/matthew-sherrill-md">Matthew Sherrill, M.D.</a></p>



<p>"It's an option that isn't too extreme one way or the other. It's halfway between mastectomy with a flat-chest appearance and full reconstruction with implants, expanders or a flap procedure," says Dr. Sherrill.</p>



<p>The procedure also is good for women who can't have or aren't interested in reconstruction immediately after mastectomy.</p>



<p>"This technique is often used in patients with other medical comorbidities who may not be good candidates for an immediate breast reconstruction because of the potential complications," says Dr. Sherrill. "The Goldilocks operation is sometimes the only step in the process, or it can be a starting block for future reconstruction. Reshaping the breast skin at the time of the mastectomy with the Goldilocks operation gives patients a template or a canvas to undergo future breast reconstruction if they desire."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Collaboration for better results</h2>



<p>Drs. Christian and Sherrill explain that a collaborative, multidisciplinary approach to breast cancer surgery and reconstruction leads to better patient outcomes and experiences.</p>



<p>"The operation is most successful when done as a team involving the surgeons, physician assistants and nursing staff in educating the patient before the surgery, coordinating the operation and supporting the patient during recovery," says Dr. Sherrill.</p>



<p>Dr. Christian applauds the work of the dedicated breast cancer team at Mayo Clinic Health System in La Crosse.</p>



<p>"We work closely together and meet regularly at our breast tumor conferences to discuss the best options available for treatment," she says. "We then individualize recommendations based on the patient's staging, tumor characteristics and what they want for surgical outcomes."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Surgery and beyond</h2>



<p>In June 2022, Kathleen underwent a bilateral mastectomy to remove both breasts and her cancer. At the same time, she underwent the Goldilocks procedure to form breast mounds from her existing tissue and skin. The surgery was a success, and soon she was recovering at home.</p>



<p>Kathleen returned to work part time three weeks after surgery and soon returned to the sidelines to cheer on her sons' sports teams.</p>



<p>After the surgery, her risk of future breast cancer was low, so no additional treatment was necessary.</p>



<p>Recovery went well but wasn't completely smooth. Over a holiday weekend, she developed hives and a rash due to a previously unknown allergy to adhesives and latex. Dr. Sherrill called her that weekend to discuss her symptoms and get her the treatment she needed for allergy relief. She hasn't had any other allergy issues.</p>



<p>Since then, Kathleen decided to have additional reconstruction procedures to give her breasts more fullness and shape without implants or more extensive flap surgeries.</p>



<p>About one year after her surgery, Kathleen says she feels well and confident that she made the right treatment choices. She also feels secure with her healthcare team.</p>



<p>"Nobody ever said, 'You've got this.' It was always a team approach, and everyone said, 'We've got this,'" she says. "Cancer is a scary word, and nobody wants cancer. But I know that I had the best team through this journey."</p>



<p>This article originally published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/patient-stories/goldilocks-for-breast-reconstruction" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/goldilocks-surgery-finding-the-perfect-balance-in-breast-cancer-reconstruction/">Goldilocks surgery: Finding the perfect balance in breast cancer reconstruction</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/kathleen-stewart-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/kathleen-stewart-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Kathleen Christian]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Steven Perkins]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Goldilocks surgery]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Kathleen Stewart]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Consumer Health: Treating thyroid cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-treating-thyroid-cancer-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laurel Kelly]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 12:16:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[thyroid cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thyroid Cancer Awareness Month]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=370823</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>September is&#160;Thyroid Cancer Awareness Month, which makes this&#160;a good time to learn about treating thyroid cancer. Nearly 44,000 new cases of thyroid cancer will be diagnosed in the U.S. this year, and more than 2,000 people will die of the disease, according to the American Cancer Society. Thyroid cancer occurs in the cells of the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-treating-thyroid-cancer-2/">Consumer Health: Treating thyroid cancer</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/06/thyroid-gland_shutterstock_1008501466-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="3D anatomy image with the thyroid gland highlighted" class="wp-image-240478" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/06/thyroid-gland_shutterstock_1008501466-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/06/thyroid-gland_shutterstock_1008501466-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/06/thyroid-gland_shutterstock_1008501466-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>September is&nbsp;Thyroid Cancer Awareness Month, which makes this<strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong>a good time to learn about treating <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-what-do-you-know-about-the-types-of-thyroid-cancer/">thyroid cancer</a>.</p>



<p>Nearly 44,000 new cases of thyroid cancer will be diagnosed in the U.S. this year, and more than 2,000 people will die of the disease, according to the <a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/thyroid-cancer/about/key-statistics.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Cancer Society</a>.</p>



<p>Thyroid cancer occurs in the cells of the thyroid, a butterfly-shaped gland at the base of your neck. Your thyroid produces hormones that regulate your heart rate, blood pressure, body temperature and weight.</p>



<p>There may be no signs or symptoms early in the disease. As thyroid cancer grows, it may cause swelling in your neck, voice changes, difficulty swallowing, and pain in your neck and throat.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Risk factors</strong></h2>



<p>Factors that may increase the risk of thyroid cancer include:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Being female.</strong><br>Thyroid cancer occurs more often in women than men. Experts think it may be related to the hormone estrogen. People who are assigned female sex at birth generally have higher levels of estrogen in their bodies.</li>



<li><strong>Exposure to high levels of radiation.</strong><br>Radiation therapy treatments to the head and neck increase the risk of thyroid cancer.</li>



<li><strong>Certain inherited genetic syndromes.</strong><br>Genetic syndromes that increase the risk of thyroid cancer include familial medullary thyroid cancer, multiple endocrine neoplasia, Cowden syndrome and familial adenomatous polyposis. Types of thyroid cancer that sometimes run in families include medullary thyroid cancer and papillary thyroid cancer.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Treatment</strong> <strong>for thyroid cancer</strong></h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/thyroid-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20354167?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Treatment</a>&nbsp;can cure most thyroid cancers. Your treatment options will depend on the type and stage of your thyroid cancer, your overall health, and your preferences.</p>



<p>Treatment might not be needed right away for very small papillary thyroid cancers because these cancers have a low risk of growing or spreading. Your healthcare team might recommend active surveillance with frequent monitoring of the cancer, including blood tests and an ultrasound exam of your neck once or twice a year. In some people, the cancer might never grow and never require treatment. In others, growth may eventually be detected, and treatment can begin.</p>



<p>If you've been diagnosed with thyroid cancer for which treatment is recommended, your options might include:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Surgery.</strong><br>Most people with thyroid cancer that requires treatment will undergo surgery to remove part or all of the thyroid. Which operation your healthcare team might recommend depends on your type of thyroid cancer, the size of the cancer, whether the cancer has spread beyond the thyroid to the lymph nodes and your preferences. Options include removing all or most of the thyroid, removing just a portion of the thyroid, and removing lymph nodes in the neck.</li>



<li><strong>Thyroid hormone replacement.</strong><br>Thyroid hormone therapy is a treatment to replace or supplement the hormones produced in the thyroid. Thyroid hormone therapy medication usually is taken in pill form. It can be used to replace thyroid hormones after surgery and to suppress the growth of thyroid cancer cells.</li>



<li><strong>Radioactive iodine.</strong><br>Radioactive iodine treatment uses a form of iodine that's radioactive to kill thyroid cells and thyroid cancer cells that might remain after surgery. It's most often used to treat differentiated thyroid cancers that have a risk of spreading to other parts of the body.</li>



<li><strong>Alcohol ablation.</strong><br>Alcohol ablation, also called ethanol ablation, involves using a needle to inject alcohol into small areas of thyroid cancer. Ultrasound imaging is used to precisely guide the needle. The alcohol causes the thyroid cancer cells to shrink. Alcohol ablation may be an option to treat small areas of thyroid cancer, such as cancer that's found in a lymph node after surgery. Sometimes it's an option if you aren't healthy enough for surgery.</li>



<li><strong>Additional treatments for advanced thyroid cancers.</strong><br>Aggressive thyroid cancers that grow more quickly may require additional treatment options to control the disease. Options include targeted drug therapy, radiation therapy, chemotherapy, radiofrequency ablation and cryoablation.</li>



<li><strong>Palliative care.</strong><br>Palliative care is specialized medical care that focuses on providing relief from pain and other symptoms of a serious illness, with the aim to improve quality of life for patients and their families. Palliative care specialists work with you, your family and your healthcare team to provide an extra layer of support that complements your ongoing care.</li>
</ul>



<p>Connect with others talking about living with thyroid cancer in the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/thyroid-cancer/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Thyroid Cancer Support Group</a> on&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Connect</a>, an online patient community moderated by Mayo Clinic.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-treating-thyroid-cancer-2/">Consumer Health: Treating thyroid cancer</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/06/thyroid-gland_shutterstock_1008501466_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/06/thyroid-gland_shutterstock_1008501466-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[thyroid cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Thyroid Cancer Awareness Month]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: The importance of supplemental screenings for dense breasts</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-the-importance-of-supplemental-screenings-for-dense-breasts/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 13:28:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=373614</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>You might need supplemental screenings if you've been diagnosed with dense breast tissue. Women with dense breast tissue have less fat and more glandular and connective tissue. They are also at a higher risk of developing cancer. Dense breast tissue refers to the way breast tissue appears on a mammogram. According to the Centers for [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-the-importance-of-supplemental-screenings-for-dense-breasts/">Mayo Clinic Minute: The importance of supplemental screenings for dense breasts</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>You might need supplemental screenings if you've been diagnosed with dense breast tissue. Women with dense breast tissue have less fat and more glandular and connective tissue. They are also at a higher risk of developing cancer.</p>



<p>Dense breast tissue refers to the way breast tissue appears on a mammogram. According to the <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/cancer/breast/basic_info/dense-breasts.htm#:~:text=Breast%20density%20reflects%20the%20amount,as%20seen%20on%20a%20mammogram.&amp;text=The%20breasts%20are%20almost%20entirely,about%2040%25%20of%20women)." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</a>, about 50% of women have this type of breast tissue.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/robinson-kristin-a-m-d/bio-20466711?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Kristin Robinson</a>, a Mayo Clinic breast radiologist, encourages women with dense breast tissue to have additional screenings.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/n3ImOj38Uhc" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutuben3ImOj38Uhc"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - The importance of supplemental screenings for dense breasts" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/n3ImOj38Uhc?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:09) is in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/jthEDITS_dense-breast-and-supplemental-tests.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script.</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/Dense-Breast-Image-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-369193" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/Dense-Breast-Image-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/Dense-Breast-Image-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/Dense-Breast-Image-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/Dense-Breast-Image-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/Dense-Breast-Image-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">What are some additional screenings?</h3>



<p></p>



<p><a href="http://mayoweb.mayo.edu/sp-forms/mc5800-mc5899/mc5803-01pf.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Supplemental screenings</a> are a good idea if your mammogram shows you have dense breast tissue.</p>



<p>"The dense tissue on a mammogram looks white, and cancer looks white," says Dr. Robinson.</p>



<p>She says these exams can assist in identifying cancer. Diagnostic tools, like MRI, use powerful magnets and radio waves to create cross-sectional images of the breasts.</p>



<p>"MRI looks at blood flow in the breast tissue and compares it to the blood flow throughout that breast and the opposite breast. And the idea is that cancer is going to have more blood flow," explains Dr. Robinson.</p>



<p>Another option to consider is getting a molecular breast imaging test, or MBI. This exam uses a radioactive tracer that can identify cancer cells.</p>



<p>"It shows up lightbulb bright to us and becomes very easy to see compared to the normal surrounding tissue," says Dr. Robinson.</p>



<p>Contrast-enhanced mammography is another way to go. It combines mammography and IV contrast to examine blood flow in the breasts.</p>



<p>"The contrast agent there, again, should go to the cancer specifically and be able to be distinguished," says Dr. Robinson.</p>



<p>The supplemental screenings provide doctors with more information and give patients peace of mind.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-determining-if-you-have-dense-breasts/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Determining if you have dense breasts</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-does-a-diagnosis-of-dense-breasts-mean/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">What does a diagnosis of dense breasts mean?</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-who-needs-molecular-breast-imaging/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Who needs molecular breast imaging?</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-the-importance-of-supplemental-screenings-for-dense-breasts/">Mayo Clinic Minute: The importance of supplemental screenings for dense breasts</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/mss_0001420215-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/10/mammography_shutterstock_292061510_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Consumer Health: What do you know about these 3 childhood cancers?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-what-do-you-know-about-these-3-childhood-cancers/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laurel Kelly]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Children's Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[acute lymphocytic leukemia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Childhood Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Childhood Cancer Awareness Month]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chimeric antigen receptor (CAR)-T cell therapy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[neuroblastoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pediatric brain tumors]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=370825</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The types of cancer that occur in children often are different from those in adults. Childhood cancers usually are not linked to lifestyle or environmental risk factors, as is often the case in adults. Nonetheless, cancer is the second-leading cause of death in children 1 to 14 years old, according to the American Cancer Society. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-what-do-you-know-about-these-3-childhood-cancers/">Consumer Health: What do you know about these 3 childhood cancers?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="682" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/1169673_3327938_0039-1024x682.jpg" alt="a young white child with no hair due to treatment for cancer, wearing a hospital smock and painting on an art project" class="wp-image-370897" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/1169673_3327938_0039-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/1169673_3327938_0039-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/1169673_3327938_0039-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/1169673_3327938_0039-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/1169673_3327938_0039.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The types of cancer that occur in children often are different from those in adults. Childhood cancers usually are not linked to lifestyle or environmental risk factors, as is often the case in adults. Nonetheless, cancer is the second-leading cause of death in children 1 to 14 years old, according to the <a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/types/cancer-in-children/key-statistics.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Cancer Society</a>. Nearly 10,000&nbsp;children in the U.S. under the age of 15 will be diagnosed with cancer in 2023, and about 1,000 children are expected to die of the disease.</p>



<p>September is&nbsp;<a href="https://www.aacr.org/patients-caregivers/awareness-months/childhood-cancer-awareness-month/#:~:text=September%20is%20Childhood%20Cancer%20Awareness%20Month%20%7C%20The%20AACR" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Childhood Cancer Awareness Month</a>, which makes this a good time to learn about three of the most common types of cancer in children: acute lymphocytic leukemia, neuroblastoma and pediatric brain tumors.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Acute lymphocytic leukemia</strong></h2>



<p><a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/acute-lymphocytic-leukemia/symptoms-causes/syc-20369077?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank">Acute lymphocytic leukemia</a>&nbsp;is a cancer of the blood and bone marrow. It's the most common type of cancer in children, and treatments result in a good chance for a cure. Acute lymphocytic leukemia also can occur in adults, though the chance of a cure is greatly reduced.</p>



<p>Signs and symptoms of acute lymphocytic leukemia can include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Bleeding from the gums.</li>



<li>Bone pain.</li>



<li>Fever.</li>



<li>Frequent infections.</li>



<li>Frequent or severe nosebleeds.</li>



<li>Swollen lymph nodes in and around the neck, armpits, abdomen or groin.</li>



<li>Pale skin.</li>



<li>Shortness of breath.</li>



<li>Weakness, fatigue or a general decrease in energy.</li>
</ul>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/acute-lymphocytic-leukemia/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20369083?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Treatment</a>&nbsp;for acute lymphocytic leukemia includes chemotherapy, targeted therapy, radiation and bone marrow transplant. There's also a specialized treatment called&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/car-t-cell-therapy-program/sections/gnc-20405215?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chimeric antigen receptor-T cell therapy</a>&nbsp;that takes your body's germ-fighting T cells, engineers them to fight cancer, and infuses them back into your body.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Neuroblastoma</strong></h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/neuroblastoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20351017?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Neuroblastoma</a>&nbsp;is a cancer that develops from immature nerve cells found in several areas of the body. It most commonly affects children 5 or younger, though it may rarely occur in older children.</p>



<p>Signs and symptoms of neuroblastoma vary, depending on what part of the body is affected. </p>



<p>Neuroblastoma in the abdomen — the most common form — can cause:</p>



<ul>
<li>Abdominal pain.</li>



<li>A mass under the skin that isn't tender when touched.</li>



<li>Changes in bowel habits, such as diarrhea or constipation. </li>
</ul>



<p>Neuroblastoma in the chest can cause:</p>



<ul>
<li>Wheezing.</li>



<li>Chest pain.</li>



<li>Changes to the eyes, including drooping eyelids and unequal pupil size. </li>
</ul>



<p>Other signs and symptoms that can indicate neuroblastoma include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Lumps of tissue under the skin.</li>



<li>Eyeballs that seem to protrude from the sockets.</li>



<li>Dark circles, similar to bruises, around the eyes.</li>



<li>Back pain.</li>



<li>Fever.</li>



<li>Unexplained weight loss.</li>



<li>Bone pain.</li>
</ul>



<p>The&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/neuroblastoma/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20351022?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">treatment</a>&nbsp;plan for neuroblastoma is based on several factors that affect the child's prognosis, including the child's age, the stage of the cancer, the types of cells involved in the cancer, and whether there are any abnormalities in the chromosomes and genes. Treatment can include surgery, chemotherapy, radiation therapy, bone marrow transplant and immunotherapy. There also is a newer form of radiation therapy that may help control high-risk neuroblastoma. The treatment uses a radioactive form of the chemical metaiodobenzylguanidine (MIBG) and sometimes is combined with chemotherapy or bone marrow transplant.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Pediatric brain tumors</strong></h2>



<p>There are many types of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pediatric-brain-tumor/symptoms-causes/syc-20361694?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pediatric brain tumors</a>. Some are noncancerous, or benign, and some are cancerous, or malignant.</p>



<p>Signs and symptoms of a brain tumor in children vary greatly, depending on the brain tumor type, size, location and rate of growth. Some signs and symptoms may not be easy to detect because they're similar to symptoms of other conditions.</p>



<p>Some of the more common symptoms of a brain tumor in children include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Headaches, which may become more frequent and more severe.</li>



<li>Feeling of increased pressure in the head.</li>



<li>Unexplained nausea or vomiting.</li>



<li>Abrupt onset of vision problems, such double vision.</li>
</ul>



<p>Other possible signs and symptoms, depending on the tumor location, include:</p>



<ul>
<li>A fuller soft spot on the skull in babies.</li>



<li>Seizures, especially when there's no history of seizures.</li>



<li>Abnormal eye movement.</li>



<li>Slurred speech.</li>



<li>Trouble swallowing.</li>



<li>Loss of appetite; or in babies, difficulty feeding.</li>



<li>Difficulty with balance.</li>



<li>Trouble walking.</li>



<li>Weakness or loss of sensation in an arm or a leg.</li>



<li>Weakness or drooping on one side on the face.</li>



<li>Confusion.</li>



<li>Irritability.</li>



<li>Memory problems.</li>



<li>Personality or behavior changes.</li>



<li>Hearing problems.</li>
</ul>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pediatric-brain-tumor/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20361706?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Treatment</a>&nbsp;of a pediatric brain tumor depends on the type of tumor, its location within the brain, whether it has spread, and the child's age and general health.<strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong>Because new treatments and technologies are being developed continually, several options may be available at different points in treatment. And treatment for brain tumors in children typically is quite different from treatment for adult brain tumors, so it's important to enlist the expertise and experience of pediatric specialists in neurology and cancer. Treatment can include surgery, traditional radiation therapy, proton beam therapy, radiosurgery, chemotherapy and targeted drug therapy.</p>



<p>Connect with others talked about childhood cancer in the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/cancer/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cancer Support Group</a> and the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/adolescent-young-adult-aya-cancer/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Adolescent &amp; Young Adult (AYA) Cancer Support Group</a> on&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Connect</a>, an online patient community moderated by Mayo Clinic.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-what-do-you-know-about-these-3-childhood-cancers/">Consumer Health: What do you know about these 3 childhood cancers?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-young-white-child-with-no-hair-due-to-treatment-for-cancer-wearing-a-hospital-smock-and-painting-on-an-art-project-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-young-white-child-with-no-hair-due-to-treatment-for-cancer-wearing-a-hospital-smock-and-painting-on-an-art-project-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[acute lymphocytic leukemia]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Childhood Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Childhood Cancer Awareness Month]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[chimeric antigen receptor (CAR)-T cell therapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[neuroblastoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[pediatric brain tumors]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>3 facts about acute lymphocytic leukemia in children</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/3-facts-about-acute-lymphocytic-leukemia-in-children/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nicole Ferrara]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 14:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[acute lymphocitic leukemia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALL]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Asmaa Ferdjallah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374815</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>September is Childhood Cancer Awareness Month. The most common type of childhood cancer is acute lymphocytic leukemia (ALL), a blood and bone marrow cancer that creates immature white blood cells that can’t perform their typical functions. Because of this, the disease worsens quickly. Most likely to occur in early childhood, ALL is more common in boys than girls, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/3-facts-about-acute-lymphocytic-leukemia-in-children/">3 facts about acute lymphocytic leukemia in children</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="938" height="527" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/ALL-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374834" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/ALL-16x9-1.jpg 938w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/ALL-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/ALL-16x9-1-768x431.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 938px) 100vw, 938px" /></figure>



<p>September is <a href="https://www.aacr.org/patients-caregivers/awareness-months/childhood-cancer-awareness-month/#:~:text=September%20is%20Childhood%20Cancer%20Awareness%20Month%20%7C%20The%20AACR" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Childhood Cancer Awareness Month</a>. The most common type of childhood cancer is <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/acute-lymphocytic-leukemia/symptoms-causes/syc-20369077" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">acute lymphocytic leukemia</a> (ALL), a blood and bone marrow cancer that creates immature white blood cells that can’t perform their typical functions. Because of this, the disease worsens quickly.</p>



<p>Most likely to occur in early childhood, ALL is more common in boys than girls, according to the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/types/leukemia-in-children/about/key-statistics.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Cancer Society</a>. Children younger than five are at highest risk for developing ALL.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/ferdjallah-asmaa-m-d-m-p-h/bio-20518146" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Asmaa Ferdjallah, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic pediatric hematologist and oncologist, treats children of all ages with ALL. Here’s what she wants families to know about this disease:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">1. ALL is rare and has a collection of persistent symptoms.</h2>



<p>In 2023, the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/types/acute-lymphocytic-leukemia/about/key-statistics.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Cancer Society</a>&nbsp;estimates that 6,540 new cases of ALL will be diagnosed in both children and adults. This represents less than half of 1% of all cancers in the U.S.</p>



<p>ALL symptoms vary and can resemble symptoms of flu and other common illnesses. Dr. Ferdjallah says most high fevers, swollen lymph nodes and bruises are part of typical childhood development. Parents should call their child’s healthcare professional if those symptoms persist, co-occur or seem unusual.</p>



<p>"With ALL, we often see frequent or daily high fevers that you can't explain," says Dr. Ferdjallah. "We'll often see rapid weight loss that doesn't make sense for a child's activity level. And we always ask about lumps or bumps, which can indicate swollen lymph nodes, as well as night sweats, bone pain and any new bruising or bleeding."</p>



<p>If your healthcare team suspects your child has ALL, they will draw blood for testing. "We would expect to see changes in blood counts" in a child with ALL, says Dr. Ferdjallah. "Low hemoglobin, low platelets, low neutrophils — having all these low blood counts may suggest ALL."</p>



<p>In addition to a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/in-depth/cancer-diagnosis/art-20046459" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">blood test</a>, healthcare professionals may also use a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bone-marrow-biopsy/about/pac-20393117" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bone marrow test</a>, imaging tests and a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/lumbar-puncture/about/pac-20394631" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">spinal fluid test</a>&nbsp;to diagnose ALL.</p>



<p>Having one ALL symptom, such as a bruise or one low blood count, generally isn’t something to worry about, says Dr. Ferdjallah. "ALL declares itself. It’s not going to sneak up on you. It creates a constellation of symptoms that we see."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">2. Children diagnosed with ALL have well-researched options for precision care.</h2>



<p>Your child’s care team will consider many factors when determining the best treatment for ALL, including:</p>



<ul>
<li>The type of lymphocytes involved — B cells or T cells.</li>



<li>The specific genetic changes present in the child’s leukemia cells.</li>



<li>The child’s age.</li>



<li>Lab test results, such as the number of white blood cells detected in a blood sample.</li>
</ul>



<p>Care teams then tailor treatment plans for each patient based on factors that indicate standard risk or high risk for relapse. Called risk stratification, this approach to treatment has improved survival.</p>



<p>"Somebody with standard risk is usually between the ages of 1 and 10. A child in this age group with a white blood cell count of less than 50,000 is considered standard risk. Patients outside these parameters need more intense therapy and are considered high risk," says Dr. Ferdjallah.</p>



<p>For standard-risk patients, treatment typically involves chemotherapy given by infusion. "We also deliver chemotherapy into the spine via a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/acute-lymphocytic-leukemia/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20369083#dialogId13734717" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">spinal tap</a>&nbsp;because we know some leukemias are very good at hiding in that space, and this can prevent relapses and later recurrences," says Dr. Ferdjallah.</p>



<p>Treatment can take two to three years, and the first few months are most intense.</p>



<p>"After the first six months, the patient enters a period called maintenance," says Dr. Ferdjallah. "Then we see patients less often because they need less intense therapy. Kids return to school, and their immune system is a little stronger. They can go on vacation, and their hair starts to grow back. ALL starts to feel like an annoying thing to manage and less like a life-altering, devastating illness."</p>



<p>The care team will perform a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bone-marrow-biopsy/about/pac-20393117" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bone marrow biopsy</a>&nbsp;to determine whether ALL is remission. "If there's no leukemia in the biopsy, that's the best sign that the patient is in remission, and that is associated with the best outcomes," says Dr. Ferdjallah.</p>



<p>There are many other options for children with high-risk genetic mutations or aggressive diseases for whom chemotherapy isn’t effective. ALL treatments may include&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/chemotherapy/about/pac-20385033"></a><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">targeted therapy</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/radiation-therapy/about/pac-20385162" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">radiation therapy</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bone-marrow-transplant/about/pac-20384854" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bone marrow transplant</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/car-t-cell-therapy-program/sections/overview/ovc-20404319" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CAR-T cell therapy</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/cancer-clinical-trials/about-cancer-clinical-trials" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">clinical trials</a>.</p>



<p>"We have multiple lines of therapy for these patients," says Dr. Ferdjallah. "Scientists and doctors have worked collaboratively for a long time to create networks, such as the&nbsp;<a href="https://childrensoncologygroup.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Children’s Oncology Group</a>, to conduct powerful clinical trials. The results of that research have informed us of the best therapy approaches," she says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">3. The outlook for kids diagnosed with ALL is excellent, and treatment options continue to improve.</h2>



<p>The five-year survival rate for children with ALL is about 90%, and if a child remains cancer-free five years after treatment, they are likely cured.</p>



<p>"Children diagnosed with ALL do well in survivorship. They're able to live normal, healthy lives — get married, have kids, and have a normal life span," says Dr. Ferdjallah.</p>



<p>Meanwhile, available treatment options continue to improve.</p>



<p>"One of the most promising new treatment options is CAR-T cell therapy for pediatric patients, which uses a patient's&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/def/t-cell" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">T cells</a>&nbsp;and genetically engineers them to target and kill their leukemia cells," says Dr. Ferdjallah. "That kind of therapy can save a patient from a stem cell transplant, which has more side effects and morbidity. We’ve seen good outcomes."</p>



<p>Dr. Ferdjallah is also excited about the development of new targeted therapies called&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/managing-cancer/treatment-types/immunotherapy/monoclonal-antibodies.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">monoclonal antibodies</a>. "These drugs target mechanisms in leukemia cells that drive their ability to replicate quickly or damage normal tissues. (The drugs) tend to have fewer side effects than chemotherapy. That's exciting because it can improve quality of life," she says.</p>



<p>Dr. Ferdjallah wants families coping with a child’s ALL diagnosis to know there is good reason to hope. "It’s completely horrifying to think about your child having cancer, but the No. 1 thing I want parents to hear is that ALL is one of the most curable cancers. And we've come a long, long way with therapies."</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/3-facts-about-acute-lymphocytic-leukemia-in-children/">3 facts about acute lymphocytic leukemia in children</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/ALL-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/ALL-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[acute lymphocitic leukemia]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[ALL]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Asmaa Ferdjallah]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Merkel cell carcinoma</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-merkel-cell-carcinoma/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cynthia Weiss]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Catherine Degesys]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[merkel cell carcinoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374183</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: I recently heard about a type of skin cancer called Merkel cell carcinoma. I'm not familiar with this condition. Can you explain what it is? Do I need to do anything different to protect myself? ANSWER: Skin cancer is the most common cancer in the U.S. The American Academy of Dermatology estimates [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-merkel-cell-carcinoma/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Merkel cell carcinoma</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="468" height="264" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Merkel-Cell-Carcinoma-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374476" style="aspect-ratio:16/9;object-fit:cover" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Merkel-Cell-Carcinoma-16x9-1.jpg 468w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Merkel-Cell-Carcinoma-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 468px) 100vw, 468px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Merkel cell carcinoma</figcaption></figure>



<p></p>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> I recently heard about a type of skin cancer called Merkel cell carcinoma. I'm not familiar with this condition. Can you explain what it is? Do I need to do anything different to protect myself?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong> Skin cancer is the most common cancer in the U.S. The American Academy of Dermatology <a href="https://www.aad.org/media/stats-skin-cancer" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">estimates</a> that 1 in every 5 people will develop <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/skin-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20377605" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">skin cancer</a> annually. In general, exposure to UV light from the sun or tanning equipment increases the risk of developing skin cancer. Anyone is at risk of developing skin cancer. People with lighter or fair skin color are at increased risk of sunburn and skin cancer, but anyone can experience sun damage and develop skin cancer.</p>



<p>There are two main types of skin cancer: melanoma and -nonmelanoma skin cancer, of which basal cell carcinoma and squamous cell carcinoma are the most common. Basal cell and squamous cell carcinoma are estimated to affect more than 5 million people in the U.S. annually. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/melanoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20374884" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Melanoma</a> is less common but can be more dangerous as it is more likely to spread if left untreated.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/merkel-cell-carcinoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20351030" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Merkel cell carcinoma</a> falls within the category of nonmelanoma skin cancer and is a rare neuroendocrine carcinoma of the skin, affecting about 2,500 people in the U.S. annually. Merkel cells are found at the base of the top layer of skin.</p>



<p>This <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/merkel-cell-carcinoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20351030" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">type of cancer</a> is more aggressive than melanoma as it tends to grow rapidly and spread quickly to other parts of the body. Merkel cell tumors often appear as flesh-colored or pink lumps or bumps on the skin.</p>



<p>Although anyone can be at risk, Merkel cell carcinoma often develops in older people. Like other types of skin cancers, long-term sun exposure is known to be a major risk factor for Merkel cell carcinoma.</p>



<p>Immunosuppressed people – such as those who have had organ transplants – or individuals who have certain types of blood cancers are at greater risk for Merkel cell carcinoma.</p>



<p>Depending on the cancer stage at diagnosis, treatment for Merkel cell carcinoma will vary. Given the propensity for this cancer to spread early, most patients will undergo a procedure to remove the cancer. Many also will have a sentinel lymph node biopsy performed. Depending on the biopsy results, additional surgery, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/in-depth/adjuvant-therapy/art-20046687" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">radiation therapy</a> or other treatment, including immunotherapy or chemotherapy, may be needed.</p>



<p>Just like any other types of skin cancer, the best way to protect yourself is to practice good sun hygiene. This includes wearing sunscreen and limiting the body's exposure to UV radiation.</p>



<p>Avoid being in the sun during peak hours, which is usually between 10 a.m. and 2 p.m. If you will be outdoors, wear sun-protective clothing, including long sleeves, a wide-brimmed hat and sunglasses.</p>



<p>Be mindful about using and reapplying sunscreen, even on cloudy days. When choosing a sunscreen, look for a broad-spectrum product with a sun protection factor (SPF) 30 or above. The higher the SPF, the better protection. You also want to find a sunscreen that is labeled as "broad-spectrum" or "full-spectrum" sunscreen.</p>



<p>There are many different types of sunscreens. Both chemical and physical sunscreens offer effective sun protection when applied correctly. Chemical sunscreens work by absorbing the UV light and causing it to undergo a chemical reaction that prevents it from damaging your skin. Physical sunscreen protects you from UV radiation by either reflecting or blocking the damaging rays. These products contain zinc oxide or titanium dioxide.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Chemical sunscreen tends to be easier to spread and blend on the skin compared to mineral/barrier sunscreen, which is usually zinc-based and, therefore, thicker and whiter in color. While zinc sunscreen is less irritating for sensitive skin, it may be more cumbersome for people with darker skin tones. Recently, many brands have created sunscreens that blend more easily with various skin tones. Find one you like and feel comfortable applying – and reapplying – to your skin.</p>



<p>The key to getting the total amount of SPF protection from sunscreen is applying it generously and frequently. Most people need to apply more. For example, most adults need about 1 ounce of sunscreen to cover their body effectively, or about enough to fill a shot glass. Reapply sunscreen at least every two hours, or more often if you’ve been sweating or swimming.</p>



<p>It is important to note rapidly growing or changing lesions. If you notice something new or changes in size, color or shape, consult with a dermatologist or other healthcare expert. The earlier a skin cancer is found the better chance of successful treatment. — <strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/degesys-catherine-a-m-d/bio-20509515" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Dr. Catherine Degesys</em></a><em>, Dermatology, Mayo Clinic, Jacksonville, Florida</em></strong></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-merkel-cell-carcinoma/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Merkel cell carcinoma</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Merkel-Cell-Carcinoma-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Merkel-Cell-Carcinoma-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Catherine Degesys]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[merkel cell carcinoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New gene markers detect Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer, Mayo Clinic study</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-gene-markers-detect-lynch-syndrome-associated-colorectal-cancer-mayo-clinic-study/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelley Luckstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 16:22:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[colorectal cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jewel Samadder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[genetic markers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genetic Testing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lynch Syndrome]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374770</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Researchers from Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center and Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine have discovered new genetic markers to identify Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer with high accuracy. Studies are underway to determine if these genetic markers are in stool samples and, if so, how this could lead to a non-invasive screening [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-gene-markers-detect-lynch-syndrome-associated-colorectal-cancer-mayo-clinic-study/">New gene markers detect Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer, Mayo Clinic study</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="689" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610-1024x689.jpg" alt="a close-up view of a deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) sequencing test illuminated in green, blue, and purple" class="wp-image-362241" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610-1024x689.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610-300x202.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610-768x517.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610-1536x1034.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610.jpg 1671w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Researchers from <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine/education/gerstner-family-career-development-awards" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine</a> have discovered new genetic markers to identify Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer with high accuracy. Studies are underway to determine if these genetic markers are in stool samples and, if so, how this could lead to a non-invasive screening option for patients with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lynch-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20374714?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lynch syndrome.</a> Their research was published in <a href="https://aacrjournals.org/cancerpreventionresearch/article/doi/10.1158/1940-6207.CAPR-23-0107/729134/Methylated-DNA-Markers-for-Sporadic-Colorectal-and" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cancer Prevention Research</a>, a journal of the American Association for Cancer Research.</p>



<p>"This is an exciting finding that brings us closer to the reality that clinicians may soon be able to offer a non-invasive cancer screening option to patients with the highest risk of getting cancer," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/samadder-niloy-jewel-jewel-j-m-d/bio-20415667?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jewel Samadder, M.D.</a>, co-lead author of the paper and gastroenterologist at Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center. "I look forward to the day when I no longer have to remind patients with Lynch Syndrome to schedule their annual colonoscopy and complete the prep, when they will instead be able to provide a stool sample to screen for cancer."</p>



<p>Lynch syndrome is an inherited genetic condition that significantly increases the risk of multiple cancers, most notably colorectal and uterine cancers. Approximately 1 in 300 people have Lynch syndrome, many of whom are unaware of it. Patients with Lynch syndrome undergo <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/colonoscopy/about/pac-20393569?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colonoscopies</a> annually to detect and remove pre-cancerous lesions that can form colorectal cancer, in addition to undergoing invasive tests or prophylactic surgery to prevent uterine cancer.</p>



<p>For this study, the researchers evaluated a panel of methylated DNA markers (MDM) for sporadic colorectal and endometrial cancers in people with Lynch syndrome (LS). Sporadic cancer is cancer that occurs randomly in people with no family history or known predisposing risk factors. The researchers also included control groups with no cancer. For colorectal cancer, there were 23 LS cases, 48 sporadic cases, 32 LS controls, and 48 sporadic controls. For endometrial cancer, there were 30 LS cases, 48 sporadic cases, 29 LS controls and 37 sporadic controls.</p>



<p>"We found that a marker panel composed of three biomarkers (LASS4, LRRC4, PPP2R5C) could effectively differentiate Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer from Lynch syndrome controls, with 92% accuracy. This three-marker panel also performed similarly in distinguishing sporadic colorectal cancer cases from controls," says Dr. Samadder. This three-marker panel is being tested in a multi-site clinical trial in patients with Lynch syndrome as a non-invasive screening option.</p>



<p>"Our findings support the feasibility of cancer detection in stool and lower gynecologic genital tract samples in the setting of Lynch syndrome and warrant further testing," says Dr. Samadder.</p>



<p>The research was funded by the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine</a> and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine/education/gerstner-family-career-development-awards#:~:text=The%20Gerstner%20Family%20Career%20Development,research%20using%20individualized%20medicine%20approaches." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gerstner Family Career Development Award</a>. For a full list of funding, authors and conflicts of interest, see the <a href="https://aacrjournals.org/cancerpreventionresearch/article/doi/10.1158/1940-6207.CAPR-23-0107/729134/Methylated-DNA-Markers-for-Sporadic-Colorectal-and" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">paper</a>.  </p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive&nbsp;Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;is defining new boundaries in possibility, focusing on patient-centered care, developing novel treatments, training future generations of cancer experts, and bringing cancer research to communities. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs that are changing approaches to cancer prevention, screening, and treatment and improving the lives of cancer survivors.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-gene-markers-detect-lynch-syndrome-associated-colorectal-cancer-mayo-clinic-study/">New gene markers detect Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer, Mayo Clinic study</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/a-close-up-view-of-a-deoxyribonucleic-acid-DNA-sequencing-test-illuminated-in-green-blue-and-purple-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/a-close-up-view-of-a-deoxyribonucleic-acid-DNA-sequencing-test-illuminated-in-green-blue-and-purple-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[colorectal cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jewel Samadder]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[genetic markers]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Genetic Testing]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Lynch Syndrome]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>On the road again &#8211; thanks to collaborative cancer care</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/on-the-road-again-thanks-to-collaborative-cancer-care/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cynthia Weiss]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 17 Sep 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bill McDermott]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Muhamad Alhaj Moustafa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lymphoma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374080</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Although he doesn't remember all of the details, Bill McDermott says he began having abdominal issues and pain in mid-2021. He went in for some tests at a local hospital, where he got a diagnosis he did not expect. Doctors told Bill he had large B cell lymphoma, a type of blood cancer. "When I [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/on-the-road-again-thanks-to-collaborative-cancer-care/">On the road again &#8211; thanks to collaborative cancer care</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/McDermot1-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374084" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/McDermot1-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/McDermot1-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/McDermot1-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/McDermot1-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/McDermot1-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>In a matter of months, Bill McDermott went from having abdominal pain and learning he had lymphoma to being told it was time for hospice care. What his family did next would steer him in an entirely different direction. &nbsp;</em></figcaption></figure>



<p>Although he doesn't remember all of the details, Bill McDermott says he began having abdominal issues and pain in mid-2021. He went in for some tests at a local hospital, where he got a diagnosis he did not expect.</p>



<p>Doctors told Bill he had large B cell lymphoma, a type of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lymphoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20352638" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">blood cancer</a>.</p>



<p>"When I first heard the diagnosis, I was really shocked," says Bill's wife, Lourdes. "Lymphoma is something you hear other people having, not something that will happen to us."</p>



<p>Bill began chemotherapy at a facility near his home in Jacksonville, but by fall, he began to have what Lourdes calls "episodes where he was not himself."</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/vY7eac005FM" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Bill's story here</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubevY7eac005FM"  title="On the road again - thanks to collaborative cancer care" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vY7eac005FM?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/Bill-McDermott-story.mp4"></video></figure>



<p>The cancer had spread to his brain. Doctors said there was nothing more to do except move Bill into hospice.</p>



<p>"The hopelessness set in very quickly," says Lourdes.</p>



<p>What they did next, however, brought him to Mayo Clinic, where a team of specialists had a different answer for Bill. The family requested a second opinion at Mayo Clinic's Comprehensive Cancer Center.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Specialized lymphoma care</strong></h2>



<p>They met with hematologist/oncologist <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/alhaj-moustafa-muhamad-m-d-m-s/bio-20516924" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Muhamad Alhaj Moustafa</a>, M.D., who explained that since the cancer had metastasized, it was now reclassified as a central nervous system lymphoma.</p>



<p>But he was at the right place to get help."This type of cancer is a unique subtype of lymphoma that is very difficult to control. It requires different treatment than other lymphomas outside the central nervous system, so you need specific expertise to know how to treat these cancers, which are mainly found at academic medical centers," says Dr. Moustafa, who is part of a specialized <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/lymphoma-group/ovc-20201567" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymphoma group</a> at Mayo Clinic in Florida.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Treating more than cancer</strong></h2>



<p>"When I saw Mr. McDermott, I knew I could offer something less toxic to control his cancer," Dr. Moustafa says.</p>



<p>Bill, an auto enthusiast, had expressed that he hoped to be able to drive his car again.</p>



<p>"For him, that was a top priority," says Dr. Moustafa. "So, we needed to cure his lymphoma but also bring him back to life."</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/McDermot3-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374088" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/McDermot3-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/McDermot3-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/McDermot3-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/McDermot3-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/McDermot3-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Dr. Moustafa selected a combination of drugs for Bill. He also assembled a team of experts from various practice areas, including neurology, neuropsychology, ophthalmology, physical therapy, and social work to get Bill back to health.</p>



<p>By the end of 2022, scans confirmed that Bill was in remission. &nbsp;</p>



<p>"It was a miracle," says Lourdes. Every day, I'm thankful to everyone at Mayo because I wouldn't have him sitting next to me today without Mayo Clinic."</p>



<p>In July, Bill and Lourdes embarked on a 10-day cruise to celebrate their 53rd wedding anniversary. The couple plans to travel to Atlanta and Nashville and Savannah, Georgia, in September and October to showcase their his-and-her Mustangs.</p>



<p>"It is great to get back behind the wheel and drive again," says Bill.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/on-the-road-again-thanks-to-collaborative-cancer-care/">On the road again &#8211; thanks to collaborative cancer care</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/McDermot1-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/McDermot1-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Bill McDermott]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Muhamad Alhaj Moustafa]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[lymphoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Consumer Health: Do you know the symptoms of prostate cancer?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-do-you-know-the-symptoms-of-prostate-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laurel Kelly]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2023 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Prostate Cancer Awareness Month]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=370824</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>September is&#160;Prostate Cancer Awareness Month, which makes this&#160;a good time to learn about treating prostate cancer. Prostate cancer&#160;will affect 1 in 8 men, according to the&#160;American Cancer Society. After skin cancer, prostate cancer is the most common cancer diagnosed in men in the U.S. More than 288,000 new cases of prostate cancer will be diagnosed [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-do-you-know-the-symptoms-of-prostate-cancer/">Consumer Health: Do you know the symptoms of prostate cancer?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="682" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1368424020-1024x682.jpg" alt="a portrait of a smiling middle-aged Black man wearing a grey herringbone cap and a dark green shirt" class="wp-image-370924" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1368424020-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1368424020-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1368424020-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1368424020-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1368424020.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>September is&nbsp;<a href="https://www.aacr.org/patients-caregivers/awareness-months/prostate-cancer-awareness-month/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Prostate Cancer Awareness Month</a>, which makes this<em><strong>&nbsp;</strong></em>a good time to learn about treating prostate cancer.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prostate-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353087?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Prostate cancer</a>&nbsp;will affect 1 in 8 men, according to the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/prostate-cancer/about/key-statistics.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Cancer Society</a>. After skin cancer, prostate cancer is the most common cancer diagnosed in men in the U.S. More than 288,000 new cases of prostate cancer will be diagnosed this year, and more than 34,000 people will die of the disease.</p>



<p>The prostate is a small walnut-shaped gland in males that produces the seminal fluid that nourishes and transports sperm. Many prostate cancers grow slowly and are confined to the prostate gland, where they may not cause serious harm. However, while some types of prostate cancer grow slowly and may need minimal or even no treatment, other types are aggressive and can spread quickly.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Symptoms</strong></h2>



<p>Prostate cancer may cause no signs or symptoms in its early stages.</p>



<p>More advanced prostate cancer may cause signs and symptoms such as:</p>



<ul>
<li>Trouble urinating.</li>



<li>Decreased force in the stream of urine.</li>



<li>Blood in the urine.</li>



<li>Blood in the semen.</li>



<li>Bone pain.</li>



<li>Losing weight without trying.</li>



<li>Erectile dysfunction.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Risk factors</strong></h2>



<p>Factors that can increase your risk of prostate cancer include:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Older age<br></strong>Your risk of prostate cancer increases as you age. It's most common after 50.</li>



<li><strong>Race</strong><br>Black men are at greater risk of prostate cancer than men of other races, and their prostate cancer is more likely to be aggressive or advanced.</li>



<li><strong>Family history<br></strong>If a blood relative, such as a parent, sibling or child, has been diagnosed with prostate cancer, your risk may be increased. Also, if you have a family history of genes that increase the risk of breast cancer ―&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/brca-gene-test/about/pac-20384815?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">BRCA1 or BRCA2</a>&nbsp;― or a strong family history of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a>, your risk of prostate cancer may be higher.</li>



<li><strong>Obesity<br></strong>Men who are obese may have a higher risk of prostate cancer compared with men considered to have a healthy weight, though studies have had mixed results. In men who are obese, the cancer is more likely to be more aggressive and more likely to return after initial treatment.</li>
</ul>



<p>If you're concerned about your risk, you may be interested in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prostate-cancer/in-depth/prostate-cancer-prevention/art-20045641?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">prostate cancer prevention</a>. While there's no proven prevention strategy, you can reduce your risk of prostate cancer by making healthy choices regarding your diet, weight and exercise.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Treatment</strong></h2>



<p>If you've been diagnosed with prostate cancer, your&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prostate-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20353093?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">treatment</a>&nbsp;options will depend on several factors, such as how fast your cancer is growing, whether it has spread, your overall health, and the potential benefits or side effects of the treatment.</p>



<p>Low-grade prostate cancer may not need treatment right away. For some, treatment may never be needed. Instead, active surveillance may be an option for cancer that isn't causing symptoms, is expected to grow slowly and is confined to a small area of the prostate.</p>



<p>If treatment is recommended, options can include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Surgery to remove the prostate.</li>



<li>Radiation therapy.</li>



<li>Ablative therapies.</li>



<li>Hormone therapy.</li>



<li>Chemotherapy.</li>



<li>Immunotherapy.</li>



<li>Targeted drug therapy.</li>
</ul>



<p>Connect with others talking about prostate cancer, screening and treatments in the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/prostate-cancer/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Prostate Cancer Support Group</a> on&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Connect</a>, an online patient community moderated by Mayo Clinic.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-do-you-know-the-symptoms-of-prostate-cancer/">Consumer Health: Do you know the symptoms of prostate cancer?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-portrait-of-a-smiling-middle-aged-Black-man-wearing-a-grey-herringbone-cap-and-a-dark-green-shirt-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-portrait-of-a-smiling-middle-aged-Black-man-wearing-a-grey-herringbone-cap-and-a-dark-green-shirt-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Prostate Cancer Awareness Month]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&#038;A: How to manage dry mouth during cancer care</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-how-to-manage-dry-mouth-during-cancer-care/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cynthia Weiss]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2023 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jeffrey Janus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dry moputh]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hyposalivation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[xerostomia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=373228</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: I was diagnosed with oral cavity cancer and will need surgery. I spoke to another patient who underwent a similar procedure, and he said he had many issues afterward with hyposalivation, which affected his eating, speaking and oral health. Can you explain what this is and how do I prevent it? ANSWER: [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-how-to-manage-dry-mouth-during-cancer-care/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: How to manage dry mouth during cancer care</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-middle-aged-woman-drinking-a-glass-of-water-to-stay-hydrated-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a middle-aged woman drinking a glass of water to stay hydrated" class="wp-image-100039" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-middle-aged-woman-drinking-a-glass-of-water-to-stay-hydrated-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-middle-aged-woman-drinking-a-glass-of-water-to-stay-hydrated-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-middle-aged-woman-drinking-a-glass-of-water-to-stay-hydrated-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> I was diagnosed with oral cavity cancer and will need surgery. I spoke to another patient who underwent a similar procedure, and he said he had many issues afterward with hyposalivation, which affected his eating, speaking and oral health. Can you explain what this is and how do I prevent it?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong> </p>



<p>While they are being treated, patients with head and neck cancer often experience xerostomia, or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/dry-mouth/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20356052" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dry mouth</a>, which may be caused by a condition known as hyposalivation or reduced saliva production. Though it is not necessarily a side effect of surgery, it is often associated with other treatments to the head and neck, such as radiation therapy. This condition can significantly affect a person's oral health and overall quality of life.</p>



<p>The standard of care for patients with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/head-and-neck-cancer-center/home/orc-20457069" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">head and neck cancer</a> can include surgery, radiation therapy, chemotherapy, targeted therapy or a combination of these treatments. Unfortunately, about 70% of patients may experience damage to healthy tissue adjacent to the treatment area. This includes the salivary glands responsible for producing and secreting saliva into the mouth.</p>



<p>Saliva plays a crucial role in maintaining oral health by helping to break down food, neutralize acids and prevent bacterial overgrowth in the mouth. Also, saliva aids in swallowing and keeps the mouth moist, preventing discomfort and speaking difficulties. Any change to the salivary gland disrupts the normal saliva flow, causing dry mouth.</p>



<p>As your friend pointed out, several challenges can arise from hyposalivation, including oral health concerns, since saliva helps protect teeth and gums from decay and infections. Reduced saliva flow can increase the risk of dental cavities, gum disease and oral infections.</p>



<p>A lack of saliva also can alter your taste. Saliva is essential for carrying taste molecules from food to our taste buds. With reduced saliva production, taste may be altered, which can lead to less enjoyment while eating and drinking. Also, saliva is necessary to create a comfortable environment for dentures. Dry mouth can make wearing dentures uncomfortable and may cause irritation.</p>



<p>Recognizing the number of people affected by hyposalivation, research is occurring to try to find new alternatives for patients. At Mayo Clinic, researchers are looking at whether stem cells can restore salivary gland function. This research is ongoing, but initial results look very promising. Between now (when you need to be treated for your head and neck cancer) and the time stem cell research can provide definitive treatments, talk with your care team to determine the risk for hyposalivation. This can help you be aware of potential changes and create a plan to manage the condition if it arises. Consider speaking with a dietitian for easy-to-chew foods you can swallow and enjoy during recovery to maintain adequate nutrition. This is particularly important if you have specific dietary restrictions or concerns outside your cancer.</p>



<p>Other <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/dry-mouth/expert-answers/dry-mouth/faq-20058424" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">tips to help manage hyposalivation</a>: <br></p>



<ul>
<li>Maintain excellent oral hygiene. Regular brushing, flossing and rinsing with fluoride mouthwashes can help prevent dental problems. It is important to continue with regular dental visits after surgery to ensure your mouth and teeth remain healthy.</li>



<li>Stay hydrated. Sipping water regularly can help keep the mouth moist. Avoiding sugary and acidic beverages is recommended, as they can contribute to dental issues.</li>



<li>Use saliva substitutes. Over-the-counter saliva substitutes can temporarily alleviate dry mouth. There are sprays, gels and lozenges available.</li>



<li>Chew gum or candy. Chewing on gum or sucking on candy can stimulate saliva flow. Be sure to choose the sugarless variety to limit the risk of cavities or other concerns.</li>



<li>Select moist or softer food. Things like eggs, oatmeal, cottage cheese, yogurt, avocado, canned fruit in natural juices, hummus or tofu are all great options that easily can be incorporated into many dishes.</li>



<li>Be mindful of the temperature. Ensure that foods are not too hot or spicy, as heat can worsen mouth discomfort.</li>



<li>Avoid dry air. Depending upon where you live, dry air can be a way of life. But consider using a humidifier at night to add moisture to the air and reduce dryness.</li>



<li>Avoid tobacco and alcohol. Both tobacco and alcohol can exacerbate dry mouth.</li>
</ul>



<p>Though hyposalivation is common for patients who have received multimodality therapy for oral cancer, with advanced preparation, you can hopefully alleviate the discomfort it causes to maintain a good quality of life and easier recovery. —<strong> <em><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/janus-jeffrey-r-m-d/bio-20097323" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Jeffrey Janus, M.D.</a>, Otolaryngology, Mayo Clinic, Jacksonville, Florida</em></strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>****************************</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-how-to-manage-dry-mouth-during-cancer-care/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: How to manage dry mouth during cancer care</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-middle-aged-woman-drinking-a-glass-of-water-to-stay-hydrated-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-middle-aged-woman-drinking-a-glass-of-water-to-stay-hydrated-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jeffrey Janus]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[dry moputh]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[hyposalivation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[xerostomia]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>