<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org">

<channel>
	<title>Cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml">
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastbuilddate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 12:16:45 +0000</lastbuilddate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updateperiod>
	hourly	</sy:updateperiod>
	<sy:updatefrequency>
	1	</sy:updatefrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>As stomach cancer rates rise in younger people, knowing symptoms and family history is key</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/as-stomach-cancer-rates-rise-in-younger-people-knowing-symptoms-and-family-history-is-key/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Jessica Saenz]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 13:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Mojun Zhu]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[stomach cancer]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=400720</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Stomach cancer rates in the United States have been steadily decreasing for decades, but&nbsp;recent trends&nbsp;reveal an increase in early-onset stomach cancer in people younger than 50, particularly women. Trends also reveal younger people have more advanced stomach cancer at the time of diagnosis. While cancer experts don't yet fully understand why younger people are getting […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/as-stomach-cancer-rates-rise-in-younger-people-knowing-symptoms-and-family-history-is-key/">As stomach cancer rates rise in younger people, knowing symptoms and family history is key</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"--><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/a-medical-illustration-of-stomach-cancer-16X9.jpg" alt="a medical illustration of stomach cancer" class="wp-image-220699" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/a-medical-illustration-of-stomach-cancer-16X9.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/a-medical-illustration-of-stomach-cancer-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px">



<p>Stomach cancer rates in the United States have been steadily decreasing for decades, but&nbsp;<a href="https://www.surgjournal.com/article/S0039-6060(19)30299-5/abstract" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">recent trends</a>&nbsp;reveal an increase in early-onset stomach cancer in people younger than 50, particularly women. Trends also reveal younger people have more advanced stomach cancer at the time of diagnosis.</p>



<p>While cancer experts don't yet fully understand why younger people are getting stomach cancer, they know that early diagnosis saves lives.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/zhu-mojun-m-d/bio-20521036" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mojun Zhu, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic medical oncologist who specializes in gastrointestinal cancers, says knowing your family history and the symptoms of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stomach-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352438" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stomach cancer</a>&nbsp;can help you get diagnosed before the disease has spread. She notes early treatment is most likely to be successful.</p>



<p>Dr. Zhu explains what you should know:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Stomach cancer symptoms can be vague.</h2>



<p>Stomach cancer doesn't always cause symptoms in the early stages. When it does,&nbsp;<a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/02/28/dear-mayo-clinic-signs-of-stomach-cancer-diagnosis-and-treatment/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">symptoms</a>&nbsp;are vague, and people often treat them with over-the-counter medications or dismiss them.</p>



<p>"The symptoms are not clear-cut, and they overlap with many other benign conditions," says Dr. Zhu. "A lot of our younger patients attribute their symptoms to indigestion or reflux, so they don't follow up or seek medical care immediately."</p>



<p>This delay allows stomach cancer to advance to later stages that are more difficult to treat.</p>



<p>Advanced stomach cancer may cause symptoms such as fatigue, unexplained weight loss, appetite loss, feeling full after eating a small amount of food, anemia, vomiting blood and black stools. Dr. Zhu says these symptoms often prompt her patients to seek medical care. "When people feel their symptoms are not getting better — they've started losing weight, struggling with eating and swallowing — that's when they come to see us."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A family history of cancer might indicate increased stomach cancer risk.</h2>



<p>There are no screening recommendations for people at average risk of stomach cancer, but if you have symptoms that align with stomach cancer and a family history of cancer, your healthcare professional might recommend additional screening or genetic testing.</p>



<p>"It's really important to know your first-degree family's history — that's parents, siblings and children — and second-degree family, such as your grandparents, uncles and aunts," says Dr. Zhu. "If you have heard about first- or second-degree family members having breast, stomach, or other types of gastrointestinal cancers before age 50, discuss that with your primary care professionals to see if you should consider more advanced genetic testing or genetic counseling."</p>



<p>If genetic test results indicate you carry an inherited condition that increases your risk of stomach cancer, your healthcare professional may recommend a screening plan tailored to your risk.</p>



<p>Screening for stomach cancer in the U.S. is often done through&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/endoscopy/about/pac-20395197" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">an upper endoscopy</a>, a procedure where a thin tube with a camera is inserted through the mouth and down the throat into the stomach.</p>



<p>Genetic conditions that increase your risk of stomach cancer include&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lynch-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20374714" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lynch syndrome</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/def/juvenile-polyposis-syndrome" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">juvenile polyposis syndrome</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/def/peutz-jeghers-syndrome" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Peutz-Jeghers syndrome</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/def/familial-adenomatous-polyposis" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">familial adenomatous polyposis</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/pediatric-adult-rare-tumor/rare-tumors/rare-digestive-system-tumors/hereditary-diffuse-gastric-cancer" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hereditary diffuse gastric cancer</a>.</p>



<p>Hereditary diffuse gastric cancer is an inherited syndrome caused by a mutation in the CDH1 gene that increases the risk of stomach and breast cancer. "For patients with this syndrome, we recommend early screening — usually beginning in their 20s — for stomach and breast cancer," says Dr. Zhu.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Stomach cancer can be difficult to treat, but therapies are improving.</h2>



<p>Though stomach cancer is less common than other cancers, it can be more aggressive, has higher mortality rates, and often recurs. In earlier stages, when stomach cancer is localized, meaning it hasn't spread to other organs or lymph nodes, treatment may be more successful. "If you have stage 1 stomach cancer, it can usually be cured by surgery," says Dr. Zhu. "When you have stage 2 or 3 stomach cancer, despite surgery and chemotherapy, the risk of recurrence can be as high as or greater than 50%. Even though we consider localized stomach cancer to be a curable condition, the risk of having relapse is high."</p>



<p>Dr. Zhu says cancer researchers are making progress in stomach cancer treatment for all stages.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Early-stage stomach cancer</h3>



<p>Mayo Clinic cancer researchers are investigating how and why stomach cancer develops and trying to find ways to detect it early in people with high risk. "Our colleagues in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/gastroenterology-hepatology-digestive-care/home/orc-20348202" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gastroenterology</a>&nbsp;are researching ways to help identify early-stage stomach cancer. This includes upcoming clinical trials to investigate the effectiveness of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mri/about/pac-20384768" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">MRI</a>&nbsp;as a screening test for people at high risk of stomach cancer," she says.</p>



<p>Dr. Zhu adds that researchers are also advancing minimally invasive surgical techniques to improve quality of life for people with early-stage stomach cancer. "Locoregional therapies such as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/endoscopic-mucosal-resection/about/pac-20385213" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">endoscopic mucosal resection</a>&nbsp;may help people with very early-stage stomach cancer avoid a full or partial gastrectomy (removal of all or part of the stomach)," she says.</p>



<p>Similar to an&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stomach-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352443#dialogId52584582" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">upper endoscopy</a>, an endoscopic resection passes a long narrow tube called an endoscope down the throat and into the stomach. The endoscope can be used to identify and remove abnormal or cancerous tissue.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Advanced stomach cancer</h3>



<p>Dr. Zhu says Mayo Clinic is researching new therapies for advanced stomach cancer in clinical trials. These include immunotherapy, which leverages your immune system to attack cancer cells, and targeted drug therapies, which target certain aspects of cancer cells that help them grow, divide and spread.</p>



<p>"There are newer classes of medications called antibody drug conjugates and bispecific antibodies that have demonstrated promising results in early-phase clinical trials," she says. Antibody drug conjugates attach a cancer-killing drug to an antibody that targets cancer cells, delivering the drug directly to cancer cells to minimize damage to healthy cells. Bispecific antibody drugs bind to cancer cells and immune cells, bringing them together so the immune cells can attack and destroy the cancer cells.</p>



<p>In late 2024, the FDA also approved the use of a new&nbsp;<a href="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/resources-information-approved-drugs/fda-approves-zolbetuximab-clzb-chemotherapy-gastric-or-gastroesophageal-junction-adenocarcinoma" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">monoclonal antibody drug</a>&nbsp;that uses a lab-made protein that binds to a specific target on a cancer cell to help the immune system identify and attack it. This drug can be used in combination with first-line chemotherapy in patients with certain advanced stomach cancers that cannot be surgically removed, have spread to other parts of the body, and are&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/def/her2-negative" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">HER2-negative</a>.</p>



<p><a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/01/18/new-chemotherapy-approach-for-late-stage-cancers/">Hyperthermic intraperitoneal chemotherapy (HIPEC)</a>, a heated liquid form of chemotherapy, is also an option for some people with advanced stomach cancer. It can be used in combination with surgery to kill any remaining cancer cells left behind in the abdominal cavity after tumor removal. Recent studies have shown this drug combination is extending the lives of people with stage 4 gastric cancers that have spread in the abdominal cavity.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Stomach cancer spread and related cancer development</h3>



<p>People with stomach cancer have a high risk of developing&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/def/peritoneal-carcinomatosis" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">peritoneal carcinomatosis</a>, a metastatic disease that occurs when cancer spreads and grows in the membrane that drapes over the organs in the abdomen and pelvis. "Up to 50% of stomach cancer patients develop peritoneal disease down the road despite having a total gastrectomy. Our surgeons are developing clinical trials to look at the use of intraperitoneal therapy (treatment placed directly in the abdominal cavity) to lower the risk," says Dr. Zhu.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity">



<p>Though there are still many unanswered questions about the increasing incidence of stomach cancer in younger people, knowing your family history and stomach cancer symptoms can help you catch the disease early when it's most treatable. If you have new symptoms associated with stomach cancer, don't delay — talk to your healthcare professional. Ask if screening or genetic testing is right for you.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Learn more</h2>



<p>Learn more about&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stomach-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352438" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stomach cancer</a>&nbsp;and find a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials/diseases-conditions/stomach-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">clinical trial</a>&nbsp;at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>Join the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/discussion/stomach-cancer-1/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stomach Cancer Support Group</a>&nbsp;on&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Connect</a>, an online community moderated by Mayo Clinic for patients and caregivers.</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2025/02/11/as-stomach-cancer-rates-rise-in-younger-people-knowing-symptoms-and-family-history-is-key/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/as-stomach-cancer-rates-rise-in-younger-people-knowing-symptoms-and-family-history-is-key/">As stomach cancer rates rise in younger people, knowing symptoms and family history is key</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/a-medical-illustration-of-stomach-cancer-1X1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/a-medical-illustration-of-stomach-cancer-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Mojun Zhu]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[stomach cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers identify a measurable genetic mutation as a significant predictor of metastasis and survival in pancreatic cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-a-measurable-genetic-mutation-as-a-significant-predictor-of-metastasis-and-survival-in-pancreatic-cancer/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Kelley Luckstein]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 16:03:35 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=401026</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — A new study by Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center researchers found that the presence of a specific genetic mutation — KRAS circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) — strongly indicates a higher risk of cancer spread and worse survival rates for patients with pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC). The mutation was identified using a readily […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-a-measurable-genetic-mutation-as-a-significant-predictor-of-metastasis-and-survival-in-pancreatic-cancer/">Mayo Clinic researchers identify a measurable genetic mutation as a significant predictor of metastasis and survival in pancreatic cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DNA7-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-396933" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DNA7-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DNA7-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DNA7-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DNA7-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DNA7.png 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A new study by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> researchers found that the presence of a specific genetic mutation — KRAS circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) — strongly indicates a higher risk of cancer spread and worse survival rates for patients with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pancreatic-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20355421" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma</a> (PDAC). The mutation was identified using a readily available and clinically approved blood and abdominal fluid test.</p>



<p>PDAC is an aggressive form of cancer that is often difficult to diagnose. Most patients already have cancer spread to other parts of their body when initially diagnosed, and current tests often miss this hidden spread. This makes it challenging to determine the best treatment strategy. The findings, published in the <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1245/s10434-025-17036-y" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Annals of Surgical Oncology</a>, may help identify patients who are more likely to have cancer spread to other parts of the body, therefore providing doctors and patients with the right information to make informed decisions about treatment.</p>



<p>"This is a major advancement for pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/truty-mark-j-m-d-m-s/bio-20114332" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mark Truty, M.D.</a>, hepatobiliary and pancreatic surgical oncologist within Mayo Clinic's <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-surgery/sections/overview/ovc-20475393" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Surgery</a>. Dr. Truty is senior author of the study. "We've had this genetic testing available for a number of years, however, we did not know the significance of the results or how to interpret them. Having the KRAS status will allow the patient and their provider to make better decisions about their individual cancer treatment."</p>



<p>The prospective cohort study, involving nearly 800 patients — the largest patient series to date in the literature using ctDNA — found that 20%-30% of patients with PDAC have detectable mutant KRAS ctDNA in the blood and/or peritoneum, and that those without any previous treatment, such as chemotherapy, had the highest incidence. Thus, the study suggests that ctDNA assays should be performed prior to treatment to have the highest yield.</p>



<p>The researchers examined data between 2018 and 2022. Blood sample tests revealed that 104 patients (14%) had KRAS ctDNA mutation. These patients were more likely to develop advanced, spreading cancer and had a lower survival rate. Further testing of fluid from around the abdominal cavity in 419 patients showed similar results: 123 (29%) had the marker, and these patients also experienced worse outcomes. The presence of this marker, whether in blood or abdominal fluid, indicated a poorer prognosis.</p>



<p>The study highlights that while surgery is the only known cure, most patients experience cancer spread after surgery. The test helps identify patients less likely to benefit from surgery alone, guiding treatment decisions towards chemotherapy and/or radiation before surgery. For patients without the KRAS mutation (approximately 10% of cases), the test is less conclusive and other tests are needed.</p>



<p>"Historically, we've known that KRAS mutations are associated with a more biologically aggressive pancreatic cancer," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/leiting-jennifer-l-m-d/bio-20579694" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jennifer Leiting, M.D.</a>, hepatobiliary and pancreatic surgeon within Mayo Clinic's Department of Surgery. Dr. Leiting is first author of the study. "But this large study gives us a much clearer understanding of how to interpret the test results and use them to improve patient care. It allows for more accurate staging at diagnosis, leading to better treatment decisions."</p>



<p>The researchers suggest that this test should become a standard part of the initial diagnosis for PDAC, enabling more personalized risk stratification and effective treatment plans.</p>



<p>"This improved diagnostic capability offers hope for patients and their families facing this challenging disease," says Dr. Truty. "It's optimistic to see how advances in genetic testing are directly helping our patients."</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newbureau@mayo.edu">newbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-a-measurable-genetic-mutation-as-a-significant-predictor-of-metastasis-and-survival-in-pancreatic-cancer/">Mayo Clinic researchers identify a measurable genetic mutation as a significant predictor of metastasis and survival in pancreatic cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/1x1-DNA.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DNA7.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>(VIDEO) Treatment options for advanced colorectal cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treatment-options-for-advanced-colorectal-cancer/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Deb Balzer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 13:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Florida]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Gastroenterology]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Umair Majeed]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=400897</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Colorectal cancer&nbsp;is one of the most treatable cancers, especially when detected early. For those in advanced stages, significant advancements in therapies are providing renewed hope.&nbsp; Dr. Umair Majeed, a Mayo Clinic oncologist, says improved treatment options mean better outcomes for patients, even for those with late-stage colorectal cancer. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute Journalists: Broadcast-quality […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treatment-options-for-advanced-colorectal-cancer/">(VIDEO) Treatment options for advanced colorectal cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<p--><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-understanding-colorectal-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Colorectal cancer</a>&nbsp;is one of the most treatable cancers, especially when detected early. For those in advanced stages, significant advancements in therapies are providing renewed hope.&nbsp;<p></p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/majeed-umair-m-b-b-s-m-d/bio-20536985" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Umair Majeed</a>, a Mayo Clinic oncologist, says improved treatment options mean better outcomes for patients, even for those with late-stage colorectal cancer.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/3yojQz85UgA" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe id="videoidhttpsyoutube3yojQz85UgA" title="Treatment options for advanced colorectal cancer" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3yojQz85UgA?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:21) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/03/SCRIPT-MCM-Treatment-options-advanced-colorectal-cancer7.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Colon cancer is&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20353674" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">staged</a>&nbsp;from 0 to 4. The stage determines the extent of the cancer — and the treatment.</p>



<p>"Stages 3 and 4 are considered advanced stages, where the cancer goes into the lymph nodes in stage 3 disease, and it goes into distant organs like the lungs, liver or bones in stage 4 disease," says Dr. Majeed.</p>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/03/a-medical-illustration-of-colon-cancer-16X9.jpg" alt="a medical illustration of the rectum, sigmoid colon, descending colon, transverse colon, ascending colon and secum, as well as an image of colon cancer seen during colonoscopy, colorectal
" class="wp-image-185207" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/03/a-medical-illustration-of-colon-cancer-16X9.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/03/a-medical-illustration-of-colon-cancer-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px"></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">When colorectal cancer spreads</h2>



<p>The liver is the most common organ colorectal spreads to.</p>



<p>"We are offering liver transplantation as an option to select patients. We have a&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/hepatic-artery-infusion-pump-therapy-for-colorectal-liver-metastases/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hepatic artery infusion pump program</a>&nbsp;also available for those patients where the cancer has spread from the colon or the rectum to the liver," he says.</p>



<p>The pump delivers chemotherapy directly to artery that supplies the liver. He says, in addition to surgery, treatment options include better drugs, immunotherapy and targeted therapies.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"We have surgeons who specialize in advanced procedures such as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/endocrinology/news/role-for-cytoreduction-surgery-in-metastatic-adrenocortical-carcinoma-new-study/mac-20535815" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cytoreductive surgery</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-new-chemotherapy-approach-for-treating-stomach-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">HIPEC</a>, which is a form of specialized chemotherapy given into the peritoneum for select patients," Dr. Majeed says.</p>



<p>With all these advanced options, Dr. Majeed remains cautiously optimistic.</p>



<p>"Colorectal cancer is a type of cancer where, even if it's stage 4, there is a chance of cure in select cases," he says.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Related topics:</strong></h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-warning-signs-of-colorectal-cancer-in-younger-adults/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Warning signs of colorectal cancer in younger adults</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-are-colon-and-rectal-cancers-treated-differently/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Are colon and rectal cancers treated differently?</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/hepatic-artery-infusion-pump-therapy-for-colorectal-liver-metastases/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hepatic artery infusion pump therapy for colorectal liver metastases</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treatment-options-for-advanced-colorectal-cancer/">(VIDEO) Treatment options for advanced colorectal cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/03/Colon-3-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/03/Colon-3-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Umair Majeed]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: So you’re having a colonoscopy: What to expect</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-so-youre-having-a-colonoscopy-what-to-expect/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Abby Smith]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 13:01:41 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Gastroenterology]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Derek Ebner]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=397860</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;I just turned 45 and am dreading my first colonoscopy. Why do I need to be screened if I'm not having issues? Can you walk me through the process? ANSWER:&nbsp;Feeling anxious or afraid surrounding a procedure, particularly when you've never done it before, is completely normal. The purpose of screening is to act […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-so-youre-having-a-colonoscopy-what-to-expect/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: So you’re having a colonoscopy: What to expect</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Mature-Asian-man-sits-on-steps-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Mature man, Asian, male, sits on stairs, outside" class="wp-image-397879" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Mature-Asian-man-sits-on-steps-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Mature-Asian-man-sits-on-steps-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Mature-Asian-man-sits-on-steps-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Mature-Asian-man-sits-on-steps-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Mature-Asian-man-sits-on-steps-16-x-9.jpg 1603w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong>&nbsp;I just turned 45 and am dreading my first <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-the-importance-of-a-colonoscopy/">colonoscopy</a>. Why do I need to be screened if I'm not having issues? Can you walk me through the process?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong>&nbsp;Feeling anxious or afraid surrounding a procedure, particularly when you've never done it before, is completely normal. The purpose of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/colonoscopy/about/pac-20393569">screening</a> is to act before someone develops symptoms. If we're able to identify&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-you-need-to-know-about-polyps-in-your-colon/">polyps</a>, which are precancerous lesions in the lining of the colon, we would then have the opportunity to remove them and prevent the development of cancer in the first place. So through screening, we can prevent cancer. At the time of diagnosing cancer, we've missed that opportunity.&nbsp;</p>



<p>There are a number of ways we can screen for&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353669">colorectal cancer</a>. In the U.S., we most often use a&nbsp;colonoscopy. Colonoscopy is an invasive test, but it allows us an opportunity to not only see polyps, but also remove them at the same time. For people with&nbsp;no additional risk factors besides age, it is recommended to start screening at the age of 45. If other risk factors are present, though, it may be recommended to have a colonoscopy sooner than 45.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-tips-to-make-colonoscopy-bowel-prep-easier/">colon preparation</a>&nbsp;prior to the colonoscopy is key. The goal of colonoscopy prep is to make sure that there is nothing in the colon by using a laxative liquid solution. Then, at the time of the colonoscopy, we're able to see and detect even small precancerous lesions so they can be removed.&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="927" height="521" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/11/pouring-colonoscopy-prep-mix-into-the-bottle-cap-16x9-1.jpg" alt="pouring colonoscopy bowel prep mix into the bottle cap" class="wp-image-323297" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/11/pouring-colonoscopy-prep-mix-into-the-bottle-cap-16x9-1.jpg 927w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/11/pouring-colonoscopy-prep-mix-into-the-bottle-cap-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/11/pouring-colonoscopy-prep-mix-into-the-bottle-cap-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 927px) 100vw, 927px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Proper preparation for colonoscopy is key to success</figcaption></figure>



<p>It is very common to hear complaints from patients about the preparation, such as the consistency or taste of the solution, cramping,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/symptoms/abdominal-pain/basics/definition/sym-20050728">abdominal bloating</a>&nbsp;or discomfort. That's to be anticipated. Unfortunately, some patients also experience&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/symptoms/nausea/basics/definition/sym-20050736">nausea</a>. Try slowing down how fast you are drinking the solution. For those who tend to struggle with the taste or consistency, try drinking it through a straw. You can also bite into a small wedge of lime or lemon, or you can chew gum or ice between drinks.&nbsp;</p>



<p>After you finish the last of the prep solution and check in for your appointment, you'll often be greeted by the front desk team and then escorted back by a healthcare team member. They will review things like your medical history and medications and see how the colon prep treated you. There is a risk that you may have to come back and repeat the test at a later time if the colon prep was not adequate.</p>



<p>Another critical thing they will do is establish your intravenous therapy or IV. The IV is the route in which they will give you the medication to help make the procedure a little bit more comfortable. Some people don't do any&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/anesthesia/about/pac-20384568">sedation</a>&nbsp;at all, but it is totally appropriate to opt for it. There are several different ways that sedation could be done for the procedure. A lot of that depends upon how the procedure is scheduled with your healthcare team. Then, you will end up going back to the procedure room where they will review the nature of the procedure before starting the colonoscopy. Afterwards, there's a bit of a recovery period, and then you're able to head back home. Because of the sedation, we don't want people driving, consuming alcohol or making any critical decisions for 24 hours.&nbsp;</p>



<p>We still don't have a perfect recipe for preventing polyps, but maintaining a&nbsp;<a href="https://mcpress.mayoclinic.org/nutrition-fitness/11-tips-for-healthier-eating-habits/">healthy diet</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/fitness/expert-answers/exercise/faq-20057916">exercise</a>&nbsp;can protect you. It is important to be aware of any symptoms and then follow through with screening. Best of luck as you take this important first step. —&nbsp;<a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/residencies-and-fellowships/gastroenterology-and-hepatology-neoplasia-fellowship-minnesota/fellow-profiles/"><em>Derek Ebner,&nbsp;M.D</em></a><em>.,&nbsp;<strong>Gastroenterology, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota.</strong></em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-so-youre-having-a-colonoscopy-what-to-expect/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: So you’re having a colonoscopy: What to expect</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Mature-Asian-man-sits-on-steps-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Mature-Asian-man-sits-on-steps-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Derek Ebner]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Warning signs of colorectal cancer in younger adults</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-warning-signs-of-colorectal-cancer-in-younger-adults/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Deb Balzer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 14:15:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Gastroenterology]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Cycle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[colorectal cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Derek Ebner]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=383156</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Colorectal cancer, the third-most common cancer in the U.S., has been rising among younger people for the past two decades. It is not one type of cancer but two cancers: colon cancer, which starts in the large intestine, and rectal cancer, which begins in the last part of the large intestine, known as the rectum.&nbsp; […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-warning-signs-of-colorectal-cancer-in-younger-adults/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Warning signs of colorectal cancer in younger adults</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="803" height="452" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Warning-signs-colorectl-16x9-1.jpeg" alt="Image, warning signs of colorectal cancer younger adults" class="wp-image-383699" style="width:850px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Warning-signs-colorectl-16x9-1.jpeg 803w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Warning-signs-colorectl-16x9-1-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Warning-signs-colorectl-16x9-1-768x432.jpeg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 803px) 100vw, 803px">



<p>Colorectal cancer, the third-most common cancer in the U.S., has been rising among younger people for the past two decades. It is not one type of cancer but two cancers: <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353669?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colon cancer</a>, which starts in the large intestine, and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/rectal-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352884?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">rectal cancer</a>, which begins in the last part of the large intestine, known as the rectum.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Derek Ebner, a Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/gastroenterology-hepatology-digestive-care/sections/overview/ovc-20348241?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gastroenterologist</a>, notes that colorectal cancer has been increasing in adults under age 50, particularly for rectal cancer. He says it's important to know the&nbsp;<a href="https://academic.oup.com/jnci/article/115/8/909/7147891" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">warning signs</a>&nbsp;of colorectal cancer and to not delay medical treatment.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/d0W3KS1N5VY" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubed0W3KS1N5VY" title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Warning signs of colorectal cancer in younger adults" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/d0W3KS1N5VY?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:59) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/SCRIPT-MCM-Warning-signs-of-colorectal-cancer.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"Historically, colorectal cancer was equally divided along the colon and rectum, but particularly for those with early onset colorectal cancer — age less than 50<sub>&nbsp;</sub>— we're seeing higher rates of rectal cancer among the younger onset," says Dr. Ebner.</p>



<div class="wp-block-media-text is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/07/a-medical-illustration-of-rectal-cancer-16X9.jpg" alt="a medical illustration of rectal cancer" class="wp-image-195705 size-full" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/07/a-medical-illustration-of-rectal-cancer-16X9.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/07/a-medical-illustration-of-rectal-cancer-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px"></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p>Case of colorectal cancer has been increasing in adults under age 50, particularly for rectal cancer.</p>
</div></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Warning signs and symptoms of colorectal cancer</h2>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Dr. Ebner says four key symptoms have been identified for people under 50 who are diagnosed with colorectal cancer.</p>



<p>"Abdominal pain, diarrhea, seeing blood with bowel motions, as well as iron deficiency anemia," he says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="804" height="452" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Warning-signs-16x9-1.jpeg" alt="Graphic of warning signs of colorectal cancer with Mayo Clnic identifier" class="wp-image-383697" style="width:856px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Warning-signs-16x9-1.jpeg 804w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Warning-signs-16x9-1-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Warning-signs-16x9-1-768x432.jpeg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 804px) 100vw, 804px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Warning signs of colorectal cancer</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Dr. Ebner notes that blood loss after bowel movements, even if not visibly apparent, can lead to low iron levels.</p>



<p>"If on a blood test, for example, we see a sign of iron deficiency, that would then prompt us to explore further," he says.</p>



<p>Even though it may be embarrassing, he stresses, "If you have any of those symptoms, you need to share it with a healthcare provider. That way, they can navigate those subsequent steps."</p>



<p>Which can lead to early treatment and better outcomes.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Reducing risks of colorectal cancer</h2>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>While it's not possible to completely prevent cancer, there are ways to reduce your risks and that includes following a healthy lifestyle.</p>



<p>"Abiding by a healthy lifestyle is critical," says Dr. Ebner. "Following a well-rounded diet,  staying physically active, for instance, perhaps can be protective. The other key, though, is just being very mindful of those symptoms, and then also underscoring the importance of screening."</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Screening</strong>: Talk to your healthcare team about colorectal cancer screening.</li>



<li><strong>Exercise</strong>: Aim for 30 minutes of exercise most days.</li>



<li><strong>Nutrition</strong>: Eat fruits, veggies and whole grains.</li>



<li><strong>Weight</strong>: Maintain a healthy weight.</li>



<li><strong>Lifestyle</strong>: Don't smoke, limit alcohol consumption.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/innovative-treatments-for-rectal-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Innovative treatments for rectal cancer</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-whats-the-right-colorectal-cancer-screening-option-for-you/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: What’s the right colorectal cancer screening option for you?</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-warning-signs-of-colorectal-cancer-in-younger-adults/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Warning signs of colorectal cancer in younger adults</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Younger-adults-1x1-1.jpeg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Warning-signs-colorectl-16x9-1.jpeg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[colorectal cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Derek Ebner]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers identify proteins linked to immunotherapy resistance in metastatic colorectal cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-proteins-linked-to-immunotherapy-resistance-in-metastatic-colorectal-cancer/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Alison Satake]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 14:30:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Discovery Science]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Frank Sinicrope]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Laboratories]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=400706</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — A discovery by Mayo Clinic researchers may help explain why immunotherapy hasn't been helpful for many patients with metastatic colorectal cancer. In findings published in Clinical Cancer Research, the team identified specific proteins — fibronectin and smooth muscle actin — within colorectal cancer tissues that are associated with resistance to immunotherapy treatment. […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-proteins-linked-to-immunotherapy-resistance-in-metastatic-colorectal-cancer/">Mayo Clinic researchers identify proteins linked to immunotherapy resistance in metastatic colorectal cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-video"--><video autoplay="" controls="" loop="" muted="" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/03/fade_immunotherapy_16x9.mp4"></video><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Immunofluorescent microscopy images of colorectal cancer tissues showing tumor cells and surrounding stroma including immune cells. Credit: Mayo Clinic</figcaption>



<p><br>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A discovery by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> researchers may help explain why immunotherapy hasn't been helpful for many patients with metastatic colorectal cancer. In findings published in <a href="https://aacrjournals.org/clincancerres/article/doi/10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-24-0853/751983/Spatially-resolved-multi-region-proteomics-for" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Clinical Cancer Research</a>, the team identified specific proteins — fibronectin and smooth muscle actin — within colorectal cancer tissues that are associated with resistance to immunotherapy treatment.</p>



<p><a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2025/02/26/what-is-cancer-immunotherapy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Immunotherapy</a> is a major advance in treating cancer, but many patients, including those with metastatic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353669" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colorectal cancer</a>, do not respond to it. Until now, researchers have not known why.</p>



<p>"We need predictive biomarkers to guide the selection of immunotherapy for patients," says medical oncologist and gastroenterologist <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/sinicrope-frank-a-m-d/bio-00028129" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Frank Sinicrope, M.D.</a>, the senior author of the study. "Identifying those who may have resistance to treatment can be useful, because then we can spare them from receiving treatment that may not be beneficial and could produce significant toxicities."</p>



<p>The research team used <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/spatial-biology-puts-potential-disease-targets-in-their-place/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">digital spatial profiling</a>, an advanced technology that simultaneously analyzes the expression of multiple proteins and where they are located within tissues. This approach allowed researchers to zoom in to get a bird's eye view of a tumor that includes proteins both within and surrounding the tumor cells and how they interact.</p>



<p>Dr. Sinicrope compares the spatial tools to an aerial view of a neighborhood where one can see relationships between driveways, houses, yards and neighboring structures. Similarly, this detailed view provides physicians and researchers with critical information about the proteins in and around a patient's cancer, potentially informing the best treatment for the patient.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"We wanted to learn more about the patients who did not respond to immunotherapy. We investigated the leading edge of the tumor where cancer cells are invading and where the immune system is attempting to fight the cancer," says Dr. Sinicrope. "It's like a battle going on here and we're getting a snapshot into who is in attendance."</p>



<p>The researchers focused on 10 regions at the invasive margin of a tumor. They applied digital spatial profiling to investigate 71 distinct proteins in both the tumor's epithelial compartment and the surrounding stromal compartment. Fibronectin and smooth muscle actin are two extracellular matrix proteins that were found in the epithelial region of the tumor and were associated with resistance to immunotherapy and shorter time before disease progression.</p>



<p>Upon further analysis, the researchers observed that cancer-associated fibroblasts were producing these proteins. The evidence, they say, suggests that these proteins can contribute to suppression of the anti-tumor immune response.</p>



<p>The discovery offers a step toward more personalized and effective colorectal cancer treatments. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Review the <a href="https://aacrjournals.org/clincancerres/article/doi/10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-24-0853/751983/Spatially-resolved-multi-region-proteomics-for" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p>###&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong> &nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a> &nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-proteins-linked-to-immunotherapy-resistance-in-metastatic-colorectal-cancer/">Mayo Clinic researchers identify proteins linked to immunotherapy resistance in metastatic colorectal cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/03/colorectal-cancer-tissue1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/03/colorectal-cancer-tissue16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Frank Sinicrope]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Laboratories]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Are colon and rectal cancers treated differently?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-are-colon-and-rectal-cancers-treated-differently/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Deb Balzer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 12:09:01 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Cycle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Colon Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[colorectal cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[colrectal cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[rectal cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Surgery]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=361500</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Colorectal cancer is a term that&nbsp;combines both colon and rectal cancers. The colon and rectum are two different parts of the lower digestive tract. These different cancers also mean different approaches to treatment that may involve the use of radiation and chemotherapy in addition to surgery.&nbsp; When it comes to treating cancer, experience matters, says&nbsp;Dr. […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-are-colon-and-rectal-cancers-treated-differently/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Are colon and rectal cancers treated differently?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/Colon-Rectal-Colorectal-Cancer-Surgery-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Surgery image of colon rectal surgery including Dr. Eric Dozois and team" class="wp-image-362353" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/Colon-Rectal-Colorectal-Cancer-Surgery-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/Colon-Rectal-Colorectal-Cancer-Surgery-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/Colon-Rectal-Colorectal-Cancer-Surgery-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/Colon-Rectal-Colorectal-Cancer-Surgery-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/Colon-Rectal-Colorectal-Cancer-Surgery-16-x-9.jpg 1824w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Eric Dozois and team during a surgical procedure</figcaption>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/digestive-diseases/news/acs-announces-new-guideline-for-colorectal-cancer-screening-for-adults-at-average-risk/mac-20437729?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Colorectal cancer</a> is a term that&nbsp;combines both <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353669?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colon</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/rectal-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352884?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">rectal cancers</a>. The colon and rectum are two different parts of the lower digestive tract. These different cancers also mean different approaches to treatment that may involve the use of radiation and chemotherapy in addition to surgery.&nbsp;</p>



<p>When it comes to treating cancer, experience matters, says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/dozois-eric-j-m-d/bio-20053346?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Eric Dozois,</a>&nbsp;a Mayo Clinic colon and rectal surgeon. And Mayo Clinic has been transforming this type of care for more than 100 years.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/OM17tt1-45Y" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls="" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/Mayo-Clinic-Minute-Are-colon-and-rectal-cancers-treated-differently-CLEAN.mp4"></video></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:55) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network.</strong>" <strong>Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/Script-MCM-Colon-and-Rectal-Cancer.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Colon and rectal cancers may be detected during the same&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-the-importance-of-a-colonoscopy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">screening</a>, but they are treated differently, says Dr. Eric Dozois.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Our approach to rectal cancer, for example, often involves more aggressive treatments that help prevent it from coming back," says Dr. Dozois.</p>



<p>Innovation plays a strong role in rectal cancer surgery at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>.</p>



<p>Robotic surgery allows your surgeon to work more efficiently in small spaces, providing an enhanced view of the area where the operation is taking place. Some of the benefits include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Surgery performed while the surgeon sits at a console and uses controls to guide high-tech surgical tools.</li>



<li>Allows surgeons to work in small spaces with three-dimensional visualization, and with more precision, flexibility and control than with conventional techniques.</li>



<li>Minimally invasive, fewer complications, quicker recovery, fewer urological complications and may reduce nerve dysfunction.</li>
</ul>



<p>"We're using laparoscopic and robotic platforms to really offer patients surgery that is most up to date in terms of minimally invasive techniques, the least amount of trauma to the patient, but yet achieving the goals of surgery to remove the cancer," he says.</p>



<p>If colon cancer is caught early, surgery may be the only treatment that is necessary, but Dr. Dozois says, "Even in some of the earlier stages, a more aggressive approach that combines chemotherapy, radiation and surgery is necessary to keep it not only from coming back locally, but from spreading to other parts of the body."</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Related content:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/innovative-treatments-for-rectal-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Innovative treatments for rectal cancer</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/early-mayo-clinic-research-finds-hope-in-stem-cell-therapy-for-perianal-fistulas-in-patients-with-crohns-disease/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Early Mayo Clinic research finds hope in stem cell therapy for perianal fistulas in patients with Crohn’s disease</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-millennials-should-know-colon-cancer-symptoms/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Why millennials should know colon cancer symptoms</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-whats-the-right-colorectal-cancer-screening-option-for-you/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: What’s the right colorectal cancer screening option for you?</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-are-colon-and-rectal-cancers-treated-differently/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Are colon and rectal cancers treated differently?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/Colon-Rectal-Colorectal-Cancer-Surgery-1x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/Colon-Rectal-Colorectal-Cancer-Surgery-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Colon Cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[colorectal cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[colrectal cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[rectal cancer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Surgery]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tomorrow’s Cure: Leveraging AI in the early detection of pancreatic cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-leveraging-ai-in-the-early-detection-of-pancreatic-cancer/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Joel Streed]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 11:04:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Ajit Goenka]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Suresh Chari]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Tomorrow's Cure]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=400482</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Early detection is critical for improving cancer survival rates, yet pancreatic cancer remains challenging to detect. Exciting new research offers hope as artificial intelligence (AI) models demonstrate the potential to detect pancreatic cancer earlier and with remarkable accuracy. Explore these groundbreaking advancements in a new episode of Tomorrow's Cure. The latest episode features insights from&nbsp;Dr. […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-leveraging-ai-in-the-early-detection-of-pancreatic-cancer/">Tomorrow’s Cure: Leveraging AI in the early detection of pancreatic cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/03/MCP-17536_TC_S02E07_AIPC_YT-Thumbnail__1280x720_-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-400485" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/03/MCP-17536_TC_S02E07_AIPC_YT-Thumbnail__1280x720_-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/03/MCP-17536_TC_S02E07_AIPC_YT-Thumbnail__1280x720_-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/03/MCP-17536_TC_S02E07_AIPC_YT-Thumbnail__1280x720_-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/03/MCP-17536_TC_S02E07_AIPC_YT-Thumbnail__1280x720_.jpg 1280w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>Early detection is critical for improving cancer survival rates, yet pancreatic cancer remains challenging to detect. Exciting new research offers hope as artificial intelligence (AI) models demonstrate the potential to detect pancreatic cancer earlier and with remarkable accuracy. Explore these groundbreaking advancements in a new episode of <a href="https://careinfo.mayoclinic.org/tomorrows-cure-podcast?mc_id=global&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=tcseasontwoepisodeseven&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=global&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=190206">Tomorrow's Cure</a>.</p>



<p>The latest episode features insights from&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/goenka-ajit-h-m-d/bio-20152402?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Ajit Goenka</a>,&nbsp;radiologist and professor of radiology at Mayo Clinic's Comprehensive Cancer Center, and <a href="https://faculty.mdanderson.org/profiles/suresh_chari.html">Dr. Suresh&nbsp;Chari</a>, professor, Department of Gastroenterology, Hepatology, and Nutrition in the Division of Internal Medicine at MD Anderson Cancer Center.</p>



<p>"These small cancers are very difficult to detect on imaging," says Dr. Goenka. "So the challenge with these small cancers is that they look exactly similar to what the rest of the pancreas would look like, and unless you are deeply suspicious and you're looking very carefully, you are likely to overlook that."</p>



<p>Recognizing that early detection is the best hope for improving survival rates, researchers have developed AI models capable of identifying cancers. These models have shown immense promise, identifying pancreatic cancer on CT scans at stages where surgical intervention can still promise a cure.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubePFJ52zTH5uo" title="Leveraging AI in the Early Detection of Pancreatic Cancer | Tomorrow's Cure Season 2 Episode 7" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PFJ52zTH5uo?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>"Early detection is really our best hope, but also our biggest challenge when it comes to pancreas cancer," states Dr. Goenka.</p>



<p>Dr. Chari further elaborates on the urgency of improving detection timelines. "We are trying to diagnose pancreatic cancer earlier. The challenge we have been facing is that half of patients have stage 4 at the time of diagnosis," he explains. "We want to reduce the number of stage 4 patients. Our early detection strategy would automatically shift everybody to an earlier stage. Right now, only 7% of pancreatic cancers are confined to the pancreas at the time of diagnosis. We want to triple that number, so we came up with a number of four months. If you diagnose all pancreatic cancers four months before they were clinically diagnosed, we would significantly shift the stage to an earlier stage." These advancements mark an exciting step forward in the fight against pancreatic cancer. Discover more about this cutting-edge technology and its lifesaving potential in the latest episode of <a href="https://careinfo.mayoclinic.org/tomorrows-cure-podcast?mc_id=global&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=tcseasontwoepisodeseven&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=global&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=190206">Tomorrow's Cure</a>. For a complete list of episodes and featured experts, visit <a href="https://careinfo.mayoclinic.org/tomorrows-cure-podcast?mc_id=global&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=tcseasontwoepisodeseven&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=global&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=190206">tomorrowscure.com</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Related Articles:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-innovation-inspires-hope-in-early-detection-of-pancreatic-cancer/">Mayo Clinic's AI innovation inspires hope in early detection of pancreatic cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-leveraging-ai-in-the-early-detection-of-pancreatic-cancer/">Tomorrow’s Cure: Leveraging AI in the early detection of pancreatic cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/03/MCP-17536_TC_S02E07_AIPC_NewsNetwork_1080x1080.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/03/MCP-17536_TC_S02E07_AIPC_YT-Thumbnail__1280x720_.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Ajit Goenka]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Suresh Chari]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Tomorrow's Cure]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>VIDEO: Making surgery for meningiomas safer with advanced technology</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-making-surgery-for-meningiomas-safer-with-advanced-technology/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Deb Balzer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 16:17:02 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Neurosciences]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Video]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[diverse representation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Victoria Clark]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=399858</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Treatment for meningiomas, the most common type of brain tumor, is now safer thanks to technological advancements. At Mayo Clinic, navigation tools and precision imaging help surgeons operate with greater accuracy, improving patient outcomes. Dr. Victoria Clark, a Mayo Clinic neurosurgeon and researcher, focuses on finding better treatments for patients with meningiomas, now and in […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-making-surgery-for-meningiomas-safer-with-advanced-technology/">VIDEO: Making surgery for meningiomas safer with advanced technology</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<p-->Treatment for <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-types-of-brain-tumors-and-treatments/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">meningiomas</a>, the most common type of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/brain-tumor/symptoms-causes/syc-20350084" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">brain tumor</a>, is now safer thanks to technological advancements. At Mayo Clinic, navigation tools and precision imaging help surgeons operate with greater accuracy, improving patient outcomes.<p></p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/clark-victoria-e-m-d-ph-d/bio-20571739" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Victoria Clark</a>, a Mayo Clinic neurosurgeon and researcher, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/neurology-neurosurgery/news/probing-the-molecular-drivers-of-meningioma/mac-20576093" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">focuses</a> on finding better treatments for patients with meningiomas, now and in the future.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/Lt47-YK7Stg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeLt47YK7Stg" title="Making brain surgery safer with advanced technology" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Lt47-YK7Stg?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:25) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/SCRIPT-VIDEO-pkg-Making-brain-surgery-safer-with-advanced-technology.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Meningiomas are usually noncancerous <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/meningioma-specialty-group/overview/ovc-20440783">tumors</a> that form in the membranes surrounding the brain. It may sound strange, but some of these tumors may not need treatment.<br><br>"But for the ones that grow or for the ones that cause symptoms, they do require treatment, which is either surgery and/or radiation," says Dr. Clark.</p>



<p>The goal of the surgery is to take out as much of the tumor as possible.</p>



<p>"Meningiomas have this tendency to enwrap very critical structures, like the types of nerves that control sight or control hearing, facial expression, and also encircle around critical blood vessels," she says.</p>



<p>Better tools allow for better outcomes.</p>



<p>"We have what's called navigation. So that allows us to use a pre-op MRI, sort of a GPS for the brain, to know exactly where the tumor is in relationship to the structures that we're trying to preserve and avoid," says Dr. Clark.</p>



<p>Advanced imaging tools used in the operating room help ensure surgeons remove all the tumor.</p>



<p>"Brain surgery is much safer with all of these wonderful new technologies," she says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Research</h2>



<p>While these advancements help patients now, Dr. Clark is looking to the future.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Dr.-Clark-Microscope-2-1024x576.jpg" alt="Dr. Victoria Clark, neurosurgeon, in her research lab, looking through a microscope" class="wp-image-400246" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Dr.-Clark-Microscope-2-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Dr.-Clark-Microscope-2-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Dr.-Clark-Microscope-2-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Dr.-Clark-Microscope-2-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Dr.-Clark-Microscope-2.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Victoria Clark in her research lab</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"My hope is that the research that we will do will create new medical treatments that can be used in combination with the surgeries and radiation that are currently available in order to improve the treatment for patients with meningiomas," says Dr. Clark.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-making-surgery-for-meningiomas-safer-with-advanced-technology/">VIDEO: Making surgery for meningiomas safer with advanced technology</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Brain-surgery-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Brain-surgery-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[diverse representation]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Victoria Clark]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A:&nbsp; Understanding colorectal cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-understanding-colorectal-cancer/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Abby Smith]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 14:16:56 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[diverse representation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Derek Ebner]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=396865</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;I recently read that more and more young people are getting diagnosed with colorectal cancer. I'm in my 30s, am I at risk? What does colorectal mean? ANSWER:&nbsp;The term colorectal cancer combines&nbsp;colon&nbsp;and&nbsp;rectal cancer, two parts of the intestine. The first part of the large intestine is called the&nbsp;colon, and the last part refers […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-understanding-colorectal-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Q and A:&nbsp; Understanding colorectal cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="5260" height="2959" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/08/shutterstock_309670805_Fotor-16x9.jpg" alt="a diverse group of young people, students, artists, laughing and smiling as they work on laptops and computers" class="wp-image-245650" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/08/shutterstock_309670805_Fotor-16x9.jpg 5260w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/08/shutterstock_309670805_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/08/shutterstock_309670805_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/08/shutterstock_309670805_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 5260px) 100vw, 5260px">



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong>&nbsp;I recently read that more and more young people are getting diagnosed with <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-millennials-should-know-colon-cancer-symptoms/">colorectal cancer</a>. I'm in my 30s, am I at risk? What does colorectal mean?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong>&nbsp;The term colorectal cancer combines&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353669">colon</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/rectal-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352884">rectal cancer</a>, two parts of the intestine. The first part of the large intestine is called the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/colon-and-rectum/img-20007597">colon</a>, and the last part refers to the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/colon-and-rectum/img-20007597">rectum</a>.&nbsp;These two divisions of colorectal cancer are important because they're often treated differently. Cancers of the colon, for example, may initially be treated through surgery. With cancers of the rectum, we may do treatment long before someone goes to surgery.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Symptoms of both cancers are similar and can include&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/symptoms/unexplained-weight-loss/basics/definition/sym-20050700">unintentional weight loss</a>, overall changes in bowel characteristics such as more frequent&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/diarrhea/symptoms-causes/syc-20352241">diarrhea</a>, blood from the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/symptoms/rectal-bleeding/basics/definition/sym-20050740">rectum</a>&nbsp;or in the stool and ongoing&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/symptoms/abdominal-pain/basics/definition/sym-20050728">abdominal pain</a>, cramps or&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/gas-and-gas-pains/symptoms-causes/syc-20372709">gas</a>.&nbsp;These symptoms&nbsp;can be embarrassing for some people to talk about, and that is normal. However, it is extremely important if you have any of those symptoms to share it with your healthcare team. Early diagnosis of colorectal cancer increases your chance of survival.</p>



<p>People of all ages are at risk for colorectal cancer. It is true that there have been increased rates of colon and rectal cancer in younger patients, which has led to a shift in screening recommendations. We used to start screening average-risk individuals at age 50, but because of this new trend, we're now encouraging average-risk individuals to start screening at age 45. Through screening, we can prevent the development of cancer and capture&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-polyps/symptoms-causes/syc-20352875">polyps</a>&nbsp;(precancerous growths) even before symptoms start.</p>



<p>It is unknown what has caused this increase among young people. Findings show that it may be an environmental factor. Over the last 50 years, we've seen major changes in diet.&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-are-ultraprocessed-foods-2/">Ultraprocessed foods</a>&nbsp;and higher quantities of red meats have potentially led to some negative changes to the bacteria that are normally in our gut, making it not as protective as it once was. A decrease in exercise and an increase in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/obesity/symptoms-causes/syc-20375742">obesity</a>&nbsp;also could be contributing factors. Living a healthylifestyle is critical —&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/fitness/expert-answers/exercise/faq-20057916">exercise</a>&nbsp;and a well-rounded&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/basics/healthy-diets/hlv-20049477#:~:text=Includes%20a%20variety%20of%20foods,and%20seeds%3B%20and%20healthy%20fats.">diet</a>&nbsp;can help protect you.</p>



<p>We typically divide people into two groups — those who are at average risk and those who are at high risk for colorectal cancer. Average-risk individuals are people who don't have any associated symptoms that would be linked to colorectal cancer or have any of the factors that would place them at high risk.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For those who are at high risk, there tends to be at least one of three variables:</p>



<ol class="wp-block-list">
<li>A medical condition that places them at higher risk.</li>



<li>A genetic condition that increases their risk.&nbsp;</li>



<li>A family history that places them at higher risk. For example, a first-degree family member such as parents or siblings who have a diagnosis of colorectal cancer or advanced polyps.</li>
</ol>



<p>Any of those three components would place you at higher risk, and therefore, you should start screening sooner and possibly more often than average-risk individuals.</p>



<p>When it comes to cancer care, we try to make our efforts personalized, particularly with rectal cancer. The treatment team consists of a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/gastroenterology-hepatology-digestive-care/home/orc-20348202">gastroenterologist</a>, an&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/oncology/home/orc-20198222">oncologist</a>, a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/colon-rectal-surgery/home/orc-20312712">surgeon</a>&nbsp;and a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/radiation-oncology/home/orc-20188588">radiation oncologist</a>&nbsp;who help direct what the next best step would be for you, whether that's&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/chemotherapy/about/pac-20385033">chemotherapy</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/discovery-translation-labs/cancer-research/cancer-immunotherapy">immunotherapies</a>, surgery or&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/radiation-therapy/about/pac-20385162">radiation</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Any delay in sharing information translates to a delay in diagnosis, which can lead to later-stage cancer. It is the later-stage cancers that can be a bit more challenging to treat. Don't delay in making an appointment.&nbsp;<em>—&nbsp;<strong>Derek Ebner, M.D.,&nbsp;</strong></em><strong><em>Gastroenterology, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota</em></strong><em></em></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-understanding-colorectal-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Q and A:&nbsp; Understanding colorectal cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/Colon-Rectal-Colorectal-Cancer-Surgery-1x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/Colon-Rectal-Colorectal-Cancer-Surgery-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[diverse representation]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Derek Ebner]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</atom:link></channel>
</rss> 