<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 12:21:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.5</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic marks medical milestone with world&#8217;s first known successful total larynx transplant performed in a patient with an active cancer as part of a clinical trial </title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-marks-medical-milestone-with-worlds-first-known-successful-total-larynx-transplant-performed-in-a-patient-with-an-active-cancer-as-part-of-a-clinical-trial/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 11:34:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. David Lott]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Girish Mour]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[larynx transplant]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=390282</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>PHOENIX — Mayo Clinic announces a groundbreaking achievement in organ transplantation, offering hope to thousands who have lost their ability to speak, swallow and breathe on their own due to diminished function or loss of their larynx. A multidisciplinary team of doctors in Arizona performed the third known total larynx transplant in the U.S. The [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-marks-medical-milestone-with-worlds-first-known-successful-total-larynx-transplant-performed-in-a-patient-with-an-active-cancer-as-part-of-a-clinical-trial/">Mayo Clinic marks medical milestone with world&#8217;s first known successful total larynx transplant performed in a patient with an active cancer as part of a clinical trial </a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3_16x9-1024x577.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390222" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3_16x9-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3_16x9-1536x865.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3_16x9-2048x1153.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>PHOENIX — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> announces a groundbreaking achievement in organ transplantation, offering hope to thousands who have lost their ability to speak, swallow and breathe on their own due to diminished function or loss of their larynx. A multidisciplinary team of doctors in Arizona performed the third known total larynx transplant in the U.S. The case also marks a medical milestone as the first known total larynx transplant performed as part of a clinical trial and the first on a patient with active cancer in the U.S.</p>



<p>"The surgery and patient's progress have exceeded our expectations," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/lott-david-g-m-d/bio-20055443" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">David Lott, M.D.</a>, chair of the Department of Otolaryngology (ENT) - <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/head-and-neck-cancer-center/sections/overview/ovc-20457072" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Head and Neck Surgery</a>/Audiology at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/arizona" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Arizona</a>. "This is a tremendous accomplishment in launching what we believe is the future for laryngeal transplantation."</p>



<p>A paper by Dr. Lott on the case was published July 9 in the peer-reviewed medical journal <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/pb/assets/raw/Health%20Advance/journals/jmcp/Lott-1720450777830.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a>. The larynx, located in the throat, is commonly known as the voice box. Larynx transplantation is a rare and complex procedure, performed only a handful of times in the world. Even more notably, Mayo Clinic's surgical team successfully performed the larynx transplant on a patient with an active cancer, making it one of the first cases of its kind globally.</p>



<p>Six surgeons at Mayo Clinic conducted the 21-hour transplant, which included the larynx, pharynx, upper trachea, upper esophagus, thyroid and parathyroid glands, blood vessels, and nerves.</p>



<p>The <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/home/orc-20203891" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">transplant</a> was performed on a Massachusetts man, Marty Kedian, who was diagnosed with a rare form of laryngeal cancer called <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/chondrosarcoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20354196" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chondrosarcoma</a>. For 10 years, Kedian underwent dozens of surgeries, which eventually robbed him of his voice and his ability to swallow and breathe normally. Several years ago, Kedian had to undergo a tracheostomy that allowed him to breathe through a hole in his neck. He says the tracheostomy, combined with the loss of his voice, significantly diminished his quality of life. "I was alive, but I wasn't living," says Kedian. "I love to talk to people everywhere I go, and I just couldn't. I felt strange, and I wouldn't go out anywhere."</p>



<p>After years of surgeries, doctors told Kedian his only remaining option was to get a laryngectomy and have his larynx completely removed. He declined. "I didn't want a laryngectomy. I wanted to find a way to get my quality of life back," he says.</p>



<p>Kedian found what he was looking for at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/larynx-trachea-transplant/overview/ovc-20508897" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic's Larynx and Trachea Transplant Program</a>, where Dr. Lott was leading the first known clinical trial on laryngeal transplantation in the U.S. After being accepted as a patient for the clinical trial, Kedian and his wife, Gina, moved to a temporary home in Phoenix. On Feb. 29, Kedian became Mayo Clinic's first patient to undergo a total larynx transplant. "I wanted this so I could talk and breathe normally with my new granddaughter. I want to read her bedtime stories with my own voice," says Kedian.</p>



<p>Because it was conducted as part of a clinical trial, Mayo's case is considered a significant pivotal step in making the rare procedure available to a wider population. "Until now, laryngeal transplants have been done as one-offs," says Dr. Lott. "This clinical trial allows us to conduct a true scientific investigation aimed at thoroughly researching the safety and efficacy of laryngeal transplantation as a trusted option for patients." The program is approved to perform additional larynx transplants in the coming years.</p>



<p>The <a href="https://www.cancer.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Cancer Society</a> estimates there will be 12,650 new cases of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/throat-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20366462" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">laryngeal cancer</a> in the U.S. this year. Until now, many of these patients had little hope of laryngeal transplantation as a possible option in the future due to the risk associated with the use of immunosuppressive therapy. Transplant patients are given immunosuppressive therapy to lower the body's immune response, which reduces the risk of organ rejection. However, immunosuppressive drugs also increase the risk of the cancer spreading.</p>



<p>Kedian's case was unique. He was already on immunosuppressive therapy from a previous kidney transplant. "Having a patient with an active cancer who already had his own immune suppression allowed us to do the transplant safely without introducing additional risk in a way that has rarely, if ever, been done before," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mour-girish-k-m-b-b-s/bio-20392405" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Girish Mour,</a> <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mour-girish-k-m-b-b-s/bio-20392405" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">M.B.B.S.</a>, medical director of the program. Dr. Lott adds, "Being able to perform this transplant in the setting of active cancer in a patient already on immunosuppressive therapy, under the rigor and oversight of a clinical trial, enabled us to take that vital step toward better understanding the safety for cancer patients and potentially making larynx transplant a standard option."</p>



<p>Removing the cancer was the surgical team's main priority. "First, we removed Mr. Kedian's cancerous larynx," explains Dr. Lott. "Then, with the confidence of our team that the cancer was gone, we focused on the transplant."</p>



<p>Four months after surgery, Kedian can speak with his new voice, swallow and breathe on his own, which Dr. Lott calls remarkable. "Mr. Kedian has already regained about 60% of his voice, which I wouldn't have thought would happen for at least a year. He still speaks with the same voice and Boston accent he had prior to the cancer," says Dr. Lott. "He can also eat hamburgers, macaroni and cheese, almost anything, and swallow with no problem. His breathing also continues to steadily improve." Doctors plan to remove the tracheostomy tube when Kedian regains full ability to breathe on his own.</p>



<p>"The team at Mayo has given me my life back," says Kedian. "I'm so grateful. I have the deepest gratitude for Dr. Lott's team and especially the generosity of my organ donor and donor family. I hope one day I get the chance to tell them, 'Thank you.'"</p>



<p>"This case signifies a monumental breakthrough. It represents the future of laryngeal transplantation, where every patient needing a total laryngectomy will have the option of a reconstruction that allows them to maintain their quality of life," says Marshall Strome, M.D., who made medical history by performing the world's first total laryngeal transplant in 1998. "With the clinical trial underway, Dr. Lott and his team are positioned to advance the field in ways no other program can currently achieve. The Mayo team has discovered the holy grail for managing laryngeal cancer, which I believe will come to fruition by the end of this decade."</p>



<p>Dr. Lott calls Kedian's case the capstone of his two decades of research. In addition to the clinical trial, Dr. Lott's research team is investigating ways to restore laryngeal function through improving transplantation techniques and pioneering <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/head-and-neck-regenerative-medicine/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">regenerative medicine technologies</a>. "I set my path on becoming a laryngeal surgeon and researcher to build a program that is pushing the boundaries of science forward," says Dr. Lott. "Our dedication is to the thousands of individuals who suffer from laryngeal dysfunction and to find trusted options that preserve their health and their quality of life. That's what this clinical trial is all about."</p>



<p>Kedian returns to Massachusetts next week. He is excited to be back with family and friends and to read bedtime stories to his granddaughter. Kedian also plans to use his own story to inspire others and be a voice for hope. "Mayo and Dr. Lott have helped me regain my quality of life," says Kedian. "My job now is to get better. My next job will be to show others they can do it too."</p>



<p><strong>Press kit, including b-roll, photos, interviews and animation available <a href="https://mcmedia.mayo.edu/Share/572tpcrrx3y37qsi2344acweijy7h7d3" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here.</a></strong></p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Marty Hames, Mayo Clinic Communications, 507-284-5005, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-marks-medical-milestone-with-worlds-first-known-successful-total-larynx-transplant-performed-in-a-patient-with-an-active-cancer-as-part-of-a-clinical-trial/">Mayo Clinic marks medical milestone with world&#8217;s first known successful total larynx transplant performed in a patient with an active cancer as part of a clinical trial </a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. David Lott]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Girish Mour]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[larynx transplant]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Breaking the silence: First known total larynx transplant on a patient with active cancer as part of landmark clinical trial</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-the-silence-first-known-total-larynx-transplant-on-a-patient-with-active-cancer-as-part-of-landmark-clinical-trial/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. David Lott]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marty Kedian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=390113</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>On Feb. 29, Marty Kedian made history by successfully undergoing a groundbreaking surgery at Mayo Clinic that is providing hope to thousands who have lost their voice and ability to swallow and breathe on their own due to diminished laryngeal function or total loss of their larynx. This is the third known larynx transplant in [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-the-silence-first-known-total-larynx-transplant-on-a-patient-with-active-cancer-as-part-of-landmark-clinical-trial/">Breaking the silence: First known total larynx transplant on a patient with active cancer as part of landmark clinical trial</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-Gina-3-20-25_16x9-1024x577.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390220" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-Gina-3-20-25_16x9-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-Gina-3-20-25_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-Gina-3-20-25_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-Gina-3-20-25_16x9-1536x865.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-Gina-3-20-25_16x9-2048x1153.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Gina and Marty Kedian</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>On Feb. 29, Marty Kedian made history by successfully undergoing a groundbreaking surgery at Mayo Clinic that is providing hope to thousands who have lost their voice and ability to swallow and breathe on their own due to diminished laryngeal function or total loss of their larynx.</p>



<p>This is the third known larynx transplant in the U.S. and the first known case performed on a patient with an active cancer as part of a clinical trial. It is also Mayo Clinic's first total larynx transplant. The multidisciplinary team, including six surgeons, was led by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/lott-david-g-m-d/bio-20055443" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. David Lott</a>, chair of the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/ent-head-neck-surgery/sections/overview/ovc-20424084" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Otolaryngology (ENT) - Head and Neck Surgery/Audiology at Mayo Clinic in Arizona</a>. Dr. Lott also leads <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/larynx-trachea-transplant/overview/ovc-20508897" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic's Larynx and Trachea Transplant Program</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/larynx-trachea-transplant/overview/ovc-20508897">.</a></p>



<p>Experts say the larynx transplant at Mayo is a pivotal milestone in making the rare procedure available as a scientifically proven, safe and effective procedure for a wider population.</p>



<p>For Marty, it marks the beginning of his quest to break the silence on laryngeal transplantation.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="795" height="1006" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Thumbs-up-March-6-2024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390154" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Thumbs-up-March-6-2024.jpg 795w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Thumbs-up-March-6-2024-237x300.jpg 237w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Thumbs-up-March-6-2024-768x972.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 795px) 100vw, 795px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Less than a week after surgery, Marty Kedian and his team give the thumbs up</strong>  Photo courtesy: Kedian Family</figcaption></figure>



<p>A multidisciplinary team, including six surgeons, conducted the 21-hour transplant. Four months after surgery, Marty has regained use of his voice and his ability to swallow and breathe on his own, exceeding the transplant team's expectations.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H9fOyKUrDmQ" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Watch: Breaking the silence: Man achieves dream of getting his voice back in world's first known total larynx transplant on a patient with an active cancer as part of a landmark clinical trial</strong></a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeH9fOyKUrDmQ"  title="Breaking the silence: Total larynx transplant on a patient with active cancer" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/H9fOyKUrDmQ?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (5:15) in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-patient-story-video-script.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script.</a></strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Silenced by cancer</strong></h2>



<p>"I love to talk to people everywhere I go," says Marty. "I'm that guy at the baseball game who doesn't know anyone sitting around them. And by the end of the game, I'm friends with everyone in my section."</p>



<p>Marty's world changed in 2013 when he went to the doctor after noticing he was having trouble swallowing his food. "Food was getting caught in my throat. I thought I had allergies. I didn't really think anything of it," recalls Marty.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="909" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-gina-in-their-apt-1024x909.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390166" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-gina-in-their-apt-1024x909.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-gina-in-their-apt-300x266.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-gina-in-their-apt-768x682.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-gina-in-their-apt-1536x1364.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-gina-in-their-apt-2048x1818.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Marty and Gina Kedian</strong> <strong>and their dog Baxter</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>A series of tests revealed Marty had a rare form of laryngeal cancer called <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/chondrosarcoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20354196" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chondrosarcoma</a>. Doctors told Marty he needed surgery. "It was a shock," recalls Marty. "It was devastating. I wasn't going to die, but I had a job that required me to talk to people all day long." For 35 years, Marty worked at a local print shop speaking with customers in Haverhill, Massachusetts, where he lives with his wife, Gina, and their family.</p>



<p>Marty underwent his first surgery in 2014. Over the next 10 years, dozens more followed, reducing Marty's voice to a raspy whisper. No longer able to breathe on his own, Marty underwent surgery to have a tracheostomy tube inserted so he could breathe through a hole in the front of his neck.</p>



<p>"Everywhere I went, the first thing people would ask me is, 'How many cigarettes did you smoke a day?' I never smoked a cigarette in my life," says Marty. "People would immediately shut down and back away from me. After a while, I just didn't want to go out anywhere. I was alive, but I wasn't living." Marty was eventually told his last option was a total laryngectomy, or removal of his voice box. He declined. "I didn't want a laryngectomy. I wanted to find a way to get my quality of life back," says Marty.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-feeding-baby-Charlotte-768x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390142" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-feeding-baby-Charlotte-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-feeding-baby-Charlotte-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-feeding-baby-Charlotte-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-feeding-baby-Charlotte.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Marty with his granddaughter, Charlotte   Photo courtesy: Kedian Family</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>"I just had my first grandchild. I wanted to be able to talk to her with my own voice, play with her in the yard and take her to baseball games and breathe normally. Gina knew I was already depressed and out of my mind. She kept saying there had to be another way. She went online, and that's when she found Dr. Lott."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Finding hope at Mayo Clinic</h2>



<p>Thousands of miles from Marty's home, at Mayo Clinic in Phoenix, Dr. Lott was leading a team of scientists researching laryngeal restoration and transplantation. Dr. Lott is an ear, nose and throat surgeon who specializes in laryngeal surgery. For the past two decades, Dr. Lott and his team have been <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/head-and-neck-regenerative-medicine/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">investigating ways to restore and save a person's voice and laryngeal function.</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="698" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_0116-698x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390168" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_0116-698x1024.jpg 698w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_0116-204x300.jpg 204w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_0116-768x1127.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_0116-1047x1536.jpg 1047w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_0116.jpg 1284w" sizes="(max-width: 698px) 100vw, 698px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Dr. David Lott discusses laryngeal transplantation with Kedian at Mayo Clinic in Phoenix, Arizona</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>"I set my path on becoming a laryngeal surgeon and researcher to build a program that is pushing the boundaries of science forward," explains Dr. Lott.</p>



<p>"Nobody really thinks of their larynx until it's gone," says Dr. Lott. "Then your ability to speak, breathe and swallow is gone, and you are left breathing through a hole in your neck. It is very isolating, and many become a shell of who they used to be. I wanted to find a way to help restore a person's quality of life."</p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/preparing-for-mayos-first-larynx-transplant/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">In 2016, Dr. Lott's program was granted approval to conduct the first clinical trial in the U.S. on laryngeal transplantation</a>. "Until now, laryngeal transplants have been done as on-offs," says Dr. Lott. "This clinical trial allows us to conduct a true scientific investigation aimed at thoroughly researching the safety and efficacy of laryngeal transplantation as a trusted option for patients."</p>



<p>One of the biggest challenges to advancing laryngeal transplantation as an option for cancer patients like Marty has been the risk associated with the use of immunosuppressive therapy. <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/11-16-four-ways-organ-transplants-are-being-transformed-to-save-more-lives/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Transplant</a> patients are given immunosuppressive drugs to lower the body's immune response, which reduces the risk of organ rejection. However, immunosuppression also increases the risk of the cancer spreading. Marty was already on immunosuppressives due to a <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-surgeons-perform-first-robotic-assisted-kidney-transplant-in-minnesota/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">kidney transplant</a> years ago.</p>



<p>"Having a patient with an active cancer who already has his own immune suppression allowed us to do the transplant safely without introducing additional risk in a way that has rarely, if ever, been done before," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mour-girish-k-m-b-b-s/bio-20392405" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Girish Mour, M.B.B.S.,</a> medical director of the program.</p>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Inside the operating room</strong></h1>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390126" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>The 21-hour landmark transplant was performed by a multidisciplinary team of doctors that included six surgeons</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>Removing the cancer was the surgical team's main priority. "First, we removed Mr. Kedian's cancerous larynx," explains Dr. Lott. "Then, with the confidence of our team that the cancer was gone, we focused on the transplant. The entire procedure went better than we expected."</p>



<p>In addition to the larynx, surgeons transplanted the pharynx, upper trachea, upper esophagus, thyroid and parathyroid glands, blood vessels, and nerves.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="753" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-figure-1024x753.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390174" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-figure-1024x753.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-figure-300x220.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-figure-768x564.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-figure-1536x1129.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-figure-2048x1505.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Marty's road to recovery</strong></h1>



<p>Four months after his transplant, Marty regained 60% of his voice. Doctors say it will continue to improve as he heals over the next year. He has also regained the ability to swallow and breathe on his own. "It is truly amazing," says Marty. "Dr. Lott and the team at Mayo have not only given me my voice back, they've also given me my life back."</p>



<p>Speech and swallow therapy at Mayo has been a significant part of Marty's recovery.</p>



<p>"Marty's progress is remarkable," describes Dr. Lott. "He is eating hamburgers, macaroni and cheese, almost anything with no problem. His breathing also continues to steadily improve." Doctors plan to remove the tracheostomy tube when Marty regains full function of his ability to breathe on his own.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/pb/assets/raw/Health%20Advance/journals/jmcp/Lott-1720450777830.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">A paper by Dr. Lott on the case was published July 9 in the peer-reviewed medical journal Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Girish-Mour-Marty-Kedian-and-Dr.-David-Lott-post-op-in-hospital-room-1-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390141" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Girish-Mour-Marty-Kedian-and-Dr.-David-Lott-post-op-in-hospital-room-1-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Girish-Mour-Marty-Kedian-and-Dr.-David-Lott-post-op-in-hospital-room-1-300x225.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Girish-Mour-Marty-Kedian-and-Dr.-David-Lott-post-op-in-hospital-room-1-768x576.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Girish-Mour-Marty-Kedian-and-Dr.-David-Lott-post-op-in-hospital-room-1-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Girish-Mour-Marty-Kedian-and-Dr.-David-Lott-post-op-in-hospital-room-1-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Dr. Girish Mour (L), Marty and Dr. Lott one week after the transplant</strong></figcaption></figure>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>"The holy grail for managing laryngeal cancer"</strong></h1>



<p>"The case signifies a monumental breakthrough," says Dr. Marshall Strome, who performed the world's first successful larynx transplant in 1998. "It represents the future of laryngeal transplantation where every patient needing a total laryngectomy will have the option of a reconstruction that allows them to maintain their quality of life."</p>



<p>Dr. Lott did some of his early training under Dr. Strome. Since then, Dr. Strome has remained a trusted mentor to Dr. Lott. In a full circle moment, Dr. Strome was present when Dr. Lott performed the transplant at Mayo in February.</p>



<p>"With the clinical trial underway, Dr. Lott and his team are positioned to advance the field in ways no other program can currently achieve. The Mayo team has discovered the holy grail for managing laryngeal cancer, which I believe will come to fruition by the end of this decade," says Dr. Strome.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Strome-and-Dr.-Lott-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390123" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Strome-and-Dr.-Lott-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Strome-and-Dr.-Lott-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Strome-and-Dr.-Lott-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Strome-and-Dr.-Lott-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Strome-and-Dr.-Lott-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>A full circle moment for Dr. Marshall Strome and Dr. Lott following Mayo's groundbreaking transplant</strong></figcaption></figure>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Breaking the silence on laryngeal transplantation</strong></h1>



<p>Less than five months after surgery, Marty and Gina are excited to return home to Massachusetts. "We couldn't have done this without everyone's love and support," says Gina.</p>



<p>"I will always be grateful to the team at Mayo and especially for the generosity of my organ donor and the donor family," says Marty.</p>



<p>Dr. Lott's clinical trial is approved to perform additional larynx transplants in the coming years.</p>



<p>Marty is looking forward to doing what he loves most — talking to family, friends and everyone else he meets. He is especially looking forward to talking with his granddaughter, Charlotte.</p>



<p>"I will be reading her lots of bedtime stories," says Marty. Meanwhile, Marty also is planning to share his own story to inspire others.</p>



<p>"My first job is to get better," says Marty. "My next job will be to tell everyone they can do it too."</p>



<p>Additional resources:</p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-marks-medical-milestone-with-worlds-first-known-successful-total-larynx-transplant-performed-in-a-patient-with-an-active-cancer-as-part-of-a-clinical-trial/">Mayo Clinic marks medical milestone with world’s first known successful total larynx transplant performed in a patient with an active cancer as part of a clinical trial&nbsp;</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/preparing-for-mayos-first-larynx-transplant/">Research prepares for Mayo's first larynx transplant</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-the-silence-first-known-total-larynx-transplant-on-a-patient-with-active-cancer-as-part-of-landmark-clinical-trial/">Breaking the silence: First known total larynx transplant on a patient with active cancer as part of landmark clinical trial</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-Gina-3-20-25_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-Gina-3-20-25_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. David Lott]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Marty Kedian]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>How a different mammogram experience led to lifesaving cancer diagnosis</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-a-different-mammogram-experience-led-to-lifesaving-cancer-diagnosis/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Mina Hanna]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jessica Johnson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Melissa Neuman]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=389989</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Melissa Neuman dreaded getting mammograms. Her small, dense breasts made the screening exceptionally uncomfortable and painful. So Melissa put off getting an&#160;annual mammogram&#160;until she felt she couldn't delay any longer. For about five years, Melissa had been plagued with a nagging pain just under her left breast. In February 2023, a recommendation from a friend [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-a-different-mammogram-experience-led-to-lifesaving-cancer-diagnosis/">How a different mammogram experience led to lifesaving cancer diagnosis</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/melissa-neuman-and-family16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-389994" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/melissa-neuman-and-family16x9.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/melissa-neuman-and-family16x9-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></figure>



<p>Melissa Neuman dreaded getting mammograms. Her small, dense breasts made the screening exceptionally uncomfortable and painful. So Melissa put off getting an&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/mammography" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">annual mammogram</a>&nbsp;until she felt she couldn't delay any longer.</p>



<p>For about five years, Melissa had been plagued with a nagging pain just under her left breast. In February 2023, a recommendation from a friend led her to seek care from&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/jessica-johnson-np" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jessica Johnson</a>, an&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/obstetrics-and-gynecology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">OB-GYN</a>&nbsp;nurse practitioner with&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/owatonna" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System in Owatonna</a>, Minnesota.</p>



<p>"She took me seriously, was curious and determined to find out what was causing the pain," says Melissa, who lives in Owatonna and works as an activities assistant at a local assisted living and memory care facility.</p>



<p>During their appointment, Johnson noticed that Melissa hadn't had a mammogram for several years. When Melissa explained why she was reluctant to be screened, Johnson suggested she have a breast MRI.</p>



<p>"I'd still be getting screened, but with less pain," says Melissa. "So I said, 'Let's do it.'"</p>



<p>The MRI revealed an area of concern. Johnson recommended that Melissa have a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/preparing-for-your-breast-biopsy" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">biopsy</a>, but it would require a mammogram first. That's when Melissa met Amanda Steinberg, a radiology technologist in Owatonna. She was just the person Melissa needed.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Overcoming mammogram fears, pain</h2>



<p>"Mammograms aren't a favorite activity for women," says Steinberg. "While it's a preventive screening, we have mammograms to make sure we don't have breast cancer. It's scary."</p>



<p>At 35, Steinberg had her own scare with a mammogram that showed an area of concern, so she understands her patients' fears and reluctance. She strives to set them at ease, explain simply and clearly what she's doing, take their mind off the compression and be as quick and effective as possible.</p>



<p>That understanding and empathy resonated with Melissa. So did Amanda's technique. Steinberg had learned that mammograms can be less painful if the patient doesn't reach forward to grip the handles on the machine.</p>



<p>"When you grip or make a fist, your pectoral muscles tense up. Squeezing a muscle that is already tight makes the pinching feeling of compression feel worse," she says.</p>



<p>That clenching also can create an undesirable "C" shape on the image. So instead, she tells patients not to raise their arms and grip but to let them hang relaxed by their sides.</p>



<p>"Women have told me how much better it is," says Steinberg.</p>



<p>Melissa agrees. "She was amazing, and I will never forget her, and I wish I'd found her sooner," she says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A closer look reveals a tumor</h2>



<p>The mammogram and a subsequent ultrasound were inconclusive, so Johnson ordered a biopsy that was performed on Dec. 6, 2023. Two days later, Melissa learned that the biopsy had confirmed an invasive ductile carcinoma tumor positioned right up against her chest wall.</p>



<p>"Suddenly, everything was insane," says Melissa.</p>



<p>The whirlwind of preoperative tests and appointments began, and she was informed of her options: a lumpectomy, radiation or a single or double mastectomy.</p>



<p>After talking through the options with her husband, Rick, she opted for a double mastectomy.</p>



<p>"I didn't want to undergo MRIs every six months or worry for the rest of my life," says Melissa.</p>



<p>Melissa met with Mayo Clinic Health System surgeons and had a double mastectomy on Jan. 30. After one night in the hospital, she was home and recovering with help from Rick and their children, Sarah and Joshua.</p>



<p>Before starting her on hormone-blocking cancer medication, Melissa's oncologist,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/mina-hanna-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mina Hanna, M.D.</a>, ordered a bone density scan. Melissa was delighted to learn that Amanda would conduct it since she had such a positive experience with the mammograms.</p>



<p>"After I've done mammograms for a patient, I usually don't know their results or even see them again," says Steinberg. "Doing Melissa's bone density scan felt like it was meant to be that we'd be on this journey together."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Genetics, recovery and a night at the ballpark</h2>



<p>At the start of her breast cancer journey, Melissa was surprised to learn her diagnosis because she didn't know of any women in her family who had breast cancer. Tests revealed the cancer was both estrogen and progesterone-positive but negative for BRCA 1 and 2 markers. Melissa wanted to learn more, so she underwent in-depth&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/medical-genetics" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">genetics testing</a>, none of which indicated a genetic predisposition for breast cancer.</p>



<p>"I wanted to do extra testing so my daughter and son would have that information," says Melissa. She's now taking the hormone-blocking cancer medication and continuing her recovery.</p>



<p>"Everyone on my care team — Jessica, Amanda, Dr. Hanna, my surgeons and everyone else — has been so great," she says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="325" height="400" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/melissa-neuman-pitching.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-389995" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/melissa-neuman-pitching.jpg 325w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/melissa-neuman-pitching-244x300.jpg 244w" sizes="(max-width: 325px) 100vw, 325px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Photo courtesy of Katie Friehl</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>To celebrate her progress, Melissa threw out the first pitch at Cancer Survivors Night, sponsored by Mayo Clinic Health System, at a recent Mankato MoonDogs baseball game.</p>



<p>"This was my first outing since my surgery, and it was so fun and inspiring. I just hoped I'd throw a good pitch," says Melissa.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Continuing to advance, refine mammograms</h2>



<p>Amanda is proud of her role in helping detect Melissa's breast cancer — and that of her other patients.</p>



<p>"I've always wanted to learn and do new things with mammography," she says.</p>



<p>She is particularly excited about new 3T MRI equipment in Owatonna, which will allow for MRI biopsies and more advanced imaging.</p>



<p>"This equipment will provide more support for breast procedures," she says. "And more patients will be able to stay close to home for first-rate care without traveling to Mayo Clinic in Rochester."</p>



<p>Melissa adds that her experience is a good example of why it's important for doctors and others working in healthcare to take women's health concerns seriously and provide them with options for preventive health scans and healthcare.</p>



<p>"If I didn't have a provider who listened and came up with a breast MRI to screen for breast cancer, we wouldn't have found it this early," she says.</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/patient-stories/different-mammogram-experience" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-a-different-mammogram-experience-led-to-lifesaving-cancer-diagnosis/">How a different mammogram experience led to lifesaving cancer diagnosis</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/melissa-neuman-pitching1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/melissa-neuman-and-family16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Mina Hanna]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Jessica Johnson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Melissa Neuman]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Sunscreen has a shelf life and other facts to know</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-sunscreen-has-a-shelf-life-and-other-facts-to-know/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dermatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Dawn Davis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skin Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sunscreen]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=367648</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Did you know sunscreen has a shelf life and can expire? Or that too much heat or cold can ruin a new bottle?   Protecting your skin from harmful sun rays will help against inflammation, burns, premature aging and, most importantly, skin cancer.&#160; Dr. Dawn Davis, a Mayo Clinic dermatologist, has more on sunscreen shelf life and other [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-sunscreen-has-a-shelf-life-and-other-facts-to-know/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Sunscreen has a shelf life and other facts to know</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Did you know sunscreen has a shelf life and can <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/adult-health/expert-answers/sunscreen-expire/faq-20057957?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">expire</a>? Or that too much heat or cold can ruin a new bottle?  </p>



<p>Protecting your skin from harmful sun rays will help against inflammation, burns, premature aging and, most importantly, skin cancer.&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/davis-dawn-marie-r-m-d/bio-20054974?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Dawn Davis,</a> a Mayo Clinic dermatologist, has more on sunscreen shelf life and other facts to help make decisions as you head into the sun.</p>



<p><a href="https://youtu.be/pW5-va0rvqI" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</strong></a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubepW5va0rvqI"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Sunscreen has a shelf life and other facts to know" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/pW5-va0rvqI?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Sunscreen has a shelf life and can expire. Watch the video.</figcaption></figure>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:03) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/SCRIPT-MCM-sunscreen-has-shelflife-and-other-facts.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></h4>



<p>You might think a dermatologist is going to ask you to ban the sun.</p>



<p>"There's nothing wrong with being outside in the sun," says Dr. Davis.&nbsp;</p>



<p>UV, or ultraviolet light, is a carcinogen. That's where sunscreen helps.</p>



<p>"Sunscreen can act as a carcinogen barrier to help keep your skin safe," says Dr. Davis.</p>



<p>Keep these sunscreen facts in mind when you're reaching for your favorite bottle:</p>



<ul>
<li>Sunscreen can expire, affecting the active ingredient and the preservative.</li>



<li>Sunscreen is sensitive to extreme temperatures. Keep it out of direct sun, and don't let it freeze during winter storage.</li>



<li>People of color need to wear sunscreen.</li>
</ul>



<p>Bottom line, everyone over age 6 months needs sunscreen — babies included.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/05/shutterstock_235124332-1024x683_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a young girl sitting on the side of a swimming pool with an adult man, perhaps her father, putting sunscreen on her" class="wp-image-237567" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/05/shutterstock_235124332-1024x683_Fotor-16x9.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/05/shutterstock_235124332-1024x683_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/05/shutterstock_235124332-1024x683_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Everyone is at risk of skin cancer, including children.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"It is a layman's myth that children do not get skin cancer. And it's a layman's myth that a person of color cannot have skin cancer," Dr. Davis says.</p>



<p>And lastly, Dr. Davis says, "There literally is no such thing as a waterproof sunscreen."&nbsp;</p>



<p>Apply sunscreen, and after you get wet, reapply.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Sunscreen application tips</h3>



<p>To be effective, sunscreen needs to be used liberally so be generous with your portions.</p>



<p>It's recommended to use&nbsp;1 ounce (30 milliliters) of sunscreen — the amount in a shot glass — to cover exposed parts of the body. You might need to apply more, depending on your body size. If you have a 4-ounce (118-milliliter) bottle, you'll use about a quarter of it during one application.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><br>Related posts:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-melanoma-misconception-dark-skin-tones-at-risk-too/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Melanoma misconception — dark skin tones at risk, too</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-men-need-to-take-melanoma-seriously/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Men need to take melanoma seriously</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/draft-5-3-mayo-clinic-minute-tips-for-protecting-babies-from-harmful-uv-rays/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Tips for protecting babies from harmful UV rays</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-sunscreen-has-a-shelf-life-and-other-facts-to-know/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Sunscreen has a shelf life and other facts to know</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/07/a-little-girl-perhaps-Latina-at-the-beach-smiling-and-wearing-a-sun-hat-sunscreen-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/07/a-little-girl-perhaps-Latina-at-the-beach-smiling-and-wearing-a-sun-hat-sunscreen-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dermatology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Dawn Davis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Skin Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[sunscreen]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic launches Rainbows, an LGBTQ-focused breast cancer clinic</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-launches-rainbows-an-lgbtq-focused-breast-cancer-clinic/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nicole Ferrara]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 14:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LGBTQ+. health]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=389844</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Today in the U.S., 7.2 % of adults identify as LGBTQ+ — that's more than 24 million people who often face stigma and discrimination that can make navigating the healthcare system difficult. Elizabeth Cathcart-Rake, M.D., a&#160;Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center&#160;medical oncologist specializing in&#160;breast cancer, wants to change that. She's launched the Rainbows Breast Cancer Clinic [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-launches-rainbows-an-lgbtq-focused-breast-cancer-clinic/">Mayo Clinic launches Rainbows, an LGBTQ-focused breast cancer clinic</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Lesbians-women-family-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Two women, lesbians, child, in home setting" class="wp-image-389849" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Lesbians-women-family-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Lesbians-women-family-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Lesbians-women-family-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Lesbians-women-family-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Lesbians-women-family-16-x-9.jpg 1824w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p>Today in the U.S., 7.2 % of adults identify as LGBTQ+ — that's more than 24 million people who often face stigma and discrimination that can make navigating the healthcare system difficult.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/cathcart-rake-elizabeth-j-m-d/bio-20558812" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Elizabeth Cathcart-Rake, M.D.</a>, a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;medical oncologist specializing in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a>, wants to change that. She's launched the Rainbows Breast Cancer Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota, to support the needs of lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, queer, gender diverse and intersex (LGBTQ+) people with or at risk for breast cancer. She is also researching how to improve their cancer care experiences and outcomes.</p>



<p>The Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center Blog team spoke with Dr. Cathcart-Rake about the Rainbows Breast Cancer Clinic. Here's what she wants people to know about the clinic and the LGBTQ+ cancer care experience:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Meeting the unique needs of LGBTQ+ people</h2>



<p>People who identify as LGBTQ+ experience significant disparities in cancer care, including higher rates of late-stage diagnoses, poorer cancer outcomes, and side effects from therapy that go unaddressed.</p>



<p>"I am interviewing folks who talk about getting surgeries on their nose and having their surgical team not feel comfortable getting them dressed after surgery because of their gender identity and gender expression. These types of experiences, to me, are heartbreaking," says Dr. Cathcart-Rake.</p>



<p>Dr. Cathcart-Rake says LGBTQ+ people are less likely to be offered fertility preservation before cancer treatment and often have unaddressed sexual side effects from treatment. For transgender and gender-diverse people, she says there are questions and concerns about the interaction between hormone therapy, gender-affirming and cancer-specific surgeries.</p>



<p>Opening the Rainbows Breast Cancer Clinic is personal for Dr. Cathcart-Rake. "I have a dear friend who came out and experienced unbelievable discrimination and stigma. That experience has fueled this — thinking through what they've gone through every step of the way. Our role is to care for the person in front of us, no matter what."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Offering cancer care services in a supportive, affirming environment</h2>



<p>The Rainbows Breast Cancer Clinic team provides specialty, multidisciplinary and person-affirming care for LGBTQ+ individuals in a safe and respectful environment while optimizing physical, emotional and social health.</p>



<p>"At every point on their cancer care journey, we want patients to see clinic staff who are excited and happy to see them and know the affirming, culturally appropriate language to use. To support that environment, we have posted LGBTQ–welcoming signage throughout the clinic, wear rainbow pins on our badges, and offer gender-neutral bathrooms," says Dr. Cathcart-Rake.</p>



<p>The team includes Dr. Cathcart-Rake and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/tevaarwerk-amye-j-m-d/bio-20527633" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Amye Tevaarwerk, M.D.</a>, another medical oncologist specializing in breast cancer. Jamie Carroll, a nurse practitioner; Gina Schultz, a registered nurse; and Nicole Sintler, a social worker, are also on the team. All team members are trained in providing care for LGBTQ+ people. The team also consults with a breast surgeon and a radiation oncologist with similar training.</p>



<p>"LGBTQ+ people experience so much discrimination and stigma — in everyday life and healthcare experiences. They deserve spaces like this where they're welcomed and supported and receive equitable healthcare," says Dr. Cathcart-Rake. "We hope this is just a starting point, and we can expand to other cancer types and subspecialties."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Conducting research to improve cancer care for LGBTQ+ people</h2>



<p>Dr. Cathcart-Rake says research is needed to help healthcare professionals understand the cancer care disparities LGBTQ+ people experience. "We know there are inequities and aspects of their cancer care we're not addressing. But there's little data to better understand those needs and how we can improve outcomes," she says.</p>



<p>Research will be central to the Rainbow Breast Cancer Clinic's purpose. "That's going to be a huge part of this clinic — to better understand and identify LGBTQ+ peoples' needs and work collaboratively with patients and advocates to address them," says Dr. Cathcart-Rake.</p>



<p>Patients will be asked to complete surveys about their care experiences and symptoms to support this research. Information from these surveys will be used to continuously improve clinical care and to develop clinical trials focused on the needs of LGBTQ+ people related to breast cancer.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How to make an appointment</h2>



<p>Housed on the 10th Floor of the Gonda Building on Mayo Clinic's campus in Rochester, Minnesota, the Rainbows Breast Cancer Clinic is open to anyone who wishes to be seen in an LGBTQ–focused breast clinic.</p>



<p>To make an appointment, call the Medical Oncology Appointment Office in Rochester, Minnesota, at 507-284-8815 and mention "Rainbows."</p>



<p>Virtual visits will be allowed for any patient, as laws allow.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h3>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/addressing-cancer-concerns-in-the-lgbtq-community/">Addressing cancer concerns in the LGBTQ+ community</a></li>



<li><a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2022/06/28/the-importance-of-cancer-screenings-for-lgbtq-community/"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/cancer-and-the-lgbtq-community-mayo-clinic-expert-addresses-key-topics/">Cancer and the LGBTQ+ community: Mayo Clinic expert addresses key topics</a></a></li>



<li><a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2022/08/02/what-people-who-identify-as-lgbtq-should-know-about-cancer/">What people who identify as LGBTQ should know about cancer</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>



<p><em>This article was originally published on the <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/06/27/mayo-clinic-launches-rainbows-an-lgbtq-focused-breast-cancer-clinic/">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center blog</a>.</em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-launches-rainbows-an-lgbtq-focused-breast-cancer-clinic/">Mayo Clinic launches Rainbows, an LGBTQ-focused breast cancer clinic</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Lesbians-women-family-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Lesbians-women-family-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[LGBTQ+. health]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>$20 million gift from Dwight and Dian Diercks to accelerate Mayo Clinic&#8217;s strategy for transformational healthcare AI and innovation</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/20-million-gift-from-dwight-and-dian-diercks-to-accelerate-mayo-clinics-strategy-for-transformational-healthcare-ai-and-innovation/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Terri Malloy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2024 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[artificial intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[benefactor gift]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. John Halamka]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Callstrom]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Platform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=389775</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A generous $20 million gift from Dwight and Dian Diercks will fuel key elements of Mayo Clinic’s vision for the future of healthcare, including Mayo Clinic Platform and the application of artificial intelligence (AI) for early detection and intervention in cancer. In honor of their support, Mayo Clinic will establish the Dwight [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/20-million-gift-from-dwight-and-dian-diercks-to-accelerate-mayo-clinics-strategy-for-transformational-healthcare-ai-and-innovation/">$20 million gift from Dwight and Dian Diercks to accelerate Mayo Clinic&#8217;s strategy for transformational healthcare AI and innovation</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Diercks_003-1116x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-389801" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Diercks_003-1116x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Diercks_003-1116x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Diercks_003-1116x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Diercks_003-1116x9-1-1536x863.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Diercks_003-1116x9-1.jpg 2005w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A generous $20 million gift from Dwight and Dian Diercks will fuel key elements of Mayo Clinic’s vision for the future of healthcare, including <a href="https://www.mayoclinicplatform.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Platform</a> and the application of artificial intelligence (AI) for early detection and intervention in cancer. In honor of their support, Mayo Clinic will establish the Dwight and Dian Diercks President, Mayo Clinic Platform, and create the Heidi Diercks Krause Fund in AI Innovation for Cancer, named in honor of Mr. Diercks’ late sister.</p>



<p>"The Dierckses’ visionary investment will bolster Mayo Clinic’s efforts through the Platform to curate the world's de-identified data, empower solution developers and transform healthcare around the world," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinicplatform.org/our-team/john-d-halamka-md-ms/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">John Halamka, M.D.</a>, the inaugural Dwight and Dian Diercks President, Mayo Clinic Platform.</p>



<p>“Through the reach of Mayo Clinic Platform, the Dierckses’ remarkable generosity will accelerate new innovations that fundamentally change how health systems and care teams provide care to improve patients' lives,” says Dr. Halamka, who also holds the Michael D. Brennan, M.D., President’s Strategic Initiative Professorship.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic Platform is a key focus of Mayo Clinic’s Bold. Forward. strategy to transform healthcare globally. Disrupting the traditional pipeline paradigm, Mayo Clinic Platform brings together solution developers, data partners and healthcare organizations to collaborate around secure, de-identified clinical data to create, validate and scale digital health solutions. It currently offers access to a diverse dataset of 46 million de-identified and longitudinal patient records, AI model validation for accuracy and removal of bias, and streamlined clinical integration. This transformative model is expediting a new era of revolutionary diagnostics and treatments that redefine the frontiers of patient care and well-being.</p>



<p>The Heidi Diercks Krause Fund in AI Innovation for Cancer will enable Mayo Clinic’s Generative Artificial Intelligence Program and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic’s Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> to advance answers for cancer. An example of this work includes developing advanced generative AI tools to gain deep insights into a person’s risk of developing cancer. This forecasting will allow clinicians to intervene earlier than ever before — even before cancer can be diagnosed.</p>



<p>“We are profoundly grateful to Mr. and Mrs. Diercks for their support, which will help us bring the promise of AI to patients at the earliest phases of their care journeys,” says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/callstrom-matthew-r-m-d-ph-d/bio-00085927" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Matthew Callstrom, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, Mayo Clinic’s medical director for Strategy, chair of Radiology in Rochester and leader of the Generative Artificial Intelligence Program. “Cancer affects people from all walks of life, and leveraging AI to tackle and treat this devastating disease will be critical for improving outcomes for all patients.”</p>



<p>As senior vice president of software engineering at NVIDIA, Mr. Diercks has been involved in AI innovation since the company’s inception.</p>



<p>“We can't afford to wait years or decades for new AI breakthroughs in healthcare. People need new therapies and cures now,” says Mr. Diercks. “Dian and I truly believe that Mayo Clinic Platform and AI innovation will be the keys to better predicting diseases like cancer, so physicians can intervene sooner with more effective treatments that save, extend or improve the quality of patient lives. It gives me comfort knowing my sister’s legacy will live on through these efforts to transform cancer care for everyone. Heidi lived for her family, and having additional time with her husband, Scott, and daughter, Kate, meant the world to her.&nbsp;In the future, we hope that extension of time can be amplified tenfold for others.”</p>



<p>Mr. Diercks grew up in Red Wing, Minnesota, less than 50 miles from Mayo Clinic’s Rochester campus, where he worked on his family’s farm as a teenager. His close family, including his late father and sister, trusted Mayo Clinic for their most complex health needs.</p>



<p>“I tell my friends that receiving care at Mayo Clinic is like being at the intersection of medicine and hardcore engineering. Everyone is focused on finding the right tests and data to solve the most personal, important health challenges in your life,” says Mr. Diercks.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Mr. Diercks earned his bachelor’s degree in computer science and engineering with a minor in business from the Milwaukee School of Engineering (MSOE). The Dierckses have provided transformational support to MSOE that has resulted in a nation-leading computer science program in applied AI and supercomputing. With their latest gift to Mayo Clinic, they aim to provide the same accelerant to AI innovation, now within healthcare.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Platform</strong><br>Founded on Mayo Clinic's dedication to patient-centered care,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinicplatform.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Platform</a> enables new knowledge, new solutions and new technologies through collaborations with health technology innovators to create a healthier world. To learn more, visit Mayo Clinic Platform at&nbsp;<a href="http://www.mayoclinicplatform.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">www.mayoclinicplatform.org</a>.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive&nbsp;Cancer Center</strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;is defining new boundaries in possibility, focusing on patient-centered care, developing novel treatments, training future generations of cancer experts and bringing cancer research to communities. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs that are changing approaches to cancer prevention, screening and treatment, and improving the lives of cancer survivors.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/20-million-gift-from-dwight-and-dian-diercks-to-accelerate-mayo-clinics-strategy-for-transformational-healthcare-ai-and-innovation/">$20 million gift from Dwight and Dian Diercks to accelerate Mayo Clinic&#8217;s strategy for transformational healthcare AI and innovation</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Diercks_003-11_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Diercks_003-1116x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[artificial intelligence]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[benefactor gift]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. John Halamka]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Callstrom]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[innovation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Platform]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Preventing cancer for future generations of Black families</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-preventing-cancer-for-future-generations-of-black-families/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Kim Barbel Johnson]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=368628</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The statistics are staggering. Black people are more likely to die from cancer than other racial and ethnic groups. According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, African Americans have the highest death rate from cancer overall. National Black Family Cancer Awareness Week is June 13-19. Dr. Kim Barbel Johnson, a Mayo Clinic family [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-preventing-cancer-for-future-generations-of-black-families/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Preventing cancer for future generations of Black families</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The statistics are staggering. Black people are more likely to die from cancer than other racial and ethnic groups. According to the <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/cancer/health-equity/groups/african-american.htm" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</a>, African Americans have the highest death rate from cancer overall.</p>



<p>National Black Family Cancer Awareness Week is June 13-19. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/barbel-johnson-kim-m-d-o-m-p-h/bio-20541459?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Kim Barbel Johnson</a>, a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician with the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>, says educating patients is essential to reducing and preventing cancer deaths among Black people.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/vE9bGqWN2c8" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubevE9bGqWN2c8"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Preventing cancer for future generations of Black families" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vE9bGqWN2c8?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:05) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network. Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/MCM-National-Black-Cancer-Awareness-Week-1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script.</a></strong></p>



<p>Black people are more likely to die from prostate, lung and breast cancer than other races. Dr. Barbel Johnson says there are many contributing factors, including genetics, habits and other mitigating circumstances.</p>



<p>"It has a lot to do with the structural racism that has created the environment, not only for access but for prioritizing and evolving treatments," says Dr. Barbel Johnson.</p>



<p>The family medicine physician says regular cancer screenings are key to increasing survival rates.</p>



<p>"It's important that we prioritize those things where we're seeing the incidence and the death rates are highest in these populations to be screened for those conditions," says Dr. Barbel Johnson.</p>



<p>Knowing your family history, regular exercise and eating a healthy diet are also crucial to cutting cancer risks.</p>



<p>"In doing so, we will then decrease things like red meat, increase things like vegetables within our diet, decrease the amounts of sugar and artificial sweeteners that we have in our diet," she says.</p>



<p>She also recommends stopping tobacco use and getting adequate sleep.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2-1024x576.jpg" alt="a Black woman in a patient gown being prepared by a medical assistant for a breast cancer screening or mammogram" class="wp-image-319507" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Preventing cancer risks:</strong></h3>



<ul>
<li>Get vaccinated against HPV and hepatitis B.</li>



<li>Schedule regular mammograms and colonoscopies.</li>



<li>Avoid heavy alcohol consumption.</li>



<li>Protect your skin from the sun.</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-preventing-cancer-for-future-generations-of-black-families/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Preventing cancer for future generations of Black families</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/01/a-young-Black-family-a-man-woman-young-girl-and-young-boy-sitting-at-table-laughing-and-smiling-while-eating-a-healthy-meal-together-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Consumer Health]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Kim Barbel Johnson]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Does expired sunscreen still work?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-does-expired-sunscreen-still-work/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skin Cancer Awareness Month]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skin Cancer Prevention]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=362678</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>It's that time of year when everyone's looking forward to some fun in the sun. Too much sun can be dangerous, though. Exposure to UV radiation from the sun damages your skin, and children are especially vulnerable because they tend to spend more time outdoors and can burn easily. Skin damage from the sun increases [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-does-expired-sunscreen-still-work/">Does expired sunscreen still work?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="680" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/shutterstock_1367126120-1024x680.jpg" alt="a woman applying sunscreen to the nose of a laughing young girl at the beach" class="wp-image-243973" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/shutterstock_1367126120-1024x680.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/shutterstock_1367126120-300x199.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/shutterstock_1367126120-768x510.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>It's that time of year when everyone's looking forward to some fun in the sun. Too much sun can be dangerous, though. Exposure to UV radiation from the sun damages your skin, and children are especially vulnerable because they tend to spend more time outdoors and can burn easily.</p>



<p>Skin damage from the sun increases your risk of developing:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Skin cancer</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/skin-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20377605?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Skin cancer</a> develops primarily on areas of sun-exposed skin, including the scalp, face, lips, ears, neck, chest, arms, hands and legs.&nbsp;Skin cancer affects people of all skin tones, including those with darker complexions. Skin cancer occurs when mutations occur in the DNA of skin cells. Much of the damage to DNA in skin cells results from UV radiation found in sunlight and in the lights used in tanning beds.</li>



<li><strong>Wrinkles</strong><br>Although genetics mainly determine skin structure and texture, sun exposure is a major cause of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/wrinkles/symptoms-causes/syc-20354927?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">wrinkles</a>, especially for people with light skin. Exposure to&nbsp;UV&nbsp;light breaks down your skin's connective tissue — collagen and elastin fibers, which lie in the deeper layer of skin. Without the supportive connective tissue, your skin loses strength and flexibility. Skin then begins to sag and wrinkle prematurely.</li>



<li><strong>Age spots</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/age-spots/symptoms-causes/syc-20355859?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Age spots</a> are caused by overactive pigment cells. UV light speeds up the production of melanin, a natural pigment that gives skin its color. On skin that has had years of sun exposure, age spots appear when melanin becomes clumped or is produced in high concentrations. Use of commercial tanning lamps and beds also can cause age spots.</li>
</ul>



<p>One way to protect your skin is to use a broad-spectrum sunscreen with a sun protection factor, or SPF, of at least 30, even on cloudy days. Apply sunscreen generously, and reapply every two hours — or more often if you're swimming or perspiring. Use a generous amount of sunscreen on all exposed skin, including your lips, the tips of your ears, and the backs of your hands and neck.</p>



<p>Sunscreens are required by the Food and Drug Administration to remain at their original strength for at least three years. This means that you can use leftover sunscreen from one year to the next. Some sunscreens include an expiration date — a date indicating when they're no longer effective. Discard sunscreen that is past its expiration date. If you buy sunscreen that doesn't have an expiration date, write the date of purchase on the bottle. Throw out the bottle when three years have passed since the purchase date.</p>



<p>In addition to sunscreen, avoid sun exposure in the middle of the day when the UV rays are strongest, wear sunglasses that block both types of UV radiation — UVA and UVB rays — and wear a broad-brimmed hat and other protective clothing.</p>



<p>Exercising and enjoying time outdoors are important for good health. Staying protected from the sun will allow you and your family to do so safely.</p>



<p>Connect with others talking about sunscreen and sun safety in the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/skin-conditions/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Skin Health Support Group</a> on&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Connect</a>, an online patient community moderated by Mayo Clinic.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-does-expired-sunscreen-still-work/">Does expired sunscreen still work?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/a-woman-applying-sunscreen-to-the-nose-of-a-laughing-young-girl-at-the-beach-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/a-woman-applying-sunscreen-to-the-nose-of-a-laughing-young-girl-at-the-beach-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Consumer Health]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Skin Cancer Awareness Month]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Skin Cancer Prevention]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Be sun savvy, protect yourself from skin cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/be-sun-savvy-protect-yourself-from-skin-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Rebecca Danhof]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=389333</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Ultraviolet rays from the sun can cause skin damage in as little as 15 minutes. Prolonged exposure and damage can lead to various forms of&#160;skin cancer, many of which, thankfully, are preventable. The sun isn't the only skin-damaging predator. Tanning beds and smoking also can have ill effects on the body's outer layer. What are [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/be-sun-savvy-protect-yourself-from-skin-cancer/">Be sun savvy, protect yourself from skin cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/wearing-hats-for-sun-protection16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-389342" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/wearing-hats-for-sun-protection16x9.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/wearing-hats-for-sun-protection16x9-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></figure>



<p>Ultraviolet rays from the sun can cause skin damage in as little as 15 minutes. Prolonged exposure and damage can lead to various forms of&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/skin-cancer/basics/definition/con-20031606" target="_blank">skin cancer</a>, many of which, thankfully, are preventable.</p>



<p>The sun isn't the only skin-damaging predator. Tanning beds and smoking also can have ill effects on the body's outer layer.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What are the common forms of skin cancer?</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Skin cancer can take many forms, but the three most common are:</h3>



<ul>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/basal-cell-carcinoma/basics/definition/con-20028996" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Basal cell carcinoma</a></strong><br>Basal cell carcinoma is the most common type of skin cancer. It typically develops on skin that receives a lot of sun, such as the scalp, face, nose, neck and hands. It often appears as a dome-shaped growth with visible blood vessels, a shiny, pinkish patch or a sore that heals and then returns.</li>



<li><strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/squamous-cell-carcinoma/basics/definition/con-20037813" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Squamous cell carcinoma</a></strong><br>Squamous cell carcinoma is the second most common type of skin cancer. It also frequently develops on skin exposed to the sun, such as the face, ears, lips, back of the hands, arms and legs. Squamous cell carcinoma often appears as a crusted or rough bump; a red, rough flat patch; a dome-shaped bump that grows and bleeds; or a sore that does not heal or heals and returns.</li>



<li><strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/melanoma/basics/definition/con-20026009" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Melanoma</a></strong><br>Melanoma is the deadliest form of skin cancer. It may develop on the skin or in an existing mole. Moles that change in size, color or shape, or develop symptoms, such as pain, itching or bleeding, can be a sign of melanoma. Melanoma can occur anywhere on the skin, including the hands and feet, under the fingernails or toenails, and in the mouth and genital area.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/OEnfK1Jldwc" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch this video to raise your skin cancer IQ:</a></strong></h3>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeOEnfK1Jldwc"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Raise your skin cancer IQ" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/OEnfK1Jldwc?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Preventing skin cancer</h2>



<p>The keys to preventing skin cancer are to be sun savvy and know how to keep your skin healthy.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Be smart in the sun and protect your skin with these tips:</h3>



<ul>
<li><strong>Avoid the sun between 10 a.m. and 4 p.m.</strong><br>This is when the sun is most intense and produces the greatest chance of sunburn. If you must be outside during these hours, seek shade using an umbrella, tree or other shelter. Use protective clothing and sunscreen even when in the shade. Learn more with this&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/skin-cancer/multimedia/skin-cancer-infographic/ifg-20441507" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">"More Fun, Less Sun" infographic</a>.</li>



<li><strong>Be aware of medications that increase your sensitivity to the sun.</strong><br>Some prescription and over-the-counter medications can make you more sensitive to sunlight. Common drugs include antihistamines such as Benadryl; nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), including naproxen or ibuprofen; certain antibiotics, including Bactrim or tetracycline; antidepressants; antipsychotics and oral diabetes medications. Check with your pharmacist regarding the side effects of your medication.</li>



<li><strong>Don the right head gear.</strong><br>A wide-brimmed hat can protect your face, ears and neck. If you wear a baseball cap, remember to apply sunscreen to your neck and ears. Also, wear protective clothing that covers exposed areas.</li>



<li><strong>Don't use tanning beds.</strong><br>Tanning beds produce harmful ultraviolet A (UVA) and ultraviolet B (UVB) rays, increasing your risk for skin cancer. There also is no proven evidence that using tanning beds to obtain a "base tan" will decrease your risk of sunburn. Beyond that, using tanning beds increases the chance of developing cataracts and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/eye-melanoma/basics/definition/con-20027875" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ocular melanoma</a>.</li>



<li><strong>Make healthy lifestyle choices.</strong><br>Your behaviors and habits affect the health of your skin. Do not smoke because it damages collagen and elastin in your skin. When&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/look-good-and-feel-better-with-skin-care" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">caring for your skin</a>, use mild soaps and daily moisturizers while limiting hot showers which can strip essential oils from your skin. Drink plenty of water to remain hydrated, and get regular sleep to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/what-to-do-about-dry-skin" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">keep your skin looking refreshed</a>.</li>



<li><strong>Perform regular skin checks.</strong><br>Look for any changes to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/the-abcdes-of-moles" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">moles</a>, freckles or birthmarks. Additionally, monitor any new skin changes that have occurred. Use a mirror to evaluate hard-to-see areas, and have regular skin evaluations by your healthcare team or dermatologist.</li>



<li><strong>Protect children's skin.</strong><br>Children younger than 6 months should not use sunscreen but should be protected from the sun's rays with protective clothing and shade. Apply sunscreen regularly to children 6 months and older.</li>



<li><strong>Use sunscreen when outdoors.</strong><br>A higher sun protection factor, or SPF, number in sunscreen indicates increased protection. The American Academy of Dermatology recommends using at least SPF 30. Use sunscreen even on cloudy or cool days because damage from the sun's rays can still occur. Reapply every two hours. You also should reapply after swimming or when sweating. Check the sunscreen's expiration date. The shelf life typically is three years or less if it has been stored in high temperatures.</li>



<li><strong>Wear sunglasses with UVA and UVB protection.</strong><br>Proper, protective sunglasses help prevent damage to the sensitive skin around your eyes and block ultraviolet light from the sun that may cause&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cataracts/basics/definition/con-20015113" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cataracts</a>.</li>
</ul>



<p><em><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/rebecca-danof-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Rebecca Danhof, M.D.</a>, is a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/dermatology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dermatologist</a>&nbsp;in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/onalaska" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Onalaska</a>, Wisconsin.</em></p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/be-sun-savvy-and-protect-yourself-from-skin-cancer" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/be-sun-savvy-protect-yourself-from-skin-cancer/">Be sun savvy, protect yourself from skin cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/wearing-hats-for-sun-protection_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/wearing-hats-for-sun-protection16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Rebecca Danhof]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Improvements in prostate surgery</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-improvements-in-prostate-surgery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Tollefson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=385041</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>There will be approximately 299,010 new cases of prostate cancer diagnosed in 2024, according to the American Cancer Society. Treatments vary, including chemotherapy, hormone therapy, ablative therapy, immunotherapy, targeted drug therapy, radiation and prostate robotic surgery. Dr. Matthew Tollefson, a urologist at Mayo Clinic, explains how advancement in robotic prostate surgery is making it easier [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-improvements-in-prostate-surgery/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Improvements in prostate surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>There will be approximately 299,010 new cases of prostate cancer diagnosed in 2024, according to the <a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/types/prostate-cancer/about/key-statistics.html#:~:text=from%20prostate%20cancer-,How%20common%20is%20prostate%20cancer%3F,35%2C250%20deaths%20from%20prostate%20cancer" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Cancer Society</a>.</p>



<p>Treatments vary, including chemotherapy, hormone therapy, ablative therapy, immunotherapy, targeted drug therapy, radiation and prostate robotic surgery.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/tollefson-matthew-k-m-d/bio-20055377" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Matthew Tollefson</a>, a urologist at Mayo Clinic, explains how advancement in robotic prostate surgery is making it easier for patients to get back on their feet.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/hjhn2rZDAvI" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubehjhn2rZDAvI"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Improvements in prostate surgery" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hjhn2rZDAvI?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:58) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/SCRIPT-jthEDITS_MCM-prostate-cancer-surgery.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>About 1 in 8 men in the U.S. will be diagnosed with prostate cancer during their lifetime. Many of those patients undergo surgery to get rid of the cancerous tumor.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Dr-Matthew-Tollefson-prostate-surgery-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Dr. Matthew Tollefson performing a prostate surgery" class="wp-image-388884" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Dr-Matthew-Tollefson-prostate-surgery-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Dr-Matthew-Tollefson-prostate-surgery-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Dr-Matthew-Tollefson-prostate-surgery-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Dr-Matthew-Tollefson-prostate-surgery-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Dr-Matthew-Tollefson-prostate-surgery-16-x-9.jpg 1824w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Matthew Tollefson in surgery</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Most of the time, prostate cancer is a slower-growing type of tumor," says Dr. Tollefson. "Physically removing it could then cure one from cancer."</p>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="632" height="598" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/02/prostate-tumor-632px.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-262543" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/02/prostate-tumor-632px.jpg 632w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/02/prostate-tumor-632px-300x284.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 632px) 100vw, 632px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Medical illustration of a normal and cancerous prostate.</figcaption></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Advancements in robotic prostate surgery</h3>



<p>He says surgery is a common option for many men, especially if the cancer is contained in the prostate. Medical innovation has improved cancer removal surgeries. Now, there's an upgrade to the robotic prostatectomy procedure.</p>



<p>"Instead of all of the instruments coming in through separate incisions, they come in through a single incision, and the robot is able to then branch out within the abdomen and remove the prostate," explains Dr. Tollefson.</p>



<p>Patients have a faster recovery and reduced pain with the single-port robotic procedure.</p>



<p>Other prostate cancer treatment options can include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Radiation therapy.</li>



<li>Ablative therapies.</li>



<li>Hormone therapy.</li>



<li>Chemotherapy.</li>



<li>Immunotherapy.</li>



<li>Targeted drug therapy.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Related Posts:</strong></h3>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/prostate-cancer-screening-and-treatment/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Prostate cancer screening and treatment options</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-importance-of-exercise-for-men-with-prostate-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Importance of exercise for men with prostate cancer</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-do-you-know-the-symptoms-of-prostate-cancer/">Consumer Health: Do you know the symptoms of prostate cancer?</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-treating-prostate-cancer/">Consumer Health: Treating prostate cancer</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-improvements-in-prostate-surgery/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Improvements in prostate surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Dr-Tollefson-prostate-surgery-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2014/02/shutterstock_86097949.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Tollefson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>