<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 13:01:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>A shared journey through breast cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-shared-journey-through-breast-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[robinhuiras]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 13:01:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Laboratories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Roberto Leon-Ferre]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395730</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>When Samantha Duke discovered she had breast cancer, she didn’t have to look far for support. Her mother Jane walked a similar path 16 years earlier. Inspired both by her mom and the strong network of healthcare physicians and professionals on her team, Samantha remained positive throughout her treatment and is committed to advancing research [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-shared-journey-through-breast-cancer/">A shared journey through breast cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Samantha_and_Jane_Duke-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Jane Hanson and Samantha Duke standing together" class="wp-image-395732" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Samantha_and_Jane_Duke-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Samantha_and_Jane_Duke-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Samantha_and_Jane_Duke-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Samantha_and_Jane_Duke-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Samantha_and_Jane_Duke-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Jane Hanson and Samantha Duke</figcaption></figure>



<p><em>When Samantha Duke discovered she had breast cancer, she didn’t have to look far for support. Her mother Jane walked a similar path 16 years earlier. Inspired both by her mom and the strong network of healthcare physicians and professionals on her team, Samantha remained positive throughout her treatment and is committed to advancing research on breast cancer.</em></p>



<p>Jane Hanson vividly recalls the day in late April 2022 when her 37-year-old daughter Samantha Duke learned that she had stage 3 <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a>.</p>



<p>“I remember that terrible phone call,” Jane says. “We were both just in shock — we couldn’t believe it because she was diligent about having exams and getting tested.”</p>



<p>Samantha’s vigilance about self-exams and monitoring stemmed from watching her mother battle breast cancer. Just 16 years earlier, at age 56, Jane faced her own fight with the condition.</p>



<p>“I’ve always been hyper-aware of and tracked any changes in my breast health,” says Samantha, who is an associate project manager in Supply Chain Management at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota. “I was in line to start preventative mammograms at age 40, but at 37 I found a lump.”</p>



<p>Samantha’s discovery of the lump in her left breast prompted a push for answers and a referral from her Mayo Clinic primary care physician to the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/breast-clinic/sections/overview/ovc-20459469" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Breast Clinic</a>. Laboratory analysis of biopsied breast and lymph node tissue revealed Samantha had a high-grade adenocarcinoma. That diagnosis set Samantha on a fast-moving course through treatment and recovery walked by her mother and millions of women before her.</p>



<p>“If my mom and I were close before, we are now bound together on a whole other level,” Samantha says. “It's hard to explain actually, but it's a deep-seated connection that I will cherish going forward.”</p>



<p>Having a breast cancer survivor as one of her biggest cheerleaders provided Samantha with a positive, hope-filled perspective that colored her journey. Access to leading-edge diagnostic tools, which enabled swift characterization of her cancer, paved the way for tailored treatment that eliminated cancer cells in her body.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>“In terms of testing early on, I really threw all of my trust in their plan,” Samantha says. “Mayo's approach to oncology care is beyond words. It's overwhelming how many groups are available for support and care 24 hours a day, seven days a week, 365 days a year.”</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Her mom, who has been cancer-free for 16 years, couldn’t agree more. “You just feel like it’s a big family,” Jane says. “It's so important and I think makes the patient feel so much more comfortable knowing that everybody is talking to each other. I just cannot say enough about the teamwork.”</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Clarity, confidence, customization</strong></h2>



<p>For Samantha, who lives with her husband, Scott, and 7-year-old daughter in Rochester, the speed at which a multidisciplinary team formed around her bolstered Samantha’s sense that her care was a priority.</p>



<p>“Before any of my treatment plans started, my surgical oncologist, radiation oncologist, and medical oncologist met in person to discuss my case, treatment plans, and moving forward,” Samatha says. “They all agreed on the path, making me feel so confident in what I was about to get into.”</p>



<p>The team’s decision-making process was informed by the results of Samantha’s laboratory testing. Because of Jane’s diagnosis, genetic testing was ordered to determine if Samantha had a hereditary cancer syndrome. Mayo Clinic Laboratories offers a full line of testing for hereditary cancer syndromes, including for breast and gynecological illness (Mayo ID: <a href="https://www.mayocliniclabs.com/test-catalog/overview/614320" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">BRGYP</a>).</p>



<p>“I wanted to make sure that if this was a genetic thing, I could best prepare my daughter and make sure she has an awareness,” Samantha says. Thankfully Samantha was negative for any genetic variants that could have been passed to her daughter.</p>



<p>Immunohistochemistry testing performed on the tumor (Mayo ID: <a href="https://www.mayocliniclabs.com/test-catalog/overview/620800" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">HERMB</a>) at Mayo Clinic, however, revealed certain traits, including HER2 positivity, that painted a clearer picture of the cancer.</p>



<p>Among women who have breast cancer, about 15% have HER2-positive breast cancer, says Samantha’s medical oncologist, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/leon-ferre-roberto-a-m-d/bio-20340746" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Roberto Leon-Ferre, M.D</a>.</p>



<p>“It's a small proportion of women with breast cancer, but until the late 1990s, this was considered one of the most aggressive and lethal subtypes of breast cancer,” Dr. Leon-Ferre says.</p>



<p>The high rates of mortality for HER2 patients compelled researchers to focus on finding an effective treatment, Dr. Leon-Ferre adds.</p>



<p>“Mayo Clinic investigators were heavily involved in the original clinical studies that led to the approval of the medications that we now use routinely, and in the refinement of testing for HER2,” Dr. Leon-Ferre says. “And now that we have several effective drugs that target the HER2 protein, this is now one of the most curable subtypes of breast cancer.”</p>



<p>Among the treatments developed to specifically target HER2-positive patients was one prescribed to Samantha. TCHP chemotherapy is a four-drug cocktail that targets HER2-positive breast cancer cells. Just one month after diagnosis, Samantha received the first in a yearlong journey of infusions.</p>



<p>“The nursing staff on Gonda 10 East are nothing short of spectacular,” Samantha says, explaining that they gave her daughter a chemo Barbie with multiple wigs and a shirt that read: Strong Like Mom.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>“It does take a village to treat a single patient with breast cancer,” Dr. Leon-Ferre says. “When patients come into the Breast Clinic, multiple teams of breast cancer specialists gather in that same clinic to review each case in detail. Rather than the patient moving to each one of our offices, we come to the patient. In conjunction, we determine the best treatment strategy, and we all meet with the patient that same morning.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>“The advantage of this approach is that it allows us to come together with a comprehensive plan, and on that same day the patient can leave with a clear direction of what the next steps will be,” Dr. Leon-Ferre says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Inspiration, optimism, altruism</strong></h2>



<p>Throughout Samantha’s treatment, which also included surgery to remove the tumor and surrounding tissues and 25 sessions of proton beam radiation therapy, her husband and mother were a constant support.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="225" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Samantha_chemotherapy-225x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395739" style="width:256px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Samantha_chemotherapy-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Samantha_chemotherapy.jpg 480w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Samantha during her first chemotherapy session in May of 2022.<br></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>“When my diagnosis came there were a lot of emotions — fear, anger, sadness,” Samantha says. “My husband, daughter, and both of my parents were with me from the very beginning. If my husband wasn't able to be with me at an appointment or for chemotherapy sessions, my mom would be there. It was this unspoken notion that I would never be alone through the journey.”</p>



<p>Jane’s journey with cancer, which was stage 1 and HER2-negative when discovered, involved a mastectomy and taking the chemotherapy pill tamoxifen for five years. Throughout her recovery, Samantha was a key support.</p>



<p>“After her surgery, my mom needed someone to be with her, so I quit my job and stayed home to offer support,” Samantha says.</p>



<p>In Jane’s own life, having a strong support network helped her manage the anxiety and exhaustion caused by the condition.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img decoding="async" width="225" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Support_socks-225x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395740" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Support_socks-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Support_socks.jpg 480w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Family and friends from across the country sent Samantha support in many ways throughout her cancer journey, including this pair of socks.<br></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>“It’s just wonderful to have family and friends to share with and talk about the journey together,” says Jane. “Samantha and I talked a lot about staying positive. But you do worry about your daughter growing up. So we talked about how Samantha would be here when her daughter graduates and we were thinking positive thoughts constantly. We were so lucky that we have each other and we can share this journey and the next.”</p>



<p>Putting a positive spin on and finding humor in her situation was essential to remain hopeful, Samantha says.</p>



<p>“Every day I looked for the positive and made fun of the situation,” Samantha says. “I don’t remember every activity, but I remember laughing a lot.”</p>



<p>The gratitude that’s grown out of her experience and outcome has motivated Samatha to use her experience to help others.</p>



<p>“I do not discount my privilege of not only working for Mayo, but for being a patient,” Samantha says. “This time in my life has taught me&nbsp;about what it is to be truly grateful for all I have. Every research study they offered, I signed up for. If small pieces of good can come from my experience, then this wasn’t for nothing.”</p>



<p>Witnessing Samantha boldly face her diagnosis, push for answers, and enroll in research has been inspiring, Jane says.</p>



<p>“I'm so proud of her. She wasn’t afraid to question everything and everyone,” Jane says.</p>



<p>While Samantha’s future is not certain — she receives follow-up testing every six months — her experience has shown her that her team is prepared to handle whatever comes her way.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>“I may have no idea what tomorrow will bring, but knowing Mayo Clinic has my back allows me to focus on other aspects of this journey with renewed energy,” Samantha says.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://news.mayocliniclabs.com/2024/09/23/a-shared-journey-through-breast-cancer-samantha-duke-and-jane-hanson/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Laboratories blog</a>.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-shared-journey-through-breast-cancer/">A shared journey through breast cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Samantha_and_Jane_Duke2-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Samantha_and_Jane_Duke-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Roberto Leon-Ferre]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Laboratories]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic experts highlight advances in breast cancer research: Decreasing the need for chemotherapy and reducing the intensity of radiation therapy</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-experts-highlight-advances-in-breast-cancer-research-decreasing-the-need-for-chemotherapy-and-reducing-the-intensity-of-radiation-therapy/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelley Luckstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 18:23:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Dr. Aaron Krych]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Goetz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Robert Mutter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Roberto Leon-Ferre]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Tufia Haddad]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395724</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Lifesaving cancer therapies can cause serious side effects, both immediately and later in life. "It is essential to continue to study innovative approaches that will eradicate the disease but won't diminish the quality of life for patients diagnosed with cancer," says Roberto Leon-Ferre, M.D., a breast medical oncologist at Mayo Clinic. With [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-experts-highlight-advances-in-breast-cancer-research-decreasing-the-need-for-chemotherapy-and-reducing-the-intensity-of-radiation-therapy/">Mayo Clinic experts highlight advances in breast cancer research: Decreasing the need for chemotherapy and reducing the intensity of radiation therapy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/breast-cancer-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395750" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/breast-cancer-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/breast-cancer-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/breast-cancer-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/breast-cancer-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/breast-cancer-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Lifesaving cancer therapies can cause serious side effects, both immediately and later in life. "It is essential to continue to study innovative approaches that will eradicate the disease but won't diminish the quality of life for patients diagnosed with cancer," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/leon-ferre-roberto-a-m-d/bio-20463845" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Roberto Leon-Ferre, M.D.</a>, a breast medical oncologist at Mayo Clinic. With breast cancer rates rising among younger people, the need for treatments that provide excellent outcomes with fewer side effects is only increasing.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> experts highlight breast cancer research that may reduce or eliminate the need for chemotherapy and endocrine treatments and may allow for shorter and less intense radiation therapy courses.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Prognostic Biomarker Identified in Triple-Negative Breast Cancer: Potential to Reduce Chemotherapy Use</h2>



<p>Dr. Leon-Ferre's research team <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-study-finds-triple-negative-breast-cancer-tumors-with-an-increase-in-immune-cells-have-lower-risk-of-recurrence-after-surgery/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">recently</a> identified a prognostic biomarker in patients diagnosed with <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/01/03/understanding-triple-negative-breast-cancer-and-its-treatment/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">triple-negative breast cancer (TNBC)</a>, a type of breast cancer that does not have estrogen or progesterone receptors and that does not have excessive expression of HER2. The researchers found that patients with high levels of naturally existing immune cells called tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes (TILs) within their tumors may have a lower risk of cancer recurrence and better survival rates, even when chemotherapy is not administered.</p>



<p>"This is an important finding because triple-negative breast cancer is a particularly aggressive form of breast cancer that does not respond to hormonal therapies or drugs targeting the HER2 protein," says Dr. Leon-Ferre. "This means treatment options are more limited, often more intense and harsher for patients. However, some patients with TNBC can be cured without chemotherapy, and the key is identifying who those patients are ahead of time." He adds that future research will explore whether TILs can be used to decide who may need and may not need chemotherapy after a TNBC diagnosis.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Study Explores Necessity of Chemotherapy in Premenopausal Women with Intermediate-Risk Breast Cancer</h2>



<p>In a separate ongoing trial, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/haddad-tufia-c-m-d/bio-10029575" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tufia Haddad, M.D.</a>, breast medical oncologist at Mayo Clinic, is co-chair of a <a href="https://aacrjournals.org/cancerres/article/84/9_Supplement/PO2-19-02/744254/Abstract-PO2-19-02-NRG-BR009-Phase-III-Trial" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> comparing two treatment regimens in premenopausal women with intermediate-risk breast cancer: one group with chemotherapy plus ovarian suppression and hormone therapy, and another group without chemotherapy but with ovarian suppression and hormone therapy. The study aims to determine whether chemotherapy's benefits come from its ability to suppress ovarian function (thereby reducing estrogen production) or from its direct cancer-fighting effects. "The results could determine if chemotherapy is necessary or if ovarian suppression and hormone therapy alone are enough in this group of patients, sparing them from the side effects of chemotherapy," says Dr. Haddad.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Endoxifen: A Potent Therapy for Estrogen-Receptor-Positive Breast Cancer Explored by Mayo Clinic</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/goetz-matthew-p-m-d/bio-00027285" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Matthew Goetz, M.D.</a>, a breast medical oncologist and director of the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/research-programs/womens-cancer-program/breast-cancer-spore/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Breast Cancer Specialized Programs of Research Excellence (SPORE)</a>, and the Erivan K. Haub Family Professor of Cancer Research Honoring Richard F. Emslander, M.D., has spent more than a decade studying the use of endoxifen for the treatment of patients with estrogen-receptor-positive breast cancer (ER-positive breast cancer or ER+), the most common subtype of breast cancer.</p>



<p>Endoxifen, the most potent byproduct of tamoxifen, stops the growth of estrogen-dependent cancer cells and blocks protein kinase C, which may contribute to the aggressiveness of some cancers. Premenopausal patients with ER+ breast cancer are treated with ovarian function suppression and aromatase inhibitors to lower estrogen levels and slow cancer growth. While effective, this regimen causes significant side effects from deep estrogen suppression. Dr. Goetz's <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/specialized-programs-research-excellence-spore-grants/breast-cancer/research-projects/improving-endocrine-management-premenopausal-er-her2-breast-cancer" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">SPORE-funded study</a> explores whether endoxifen alone can eradicate cancer cells, potentially eliminating the need for more toxic treatments like chemotherapy. He is also studying the role of protein kinase C in ER+ breast cancer.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Mayo Clinic Study Finds Shortened and Less Intense Radiation Therapy Effective for Breast Cancer Patients</h2>



<p>Radiation therapy can be an essential part of a person's breast cancer treatment plan; however, it can lead to changes in the appearance of the skin, swelling, pain and other complications. These side effects can be detrimental to a patient's quality of life. In a recent <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0360301624033893?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>, Mayo Clinic breast cancer researchers found they can safely reduce the intensity and shorten the course of radiation treatment to three days for select patients with breast cancer following their lumpectomy.</p>



<p>"Normally, this treatment takes five to 15 days and can sometimes cause unwanted side effects, including changes in how the breast looks. However, this new method administers a lower dose of radiation over just three sessions using either photons, protons or brachytherapy," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/mutter-robert-w-m-d/bio-20343551" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Robert Mutter, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic radiation oncologist and lead author of the study. "The new personalized approach was well-tolerated by the patients and resulted in excellent cancer control with better long-term aesthetic results compared to what has previously been reported with longer treatments."</p>



<p>Collectively, this research is leading to innovative approaches and helping clinicians and patients make informed treatment decisions, potentially sparing patients from some of the more severe side effects of chemotherapy, endocrine therapy and radiation.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-experts-highlight-advances-in-breast-cancer-research-decreasing-the-need-for-chemotherapy-and-reducing-the-intensity-of-radiation-therapy/">Mayo Clinic experts highlight advances in breast cancer research: Decreasing the need for chemotherapy and reducing the intensity of radiation therapy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/breast-cancer-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/breast-cancer-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Dr. Aaron Krych]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Goetz]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Robert Mutter]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Roberto Leon-Ferre]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Tufia Haddad]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: How breast cancer screening can save lives</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-how-breast-cancer-screening-can-save-lives/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Abby Smith]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2024 15:51:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Elizabeth Cathcart-Rake]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395529</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: I'm about to turn 40, and I'm nervous about getting my first mammogram. I hear they can be uncomfortable or even painful. Is breast cancer screening really that important?&#160; ANSWER: It can be a bit daunting at first, but breast cancer screening helps people live longer. Screening can catch cancer early, either [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-how-breast-cancer-screening-can-save-lives/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: How breast cancer screening can save lives</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="An ultrasound technician positions a patient for a mammogram" class="wp-image-386745" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9.jpg 1604w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> I'm about to turn 40, and I'm nervous about getting my first mammogram. I hear they can be uncomfortable or even painful. Is breast cancer screening really that important?&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong> It can be a bit daunting at first, but <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a> screening helps people live longer. Screening can catch cancer early,<strong> </strong>either in the precancerous stage or when it's localized to a very small part of the body. When we can catch it early and decrease the risk of it coming back in the future, patients not only live longer, but they also may live with fewer symptoms and breast cancer or cancer treatment-related concerns.&nbsp;</p>



<p>A common misconception around screening is, "I don't have a family history of breast cancer, so I don't know that I need a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mammogram/about/pac-20384806" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">mammogram</a>." That's concerning because we know 1 in 8 women get breast cancer, which is common. It's critical that, no matter what your history is, you still consider breast cancer screening for the future.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>We recommend that breast cancer screenings start at age 40, although these decisions should be individualized. Some patients may need screening earlier based on family history, personal history or genetic predisposition. It's not one-size-fits-all, and it's good to decide with a primary care clinician, depending on your specific risk. For example, if there are any hints of a strong breast cancer history in the family, we may consider <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/genetic-testing/about/pac-20384827" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">genetic testing</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Traditionally, breast cancer screening is with a 3D mammogram. With breast self-exams, we recommend patients get to know their breasts — or, if they've had a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mastectomy/about/pac-20394670" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">mastectomy</a>, their chest wall — and notice if there are any changes, such as any new lumps or bumps, and then bring that to their healthcare team's attention. It's not uncommon to have breast changes over time. This can happen due to menstrual cycles or hormonal changes. But if you feel a lump that does not go away or worsens over a matter of weeks, that's a reason to get examined. Other things to look out for include flattening of the nipple, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/symptoms/nipple-discharge/basics/definition/sym-20050946" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">nipple discharge</a> or a hard lump in the underarm.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>We eliminate many early-stage breast cancers with a combination of surgery, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/radiation-therapy/about/pac-20385162" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">radiation</a> and medications. Most breast cancers are very treatable and curable. With breast cancers that are detected at a later stage, there are still ways that we can suppress these cancers to help people live longer with fewer symptoms.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The question of how frequently someone needs to be screened comes up a lot. Our general guidance is annual screening with mammograms or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/3d-mammogram/about/pac-20438708" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">3D mammograms</a>. For patients with a very high risk for breast cancer, extremely <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mammogram/in-depth/dense-breast-tissue/art-20123968" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dense breasts</a> or another reason that makes it harder to detect breast cancer in a screening 3D mammogram, we might recommend additional or supplemental screening, often with an <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mri/about/pac-20384768" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">MRI</a> or an <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/molecular-breast-imaging/about/pac-20394710" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">MBI</a> (molecular breast imaging). It really depends on risk.&nbsp;</p>



<p>We have patients who strongly prefer or request to have screening less often. Overall, the most important parts of this process are discussing screening with your primary healthcare clinician and sharing decision-making. It's important for patients to know the general guidelines and to advocate for themselves if they're in a group that might fall outside our typical guidance, such as high-risk patients who might need to be screened earlier. Talk to your healthcare team about what's right for you. — <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/cathcart-rake-elizabeth-j-m-d/bio-20558812" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>Elizabeth Cathcart-Rake, M.D.</em></strong></a>, <strong><em>Medical </em></strong><strong><em>Oncology, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota</em></strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-how-breast-cancer-screening-can-save-lives/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: How breast cancer screening can save lives</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Mammogram.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Elizabeth Cathcart-Rake]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The 4 types of systemic therapy for breast cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/the-4-types-of-systemic-therapy-for-breast-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jessica Saenz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2024 14:00:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=394786</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Editor's note:&#160;October is Breast Cancer Awareness Month. Treatment for breast cancer can come in many forms. In addition to surgery to remove cancerous tissue and radiation therapy, breast cancer also is commonly treated with drugs that are taken orally or intravenously, as an infusion into a vein. Drugs that treat cancer also are called systemic [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/the-4-types-of-systemic-therapy-for-breast-cancer/">The 4 types of systemic therapy for breast cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/Woman-drinking-coffee-looking-out-the-window-thinking-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Woman drinking coffee, looking out the window, thinking" class="wp-image-342450" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/Woman-drinking-coffee-looking-out-the-window-thinking-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/Woman-drinking-coffee-looking-out-the-window-thinking-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/Woman-drinking-coffee-looking-out-the-window-thinking-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/Woman-drinking-coffee-looking-out-the-window-thinking-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/Woman-drinking-coffee-looking-out-the-window-thinking-16x9-1.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Getty Images</figcaption></figure>



<p><em><strong>Editor's note:</strong>&nbsp;October is Breast Cancer Awareness Month.</em></p>



<p>Treatment for breast cancer can come in many forms. In addition to surgery to remove cancerous tissue and radiation therapy, breast cancer also is commonly treated with drugs that are taken orally or intravenously, as an infusion into a vein.</p>



<p>Drugs that treat cancer also are called systemic therapies. Types of systemic therapies for breast cancer include&nbsp;chemotherapy, hormone therapy, targeted-drug therapy and immunotherapy.</p>



<p>"The goal of systemic therapy is to either inhibit the growth of cancer cells or to eradicate them from the body," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/goetz-matthew-p-m-d/bio-20054460" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Matthew Goetz, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic medical oncologist. Dr. Goetz is also deputy director, translational research for the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> and principal investigator of the Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/research-programs/womens-cancer-program/breast-cancer-spore/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Breast Cancer SPORE</a>.</p>



<p>Here's an overview of the four types of systemic therapy for breast cancer:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="chemotherapy">Chemotherapy</h2>



<p>"The&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352475" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a>&nbsp;drug treatment we think about most commonly is&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/chemotherapy/about/pac-20385033" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chemotherapy</a>, a medication that's usually delivered by vein," says Dr. Goetz. "Depending on the type of cancer and the situation, chemotherapy can be very effective at either eradicating or substantially reducing the total volume of cancer cells in the body."</p>



<p>Chemotherapy and drug treatments also are effective at killing cancer cells that are not yet active, which can help reduce the chance of recurrence.</p>



<p>"When a woman is first diagnosed with breast cancer and she does not have any obvious evidence for cancer that has spread throughout the body, there is a chance that there may be cancer cells that are undetected," says Dr. Goetz.</p>



<p>Chemotherapy is used often in combination with other treatments, such as surgery, radiation or hormone therapy. Before or after surgery, your healthcare provider might recommend chemotherapy to shrink an existing tumor, or destroy remaining or undetected cancer cells throughout the body. This type of treatment is called <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/in-depth/adjuvant-therapy/art-20046687" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">adjuvant</a> chemotherapy.</p>



<p>Chemotherapy can have some unpleasant side effects, such as nausea, vomiting, hair loss and loss of appetite. These side effects often can be prevented and improved after treatment ends, but it's important to discuss these with your healthcare provider and weigh the options of different drug treatments for your cancer diagnosis.</p>



<p>"There may be some women who are not candidates for these medications. We certainly encounter that," says Dr. Goetz. "The good news is that we have a variety of medications, and if a woman is unable to tolerate one medication, we can try another. We know that one drug does not fit all, so having a number of different options is very important for our patients."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="hormone-therapy">Hormone therapy</h2>



<p>Some types of breast cancer are fueled by natural hormones, such as estrogen or progesterone. Your health care provider can order tests to determine if this is the case for your cancer type. If it is,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/hormone-therapy-for-breast-cancer/about/pac-20384943" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hormone therapy</a>&nbsp;might be recommended.</p>



<p>"The most common type of breast cancer, which accounts for about 70% of breast cancers, is the estrogen-receptor-positive, or hormone-receptor-positive, type of breast cancer," says Dr. Goetz. "With this type of cancer, we know that cancer cells respond to estrogen or hormones, using them to grow or proliferate. When we use hormonal therapy, we're using drugs to either block, remove or substantially downregulate the estrogen receptor."</p>



<p>Because of the high prevalence of hormone-sensitive breast cancer, clinical trials have been conducted to determine if hormone therapy can be used as a prevention method for women who are at high risk for breast cancer. "These medications have been used in patients that are at high risk for developing breast cancer, and they are quite effective in that setting," says Dr. Goetz.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="targeted-drug-therapy">Targeted-drug therapy</h2>



<p>Like chemotherapy, targeted-drug therapy works throughout the body, and it is especially effective in cancers that have spread. But targeted-drug therapy differs from chemotherapy in how it kills cancer cells. Targeted-drug therapies focus on the abnormalities of cancer cells, particularly proteins, that allow them to survive and replicate, according to the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>.</p>



<p>Proteins such as the human epidermal growth factor receptor 2, also known as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/breast-cancer/expert-answers/faq-20058066" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">HER2</a>, promote the growth of cancer cells. When patients have cancer that is HER2 positive, cancerous tumors can be more aggressive. "HER2 is present in about 20% of breast cancers," says Dr. Goetz.</p>



<p>"HER2-positive breast cancer was once feared by patients. When I first started my training at Mayo Clinic, we had patients who had HER2-positive breast cancer that was incurable," says Dr. Goetz. "Over the past 20 years, there have been multiple new drugs developed that have reduced the risk for HER2-positive breast cancer by 70% to 80%. Now it is something where we say 'Well, this is a good thing because we have very active drugs that can work.'"</p>



<p>Identifying the abnormalities of cancer cells can help your healthcare professional determine what targeted drugs are most effective for your cancer type.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="immunotherapy">Immunotherapy</h2>



<p>While the immune system is trained to fight off perceived threats, cancer cells can manipulate the immune system by turning off the mechanism that triggers a fight response, allowing cancer cells to replicate.&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-immunotherapy-and-breast-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Immunotherapy</a>&nbsp;is a newer targeted-drug therapy that teaches your immune system to identify and kill cancer cells.</p>



<p>Currently,&nbsp;<a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2022/11/29/immune-checkpoint-inhibitors-immunotherapy-for-people-with-triple-negative-breast-cancer/">immunotherapy</a>&nbsp;is approved for patients with locally advanced&nbsp;<a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/01/03/understanding-triple-negative-breast-cancer-and-its-treatment/">triple-negative breast cancer</a>. Triple-negative breast cancer, also known as basal-like breast cancer, is not sensitive to hormones or the HER2 protein.</p>



<p>"When a woman has a diagnosis of triple-negative breast cancer, traditionally we've used chemotherapy. But one of the real success stories in triple-negative breast cancer treatment is immunotherapy," says Dr. Goetz.</p>



<p>Triple-negative breast cancer is more likely to affect people according to race. "This type of breast cancer is seen at much higher rates in African American women than in Caucasian women," says Dr. Goetz. "It's an area of intense research focus right now."</p>



<p>Cancer experts at Mayo Clinic continue to explore how immunotherapy and other drugs — new and existing — can fight breast cancer in different populations.</p>



<p>"We need to be able to individualize treatment," says Dr. Goetz. &nbsp;"As&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/weinshilboum-richard-m-d/bio-00025916" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Richard Weinshilboum</a>, one of my mentors, says: 'It's about the right drug, at the right dose, for the right patient.' That's what we need to focus on."</p>



<p></p>



<p><em>This article originally was published on the <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center blog.</a></em></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/the-4-types-of-systemic-therapy-for-breast-cancer/">The 4 types of systemic therapy for breast cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/Woman-drinking-coffee-looking-out-the-window-thinking-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/Woman-drinking-coffee-looking-out-the-window-thinking-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Diversity]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Surgical innovations help personalize breast cancer treatment, improve quality of life </title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/surgical-innovations-help-personalize-breast-cancer-treatment-improve-quality-of-life/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sharon Theimer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sarah McLaughlin]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395251</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>October is Breast Cancer Awareness Month&#160;&#160; JACKSONVILLE, Florida — There are two surgical options to treat breast cancer: lumpectomy and&#160;mastectomy. But there are many more reasons why women choose one over another, says Sarah McLaughlin, M.D., a breast surgical oncologist and chair of the Department of Surgery at Mayo Clinic in Jacksonville, Florida. "Some of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/surgical-innovations-help-personalize-breast-cancer-treatment-improve-quality-of-life/">Surgical innovations help personalize breast cancer treatment, improve quality of life </a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Featured_image_Dr_Mclaughlin-operating-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395253" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Featured_image_Dr_Mclaughlin-operating-16x9-1.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Featured_image_Dr_Mclaughlin-operating-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Featured_image_Dr_Mclaughlin-operating-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Sarah McLaughlin in surgery</figcaption></figure>



<p><em>October is Breast Cancer Awareness Month</em><strong>&nbsp;</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>JACKSONVILLE, Florida — There are two surgical options to treat <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a>: <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/lumpectomy/about/pac-20394650" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lumpectomy</a> and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mastectomy/about/pac-20394670" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">mastectomy</a>. But there are many more reasons why women choose one over another, says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mclaughlin-sarah-a-m-d/bio-20055048" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sarah McLaughlin, M.D.</a>, a breast surgical oncologist and chair of the Department of Surgery at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/international" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> in Jacksonville, Florida.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="225" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Sarah-McLaughlin-3x4-1-225x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395256" style="width:256px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Sarah-McLaughlin-3x4-1-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Sarah-McLaughlin-3x4-1.jpg 400w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Sarah McLaughlin, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Some of that can be cancer-based, some of it can be family history and genetic, some of it can be personal peace of mind," Dr. McLaughlin explains.</p>



<p>More than 2 million women&nbsp;are diagnosed with breast cancer every year, according to the <a href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/breast-cancer" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">World Health Organization</a>. Advances in&nbsp;treatment including surgical innovations are helping women and their healthcare teams personalize care and improve quality of life.</p>



<p>Breast cancer treatment involves a surgery to remove the cancer from the breast. It’s often used with other treatments, such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/radiation-therapy-for-breast-cancer/about/pac-20384940" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">radiation therapy</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/chemotherapy-for-breast-cancer/about/pac-20384931" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chemotherapy</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/hormone-therapy-for-breast-cancer/about/pac-20384943#:~:text=Hormone%20therapy%20for%20breast%20cancer%20is%20only%20used,called%20estrogen%20receptor%20positive%2C%20also%20called%20ER%20positive." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hormone therapy</a> and <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2022/06/07/using-targeted-therapy-to-treat-breast-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">targeted therapy</a>. Surgery may also be used to reduce the risk of future cancer.</p>



<p>Surgical options include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Lumpectomy: Removing cancerous tissue and the surrounding margin of normal breast tissue.</li>



<li>Mastectomy: Removing the entire breast.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/sentinel-node-biopsy/about/pac-20385264" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sentinel lymph node biopsy</a>: Removing a few lymph nodes to check whether cancer has spread to them.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/sentinel-lymph-node-axillary-lymph-node-procedures-for-breast-cancer-at-mayo-clinic/vid-20535475" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Axillary lymph node dissection</a>: removing more lymph nodes from under the arm if there is many sentinel lymph nodes with cancer in them.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>



<li>Reconstructive surgery: <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/08/07/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-options-for-breast-reconstruction/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Breast reconstruction</a> following a mastectomy rebuilds the breast.</li>
</ul>



<p>The approaches to all of these options are evolving as knowledge grows. For example, decades of research have shown similar long-term survival rates for lumpectomies and mastectomies, Dr. McLaughlin explains.</p>



<p>"If you don't need a mastectomy, you wouldn’t do better or live longer because you have one,” &nbsp;Dr. McLaughlin says.</p>



<p>Some patients no longer need lymph nodes under the armpit removed.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Contemporary mastectomy techniques focus on removing less skin and preserving the nipple and areola when possible.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In oncoplastic surgery for lumpectomies, surgeons place incisions remote from the actual site of cancer and, after removing cancerous tissue, rearrange the breast tissue that remains to maintain a cosmetically acceptable breast, Dr. McLaughlin says.</p>



<p>Dr. McLaughlin’s research focuses on improving the quality of life for breast cancer survivors. She is contributing to the establishment of a breast organoid biobank at Mayo Clinic using excess breast tissue from volunteers to speed research.</p>



<p>“Breast cancer patients are living longer and longer and longer, so issues of survivorship are becoming much more important,” Dr. McLaughlin says.</p>



<p>One significant issue for breast cancer survivors who have had lymph nodes removed can be <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lymphedema/symptoms-causes/syc-20374682" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymphedema</a>, tissue swelling caused by an accumulation of fluid that usually is removed by lymph nodes. Lymphedema can cause symptoms ranging from mild to severe, including discomfort, swelling, a feeling of tightness or heaviness, limited range of motion, recurring infections and hardened skin.</p>



<p>Dr. McLaughlin’s work includes studies to predict, prevent and improve treatment of lymphedema, including identifying biomarkers and developing tailored treatment strategies.</p>



<p>“There’s a lot of current focus on techniques to reduce the risk of developing lymphedema,” she explains.</p>



<p>Those techniques include axillary reverse mapping, which maps the lymph nodes that drain the arm, separating them from those that drain the breast, allowing the surgeon to remove only those that drain the breast. Another option is reconstructing the lymphatic system if there is extensive lymph node removal.</p>



<p>Lymphedema can be debilitating and a chronic reminder of the cancer treatment, &nbsp;Dr. McLaughlin says.</p>



<p>“The intense focus on management and therapy related to it becomes time-consuming, expensive and painful for patients to manage,” she adds. “We want to try to reduce that as much as possible.”</p>



<p>It's important to work with your healthcare team to determine what treatments are best for you. Considerations may include the stage of cancer, your personal preferences and overall health.</p>



<p>“Our goal is to do as little as possible while achieving the highest level of success, which is long- term survival,” Dr. McLaughlin says.</p>



<p>For more information about breast cancer, visit the <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer-type/breast-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center blog</a>.</p>



<p>###&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> &nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and to providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.  &nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong> &nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Sharon Theimer, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/surgical-innovations-help-personalize-breast-cancer-treatment-improve-quality-of-life/">Surgical innovations help personalize breast cancer treatment, improve quality of life </a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Featured_image_Dr-Mclaughlin-operating_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Featured_image_Dr_Mclaughlin-operating-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Sarah McLaughlin]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: How surgery can reduce breast cancer risk</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-how-surgery-can-reduce-breast-cancer-risk/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chloe Corey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 16:29:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Mary Mrdutt]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395261</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: My mother and sister were both diagnosed with breast cancer. With my family history, when should I consider preventive surgery options, and what do those look like? Are there other risk factors I should be aware of? ANSWER: Given your family history of breast cancer, I'm so glad you want to know [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-how-surgery-can-reduce-breast-cancer-risk/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: How surgery can reduce breast cancer risk</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="737" height="414" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/10/mss_0001606622_Fotor-16x9.jpg" alt="Mayo Clinic breast cancer surgeons in scrubs, operating on a patient" class="wp-image-252437" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/10/mss_0001606622_Fotor-16x9.jpg 737w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/10/mss_0001606622_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 737px) 100vw, 737px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> My mother and sister were both diagnosed with breast cancer. With my family history, when should I consider preventive surgery options, and what do those look like? Are there other risk factors I should be aware of?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong> Given your family history of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a>, I'm so glad you want to know more about reducing breast cancer risk. There are a number of ways you can reduce your risk of getting breast cancer. These can be with surgery, such as a bilateral or double mastectomy, but also with less invasive methods such as healthy lifestyle choices and medication. </p>



<p>An important first step when considering the prevention of breast cancer is <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/breast-cancer-risk-assessment/about/pac-20393195" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">understanding your personal risk</a>. If you have not yet, I would recommend establishing care with a breast health specialist, or healthcare professional comfortable with breast cancer risk prediction counseling. This may be at a dedicated breast clinic, like the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/breast-clinic/sections/overview/ovc-20459469" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Breast Clinic</a>, or with your primary care clinician or OB-GYN. There are an increasing number of programs specifically created for people at high risk for breast cancer, and the healthcare team uses multiple prediction tools to identify your personal risk. Many factors, including age, hormone-related life events such as age of first period, pregnancy and breastfeeding, and prior breast imaging contribute to an individual’s risk. </p>



<p>Genetic counseling is also an important part of determining your personal risk and the benefit you would receive from risk-reducing medication or surgery. I would ask if either your mother or sister has undergone genetic testing and if they are comfortable sharing those results. If not, a genetic counselor will talk through your family tree and ask about each relative and what cancer(s), if any, each relative has had and their age when they developed cancer to help assess your risk. If appropriate, genetic testing will be offered.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Once you know your personal risk of breast cancer, then it is important to discuss both screening and prevention, meaning what you can do to decrease that risk and by how much. Breast clinics and high-risk programs provide recommendations on what type of enhanced screening you should have in the future. Often tests such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/breast-mri/about/pac-20384809" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast MRI</a> are offered in addition to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mammogram/about/pac-20384806" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">traditional mammograms</a>. Your age, risk and characteristics of your breast tissue, such as density, are combined to create a personalized screening plan. </p>



<p>In terms of action items to decrease the risk of breast cancer, we know that a healthy lifestyle can decrease a woman's risk of developing breast cancer or of it coming back after a prior diagnosis. All of us can benefit from being active, maintaining a healthy weight, not smoking and limiting alcohol use. Newer data suggests we need both cardio-based and weightlifting each week to get the most benefit.</p>



<p>There are certain medications that can be taken to reduce a person's risk of breast cancer. These can reduce your personal risk by 50%-70% and are taken daily for multiple years to see that benefit.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Risk-reducing surgery, such as a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mastectomy/about/pac-20394670" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bilateral mastectomy</a>, decreases the chance of getting breast cancer; surgery decreases your personal risk by about 90%-95%. And while extremely effective, not even surgery can completely eliminate the risk of breast cancer. It is important to note that bilateral mastectomy is a permanent change to your body, including appearance and sensation, and the impact on your quality of life, sex life and body image should all be carefully discussed before having surgery. </p>



<p>Risk-reducing surgery can be performed with or without reconstruction. A bilateral total mastectomy removes both breasts without reconstruction and leaves a flat chest wall. You can wear a prosthesis, and prostheses are also available for swimming suits. Breast reconstruction is also a great option for many women, and the process often can be started at the time of the mastectomy. A skin-sparing mastectomy can be performed which preserves the skin envelope of the breast. Nipple-sparing mastectomy is also an option for some women and preserves the skin envelope and the nipple-areola complex. Generally, however, while the nipple is preserved, the sensation is lost from the nipple with a nipple-sparing mastectomy. Newer techniques, including a robotic-assisted approach to nipple-sparing mastectomy, are currently being evaluated.</p>



<p>I would recommend meeting with a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/breast-melanoma-surgical-oncology/sections/overview/ovc-20535267" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast surgical oncologist</a> and a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/plastic-surgery/sections/overview/ovc-20473067" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">reconstructive plastic surgeon</a> to discuss options further.</p>



<p>It's important to note that the decision to take medication or have surgery to reduce your risk of breast cancer is personal. It also is a fluid decision and may change over time. Factors such as menopausal status, desire to have children, and family and work obligations are all important to consider when making these decisions. I'd recommend discussing all these parts of life with your healthcare team.&nbsp;</p>



<p>I commend you for being proactive and exploring your options to reduce your risk of breast cancer. <em>—</em> <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mrdutt-mary-m-m-d-m-s/bio-20523392" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Mary Mrdutt, M.D.</strong></a><strong><em>, Breast and Melanoma Surgical Oncology, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota</em></strong></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-how-surgery-can-reduce-breast-cancer-risk/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: How surgery can reduce breast cancer risk</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/10/mss_0001606622_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/10/mss_0001606622_Fotor-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Mary Mrdutt]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-radiation-therapy-for-patients-with-breast-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 13:58:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Laura Vallow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395065</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Radiation therapy is a common component of breast cancer treatment for patients. The high-powered beams of intense energy kill cancer cells and reduce the risk of the cancer recurring. Dr. Laura Vallow, chair of the Radiation Oncology Department at Mayo Clinic in Florida, explains how innovation is transforming radiation treatments. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-radiation-therapy-for-patients-with-breast-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Radiation therapy is a common component of breast cancer treatment for patients. The high-powered beams of intense energy kill cancer cells and reduce the risk of the cancer recurring.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/vallow-laura-a-m-d/bio-20054004">Dr. Laura Vallow</a>, chair of the Radiation Oncology Department at Mayo Clinic in Florida, explains how innovation is transforming radiation treatments.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/aCjypSH3cZw" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeaCjypSH3cZw"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/aCjypSH3cZw?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:05) is in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/MCM-Radiation-for-web-insert.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Patients with breast cancer now have more options when it comes to radiation treatments. The goal is to remove any remaining cancer cells following chemotherapy or surgery.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"In other situations, we use radiation if the cancer is more advanced, or spread to the lymph nodes," says Dr. Vallow.</p>



<p>Advancements in technology allow healthcare professionals to treat patients more safely. One technique called "prone positioning" reduces the chance of beams targeting other organs. For this procedure, patients lie on their stomachs.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1920" height="1080" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395137" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1.jpg 1920w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" /></figure>



<p>"We take advantage of gravity, the breast pulls away from the body, and we can treat the breast without exposing the underlying lung and heart to unnecessary radiation," explains Dr. Vallow.</p>



<p>Intensity-modulated radiation therapy is cutting-edge. Unlike traditional radiation, this procedure delivers X-rays directly to the targeted area from multiple angles, allowing for higher, more effective doses.</p>



<p>"Before intensity-modulated radiation therapy, we were not able to conform the dose around the chest wall," says Dr. Vallow.</p>



<p>For patients undergoing radiation therapy, it's crucial to stay hydrated and try to sleep well to fight fatigue. It's also important to use sunscreen after treatment.</p>



<p><strong>Related Posts:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-study-reveals-proton-beam-therapy-may-shorten-breast-cancer-treatment/">Mayo Clinic study reveals proton beam therapy may shorten breast cancer treatment</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-breaking-through-radiation-therapy-myths/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Breaking through radiation therapy myths</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-radiation-therapy-for-patients-with-breast-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/patient-receiving-external-beam-radiation-therapy_GettyImages-108270897_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/01/a-medical-illustration-of-radiation-therapy-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Laura Vallow]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cheryl Robinson volunteering on the same floor where her husband received cancer care</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/cheryl-robinson-volunteering-on-the-same-floor-where-her-husband-received-cancer-care/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Osiadacz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sikander Ailawadhi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395022</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Blink and you'll miss Cheryl Robinson going in and out of rooms and preparing each for patients. Her speed is matched by her dedication as a volunteer and the compassion shown toward those seeking care on the Hematology/Oncology floor in Florida. A former commercial insurance professional, Cheryl’s journey took a heartfelt turn when she became [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/cheryl-robinson-volunteering-on-the-same-floor-where-her-husband-received-cancer-care/">Cheryl Robinson volunteering on the same floor where her husband received cancer care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="579" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/SELECTED_Cheryl-Robinson_16x9-1024x579.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395030" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/SELECTED_Cheryl-Robinson_16x9-1024x579.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/SELECTED_Cheryl-Robinson_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/SELECTED_Cheryl-Robinson_16x9-768x434.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/SELECTED_Cheryl-Robinson_16x9-1536x868.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/SELECTED_Cheryl-Robinson_16x9-2048x1157.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Cheryl Robinson volunteering in Florida.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Blink and you'll miss Cheryl Robinson going in and out of rooms and preparing each for patients. Her speed is matched by her dedication as a volunteer and the compassion shown toward those seeking care on the Hematology/Oncology floor in Florida.</p>



<p>A former commercial insurance professional, Cheryl’s journey took a heartfelt turn when she became a caregiver to her husband, <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/back-to-the-drawing-table-thanks-to-individualized-care-for-blood-cancer/">Jim Robinson</a>. Their love story, rooted in shared struggles and triumphs, inspired Cheryl’s commitment to volunteerism at Mayo Clinic, where Jim once received his care.</p>



<p>"I just remember walking into the clinic the first time and thinking, 'Wow, when I retire, I want to volunteer at Mayo and wear that smock,'" says Cheryl.</p>



<p>Cheryl and Jim’s bond was fortified through adversity. Jim, who bravely navigated the challenges of global aphasia and leukemia, found solace and expression in drawing. His artwork became a symbol of hope for Cheryl, who supported him unwaveringly. The couple’s daily routine, punctuated by Jim’s 7 a.m. drawing sessions, was a testament to their resilience.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Volunteering at Mayo Clinic</h2>



<p>The loss of Jim in the fall of 2023 left a void in Cheryl’s life, but it also planted the seeds of a new purpose. After retiring in January 2024, she followed her dream and became a Mayo Clinic volunteer.</p>



<p>"Going to work was an outlet for me, and being a caretaker gave me a feeling of being appreciated,” says Cheryl. "I knew I needed those things in my life, so to find that volunteering at Mayo Clinic has been fulfilling."</p>



<p>Cheryl’s presence on Mangurian 3, where she volunteers four hours weekly, is more than just a helping hand; it’s a legacy in the making. Her tasks are straightforward yet vital: prepping rooms, stocking supplies and cleaning. These actions are reminiscent of the care she saw while taking Jim to appointments.</p>



<p>"Over the years, I would see Cheryl with her husband while he went through treatment for leukemia, then follow-ups when he went into remission," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/ailawadhi-sikander-m-d/bio-20087330" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sikander Ailawadhi, M.D.</a>, Hematology/Oncology. "I've seen Cheryl transform from her husband's caretaker to really providing care and service to our patients and staff. It's a remarkable and selfless gift."</p>



<p>Staff recognize her dedication, and she finds joy in the difference she makes, honoring Jim’s memory and serving others. As she moves through Mayo Clinic, memories of Jim, especially her interactions with his former care team members, stir deep emotions and strengthen her resolve to serve.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic volunteers</strong></p>



<p>Mayo Clinic Volunteer Services is a group of talented, giving and compassionate people who offer comfort and support to Mayo Clinic's patients and visitors.</p>



<p><a href="https://volunteer.mayoclinic.org/custom/527/volunteer_home">Apply</a> to become a Mayo Clinic volunteer.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/cheryl-robinson-volunteering-on-the-same-floor-where-her-husband-received-cancer-care/">Cheryl Robinson volunteering on the same floor where her husband received cancer care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/SELECTED_Cheryl-Robinson-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/SELECTED_Cheryl-Robinson_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Sikander Ailawadhi]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[volunteer]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Gynecologic cancers: 4 affirmations to help you advocate for yourself</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/gynecologic-cancers-4-affirmations-to-help-you-advocate-for-yourself/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jessica Saenz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 15:41:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Kristina Butler]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395162</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Gynecologic exams might not top the list of things you look forward to, but whether it's for a wellness visit or a new concern, such exams are critical for detecting gynecologic cancers early when they are most treatable. Gynecologic cancers include&#160;endometrial,&#160;ovarian,&#160;cervical,&#160;vulvar&#160;and&#160;vaginal cancer. Gynecology visits should provide a valuable opportunity for you to ask questions, raise [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/gynecologic-cancers-4-affirmations-to-help-you-advocate-for-yourself/">Gynecologic cancers: 4 affirmations to help you advocate for yourself</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="938" height="527" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Woman-Stretching-eyeem-100068071-184616174_16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395168" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Woman-Stretching-eyeem-100068071-184616174_16x9.jpg 938w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Woman-Stretching-eyeem-100068071-184616174_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Woman-Stretching-eyeem-100068071-184616174_16x9-768x431.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 938px) 100vw, 938px" /></figure>



<p>Gynecologic exams might not top the list of things you look forward to, but whether it's for a wellness visit or a new concern, such exams are critical for detecting gynecologic cancers early when they are most treatable. Gynecologic cancers include&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/endometrial-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352461" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">endometrial</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/ovarian-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20375941" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ovarian</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cervical-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352501" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cervical</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/vulvar-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20368051" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">vulvar</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cervical-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352501" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">vaginal cancer</a>.</p>



<p>Gynecology visits should provide a valuable opportunity for you to ask questions, raise concerns and learn about your body from an expert who prioritizes your health and well-being. But if you've had difficulty getting answers, accessing the care you need or your experiences haven't been positive, these visits can cause some anxiety.</p>



<p>Learning how to advocate for your gynecologic health might help you feel more prepared for your next appointment, says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/butler-kristina-a-m-d-m-s/bio-20110364" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kristina Butler, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic gynecologic oncologist. This is what she wants you to know:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">You deserve a trusting relationship with your gynecologist.</h2>



<p>Trust is a critical part of the patient-clinician relationship. It allows you to have frank and open discussions with your gynecologist and alert them to significant details that might affect your care.</p>



<p>"Gynecologic cancers are difficult to talk about because they involve parts of the body that we don't routinely discuss with other people," says Dr. Butler. "It can be difficult for a patient to bring up, for example, that they have pain in their vulva."</p>



<p>If you don't feel comfortable or confident expressing concerns like these to your gynecologist, there's a risk that serious conditions like gynecologic cancers could be missed. If you don't feel heard, Dr. Butler says it's OK to look for someone who is a better fit for your needs. Recommendations from friends and family can often be a good starting point.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">You are the expert on your body.</h2>



<p>When changes happen in your body, you might be the first — and often the only one — to notice. Informing your gynecologist of these changes helps them gain a more accurate understanding of your health and alerts them to anything that might require additional examination.</p>



<p>As life gets busy, it can be easy to overlook or dismiss certain changes, but Dr. Butler stresses the importance of being in tune with your body. "This means understanding what's normal for you. That can be difficult because everyone's 'normal' is a little bit different," she says. "If something is repetitive and doesn't feel right, it's important to talk about it."</p>



<p>While each gynecologic cancer has symptoms associated with it, some symptoms overlap. If you're experiencing any symptoms associated with gynecologic cancer, Dr. Butler says it's important to talk to a clinician who specializes in gynecologic health, especially if you don't feel your questions have been answered by your primary care physician. "Many gynecologic cancers have vague symptoms. Often, patients share symptoms with a provider who isn't a gynecologist, but it's important that they voice their concerns to multiple providers until they get the answers they need to know that they're safe," she says.</p>



<p>Symptoms you should always discuss with your healthcare professional include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Abnormal vaginal bleeding:</strong> Bleeding between periods, prolonged bleeding or any bleeding that occurs after menopause.</li>



<li><strong>Pelvic pain or discomfort: </strong>Pain or pressure in your pelvic area — the area of the body below the abdomen located between the hip bones.</li>



<li><strong>Early satiety: </strong>Feeling full after eating a small amount of food.</li>



<li><strong>Vulvar discomfort or itching: </strong>Pain, discomfort or itching in the vulva, which includes all the structures that make up the exterior genitals.</li>
</ul>



<p>"Many providers care for the pelvic area, and this can begin with your primary care physician, but may also progress to a gynecologist, urologist or gastroenterologist," adds Dr. Butler. "We can collaborate together for your best outcome."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">You have the right to be informed about your health.</h2>



<p>Staying informed about your health can help you relay information to your healthcare professional and better prepare for appointments. Dr. Butler says you can do this in various ways.</p>



<p>"It's always helpful for patients to have a timeline. I am a proponent of having lists — lists of medications, surgeries, diagnoses and family history, which is tremendously important. All of this is lengthy and can be confusing or forgotten so keeping a timeline and a list of these things can help focus the visit," says Dr. Butler.</p>



<p>Dr. Butler recommends you&nbsp;<a href="https://www.healthit.gov/how-to-get-your-health-record/get-it/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">take ownership of your medical records</a>&nbsp;so you can share them with your healthcare team. "Your healthcare information — reports, pathology, surgical information, radiology imaging including discs of viewable pictures — you own that. You are allowed to have access to that information through medical record departments. It's your right, and I empower patients to keep those for themselves and carry these items with you on your visits."</p>



<p>As you seek to learn more about your health, Dr. Butler says it's important to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nia.nih.gov/health/healthy-aging/how-find-reliable-health-information-online" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">find reliable health information</a>. "Access to the internet is tremendously valuable for educating ourselves. However, we have to be careful about the resources from which we obtain information. Websites and blogs with inaccurate or completely false information can be anxiety-provoking and sometimes dangerous."</p>



<p>Dr. Butler recommends starting with these sites:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://www.nccn.org/patientresources/patient-resources" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Comprehensive Cancer Network</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/obstetrics-gynecology/sections/conditions-treated/orc-20423744" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.cancer.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Cancer Society</a></li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">You are allowed to ask for a second opinion.</h2>



<p>You have the right to seek a second opinion, and, Dr. Butler says, your gynecologist should never discourage you from doing so. "I find it concerning when a provider is bothered by a second opinion because patients have a right to formulate the best decision for themselves," she says.</p>



<p>You might wish to seek a second opinion for many reasons, including:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>You feel your symptoms have been dismissed.</li>



<li>You are unclear on your diagnosis.</li>



<li>You are unsure of your treatment options.</li>



<li>You don't feel comfortable with the treatments recommended.</li>



<li>You have unanswered questions.</li>



<li>You don't feel you can trust your physician.</li>
</ul>



<p>Regardless of your reason, it's your choice and part of your right to advocate for yourself. "I encourage my patients to ask for second opinions because it's the best way to know that they're making the right decision for themselves," says Dr. Butler.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Learn more</h2>



<p>Learn more about&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/endometrial-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352461" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">endometrial</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/ovarian-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20375941" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ovarian</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cervical-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352501" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cervical</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/vulvar-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20368051" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">vulvar</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cervical-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352501" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">vaginal</a>&nbsp;cancers, and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials/search-results?keyword=gynecology&amp;studySiteStatusesGrouped=Open/Status%20Unknown" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">find a clinical trial</a>&nbsp;at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>Join the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/gynecologic-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gynecologic Cancers Support Group</a>&nbsp;on&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Connect</a>, an online community moderated by Mayo Clinic for patients and caregivers.</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/09/25/gynecologic-cancers-4-affirmations-to-help-you-advocate-for-yourself/">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/gynecologic-cancers-4-affirmations-to-help-you-advocate-for-yourself/">Gynecologic cancers: 4 affirmations to help you advocate for yourself</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Woman-Stretching-eyeem-100068071-184616174_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Woman-Stretching-eyeem-100068071-184616174_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Kristina Butler]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Health screenings in underserved populations</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-health-screenings-in-underserved-populations/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 14:23:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jesse Bracamonte]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=393520</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Cancer is a leading cause of death among Hispanic people in the U.S., according to the&#160;American Cancer Society. Compared to non-Hispanic white people, Hispanic men and women are less likely to be diagnosed with common cancers such as lung, colorectal, breast and prostate cancer, and they are more likely to develop cancers in the liver, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-health-screenings-in-underserved-populations/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Health screenings in underserved populations</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Cancer is a leading cause of death among Hispanic people in the U.S., according to the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.org/research/cancer-facts-statistics/hispanics-latinos-facts-figures.html">American Cancer Society</a>. Compared to non-Hispanic white people, Hispanic men and women are less likely to be diagnosed with common cancers such as lung, colorectal, breast and prostate cancer, and they are more likely to develop cancers in the liver, stomach and cervix, often linked to infections like HPV.</p>



<p>Early detection through screening can prevent serious health issues.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/bracamonte-jesse-d-d-o/bio-20432246">Dr. Jesse Bracamonte</a>, a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician, stresses the need for healthcare workers to discuss the importance of health screenings with patients, especially in&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-health-disparities-in-gynecologic-cancers/">underserved communities</a>.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=F7SzmGYjja4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidF7SzmGYjja4"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Health screenings in underserved communities" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/F7SzmGYjja4?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (:59) is in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/SCRIPT-MCM-Health-screenings-in-underserved-communities.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"Educating underrepresented groups is very important to prevent cancer," says Dr. Bracamonte.</p>



<p>He says some groups of people, including those in the Hispanic community, have higher rates of disease because they may not be getting the proper screenings.</p>



<p>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-who-should-be-screened-for-colorectal-cancer-2/">Colon cancer screening,</a>&nbsp;breast cancer screening, cervical cancer screening, screening for heart disease are all very important because those things are very predominant in our culture, in our society, and if caught early, it can be prevented," Dr. Bracamonte explains.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Health screenings</h2>



<p>The type of health screening depends on a person's age and gender.</p>



<p>"For example, colorectal cancer screening is, at age 45, looking for colon cancer. Cervical cancer screenings, such as Pap tests, we start at 21 in females," he says.</p>



<p>Breast cancer screening is recommended to start at age 40, and regular blood pressure checks can help monitor overall health.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374577" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p>"One of the most important things that you can do is see your clinician, minimum, probably once a year, based on your age level, which is really important to stay healthy and stay out of the doctor’s office," says Dr. Bracamonte.</p>



<p><strong>Related posts:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-closing-the-gaps-in-cancer-care/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Closing the gaps in cancer care</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-breaking-healthcare-barriers-in-the-hispanic-community/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Breaking healthcare barriers in the Hispanic community</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-health-screenings-in-underserved-populations/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Health screenings in underserved populations</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Getty-Hispanic-family-man-woman-daughter-adult-1-x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Getty-Hispanic-family-man-woman-daughter-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Diversity]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jesse Bracamonte]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>