<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2023 19:44:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Identifying new potential in cancer-killing T cells</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/identifying-new-potential-in-cancer-killing-t-cells/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kate Ledger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Joanina Gicobi]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=378084</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>When Joanina Gicobi began her Ph.D. degree five years ago at Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences, she was interested in thinking creatively about ways to improve cancer treatment. In particular, she was curious about the body's natural ability to fight tumors: Could that process be improved? In the laboratory of Haidong Dong, M.D., Ph.D., she [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/identifying-new-potential-in-cancer-killing-t-cells/">Identifying new potential in cancer-killing T cells</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="500" height="282" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Cancer-t-cells-mRNA-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378089" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Cancer-t-cells-mRNA-16x9-1.jpg 500w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Cancer-t-cells-mRNA-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></figure>



<p>When Joanina Gicobi began her Ph.D. degree five years ago at <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a>, she was interested in thinking creatively about ways to improve <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer treatment</a>. In particular, she was curious about the body's natural ability to fight tumors: Could that process be improved? In the laboratory of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/dong-haidong-m-d-ph-d/bio-20055136" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Haidong Dong, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, she joined efforts to learn more about the T cells that are part of an inherent cancer-killing immune response.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img decoding="async" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Joanina_Gicobi-250x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378091" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Joanina_Gicobi-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Joanina_Gicobi.jpg 667w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Joanina Gicobi, Ph.D.,</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"From the beginning, she was asking impressive questions about an issue that's been a great challenge," says Dr. Dong, whose lab focuses on cancer immunology and immunotherapy.</p>



<p>The inquisitive approach to problem-solving paid off. Dr. Gicobi, who recently completed her Ph.D. thesis, Dr. Dong and a team of Mayo Clinic researchers have provided a new understanding of the body’s cancer-fighting T cells, known as CD8<sup>+</sup>&nbsp;T cells. In&nbsp;<a href="http://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adi2414" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Science Advances</a>, the research team describes a previously unknown type of CD8<sup>+</sup>&nbsp;T cells that can withstand the toxicity of treatments like chemotherapy and radiation therapy. The cells, which they call resilient T cells, remain functional, suggesting there may be additional opportunity after chemotherapy and radiotherapy to target the cancer via the immune system. What's more, the team identified a potential strategy to bolster the cancer-killing capabilities of these hardy cells.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Scrutinizing cells that survive</strong></h2>



<p>One detail that has baffled researchers about CD8<sup>+</sup>&nbsp;T cells is their persistence, particularly in patients who seem to have run out of treatment options.</p>



<p>Some people with advanced cancer undergo what’s known as "salvage therapy" to ease late-stage symptoms. Salvage therapy may include chemotherapy and radiotherapy to shrink tumors that are not responding to immunotherapy or are too large to remove surgically, though the treatments are typically not expected to be a cure. However, researchers had noticed that even after several rounds of therapies that kill off immune cells along with the cancer, some patients sometimes still had cancer-killing CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells circulating in their blood. And those cells, however beaten down, seemed capable of rallying an immune response.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Haidong_Dong-300x200.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378092" style="width:332px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Haidong_Dong-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Haidong_Dong-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Haidong_Dong.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Haidong Dong, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"But we didn't know the nature of these particular CD8<sup>+</sup>&nbsp;T cells, how to identify them or what might make them unique," Dr. Dong says, adding that the lab hit numerous dead ends as they tried to characterize the cells. "It was not a straightforward route as we searched for answers."</p>



<p>The team monitored a cohort of patients who underwent salvage radiotherapy and then examined those patients' T cells. People who responded better to radiotherapy had T cells that used cellular energy most efficiently and could still kill cancer cells. Somehow the cells were less "exhausted" than other T cells. However, the phenotype didn't fully distinguish what was special about the cells.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Following the data</strong></h2>



<p>In her research, Dr. Gicobi set out to look for molecular markers particular to the T cells that rebound after cancer treatment. Using RNA sequencing, which can provide a map of all potential gene expression in a cell, she came across interesting findings that pointed back to certain genes. Dr. Gicobi noted several genes that were slightly different from those in typical CD8<sup>+</sup>&nbsp;T cells. Among them, she found a gene related to the cells' metabolic pathway, the process by which the cells produce and burn energy. This aligned with the earlier finding, and Dr. Gicobi felt encouraged to delve into the metabolism of the cells as a key differentiator.</p>



<p>"Dr. Dong has told me through my training, 'Always follow the data,'" Dr. Gicobi says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Cancer-T-cells-Dong-mRNA1x1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378090" style="width:214px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Cancer-T-cells-Dong-mRNA1x1.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Cancer-T-cells-Dong-mRNA1x1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">A confocal microscopy image of resilient T cells over-expressing the enzyme ME1.<br></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>As the team members looked further, they found the cells had heightened expression of the enzyme called malic enzyme 1, or ME1. "That was really interesting to us because ME1 is known to deal with molecules called reactive oxygen species, a metabolic byproduct that is important for the functions of immune cells but toxic when in excess. So we were looking at an enzyme that helps reduce the negative effects of metabolic pathways," she says. The finding helped confirm that the resilient T cells in people are a distinct subgroup of CD8<sup>+</sup>&nbsp;T cells.</p>



<p>Then, Dr. Gicobi had the idea that tinkering with ME1 to address the function and energy of immune cells might heighten their response to a tumor.&nbsp;</p>



<p>She engineered the resilient T cells to overproduce ME1. The laboratory experiments found the increase of ME1 revived the cells and made them even better at killing off tumor cells.&nbsp; Importantly, Dr. Gicobi says, "We were able to increase their cancer-killing capacity without the accumulation of reactive oxygen species that induce cellular exhaustion."&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>During her graduate training, Dr. Gicobi presented the findings at the annual meeting of the American Association of Immunologists.</p>



<p>Says Dr. Dong, "The excitement and the questions from attendees were a sign that this work suggests new approaches and more options for improving T cell health, which is an important avenue for the field."</p>



<p>He says further research is necessary to determine how resilient T cells affect patient outcomes and why some people have resilient T cells and others don't. He also hopes to learn more about the mechanisms underlying the function of resilient T cells and to explore the potential development of ME1 as a therapy.</p>



<p>But an important first step has been the understanding that the presence of resilient T cells indicates the perseverance of the body's inherent immune response. "This is one milestone toward new discoveries that can hopefully be translated to help patients," he says.</p>



<p>The study was supported with funding from <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine</a>; <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-biomedical-discovery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Center for Biomedical Discovery</a>; <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>; and the National Institutes of Health.</p>



<p>This article first published on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/11/15/identifying-new-potential-in-cancer-killing-t-cells/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/identifying-new-potential-in-cancer-killing-t-cells/">Identifying new potential in cancer-killing T cells</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Cancer-T-cells-Dong-mRNA1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Cancer-t-cells-mRNA-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Joanina Gicobi]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic expert on future of HIV on World AIDS Day</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-expert-of-future-of-hiv-on-world-aids-day/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 16:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Infectious Diseases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Stacey Rizza]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HIV screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HIV/AIDS]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377663</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>World AIDS Day, observed on Dec. 1, raises awareness about HIV/AIDS and pays tribute to those affected by the disease. Globally, about 39 million people are living with HIV infection, according to the World Health Organization.  HIV is the virus that causes the condition. The virus can spread through sexual contact, sharing infected needles and, less commonly, it can pass [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-expert-of-future-of-hiv-on-world-aids-day/">Mayo Clinic expert on future of HIV on World AIDS Day</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>World AIDS Day, observed on Dec. 1, raises awareness about <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hiv-aids/symptoms-causes/syc-20373524" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">HIV/AIDS</a> and pays tribute to those affected by the disease. Globally, about 39 million people are living with HIV infection, <a href="https://www.who.int/teams/global-hiv-hepatitis-and-stis-programmes/hiv/strategic-information/hiv-data-and-statistics" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">according</a> to the World Health Organization. </p>



<p>HIV is the virus that causes the condition. The virus can spread through sexual contact, sharing infected needles and, less commonly, it can pass from mother to child. </p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/rizza-stacey-a-m-d/bio-20054180?_ga=2.14289719.1803138945.1623070888-731220084.1621949447?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Stacey Rizza</a>, a Mayo Clinic infectious diseases physician and HIV researcher, says that, while there has been much progress in fighting the infectious disease, HIV continues to be prevalent in "virtually every continent, every country, every religion and every socioeconomic class." That's one of the reasons she'd like to see universal <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-know-your-status-the-importance-of-hiv-testing/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">screening</a> of all people who come to a healthcare facility.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/ZY7mhwo9JY0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Stacey Rizza talks about future of HIV on World AIDS Day</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeZY7mhwo9JY0"  title="Mayo Clinic expert of future of HIV on World AIDS Day" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZY7mhwo9JY0?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites with Dr. Rizza are in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy "Stacey Rizza, M.D. / Infectious Diseases / Mayo Clinic."</strong></p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">How HIV affects the body</h3>



<p>The virus harms the body's immune system, affecting its ability to fight infections and diseases.</p>



<p>"The problem with HIV is it kills part of our immune cells, called the CD4 cell. And that makes people vulnerable to getting infections as well as cancers. It can hide away in the body in a latent state for many years. And that's why it's so difficult to cure HIV," she says. </p>



<p>"People may feel fine, but they're slowly living with the virus killing part of the immune system. And when the immune system gets low, people get significant and serious infections and cancers," Dr. Rizza adds.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">HIV in society</h3>



<p>Though people with HIV now enjoy longer and healthier lives due to improved treatments, the challenges of curbing the ongoing HIV epidemic persist.</p>



<p>How to protect yourself from HIV:</p>



<ul>
<li>Practice safe sex.</li>



<li>Don't inject drugs, don't share needles or other drug injection devices.</li>



<li>Get tested.</li>
</ul>



<p>Anyone who suspects exposure through sexual contact, needle use or workplace incidents should reach out to their healthcare team or visit the emergency department. </p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Goal of treatment</h3>



<p>"Our goal is to diagnose people before they get to AIDS — to diagnose them when they have early-stage HIV, get them on treatment early on before the immune system is hurt, before the virus hurts any other part of the body and before they can infect other people," Dr. Rizza says. "If you start treatment during HIV at some point in the spectrum and you're stabilized, the virus is suppressed, and the immune system goes back to a normal level."</p>



<div class="wp-block-media-text has-media-on-the-right is-stacked-on-mobile"><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p>"I wait for the day that we can cure most of our patients rather than treat most of our patients."</p><cite>STACEY RIZZA, M.D.</cite></blockquote></figure>
</div><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="683" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Stacey-Rizza-MD-683x1024.jpg" alt="Portrait of Stacey Rizza, M.D., Mayo Clinic Infectious Diseases, HIV/AIDS researcher " class="wp-image-377758 size-full" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Stacey-Rizza-MD-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Stacey-Rizza-MD-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Stacey-Rizza-MD.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 683px) 100vw, 683px" /></figure></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Hope for HIV cure</h3>



<p>There's no universal cure for HIV/AIDS, but medications can help control it and stop it from getting worse. These antiviral treatments have cut down AIDS deaths worldwide.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Research and hope for a cure continues, says Dr. Rizza. </p>



<p>"Every year, we see a few more people get functionally cured of HIV, which means they've gone through some kind of intervention that they no longer need to take the pills, but the virus stays completely suppressed. At Mayo Clinic, we are doing research on HIV cure. And several other places around the world are doing this research. And it's incredibly exciting," she says.</p>



<p></p>



<p>Read about the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/hiv-clinic/overview/ovc-20457114" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic HIV Clinic</a></p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/hiv-research-provided-foundation-for-covid-19-research/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">HIV research provided foundation for COVID-19 research</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/forty-years-of-hiv-aids-will-the-epidemic-end/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Forty years of HIV/AIDS: Will the epidemic end?</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-expert-of-future-of-hiv-on-world-aids-day/">Mayo Clinic expert on future of HIV on World AIDS Day</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/11/World-AIDS-Day-logo-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/11/World-AIDS-Day-logo-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Stacey Rizza]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[HIV screening]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[HIV/AIDS]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Infectious Diseases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Innovation in lung cancer screening, treatment</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/innovation-in-lung-cancer-screening-treatment/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 16:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic News Network Video Pkg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bronchoscopy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Janani Reisenauer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lung Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[robotic bronchoscopy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377708</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Lung cancer is the largest cancer killer of adult men and women worldwide. One of the reasons is that by the time symptoms develop, the cancer is too advanced for a cure. The goal of lung cancer screening is to detect cancer at an earlier stage and save more lives. Smoking is the No. 1 [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/innovation-in-lung-cancer-screening-treatment/">Innovation in lung cancer screening, treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lung-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20374620?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lung cancer</a> is the largest cancer killer of adult men and women worldwide. One of the reasons is that by the time symptoms develop, the cancer is too advanced for a cure.</p>



<p>The goal of <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-expert-on-the-importance-of-lung-cancer-screening/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lung cancer screening</a> is to detect cancer at an earlier stage and save more lives. Smoking is the No. 1 cause of lung cancer, and it's recommended that anyone over 55 who has a significant history of smoking, even if they no longer smoke, should be screened.</p>



<p>Lung cancer screening, for those eligible, should be done annually, and it involves a low-dose CT scan of the lungs. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/reisenauer-janani-s-m-d/bio-20433096?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Janani Reisenauer</a>, a thoracic surgeon and interventional pulmonologist, says Mayo Clinic is one of the pioneers in using new technology to fight the disease.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/VaqcSTBWnfw" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Innovation in lung cancer screening, treatment</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeVaqcSTBWnfw"  title="Innovation in lung cancer screening, treatment" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VaqcSTBWnfw?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:22) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/SCRIPT-Innovation-in-lung-cancer-screening-and-treatment.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>A lung nodule or lesion is an abnormality revealed on a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ct-scan/about/pac-20393675?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CT scan</a> that looks like a cancer. And to find out if it is cancer, doctors may recommend a technique called <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bronchoscopy/about/pac-20384746?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bronchoscopy</a>.</p>



<p>"Very similar to having a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/colonoscopy/about/pac-20393569?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colonoscopy</a> performed where somebody is holding a scope. They're twisting the dials on that scope as they're maneuvering that scope through your airway or through your intestines for example," says Dr. Reisenauer.</p>



<p>That's a traditional manual bronchoscopy. Dr. Reisenauer says Mayo Clinic is one of only a handful of medical centers approved by the Food and Drug Administration to use robotic bronchoscopy.</p>



<p>"I would think about robotic bronchoscopy as a remote-controlled car. It doesn't go anywhere without you driving it and telling it where to go. But rather than me holding a scope that's maneuvered through a patient, the scope is docked to a robotic instrument," says Dr. Reisenauer.</p>



<p>Offering more precision, flexibility and control than a traditional bronchoscopy. She says it improves the ability to not only diagnose lung cancer, but now, in some cases, treat it.</p>



<p>"Mayo Clinic is participating in many cancer trials now, where we are treating lung nodules with a variety of ablative mechanisms. So we're either using extreme heat or cold, or even in some cases electricity. Or viruses injecting into tumors to try to reduce tumor burden or kill tumors," says Dr. Reisenauer.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/innovation-in-lung-cancer-screening-treatment/">Innovation in lung cancer screening, treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/09/a-medical-illustration-of-a-CT-lung-cancer-screening-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/09/16-x-9-lung-CT.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[bronchoscopy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Janani Reisenauer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Lung Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[robotic bronchoscopy]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Unleashing viruses aimed at killing cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/unleashing-viruses-aimed-at-killing-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Buckles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CAR-T cell therapy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Richard Vile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[viruses]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377675</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>During breaks from his doctoral research in London, Richard Vile, Ph.D., would visit a pediatric brain tumor clinic next to his lab for inspiration. Seeing children suffer changed the course of his career, igniting his passion for finding cancer treatments that would be easier for people to tolerate. "I became very, very motivated to try and apply the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/unleashing-viruses-aimed-at-killing-cancer/">Unleashing viruses aimed at killing cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/07/a-medical-illustation-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-T-CAR-T-cell-therapy-16X9.jpg" alt="a medical illustation of chimeric antigen receptor-T (CAR-T) cell therapy" class="wp-image-343592" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/07/a-medical-illustation-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-T-CAR-T-cell-therapy-16X9.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/07/a-medical-illustation-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-T-CAR-T-cell-therapy-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/07/a-medical-illustation-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-T-CAR-T-cell-therapy-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p>During breaks from his doctoral research in London, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/vile-richard-g-ph-d/bio-00027663" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Richard Vile, Ph.D.</a>, would visit a pediatric brain tumor clinic next to his lab for inspiration. Seeing children suffer changed the course of his career, igniting his passion for finding <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer</a> treatments that would be easier for people to tolerate.</p>



<p>"I became very, very motivated to try and apply the science I learned to make cancer treatments gentler," says Dr. Vile. "My goal was to deliver an option that would extend and improve quality of life."</p>



<p>Decades later, Dr. Vile is leading research into genetically engineered viruses aimed at unleashing a two-pronged attack on cancer. One part of this technology, known as an <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/cancer/news/oncolytic-virus-optimizes-car-t-cell-therapy-for-solid-tumors/mac-20537878" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">oncolytic virus</a>, is designed to infect, break open and destroy cancer cells while sparing healthy tissue. Dr. Vile's <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/scitranslmed.abn2231" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">preclinical studies</a> have shown that oncolytic viruses replicated in cancer cells and cascaded to kill other diseased cells. That, in turn, triggered an immune response in which the patient’s own T cells, stimulated by the virus, recognized and targeted metastasized tumors for a second wave of cancer destruction.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="533" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Vile_1620845_3874783_0005.jpg" alt="Richard Vile, Ph.D." class="wp-image-377676" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Vile_1620845_3874783_0005.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Vile_1620845_3874783_0005-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Vile_1620845_3874783_0005-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Richard Vile, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure>



<p>"Oncolytic viruses are a way to alert the immune system and mobilize it to kill cells infected with cancer," says Dr. Vile. "There's the direct killing of cancer cells with the virus, and then there's the major effect of immune activation. The immune system is incredibly well evolved to recognize infection, clear infection and kill all the cells around it that could be harboring infection."</p>



<p>In groundbreaking research, Dr. Vile's team is combining oncolytic viruses with&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/car-t-cell-therapy-program/home/orc-20404317" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chimeric antigen receptor T-cell therapy (CAR-T cell therapy</a>) to target solid tumors from liver cancer. This experimental approach of loading CAR-T cells with oncolytic virus is a new way to expand CAR-T cell therapy beyond treatment for blood cancers into treatment for solid tumors.</p>



<p>CAR-T cell therapy is a regenerative immunotherapy in which a patient's T-cells are genetically modified to recognize and stop cancer. It has shown great promise by putting some B-cell lymphomas and leukemias into remission. CAR-T cells are highly targeted to tumor cells, with the goal of having fewer side effects than cancer treatments that also kill nearby healthy tissue.</p>



<p>"Loading the oncolytic virus onto CAR-T cells may give us three levels of killing. First, the CAR-T cells target the tumor and kill some of the cells," says Dr. Vile. "Next, it delivers the oncolytic virus, which infects tumor cells, replicates and kills them. Third, that alerts the immune system of the patient to the fact that there's something majorly wrong. The immune system starts to see the cancer and starts to react against it and kill it."</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic's&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</a>&nbsp;supports Dr. Vile's research as part of its objective of delivering new cell therapies to people with complex disorders such as cancer.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Addressing the challenges</strong></h2>



<p>Oncolytic viruses are advancing from the lab to first-in-human clinical trials. Dr. Vile is working with the Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics to biomanufacture oncolytic viruses onsite in Mayo Clinic's Current Good Manufacturing Practices (CGMP) facilities. CGMP facilities are sterile rooms that help ensure that the therapy meets the identity, strength, quality and purity standards that the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) requires for testing new therapeutics.</p>



<p>On-site biomanufacturing could lower production costs, allow for more individualized treatment and deliver the treatment to patients sooner than might be possible with an outside manufacturer.</p>



<p>"We are completing our studies in the lab and are transitioning to safety studies in the patient," explained Dr. Vile. "At the same time, we will manufacture the virus at a level of cleanliness (sterility) to meet FDA standards."</p>



<p>Oncolytic virus therapy is evolving, with more research needed to validate its safety and effectiveness. Dr. Vile hopes to test oncolytic viruses with CAR-T cell therapy for liver cancer in a phase 1 clinical trial in the next year or two.</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://regenerativemedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/11/10/unleashing-viruses-aimed-at-killing-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Regenerative Medicine blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/unleashing-viruses-aimed-at-killing-cancer/">Unleashing viruses aimed at killing cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/07/a-medical-illustation-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-T-CAR-T-cell-therapy-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/07/a-medical-illustation-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-T-CAR-T-cell-therapy-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[CAR-T cell therapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Richard Vile]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[viruses]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: GERD is not &#8216;just&#8217; heartburn</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-gerd-is-not-just-heartburn/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[acid reflux]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Alex Osiadacz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barrett's Esophagus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. James East]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[esophageal adenocarcinoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[esophagitis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[esophagus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gastroesophageal reflux disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GERD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[heartburn]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Proton Pump Inhibitors]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[treatment]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=352736</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD) is one of the most common digestive disorders in the world. It happens when acid comes up from the stomach, which is acid-resistant, into the esophagus, which is less acid-resistant. Dr. James East, a gastroenterologist at Mayo Clinic Healthcare in London, says GERD may be common, but there can be potentially [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-gerd-is-not-just-heartburn/">Mayo Clinic Minute: GERD is not &#8216;just&#8217; heartburn</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/gerd/symptoms-causes/syc-20361940?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD)</a> is one of the most common digestive disorders in the world.</p>



<p>It happens when acid comes up from the stomach, which is acid-resistant, into the esophagus, which is less acid-resistant.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/doctors/james-east-md?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. James East</a>, a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/patient-care/gastroenterology?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gastroenterologist</a> at <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/?_ga=2.69360720.1379129896.1667219896-207578559.1656678297?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Healthcare in London</a>, says GERD may be common, but there can be potentially severe complications if it's ongoing and left untreated.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/zFZETgXW_3U" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubezFZETgXW3U"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - GERD is not &#039;just&#039; heartburn" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zFZETgXW_3U?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:08) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post.&nbsp;Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network."&nbsp;Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/11/MCM-GERD-is-not-just-heartburn-ready40.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heartburn/symptoms-causes/syc-20373223?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Heartburn</a> — it's the cardinal symptom of GERD.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"GERD, gastroesophageal reflux disease, is when you get acid and chemical damage to the lining of the esophagus," says Dr. East.</p>



<p>You might feel a lump in the throat, have difficulty swallowing, have chest pain, a cough, or have worsening <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/is-there-a-connection-between-asthma-and-acid-reflux/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">asthma-type</a> symptoms.</p>



<p>"Complications of GERD include <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/esophagitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20361224?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">esophagitis</a>, inflammation in the bottom of the esophagus," says Dr. East. "If this is persistent, you can develop scarring and a stricture."</p>



<p>But if it's persistent and heals, the lining of the esophagus can change to a more acid-resistant form, which is <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/barretts-esophagus/symptoms-causes/syc-20352841?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Barrett's esophagus</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/barretts-esophagus/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352846?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Barrett's esophagus</a> is a reasonably common complication of GERD," he says.</p>



<p>It affects 10% to 15% of people with GERD. And a much smaller group faces another risk, says Dr. East.</p>



<p>"About 1 in 200 patients with Barrett's esophagus per year will develop <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/esophageal-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20356084?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">esophageal adenocarcinoma.</a>"</p>



<p>There are <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/digestive-diseases/news/transoral-endoscopic-incisionless-fundoplication/mqc-20454990?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">innovative treatments</a> for GERD and medications, like <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-balancing-proton-pump-inhibitor-risks-and-benefits/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">proton pump inhibitors</a>. But first, avoid triggers, like coffee, alcohol and smoking.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"If you have severe or frequent GERD, you should seek medical advice," advises Dr. East.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Learn more about Barrett's esophagus:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/podcast-episode/353358/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A podcast: Barrett’s esophagus requires monitoring and treatment to decrease esophageal cancer risk</strong></a></li>
</ul>



<p>&nbsp; <strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bbnWG7t62uU" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch:&nbsp;Dr. East discusses Barrett's esophagus</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidbbnWG7t62uU"  title="Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A podcast: Barrett’s esophagus requires monitoring and treatment" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bbnWG7t62uU?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-gerd-is-not-just-heartburn/">Mayo Clinic Minute: GERD is not &#8216;just&#8217; heartburn</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/10/shutterstock_104000960_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/10/shutterstock_104000960_Fotor-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[acid reflux]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Alex Osiadacz]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Barrett's Esophagus]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. James East]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[esophageal adenocarcinoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[esophagitis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[esophagus]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[gastroesophageal reflux disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[GERD]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[heartburn]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[international]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Proton Pump Inhibitors]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[treatment]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Signs of stomach cancer? Diagnosis and treatment</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-signs-of-stomach-cancer-diagnosis-and-treatment/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chloe Corey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Travis Grotz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gastric cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterolgy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q&A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stomach cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stomach pain]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377012</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: A 62-year-old man I worked with was diagnosed with stomach cancer earlier this year. He reportedly was feeling full even after eating small meals and experienced stomach pain above his belly button. I am starting to worry because I have recently started to experience similar symptoms. I’m only 38. Is it possible [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-signs-of-stomach-cancer-diagnosis-and-treatment/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Signs of stomach cancer? Diagnosis and treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/stomach-pain_16x9_GettyImages-1276569365.png" alt="" class="wp-image-377024" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/stomach-pain_16x9_GettyImages-1276569365.png 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/stomach-pain_16x9_GettyImages-1276569365-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/stomach-pain_16x9_GettyImages-1276569365-768x432.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> A 62-year-old man I worked with was diagnosed with stomach cancer earlier this year. He reportedly was feeling full even after eating small meals and experienced stomach pain above his belly button. I am starting to worry because I have recently started to experience similar symptoms. I’m only 38. Is it possible I could have stomach cancer? How do I get screened? What are the treatment options?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong> Most people diagnosed with<strong>&nbsp;</strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/endoscopy/about/pac-20395197?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">stomach cancer</a>, which is also called gastric cancer,&nbsp;are over the age of 60. However,&nbsp;in the U.S., stomach cancers&nbsp;in people under 40 have been steadily rising. Overall, this form of cancer is not very common, but factors that increase your risk include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Eating smoked, salted, processed or charcoaled meats, and pickled vegetables.</li>



<li>Eating few or no fruits and vegetables.</li>



<li>Alcohol use.</li>



<li>Previous stomach surgery.</li>



<li>Helicobacter pylori (H. pylori) infection.</li>



<li>Inherited cancer syndromes such as: hereditary diffuse gastric cancer, Lynch syndrome (hereditary nonpolyposis colorectal cancer), familial adenomatous polyposis, gastric adenoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach, Li-Fraumeni syndrome, and Peutz-Jeghers syndrome.</li>
</ul>



<p>Unfortunately, stomach cancer doesn’t always cause symptoms in its early stages, and many symptoms may not happen until the cancer is advanced. Signs and symptoms of stomach cancer may include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Difficulty swallowing.</li>



<li>Belly pain.</li>



<li>Feeling bloated after eating.</li>



<li>Feeling full after eating small amounts of food.</li>



<li>Not feeling hungry when you would expect to be hungry.</li>



<li>Losing weight without trying.</li>



<li>Feeling very tired.</li>



<li>Stools that look black.</li>
</ul>



<p>If you have signs and symptoms that worry you, you should make an appointment with your healthcare team. Many other conditions can cause symptoms that are similar to stomach cancer. Your healthcare team may recommend testing such as an <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/endoscopy/about/pac-20395197?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">upper endoscopy</a>, also called an upper gastrointestinal endoscopy, which is a procedure that is used to visually examine your upper digestive system. This can be used to screen for stomach cancer as the cause of your symptoms. An EGD allows the doctor to look at the inside of your stomach. Stomach cancer can appear as an ulcer, a mass or a thickening of the stomach wall. Your physician then can obtain biopsies of the area to determine if you have stomach cancer.</p>



<p>The treatment of stomach cancer depends on the stage. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/endoscopic-ultrasound/about/pac-20385171?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">Endoscopic ultrasound</a>, a minimally invasive procedure to assess diseases of the digestive (gastrointestinal) tract and other nearby organs and tissues, CT or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/pet-scan/about/pac-20385078?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">PET scan imaging</a>, and a staging laparoscopy are used to determine the clinical stage.</p>



<p>While it is uncommon to find early stomach cancer, treatment for early-stage disease often only requires local treatment. For example, in early stomach cancers that involve only the mucosa, or inner lining of the stomach, and measure less than 2-3 centimeters in size, the stomach cancer can be removed using endoscopic submucosal dissection without the need for surgery or additional treatment. For other early stomach cancers that do not meet these criteria, surgery to remove the stomach cancer and regional lymph nodes is recommended.</p>



<p>However, if the cancer is found to have spread to the lymph nodes at the time of surgery, then the patient is at a higher risk of stomach cancer returning after surgery alone. Therefore, chemotherapy after surgery is often recommended to decrease the risk of cancer recurrence.</p>



<p>Typically, patients are diagnosed with more advanced stomach cancer, which means a deeper involvement of the stomach or spread to regional lymph nodes. In this more common situation, combining chemotherapy and surgery is necessary for the best outcomes. Chemotherapy usually is given before and after surgery in this case.</p>



<p>Finally, if the stomach cancer has been found to have spread outside the stomach and regional lymph nodes, then this is stage 4 cancer. The primary treatment is systemic therapy. Additional testing can be done on the tumor to determine if the stomach cancer might respond to targeted therapy or immunotherapy. In some cases where there is a small amount of tumor spread to the lining of the abdomen, also called the peritoneum, surgery called cytoreductive surgery and <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/more-adventures-thanks-to-advanced-cancer-care-robotic-surgery/">hyperthermic intraperitoneal chemotherapy</a>&nbsp;can be used to prolong a patient’s survival.</p>



<p>Treatment options to treat stomach cancer are complex and should be individualized to your particular situation. It is essential to seek out an experienced team to help with the accurate staging of cancer, help with management decisions and for high-quality endoscopic or surgical resection.<em> —&nbsp;</em><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/grotz-travis-e-m-d/bio-20342285"><strong><em>Dr. Travis Grotz</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Surgical Oncology, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota</em></strong></p>



<p>________________________</p>



<p><em><strong>Related Articles&nbsp;</strong></em></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-treating-stomach-cancer/"><strong><span class="s1">Consumer Health: Treating stomach cancer</span></strong></a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-stomach-cancer-concerns/"><strong><span class="s1">Mayo Clinic Minute: Stomach cancer concerns</span></strong></a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-what-do-you-know-about-stomach-cancer/"><strong><span class="s1">Consumer Health: What do you know about stomach cancer?</span></strong></a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-signs-of-stomach-cancer-diagnosis-and-treatment/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Signs of stomach cancer? Diagnosis and treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/stomach-pain_1x1_GettyImages-1276569365.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/stomach-pain_16x9_GettyImages-1276569365.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Travis Grotz]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[gastric cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Gastroenterolgy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[GI]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[stomach cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[stomach pain]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Telehealth&#8217;s lasting impact on cancer care delivery</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/telehealths-lasting-impact-on-cancer-care-delivery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Vincent Jacobbi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2023 13:05:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Joshua Pritchett]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Tufia Haddad]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=378072</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A recent Mayo Clinic retrospective&#160;study&#160;shows that cancer practices can integrate telehealth without duplicative care, allowing for a more streamlined healthcare experience for patients and their caregivers. Researchers analyzed trends in telehealth use from 2019 to 2021 across&#160;Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center. The study looked at hematology and oncology visits conducted across Mayo Clinic campuses in [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/telehealths-lasting-impact-on-cancer-care-delivery/">Telehealth&#8217;s lasting impact on cancer care delivery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="533" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Telehealth-GettyImages-1280371057-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378075" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Telehealth-GettyImages-1280371057-16x9-1.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Telehealth-GettyImages-1280371057-16x9-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Telehealth-GettyImages-1280371057-16x9-1-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p>A recent Mayo Clinic retrospective&nbsp;<a href="https://ascopubs.org/doi/10.1200/OP.23.00118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;shows that cancer practices can integrate telehealth without duplicative care, allowing for a more streamlined healthcare experience for patients and their caregivers.</p>



<p>Researchers analyzed trends in telehealth use from 2019 to 2021 across&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>. The study looked at hematology and oncology visits conducted across Mayo Clinic campuses in Minnesota, Florida and Arizona, as well as at community-based clinics across&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System</a>.</p>



<p>In 2019, telehealth visits accounted for fewer than 0.01% of all visits. In 2020, a significant rise in telehealth use occurred in response to the COVID-19 pandemic, with the portion of visits conducted via telehealth increasing to 11%. By 2021, that figure rose to 14%, demonstrating a continued turn toward telehealth beyond the immediate pandemic response.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Pritchett_Joshua_C._16081960_20230925-240x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378074" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Pritchett_Joshua_C._16081960_20230925-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Pritchett_Joshua_C._16081960_20230925.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Joshua C. Pritchett, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We're showing that not only did our providers continue to use telehealth after the initial surge, but adoption (of the technology) increased over time and did not lead to increases in per-patient or per-provider care volumes," says lead author of the study, Joshua C. Pritchett, M.D., a hematology and oncology fellow at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>Overall, researchers examined over 100,000 visits conducted from 2019 to 2021, representing one of the largest analyses of telehealth use trends among cancer patients to date. Among people receiving established, ongoing care during the study, it found that 39.4% took part in at least one telehealth visit, demonstrating the critical role telehealth has played in the care of patients with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer</a> since the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>



<p>Researchers note that the study demonstrates that patient satisfaction ratings for telehealth visits remained similar to satisfaction with in-person care.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Digital health tools provide in-between visit care for patients</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Haddad_Tufia_C._10120386_20220907-240x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378073" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Haddad_Tufia_C._10120386_20220907-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Haddad_Tufia_C._10120386_20220907.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Tufia C. Haddad, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Beyond telehealth, the Mayo Clinic remote patient monitoring program is continuing to expand into the cancer space, allowing us to provide tablets and wearable devices for improved monitoring and in-between visit care," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/haddad-tufia-c-m-d/bio-20055534" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tufia C. Haddad, M.D.,</a> a Mayo Clinic medical oncologist and the study's senior author. "This will continue to help us understand how our patients are doing, how their symptoms and vital signs are tracking so that we can intervene earlier when things are not trending in a favorable direction."</p>



<p>With the many challenges of needing to get to and from appointments, telehealth has proved to be a worthy resource for many patients and their caregivers. The study showed that 52% of all visits by people undergoing treatment for various forms of brain cancer were conducted by video or phone technologies, demonstrating how access to care from home can be invaluable for many.</p>



<p>"The home is where healthcare happens," says Dr. Haddad. "Increasingly, we are seeing a continued shift in care to the home environment where smart homes enabled by digital technologies help assess and monitor patients. In the future, I think that will be more commonplace, and from there, we will only see the continued growth of virtual care delivery."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Reimbursement structures may affect the future of telehealth growth</strong></h2>



<p>Researchers noted that 20% of the U.S. population lives and works in rural areas; however, only 3% of oncology practices provide care there. For those in rural areas finding it difficult to travel for cancer care, telehealth has proven to be a lifeline when available.</p>



<p>The study showed a significantly higher rate of phone visits in rural populations versus video visits. Dr. Pritchett says the increased use of telehealth through phone visits is encouraging and shows a willingness by rural patients with cancer to engage with telehealth overall.</p>



<p>However, he notes that with the end of the Public Health Emergency Declaration applied in response to COVID-19, there has been a decline in reimbursement for phone visits compared to video visits. This change has the potential to create a widening disparity between urban, suburban and rural residents, and shows a need for future studies to examine how to increase video visit use among rural populations, he says.</p>



<p>"Telehealth in cancer care isn't simply a byproduct of the pandemic response. Patients desire this type of care, and it has become an integral part of patient-centered cancer care that continues to evolve," says Dr. Pritchett. "I think a big takeaway from this work is going to be how we make sure that it continues to be equitable and accessible to patients, as well as sustainable for practices."</p>



<p>The Mayo Clinic&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</a>&nbsp;supported this research. Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://ascopubs.org/doi/10.1200/OP.23.00118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p>This article first published on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/11/17/telehealths-lasting-impact-on-cancer-care-delivery/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/telehealths-lasting-impact-on-cancer-care-delivery/">Telehealth&#8217;s lasting impact on cancer care delivery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Telehealth-GettyImages-1280371057-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Telehealth-GettyImages-1280371057-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Joshua Pritchett]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Tufia Haddad]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Pass the turkey &#8212; and your family health insights &#8212; this Thanksgiving</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/pass-the-turkey-and-your-family-health-insights-this-thanksgiving/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. John Presutti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Niloy Jewel Samadder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Family Health History Day]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genomics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377654</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Thanksgiving Day is also&#160;Family Health History Day, an annual national campaign to promote awareness of hereditary health traits in families. Has your grandmother, mother, aunt or sister had breast or ovarian cancer? Has your grandfather, father or uncle had prostate, breast or pancreatic cancer? Is there a history in your family of colon cancer, diabetes [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/pass-the-turkey-and-your-family-health-insights-this-thanksgiving/">Pass the turkey &#8212; and your family health insights &#8212; this Thanksgiving</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="893" height="502" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/THANKSGIVING-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377656" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/THANKSGIVING-16x9-1.jpg 893w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/THANKSGIVING-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/THANKSGIVING-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 893px) 100vw, 893px" /></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Thanksgiving Day is also&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cdc.gov/genomics/famhistory/knowing_not_enough.htm?CDC_AA_refVal=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.cdc.gov%2Ffeatures%2Ffamilyhealthhistory%2Findex.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Family Health History Day</a>, an annual national campaign to promote awareness of hereditary health traits in families.</strong></h3>



<p>Has your grandmother, mother, aunt or sister had breast or ovarian cancer? Has your grandfather, father or uncle had prostate, breast or pancreatic cancer? Is there a history in your family of colon cancer, diabetes or high cholesterol?&nbsp;</p>



<p>If any of these scenarios resonate within your family, you could also be at risk.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Many hereditary health conditions follow patterns within families, with sometimes as high as a 50% likelihood that if one parent possesses a mutated gene, their child will inherit it. Recent Mayo Clinic&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-finds-1-in-8-patients-with-cancer-harbor-inherited-genetic-mutations/">research</a>&nbsp;shows that inherited, faulty genes cause more than 10% of all cancers.</p>



<p>"The biggest advice I would give is that if you are with your family this Thanksgiving, spend a few moments to share some of that family health history information. And if a red flag goes up, report that to your doctor. It could actually save someone's life," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/presutti-richard-john-j-d-o/bio-20053922" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">John Presutti, D.O.</a>, a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician and a researcher at the Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Predictive power of genomics</strong></h3>



<p>Dr. Presutti has integrated genomics into his everyday medical decision-making for his patients, realizing the potential for improving health outcomes.</p>



<p>"If I can help identify patients at high risk for cancer and other diseases, then I can help get them started on screening earlier and avoid the situation of metastatic cancer and early cancer deaths," he says.</p>



<p>Equally important to the discovery of a person's inherited cancer mutation is the potential for them to share the heritable cause of their disease with their blood relatives, allowing family members to pursue care for earlier disease detection and cancer management.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"The power of genetics is that we can potentially foresee the cancer that will develop in other family members," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/samadder-niloy-jewel-jewel-j-m-d/bio-20396993" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Niloy Jewel Samadder, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic gastroenterologist and cancer geneticist. "This can allow us to target cancer screening to those high-risk individuals and hopefully prevent cancer altogether in the next generation of the family."</p>



<p>Dr. Samadder emphasizes that knowing your family health history can help you, but only if you act on it.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Questions to ask family about health history</strong></h3>



<ul>
<li>Do you have chronic conditions, such as heart disease or diabetes, high blood pressure or high cholesterol?</li>



<li>Have you had serious diseases, such as cancer or stroke?</li>



<li>How old were you when each of these diseases or health conditions was diagnosed?</li>



<li>What is your family's ancestry? What countries or regions did your ancestors come from?</li>



<li>What were the causes and ages of death for relatives who have died?</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Examples of family health syndromes:</strong></h3>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/brca-gene-test/about/pac-20384815" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hereditary breast and ovarian cancer syndrome</a>&nbsp;is an inherited mutation in the BRCA1 or BRCA2 gene. Along with breast and ovarian cancer, this syndrome also can lead to male breast cancer, pancreatic cancer and prostate cancer.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lynch-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20374714" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lynch syndrome</a>&nbsp;is a cluster of mutations that can boost the risk of a wide range of cancers, including colon, rectal, endometrial, ovarian, stomach, small intestine, pancreas, kidney, brain, uterus and bile duct.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/familial-hypercholesterolemia/symptoms-causes/syc-20353755" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Familial hypercholesterolemia</a>&nbsp;is a genetic disorder characterized by high cholesterol, which can lead to premature cardiovascular disease.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Health history situations that raise a red flag</strong></h3>



<ul>
<li>A person developed cancer at an unusually young age.</li>



<li>A person has had several different types of cancer.</li>



<li>Cancer developed in both organs in a set of paired organs, such as both kidneys or both breasts.</li>



<li>Several first-degree relatives ― parents, siblings or a person's children ― have the same type of cancer. Examples might include a mother, daughter and sisters with breast cancer; multiple family members with breast or ovarian cancer; or family members with colon cancer and endometrial cancer.</li>



<li>Unusual cases of a specific cancer type, such as breast cancer in a man.</li>



<li>Being a member of a racial or ethnic group that is known to have an increased risk of having a certain inherited cancer susceptibility syndrome.</li>



<li>Several family members with cancer.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What to do with the information</strong></h3>



<p>If you have a family health history of disease, here are some steps to take:</p>



<ul>
<li>Consult a healthcare professional: Schedule a consultation with a doctor or genetic counselor to discuss your family health history and any potential risks.</li>



<li>Genetic testing: In some cases, your healthcare team may recommend genetic testing to determine whether you have specific genetic mutations or markers associated with hereditary diseases.</li>



<li>Lifestyle modifications: Make lifestyle changes to reduce risk factors, such as maintaining a healthy diet, staying physically active, and avoiding tobacco and excessive alcohol consumption.</li>



<li>Communicate: Keep open lines of communication with family members about their health histories, as it can provide valuable insights for everyone's well-being.</li>
</ul>



<p>This article first appeared on the <a href="https://individualizedmedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/11/10/pass-the-turkey-and-your-family-health-insights-this-thanksgiving/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Individualized Medicine blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/pass-the-turkey-and-your-family-health-insights-this-thanksgiving/">Pass the turkey &#8212; and your family health insights &#8212; this Thanksgiving</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/THANKSGIVING-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/THANKSGIVING-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. John Presutti]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Niloy Jewel Samadder]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Family Health History Day]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Genomics]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers demonstrate nearly 20% boost in adolescent HPV vaccination rates using comprehensive strategy</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-demonstrate-nearly-20-boost-in-adolescent-hpv-vaccination-rates-using-comprehensive-strategy/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2023 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Lila Finney Rutten]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Robert Jacobson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HPV]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HPV vaccination]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vaccine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377625</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic researchers demonstrated a nearly 20% increase in human papillomavirus (HPV) vaccination rates among adolescents through a combination intervention approach, a new Mayo Clinic study finds. The strategy involved mailing reminders to parents about their child's eligibility for the HPV vaccine and simultaneously giving healthcare providers feedback about successful HPV vaccine [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-demonstrate-nearly-20-boost-in-adolescent-hpv-vaccination-rates-using-comprehensive-strategy/">Mayo Clinic researchers demonstrate nearly 20% boost in adolescent HPV vaccination rates using comprehensive strategy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="vial of human papillomavirus vaccine" class="wp-image-103619" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic researchers demonstrated a nearly 20% increase in <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hpv-infection/symptoms-causes/syc-20351596" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">human papillomavirus (HPV)</a> vaccination rates among adolescents through a combination intervention approach, a new Mayo Clinic study finds. The strategy involved mailing reminders to parents about their child's eligibility for the HPV vaccine and simultaneously giving healthcare providers feedback about successful HPV vaccine administration among the patients they had recently seen.</p>



<p>The findings, published in <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamapediatrics/fullarticle/2812161">JAMA Pediatrics</a>, suggest healthcare practices could adopt this evidence-based approach to boost HPV vaccination uptake in 11- and 12-year-olds.</p>



<p>"HPV vaccine uptake at 60% of eligible adolescents falls short of national public health goals and lags other adolescent vaccines," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/jacobson-robert-m-m-d/bio-00083020" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Robert Jacobson, M.D.</a>, a pediatrician in the Mayo Clinic Division of Community Pediatric and Adolescent Medicine. Dr. Jacobson is a co-principal investigator of the study.</p>



<p>Human papillomaviruses cause viral infections transmitted sexually through skin-to-skin contact. HPV infections may occur without symptoms or signs in late adolescence or early adulthood and affect both males and females. The virus can cause several types of cancers, including of the cervix, anus, genital area, mouth and throat.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/cancer/hpv/statistics/cases.htm" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">estimates</a> 37,000 HPV-linked cancers occur each year in the U.S., all of which may be prevented by the HPV vaccination.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For the study, the researchers evaluated their intervention strategy at six Mayo Clinic primary care practices in Southeastern Minnesota. The investigation involved 9,242 adolescents who were due to receive at least one dose of the HPV vaccine. When parents received reminders in the mail and providers were simultaneously given feedback, 39.7% of patients got their doses due in the months that followed the interventions, as contrasted to 21.9% without the interventions.</p>



<p>“Our study investigated both parent- and provider-facing interventions. By targeting parents and providers, we achieved much higher improvements in HPV vaccine uptake than the use of these strategies in isolation,” says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/rutten-lila-j-ph-d/bio-20551780" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lila Finney Rutten, Ph.D.</a>, lead author and chair of the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/departments-divisions/quantitative-health-sciences/divisions/epidemiology/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Division of Epidemiology</a>.</p>



<p>The researchers say the study not only addresses the low HPV vaccination rate but also holds the potential to reshape other public health and vaccination campaigns.</p>



<p>Review the&nbsp;study&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures, and funding.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> &nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and to providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.  &nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong>  &nbsp;</p>



<ul>
<li>Susan Murphy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>  &nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-demonstrate-nearly-20-boost-in-adolescent-hpv-vaccination-rates-using-comprehensive-strategy/">Mayo Clinic researchers demonstrate nearly 20% boost in adolescent HPV vaccination rates using comprehensive strategy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Lila Finney Rutten]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Robert Jacobson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[HPV]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[HPV vaccination]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Vaccine]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Consumer Health: What do you know about pancreatic cancer?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-what-do-you-know-about-pancreatic-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laurel Kelly]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pancreatic Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pancreatic Cancer Awareness Month]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=371506</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>November is&#160;Pancreatic Cancer Awareness Month, which makes this a good time to learn more about the risk factors for pancreatic cancer and what you can do to keep yourself safe. More than 64,000 people in the U.S. will be diagnosed with pancreatic cancer this year, and more than 50,000 people will die of the disease, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-what-do-you-know-about-pancreatic-cancer/">Consumer Health: What do you know about pancreatic cancer?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Mom-Daughter-Original-with-Ribbon-1024x683.jpg" alt="a portrait of two women, one elderly, the other middle age, perhaps a mother and daughter with a purple Pancreatic Cancer Awareness ribbon graphic" class="wp-image-352950" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Mom-Daughter-Original-with-Ribbon-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Mom-Daughter-Original-with-Ribbon-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Mom-Daughter-Original-with-Ribbon-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Mom-Daughter-Original-with-Ribbon-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Mom-Daughter-Original-with-Ribbon-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>November is&nbsp;<a href="https://www.aacr.org/patients-caregivers/awareness-months/pancreatic-cancer-awareness-month/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pancreatic Cancer Awareness Month</a>, which makes this a good time to learn more about the risk factors for pancreatic cancer and what you can do to keep yourself safe.</p>



<p>More than 64,000 people in the U.S. will be diagnosed with pancreatic cancer this year, and more than 50,000 people will die of the disease, according to the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/pancreatic-cancer/about/key-statistics.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Cancer Society</a>. Pancreatic cancer is the&nbsp;<a href="https://cancerstatisticscenter.cancer.org/?_ga=2.189398057.347593919.1602700843-1875348864.1599565997&amp;_gac=1.45345424.1602700843.EAIaIQobChMIsIfA8N207AIVksDACh2zsQq-EAAYASAAEgItfvD_BwE#!/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">third-leading cause of cancer death</a>&nbsp;in the U.S.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pancreatic-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20355421?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pancreatic cancer</a>&nbsp;begins in the tissues of your pancreas — an organ in your abdomen that lies behind the lower part of your stomach. Your pancreas releases enzymes that aid digestion and produces hormones that help manage your blood sugar.</p>



<p>Several types of growths can occur in the pancreas, including cancerous and noncancerous tumors. The most common type of cancer that forms in the pancreas is pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma, which begins in the cells that line the ducts that carry digestive enzymes out of the pancreas.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Symptoms</strong></h2>



<p>Signs and symptoms of&nbsp;pancreatic cancer&nbsp;often don't occur until the disease is advanced. This means the disease rarely is detected at its early stages when it's most curable.</p>



<p>Pancreatic cancer symptoms can include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Abdominal pain that radiates to your back.</li>



<li>Loss of appetite or unintended weight loss.</li>



<li>Yellowing of your skin and the whites of your eyes.</li>



<li>Light-colored stools.</li>



<li>Dark-colored urine.</li>



<li>Itchy skin.</li>



<li>New diagnosis of diabetes or existing diabetes that's becoming more difficult to control.</li>



<li>Blood clots.</li>



<li>Fatigue.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Risk Factors</strong></h2>



<p>Factors that can increase your risk of pancreatic cancer include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Smoking.</li>



<li>Diabetes.</li>



<li>Chronic inflammation of the pancreas, or&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pancreatitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20360227?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pancreatitis</a>.</li>



<li>Family history of genetic syndromes that can increase cancer risk, including a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/brca-gene-test/about/pac-20384815?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">BRCA2 gene mutation</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lynch-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20374714?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lynch syndrome</a>&nbsp;and familial atypical mole malignant melanoma syndrome.</li>



<li>Family history of pancreatic cancer.</li>



<li>Obesity.</li>



<li>Older age, as most people are diagnosed after 65.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Reducing your risk</strong></h2>



<p>While some of these risk factors are out of your control, here are some lifestyle choices you can make to reduce your risk:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Stop smoking.<br></strong>If you smoke, try to stop. Talk to your healthcare team about strategies to help you stop, including support groups, medications and nicotine replacement therapy. If you don't smoke, don't start.</li>



<li><strong>Maintain a healthy weight.<br></strong>If you are at a healthy weight, work to maintain it. If you need to lose weight, aim for a slow, steady weight loss — 1 to 2 pounds a week. Combine daily exercise with a diet rich in vegetables, fruit and whole grains, with smaller portions to help you lose weight.</li>



<li><strong>Choose a healthy diet.</strong><br>A diet full of colorful fruits and vegetables, and whole grains, may reduce your risk of cancer.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Treatment</strong></h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pancreatic-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20355427?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Treatment</a> for pancreatic cancer depends on the stage and location of the cancer as well as on your overall health and personal preferences. For most people, the first goal of pancreatic cancer treatment is to eliminate the cancer, when possible. When that isn't an option, the focus may be on improving your quality of life and limiting the cancer from growing or causing more harm.</p>



<p>Treatment may include surgery, radiation therapy, chemotherapy or a combination of these. When pancreatic cancer is advanced and these treatments aren't likely to offer a benefit, your healthcare professional will focus on symptom relief with palliative care to keep you as comfortable as possible for as long as possible.</p>



<p>Connect with others talking about pancreatic cancer in the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/pancreatic-cancer/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pancreatic Cancer Support Group</a> on&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Connect</a>, an online patient community moderated by Mayo Clinic.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-what-do-you-know-about-pancreatic-cancer/">Consumer Health: What do you know about pancreatic cancer?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/11/a-purple-and-white-graphic-with-written-information-that-November-is-Pancreatic-Cancer-Awareness-Month-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Mom-Daughter-Original-with-Ribbon.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Pancreatic Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Pancreatic Cancer Awareness Month]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>