<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 20:47:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: What is TIL therapy?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-til-therapy/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Osiadacz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. James Jakub]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immune cells]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[TIL therapy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tumor-infiltrating lymphocyte therapy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=392684</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Melanoma is a dangerous form of skin cancer that has the potential to spread to other parts of the body. Approximately 100,000 people in the U.S. will be diagnosed with melanoma this year, according to the American Cancer Society. In early 2024, the Food and Drug Administration approved a new treatment for advanced melanoma called&#160;tumor-infiltrating [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-til-therapy/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What is TIL therapy?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/melanoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20374884" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Melanoma</a> is a dangerous form of skin cancer that has the potential to spread to other parts of the body.</p>



<p>Approximately <a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/types/melanoma-skin-cancer/about/key-statistics.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">100,000 people</a> in the U.S. will be diagnosed with melanoma this year, according to the American Cancer Society. In early 2024, the Food and Drug Administration approved a <a href="https://www.fda.gov/news-events/press-announcements/fda-approves-first-cellular-therapy-treat-patients-unresectable-or-metastatic-melanoma" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">new treatment</a> for advanced melanoma called&nbsp;tumor-infiltrating lymphocyte therapy (TIL therapy).</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/jakub-james-w-m-d/bio-20055124" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. James Jakub</a>, a Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">surgical oncologist</a>, explains that TIL therapy can be a one-time treatment for some patients diagnosed with advanced melanoma.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/Gw5mhrWPm0I" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe id="videoidhttpsyoutubeGw5mhrWPm0I"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - What is TIL therapy?" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Gw5mhrWPm0I?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:56) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/SCRIPT-Mayo-Clinic-Minute-What-is-TIL-therapy_JJ.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Tumor-infiltrating lymphocyte therapy, or TIL therapy, uses the body's own immune cells to target cancer — in this case, advanced melanoma. The process, which takes about three weeks, begins with surgery.</p>



<p>"We remove the cancer; it's sent off to a lab, and those immune cells, those lymphocytes, are isolated, separated out and enriched."</p>



<p>While the cells are prepared, the patient undergoes chemotherapy in preparation for their own immune cells, which recognize the melanoma, to be infused back into their body.</p>



<p>"When we give them back to the patient, they can effectively target the cancer," says Dr. Jakub. And now, in numbers, they can overwhelm the cancer and kill it."</p>



<p>Blood tests and scans measure the body's response three months after treatment. For those who have failed multiple lines of treatment, this one-time therapy offers hope.</p>



<p>"It's the potential that their cancer may not come back again, and they may not need any additional therapy," says Dr. Jakub.</p>



<p><strong>Related content:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-who-should-be-screened-for-skin-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Who should be screened for skin cancer?</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-study-finds-triple-negative-breast-cancer-tumors-with-an-increase-in-immune-cells-have-lower-risk-of-recurrence-after-surgery/">New study finds triple-negative breast cancer tumors with an increase in immune cells have lower risk of recurrence after surgery</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-chimeric-antigen-receptor-t-cell-therapy/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What is CAR-T cell therapy?</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-til-therapy/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What is TIL therapy?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Til-Therapy1-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Til-Therapy1-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. James Jakub]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[immune cells]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[TIL therapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[tumor-infiltrating lymphocyte therapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>To combat heart disease and cancer, genomics researcher looks abroad</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/to-combat-heart-disease-and-cancer-genomics-researcher-looks-abroad/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[mbroadfoot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Iftikhar Kullo]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=393805</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Genetic technology has the potential to significantly improve human health by improving disease risk prediction and guiding prevention strategies. The development of a new genetic test called a polygenic risk score is a major advance. Still, it may widen health disparities because such scores may not work equally well for different populations. Iftikhar Kullo, M.D., [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/to-combat-heart-disease-and-cancer-genomics-researcher-looks-abroad/">To combat heart disease and cancer, genomics researcher looks abroad</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Iftikhar-Kullo-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Image of Iftikhar Kullo, M.D." class="wp-image-393806" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Iftikhar-Kullo-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Iftikhar-Kullo-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Iftikhar-Kullo-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Iftikhar-Kullo-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Iftikhar-Kullo-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mayo Clinic cardiologist Iftikhar Kullo, M.D., believes that global collaboration is needed to refine polygenic risk scores so they perform equitably across people from diverse groups.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Genetic technology has the potential to significantly improve human health by improving disease risk prediction and guiding prevention strategies. The development of a new genetic test called a polygenic risk score is a major advance. Still, it may widen health disparities because such scores may not work equally well for different populations. <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/kullo-iftikhar-j-m-d/bio-00084951" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Iftikhar Kullo, M.D.</a>, a cardiologist at Mayo Clinic, believes that global collaboration is needed to refine polygenic risk scores so they perform equitably across people from diverse groups.</p>



<p>Dr. Kullo recently authored a perspective piece in <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41588-024-01843-2#:~:text=Such%20collaborations%20should%20be%20guided,assessment%2C%20global%20collaboration%20is%20critical." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nature Genetics</a>, where he made the case for efforts to bring genomics to low- and middle-income countries. His argument is that the information gleaned from testing could not only benefit local populations but also many other groups around the world, including in the U.S. Here, he elaborates on this.</p>



<p><strong>Q:</strong> You've noted that the disease burden worldwide is shifting from communicable diseases such as &nbsp;hepatitis and influenza to noncommunicable diseases such as heart disease and cancer. How can genetics address this shift?</p>



<p><strong>Dr. Kullo:</strong> The shift from infectious disease to noncommunicable disease is part of the "epidemiologic transition." Famines and pandemics were once the leading cause of mortality, but fortunately, these were addressed by antibiotics, vaccinations and adequate food production. Now, we live longer and, as a result, are prone to developing other diseases like heart disease, diabetes or cancer. One of the ways that we can reduce the burden of these noncommunicable diseases is to employ better ways of predicting risk. For many of these conditions, we have existing tools for risk prediction, but they don't always perform as well as we would like them to.</p>



<p><strong>Q:</strong> You are referring to a new genetic test called a polygenic risk score. Could you explain what a polygenic risk score is, and how it works?</p>



<p><strong>Dr. Kullo:</strong> Genetically, humans are 99.9% similar. Our genome has three billion letters (A, G, T and C), and every 1,000 letters or so, there is a variation or difference between any two people. These differences, or variants, account for how we look or behave, how we might react to drugs, and our predisposition to different diseases. Polygenic risk scores add up information from multiple such genetic variants that affect our risk of developing certain diseases. Each variant is not very useful by itself, but if we combine the information from many — thousands or even millions of variants in some cases — we get useful and actionable information about disease risk.</p>



<p><strong>Q:</strong> What is the limitation of polygenic risk scores? How could they widen global health disparities?</p>



<p><strong>Dr. Kullo:</strong> Polygenic risk scores don't perform well across different genetic ancestry groups. Because the vast majority of genetic studies are done in people of European genetic ancestry, these scores don't work very well, for example, in people of African genetic ancestry. One way we can address that disparity is to increase diversity in our studies here in the U.S., but an even better approach may be to undertake a global effort, conducting this work in diverse regions across the globe. We know that using diverse sources of data will improve the performance of these scores for everybody.</p>



<p><strong>Q:</strong> You wrote that African datasets are still a high priority for genomic studies. Yet, they are the least represented — less than 2% of human genomes analyzed so far are of people with African genetic ancestry. How can studying African genomes help advance our understanding of the genomic basis of common diseases in all people?</p>



<p><strong>Dr. Kullo:</strong> Africa contains the greatest genetic diversity among the continents, accumulated over 300,000 years of human evolution. By studying people of African ancestry, we will learn so much more about human origins and genetics because we're all Africans, in a way — that's where Homo sapiens arose. That long evolutionary history means that African populations could yield more information about genetic variants associated with disease. And it's a chance to make up for this big disparity in the number of Africans in genomic studies thus far.</p>



<p><strong>Q:</strong> What steps do you believe are necessary to achieve equity in the availability of polygenic risk scores to improve global health?</p>



<p><strong>Dr. Kullo:</strong> We certainly need to increase the representation of minorities in genomic studies. Mayo Clinic is part of a large National Institutes of Health (NIH)-funded consortium called <a href="https://emerge.study/mayo-clinic/">eMERGE</a> that is looking at polygenic risk scores for 10 common conditions, including heart disease, diabetes, chronic kidney disease, breast cancer and prostate cancer. The consortium is committed to ensuring that at least half of the 25,000 participants across the country come from diverse groups.</p>



<p>It's important to learn about the spectrum of genetic variation in all of humanity, not just in one group. I believe that means going beyond our borders, helping other countries to set up infrastructure to generate their own genetic data and creating resources for data-sharing across the globe. It's not an easy task, but we have many elements in place, and I think it's doable.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/to-combat-heart-disease-and-cancer-genomics-researcher-looks-abroad/">To combat heart disease and cancer, genomics researcher looks abroad</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Iftikhar-Kullo-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Iftikhar-Kullo-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Iftikhar Kullo]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Palliative medicine for cancer patients</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-palliative-medicine-for-cancer-patients/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Toure Barksdale]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=392295</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Patients undergoing cancer treatments often use palliative medicine to cope with nausea, fatigue and other bothersome symptoms. Palliative medicine is a medical specialty whose main focus is supporting patients and families/caregivers who need help managing symptoms related to cancer or side effects related to the treatment of cancer, along with other life-limiting diseases. Dr. Touré [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-palliative-medicine-for-cancer-patients/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Palliative medicine for cancer patients</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Patients undergoing cancer treatments often use palliative medicine to cope with nausea, fatigue and other bothersome symptoms.</p>



<p>Palliative medicine is a medical specialty whose main focus is supporting patients and families/caregivers who need help managing symptoms related to cancer or side effects related to the treatment of cancer, along with other life-limiting diseases.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/barksdale-toure-m-d/bio-20517681">Dr. Touré Barksdale</a>, a Mayo Clinic cancer rehabilitation and palliative medicine specialist, explains the benefits of palliative care.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/wO0fIVPiCfM" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe id="videoidhttpsyoutubewO0fIVPiCfM"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Palliative medicine for cancer patients" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wO0fIVPiCfM?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:03) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please "Courtesy: Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/SCRIPT-jthEDITS_MCM-palliative-care-version-1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Patients with cancer not only have to worry about fighting the disease, but they also must battle the cumbersome side effects, like fatigue and other symptoms related to cancer and its treatment.</p>



<p>"Side effects from cancer and treatment of cancer, such as pain, delirium, nausea, vomiting and debility, can also contribute to their cancer-related fatigue," says Dr. Barksdale.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Palliative care provides relief </h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/01/shutterstock_256121824_Fotor-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="a group of people, athletes outside in a park stretching and exercising, perhaps doing yoga or Tai chi" class="wp-image-260270" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/01/shutterstock_256121824_Fotor-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/01/shutterstock_256121824_Fotor-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/01/shutterstock_256121824_Fotor-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/01/shutterstock_256121824_Fotor-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/01/shutterstock_256121824_Fotor-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Tai Chi is often used in palliative medicine. </figcaption></figure>



<p>Palliative medicine is a crucial component of cancer treatment. Its main purpose is to improve the patient's overall well-being.</p>



<p>"Whether that's more holistic care through integrative and complementary medicine, more Western-based medicines, psychological care, music therapy, aromatherapy, Reiki, tai chi — we have lots of things we can do to help reduce suffering," explains Dr. Barksdale.</p>



<p>Palliative care is not the same as hospice care. The latter focuses on making patients comfortable and managing symptoms nearing the end of life when further curative treatments are no longer available.</p>



<p>"Palliative care, to me, is hope because what we're doing is we're improving your quality of life," says Dr. Barksdale.</p>



<p>This type of care is available at any stage of cancer treatment.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Related Content:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/transforming-cancer-care-with-treatments-at-home/">Transforming cancer care with treatments at home</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-creating-an-advance-directive-for-your-future-well-being/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Creating an advance directive for your future well-being</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-palliative-medicine-for-cancer-patients/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Palliative medicine for cancer patients</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Nurse-Helping-patient-GettyImages-1473157220_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2015/03/shutterstock_239820817.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Toure Barksdale]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: What you should know about prostate cancer screening</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-you-should-know-about-prostate-cancer-screening/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 15:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Oliver Sartor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Men's Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[oncology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[prostatel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PSA]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=393018</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The prostate is a small gland in males that aids in reproduction. Prostate cancer is one the most common types of cancer, and when it's detected early, often by a simple blood test, it has the best chance for successful treatment.&#160; Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:04) is in the downloads at [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-you-should-know-about-prostate-cancer-screening/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What you should know about prostate cancer screening</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The prostate is a small gland in males that aids in reproduction. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prostate-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353087?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Prostate cancer</a> is one the most common types of cancer, and when it's detected early, often by a simple blood test, it has the best chance for successful treatment.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/-hyeNxs4Jic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubehyeNxs4Jic"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - What you should know about prostate cancer screening" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-hyeNxs4Jic?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:04) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/MCM_What-you-should-know-about-prostate-cancer-screening.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></strong></p>



<p>"Prostate cancer is incredibly common, probably going to be diagnosed in about 300,000 men this year in the United States," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/sartor-alton-o-m-d/bio-20548417?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Oliver Sartor</a>, a Mayo Clinic medical oncologist.</p>



<p>Dr. Sartor, whose practice is focused on prostate cancer, stresses the importance of screening for the disease with a prostate-specific antigen test, or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/psa-test/about/pac-20384731?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">PSA</a>.</p>



<p>"I think the No. 1 issue of being diagnosed with advanced prostate cancer is not getting a PSA," he says.</p>



<p>It's a blood test that's analyzed for prostate-specific antigen, a substance naturally produced by your prostate. If a high amount of PSA is found in your bloodstream, it could indicate prostate infection, inflammation, enlargement or cancer.</p>



<p>"I think generally starting at age 50 is a very reasonable number to start getting a PSA. But if you are African American or have a significant family history of prostate cancer or have a genetic alteration that might predispose to prostate cancer, then you should probably get one even earlier," says Dr. Sartor.</p>



<p>If the PSA detects an abnormality, further tests, such as ultrasound, MRI or a biopsy, may be recommended to determine if you have prostate cancer.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-you-should-know-about-prostate-cancer-screening/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What you should know about prostate cancer screening</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Blood-Draw2-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Blood-Draw1-16x9-1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Oliver Sartor]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Men's Health]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[oncology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[prostatel]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[PSA]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: What does a diagnosis of  dense breasts mean?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-does-a-diagnosis-of-dense-breasts-mean/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dense Breast Tissue]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Kristin Robinson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=369158</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Food and Drug Administration issued a rule in March of 2023 that requires healthcare professionals to notify people if they have dense breasts. Facilities subject to the Mammography Quality Standards ACT (MQSA) must comply with this requirement no later than Sept. 10 of this year.&#160;Studies have shown that dense breast tissue can make it [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-does-a-diagnosis-of-dense-breasts-mean/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What does a diagnosis of  dense breasts mean?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The <a href="https://www.fda.gov/radiation-emitting-products/mammography-quality-standards-act-and-program/important-information-final-rule-amend-mammography-quality-standards-act-mqsa" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Food and Drug Administration</a> issued a rule in March of 2023 that requires healthcare professionals to notify people if they have dense breasts. Facilities subject to the <a href="https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2023/03/10/2023-04550/mammography-quality-standards-act" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mammography Quality Standards ACT (MQSA)</a> must comply with this requirement no later than Sept. 10 of this year.&nbsp;<a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaoncology/fullarticle/2804130" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Studies</a> have shown that dense breast tissue can make it more difficult to detect breast cancer early.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/robinson-kristin-a-m-d/bio-20466711?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Kristin Robinson</a>, a Mayo Clinic breast radiologist, says women with dense breast tissue are at a slightly increased risk of developing breast cancer compared to women without, and that’s why early detection is so important.</p>



<p>"About 50% of women have dense breast tissue," says Dr. Robinson.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/TrYQiUsckmQ" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: What does a diagnosis of dense breasts mean?</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/Mayo-Clinic-Minute-What-does-a-dense-breast-tissue-diagnosis-mean_CLEAN.mp4"></video></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (01:04) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the</strong> <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/MCM-Dense-Breasts.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>script</strong>.</a></p>



<p>Dr. Robinson says you can't tell by looking at a woman whether she has dense breasts. She says people with dense breasts have less fat and more glandular and connective tissue in their breasts.</p>



<p>"When we see a woman's <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mammogram/multimedia/mammogram/vid-20084742?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">mammogram,</a> that dense tissue, that fibroglandular tissue, looks white, whereas the fat looks dark or like a black color. So, when we're looking at a mammogram, the more white tissue we see, the more dense a woman’s breasts are considered," says Dr. Robinson.</p>



<p>She says it's difficult to detect cancer in dense breasts because breast cancer and dense tissue appear white on a mammogram.</p>



<p>"Our sensitivity or our ability to detect breast cancer goes down in women who have dense breast tissue for that reason," she explains.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Dense breast tissue supplemental screenings</strong></h3>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2-1024x576.jpg" alt="A Black woman in a patient gown being prepared by a medical assistant for a breast mammogram for possible dense breast" class="wp-image-319507" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The radiologist encourages women with dense breast tissue to have supplemental screenings.</p>



<p>"Whole-breast screening ultrasound, MRI, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/molecular-breast-imaging/about/pac-20394710?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">molecular breast imaging</a>, and contrast-enhanced mammography" are some options patients might consider, says Dr. Robinson.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic healthcare professionals recommend annual mammograms starting at age 40 for most women. In addition, a personalized breast cancer risk assessment is suggested at age 30 for all women to see if screening is needed before age 40.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-does-a-diagnosis-of-dense-breasts-mean/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What does a diagnosis of  dense breasts mean?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-1x1-.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/10/mammography_shutterstock_292061510_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dense Breast Tissue]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Kristin Robinson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic to expand access to state-of-the-art cancer care through transformational gift</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-to-expand-access-to-state-of-the-art-cancer-care-through-transformational-gift/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelley Luckstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Care Beyond Walls]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Clinical Trials Beyond Walls]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Cheryl Willman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health disparities]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stephen and Barbara Slaggie]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=393541</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic will enhance and expand access to cancer care and clinical trials for patients and communities, thanks to a generous philanthropic commitment from Stephen M. and Barbara J. Slaggie of Marco Island, Florida, and Winona, Minnesota. The Slaggies' $50 million investment accelerates Mayo Clinic's Bold. Forward. strategy to Cure, Connect and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-to-expand-access-to-state-of-the-art-cancer-care-through-transformational-gift/">Mayo Clinic to expand access to state-of-the-art cancer care through transformational gift</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Slaggie-Photo-WF4175855_004758-1024x768.jpg" alt="Stephen M. and Barbara J. Slaggie" class="wp-image-393554" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Slaggie-Photo-WF4175855_004758-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Slaggie-Photo-WF4175855_004758-300x225.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Slaggie-Photo-WF4175855_004758-768x576.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Slaggie-Photo-WF4175855_004758.jpg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> will enhance and expand access to cancer care and clinical trials for patients and communities, thanks to a generous philanthropic commitment from Stephen M. and Barbara J. Slaggie of Marco Island, Florida, and Winona, Minnesota.</p>



<p>The Slaggies' $50 million investment accelerates Mayo Clinic's Bold. Forward. strategy to Cure, Connect and Transform healthcare by supporting <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> in revolutionizing the delivery of cancer care. Mayo Clinic is leading this shift by developing the optimal blend of in-facility, digital and home-based care to reach more patients beyond traditional care delivery methods.</p>



<p>Already, through the creation of innovative programs, including Cancer Care Beyond Walls and Clinical Trials Beyond Walls — in collaboration with partners in Mayo Clinic's practice and research endeavors — Mayo Clinic is delivering chemotherapy and clinical trials to patients in their homes and community environments.</p>



<p>"Through our platform-based strategies, Mayo Clinic is enabling the delivery of cancer care and clinical trials broadly to patients and communities across the United States and around the world, overcoming geographic barriers to assure access to quality cancer care and clinical trials to patients anywhere, at any time," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/willman-cheryl-l-m-d/bio-20537787" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cheryl Willman, M.D.</a>, the Stephen and Barbara Slaggie Executive Director, Mayo Clinic Cancer Programs, and director, Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is the only National Cancer Institute-Designated Comprehensive Cancer Center with three integrated geographic sites — in Arizona, Florida and Minnesota — achieving national and international recognition for the delivery of advanced and complex cancer care. For over five decades, Mayo Clinic has made important contributions as a leading cancer center because of a focus on patient-centered care, multidisciplinary team science, and translation of cutting-edge research from the bench to the bedside and into communities.</p>



<p>The Slaggies' support for enhanced access to Mayo Clinic knowledge and expertise, cancer care delivery, cancer clinical trials, and community outreach and engagement will enable more patients to access Mayo Clinic's innovative and expert care, no matter where they live. Key activities advanced through this gift include enhancing platform and digital tools to deliver cancer care and trials anywhere, developing community partnerships, and recruiting patient navigators and clinical staff to expand Mayo Clinic's Cancer Care Beyond Walls and Clinical Trials Beyond Walls programs to Mayo Clinic partners.</p>



<p>Making care more accessible inspired the Slaggies.</p>



<p>"Being a cancer survivor, I know firsthand the anxiety of seeking prompt, exceptional care," Stephen Slaggie says. "We're honored to help people with cancer by providing treatment in their home without the time, expense and travel involved in accessing a clinic or hospital."</p>



<p>For example, through its Cancer Care Beyond Walls program, Mayo Clinic has successfully delivered more than 140 chemotherapy infusions in patients' homes and has opened three national clinical trials testing the safety, efficacy and patient satisfaction of this approach.</p>



<p>"Think of what this means for patients who are going through a cancer diagnosis," Dr. Willman says. "Access to cutting-edge therapies from the most trusted name in healthcare, all in the healing environment of your home."</p>



<p>Areas benefiting from the Slaggies' gift include:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Cancer Care Delivery/Cancer Care Beyond Walls</h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic is transforming cancer care delivery by blending virtual, in-facility and at-home treatments to meet our patients where they are. By expanding these innovative programs, Mayo Clinic will enhance the patient and family experience and ensure Mayo's high-quality science and care reach all communities.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is also extending the Cancer Care Beyond Walls program, which began in Florida, to Mayo Clinic Health System, a community-based rural healthcare delivery system serving 49 communities across Minnesota and Wisconsin; Mayo Clinic in Arizona; partners in the Mayo Clinic Care Network; and, ultimately, healthcare systems around the nation and globe. Cancer Care Beyond Walls is using virtual and digital platforms and allied health teams to deliver cancer treatment, cancer chemotherapy and cancer clinical trials in the home environment, reducing the financial and emotional burden for patients with cancer who may otherwise have to travel long distances for care.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Cancer Clinical Trials/Clinical Trials Beyond Walls</h2>



<p>Each year, Mayo Clinic conducts thousands of clinical trials that are pioneering possible cures, yet there remain significant societal, geographic and logistical barriers that prevent some patients from accessing those options. The ability to decentralize clinical trials assures access for patients and communities by overcoming these barriers.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is addressing these systemic issues by using new digital tools — developed by its Center for Digital Health, <a href="https://www.mayoclinicplatform.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Platform</a> and Mayo's research enterprise — to connect more people to clinical trials, testing new means to screen, and prevent and treat cancer and other diseases. In its Clinical Trials Beyond Walls program, Mayo Clinic's research teams and Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center have opened nine decentralized clinical trials in community settings and patients' homes.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Community Outreach and Engagement Programs</h2>



<p>A significant driver of health disparities and poorer health outcomes in minority and underrepresented groups is the lack of access to care and engagement of underserved populations in clinical trials. In 2022, Mayo Clinic launched the Mayo Clinic Community Research Registry, which partners with faith-based organizations, fraternities, sororities, American Legion posts and others to educate communities about clinical trials and match interested individuals to trials at Mayo Clinic. More than 900 diverse community participants are currently enrolled in the registry.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is also seeking to create financial pathways and partnerships that will increase clinical access for patients within its communities. These initiatives will establish patient finance consulting and concierge services at each Mayo Clinic site to help patients navigate medical costs. Mayo Clinic also will look to support additional patient populations through expanded payer contracts.</p>



<p>###  </p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the <a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact</strong>:     </p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-to-expand-access-to-state-of-the-art-cancer-care-through-transformational-gift/">Mayo Clinic to expand access to state-of-the-art cancer care through transformational gift</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Slaggie-Photo-WF4175855_004758_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Slaggie-Photo-WF4175855_004758_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer Care Beyond Walls]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Clinical Trials Beyond Walls]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Cheryl Willman]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[health disparities]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Stephen and Barbara Slaggie]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Understanding athletes with lymphoma</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/understanding-athletes-with-lymphoma/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Magazine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=393251</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>One July evening,&#160;Allison Rosenthal, D.O., received a flurry of texts with exclamations like, “Yo, my doctor friend is famous!” “What is going on?” she thought. She soon learned that her patient, MLB pitcher Liam Hendriks, had just thanked her while accepting ESPN’s Jimmy V Award for Perseverance at the 2023 ESPYs, with more than 2.3 million [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/understanding-athletes-with-lymphoma/">Understanding athletes with lymphoma</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="938" height="527" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Dr-Rosenthal-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-393253" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Dr-Rosenthal-16x9-1.jpg 938w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Dr-Rosenthal-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Dr-Rosenthal-16x9-1-768x431.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 938px) 100vw, 938px" /></figure>



<p>One July evening,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/rosenthal-allison-c-d-o/bio-20178616" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Allison Rosenthal, D.O.</a>, received a flurry of texts with exclamations like, “Yo, my doctor friend is famous!”</p>



<p>“What is going on?” she thought.</p>



<p>She soon learned that her patient, MLB pitcher <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/09/06/all-star-pitcher-liam-hendriks-shares-how-he-closed-out-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Liam Hendriks</a>, had just thanked her while accepting ESPN’s Jimmy V Award for Perseverance at the 2023 ESPYs, with more than 2.3 million people watching the broadcast that evening.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/Liam-1-x-1-300x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-370983" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/Liam-1-x-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/Liam-1-x-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/Liam-1-x-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/Liam-1-x-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/Liam-1-x-1.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Liam Hendriks</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>“She is one of the main reasons that I am up here tonight,” said Liam, who beat stage 4&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/non-hodgkins-lymphoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20375680" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">non-Hodgkin’s lymphoma</a>&nbsp;in the 2023 off-season.</p>



<p>A few hours later, when the program aired in her time zone in Arizona, Dr. Rosenthal, a lymphoma specialist at Mayo Clinic, tuned in.</p>



<p>“It was emotional for me to watch,” she says. “I was moved by his gratitude.”</p>



<p></p>



<p>Dr. Rosenthal has a history of helping athletes like Liam return to sports. As a former Division I gymnast who also received a cancer diagnosis at a young age, she understands how much they want to get back in the game.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Motivation and medicine</h2>



<p>During her childhood, Dr. Rosenthal was certain of two things: She loved gymnastics, and she was going to be a doctor.</p>



<p>Her plan was to earn a college gymnastics scholarship and then study to become an orthopedic surgeon. “Sports medicine doctors patched me together time and time again,” she says. “That’s what motivated me to go to medical school. I wanted to give back.”</p>



<p>She landed that college scholarship to Utah State University, where her rock-solid floor exercise and balance beam routines helped propel her team to a Big West Conference championship.</p>



<p>“It came with a lot of commitment,” recalls Dr. Rosenthal. “I had to work all of my prerequisites — my labs and everything you have to do to get into medical school — somehow around practice.”</p>



<p>The effort paid off. Dr. Rosenthal was accepted into medical school at Midwestern University in Glendale, Arizona. But two years in, she started to feel sick. She went to the emergency room suspecting the flu. Instead, she was diagnosed with a rare form of cancer known as acute promyelocytic&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/leukemia/symptoms-causes/syc-20374373" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">leukemia</a>. The care she received over the following two-plus years inspired her to shift to oncology.</p>



<p>Dr. Rosenthal now specializes in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lymphoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20352638" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymphoma</a>, a blood cancer with many forms. But she still supports athletes. “For people under the age of 40, one of the most common types of cancer they get is lymphoma,” she says. Because these patients are young, they are more likely to still play sports. Dr. Rosenthal has treated high school, college and professional athletes in baseball, wrestling, water polo, soccer and more.</p>



<p>“My personal experience as a patient with cancer has influenced how I approach patient care,” she says. “My experience as a competitive athlete for my whole life definitely influences how I approach people who are active.”</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Mental toughness</h2>



<p>Dr. Rosenthal shares her story with patients to inspire hope, especially in those who see her as an athlete like themselves.</p>



<p>“She’s been through something similar, she’s still here now, she’s happy, she’s still pushing forward and fighting that fight,” says Liam, who was so moved by his own care that he and his wife, Kristi, became benefactors of Mayo Clinic to support the clinic’s cancer efforts.</p>



<p>In her patients, Dr. Rosenthal sees athletes accustomed to working through discomfort without complaining, just as she did. While staying silent works in practice, Dr. Rosenthal needs patients to describe how they are feeling so she can give them the best possible care.</p>



<p>“It helps to know a little bit about the psyche and the mindset of a competitive athlete,” she says. “This is not a test to see how much you can tolerate without speaking up and saying, ‘I don’t feel good.’”</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Back in the game</h2>



<p>When patients do feel well enough, Dr. Rosenthal encourages them to return to sports, even during treatment. “It helps with managing this experience if you are able to have something that feels regular,” she says.</p>



<p>That doesn’t mean going all out right away. In many cases, lymphoma makes people feel tired rather than sick, so elite athletes might be tempted to push too hard through fatigue. She works with them to define limits that keep them active without setting back their treatment.</p>



<p>“We are keeping an eye on what is important to them,” she says. “And helping them get back to whatever that may be.”</p>



<p>Sometimes, Dr. Rosenthal says, what is important changes for a patient, like how she gave up her dream of becoming an orthopedic surgeon to pursue oncology.</p>



<p>And sometimes, that leads to the unexpected and maybe even a shoutout on national TV.</p>



<p>“I can’t imagine doing anything different at this point,” she says. “I am certain that this is my purpose.”</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Learn more</h2>



<p>Learn more about&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lymphoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20352638" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymphoma</a>&nbsp;and find a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials/search-results?studySiteStatusesGrouped=Open/Status%20Unknown&amp;pocId=CON-20304579" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">clinical trial</a>&nbsp;at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>Join the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/blood-cancers-disorders/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Blood Cancer and Disorders Support Group</a>&nbsp;or the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/adolescent-young-adult-aya-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Adolescent and Young Adult Cancer Support Group</a>&nbsp;on&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Connect</a>, an online community moderated by Mayo Clinic for patients and caregivers.</p>



<p>Join the next&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/event/aya-adolescents-and-young-adults-support-group-14-8371/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">AYA (Adolescents and Young Adults) Cancer Support Group in Arizona</a>, which alternates between online and in-person meetings.</p>



<p>Also, read these articles:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/06/18/fighting-lymphoma-treatment-options-include-alternatives-to-chemotherapy/">Fighting lymphoma: Treatment options include alternatives to chemotherapy</a></li>



<li><a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/03/07/how-precise-diagnosis-of-lymphoma-offers-patients-best-treatment-options/">How precise diagnosis of lymphoma offers patients best treatment options</a></li>



<li><a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/09/06/all-star-pitcher-liam-hendriks-shares-how-he-closed-out-cancer/">All-Star pitcher Liam Hendriks shares how he closed out cancer</a></li>
</ul>



<p><em>A version of this article was originally published by&nbsp;<a href="https://mayomagazine.mayoclinic.org/2024/02/understanding-athletes/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Magazine</a>.</em></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/understanding-athletes-with-lymphoma/">Understanding athletes with lymphoma</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Dr-Rosenthal-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Dr-Rosenthal-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Magazine]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic study finds dysfunctional white blood cells linked to heightened melanoma risk</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-finds-dysfunctional-white-blood-cells-linked-to-heightened-melanoma-risk/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alison Satake]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 20:28:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Discovery Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chronic lymphocytic leukemia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[discovery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Susan Slager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=393487</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — About 8 to 10 million Americans over age 40 have an overabundance of cloned white blood cells, or lymphocytes, that hamper their immune systems. Although many who have this condition — called monoclonal B-cell lymphocytosis (MBL) — do not experience any symptoms, a new study shows they may have an elevated risk [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-finds-dysfunctional-white-blood-cells-linked-to-heightened-melanoma-risk/">Mayo Clinic study finds dysfunctional white blood cells linked to heightened melanoma risk</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-left-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/shutterstock-1440889238-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-393493" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/shutterstock-1440889238-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/shutterstock-1440889238-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/shutterstock-1440889238-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/shutterstock-1440889238-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/shutterstock-1440889238-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Shutterstock</figcaption></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — About 8 to 10 million Americans over age 40 have an overabundance of cloned white blood cells, or lymphocytes, that hamper their immune systems. Although many who have this condition — called monoclonal B-cell lymphocytosis (MBL) — do not experience any symptoms, a new study shows they may have an elevated risk for several health complications, including <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/melanoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20374884" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">melanoma</a>, a form of skin cancer. The findings, by Mayo Clinic researchers, are published in a new <a href="https://ascopubs.org/doi/10.1200/JCO.24.00332" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">paper</a> in the Journal of Clinical Oncology.</p>



<p>People with MBL fall along a spectrum that spans from a low amount to a high amount of these dysfunctional lymphocytes. Previous research has shown that MBL is a precursor to a type of blood and bone marrow cancer known as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/chronic-lymphocytic-leukemia/symptoms-causes/syc-20352428" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chronic lymphocytic leukemia</a> (CLL). People with CLL also have a heightened risk of melanoma.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="225" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/WF4131351_0017-300x225.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-393495" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/WF4131351_0017-300x225.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/WF4131351_0017-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/WF4131351_0017-768x576.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/WF4131351_0017.jpg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/slager-susan-l-ph-d/bio-00083823" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Susan Slager, Ph.D.</a></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Our study is the first to show that people with this pre-cancerous stage of MBL have a 92% elevated risk of developing melanoma. The risk of melanoma is similar to what we see among people with chronic lymphocytic leukemia," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/slager-susan-l-ph-d/bio-00083823" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Susan Slager, Ph.D.</a>, researcher with the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> and senior author of the study.</p>



<p>The findings suggest that having MBL, even at low levels, can serve as a biological signal, or biomarker, for early detection of melanoma, which is increasing worldwide.</p>



<p>Dr. Slager and her research team have been studying the largest available cohort of individuals — more than 7,000 people screened for MBL through the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/mayo-clinic-biobank/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Biobank</a>. The researchers have now followed these individuals for about four years and are finding a collection of potentially related diagnoses among those who screened positive for MBL.</p>



<p>In addition to the increased risk of melanoma, the researchers found that people with MBL were also at <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35969843/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">higher risk of cancers originating in the lymphatic system</a> and <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41375-020-0799-8" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hospitalizations due to serious infections</a> including from <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41408-022-00754-x" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">COVID-19</a>.</p>



<p>"Previously, scientists would equate MBL as just a part of the aging process. What we're seeing, though, is there are clinical consequences to having MBL — contracting serious infections and melanoma are some of them," Dr. Slager says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Technological advances provide a closer look</h2>



<p>Advances in flow cytometry, a high-resolution technology that enables researchers to look at cells in the blood and identify their varied physical characteristics, has helped propel this research. Clinicians and researchers can now identify people with MBL, the precursor to CLL, more easily.</p>



<p>People with CLL have a very high number of these identical circulating lymphocytes: more than 5,000 lymphocytes per microliter. (A microliter is about 1/50th of a drop of blood.) That's compared to a person with MBL, who typically has 1-5 of these circulating lymphocytes per microliter of blood. Through more sensitive flow cytometry, scientists can identify people earlier when their levels are still low.</p>



<p>"The risk of melanoma seems to be the same no matter how many of these cloned lymphocytes are in the blood, suggesting that just having a clonal population of these lymphocytes — meaning, having MBL— increases your risk of getting melanoma," she says.</p>



<p>Patients with CLL are encouraged to get annual skin cancer screenings by a dermatologist and to protect their skin from sun exposure to prevent melanoma.</p>



<p>"Our findings suggest that people with the precursor MBL stage should also be more diligent about following the established guidelines for skin cancer prevention including, for example, use of sunscreen and protective clothing," Dr. Slager says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Next steps</h2>



<p>One of the questions Dr. Slager's team plans to explore next is whether there is a genetic overlap between MBL, CLL and melanoma. One hypothesis is that inheriting a genetic variant that increases the risk of MBL and CLL may also increase the risk of melanoma.</p>



<p>Another area the researchers are investigating is whether MBL impacts the clinical outcome among people with melanoma, including if having both MBL and melanoma reduces one's overall survival or affects a person's response to therapy.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Review the <a href="https://ascopubs.org/doi/10.1200/JCO.24.00332" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive&nbsp;Cancer Center</strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;is defining new boundaries in possibility, focusing on patient-centered care, developing novel treatments, training future generations of cancer experts and bringing cancer research to communities. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs that are changing approaches to cancer prevention, screening and treatment, and improving the lives of cancer survivors.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li> Kelley Luckstein, Communications Department, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-finds-dysfunctional-white-blood-cells-linked-to-heightened-melanoma-risk/">Mayo Clinic study finds dysfunctional white blood cells linked to heightened melanoma risk</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/shutterstock-1440889238-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/shutterstock-1440889238-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[chronic lymphocytic leukemia]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[discovery]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Susan Slager]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>(Video) New hope for patients with metastatic prostate cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-new-hope-for-patients-with-metastatic-prostate-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 14:24:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Alton Sartor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=360616</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic is leading the way with a new treatment for advanced prostate cancer, specifically for prostate-specific membrane antigen-positive metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer (PSMA-positive mCRPC). This treatment involves a radiopharmaceutical known as Pluvicto. It acts like a smart missile, targeting and eliminating cancer cells. Mayo Clinic experts offer this therapy for patients whose prostate cancer [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-new-hope-for-patients-with-metastatic-prostate-cancer/">(Video) New hope for patients with metastatic prostate cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1824" height="1026" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Infusion-advanced-prostate-cancer-16-x-9.jpg" alt="Patient receiving treatment for advanced prostate cancer" class="wp-image-392988" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Infusion-advanced-prostate-cancer-16-x-9.jpg 1824w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Infusion-advanced-prostate-cancer-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Infusion-advanced-prostate-cancer-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Infusion-advanced-prostate-cancer-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Infusion-advanced-prostate-cancer-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1824px) 100vw, 1824px" /></figure></div>


<p>Mayo Clinic is leading the way with a new treatment for <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stage-4-prostate-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20377972">advanced prostate cancer,</a> specifically for prostate-specific membrane antigen-positive metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer (PSMA-positive mCRPC).</p>



<p>This treatment involves a radiopharmaceutical known as Pluvicto. It acts like a smart missile, targeting and eliminating cancer cells.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic experts offer this therapy for patients whose prostate cancer has spread and is resistant to standard treatments such as hormonal treatments and chemotherapy.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/sartor-alton-o-m-d/bio-20548417">Dr. Oliver Sartor</a>, a Mayo Clinic medical oncologist focused on prostate cancer, says Mayo Clinic is at the forefront of treating patients with this novel therapy, offering new options and hope for patients with advanced prostate cancer. He explains what this means.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/yBasGnz6_BM" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: New hope for patients with metastatic prostate cancer</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeyBasGnz6BM"  title="New hope for patients with metastatic prostate cancer" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/yBasGnz6_BM?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:19) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please "Courtesy: Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/SCRIPT-jthEDITS_Metastatic-prostate-cancer-treatment_KLC-.docx_.Oliver65.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Prostate cancer that spreads beyond the prostate is known as stage 4 or metastatic prostate cancer. There's a variety of treatments – including hormonal treatments that can help control the disease.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Therapy for advanced prostate cancer</h2>



<p>"Once the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/hormone-therapy-for-prostate-cancer/about/pac-20384737">hormonal therapies</a> begin to fail, then we have a new term, and we call it castrate-resistant. Metastatic means spread, so it has spread and it's resistant to the hormones. That's metastatic castrate-resistant," says Dr. Sartor.</p>



<p>He says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/cancer/news/lutetium-177-shows-significant-rpfs-benefit-for-metastatic-prostate-cancer/mac-20561488">PSMA lutetium-177,</a> the chemical name for Pluvicto, may be an option for some patients.</p>



<p>"We have to do a scan to be able to determine eligibility because we only want to treat the people that have good PSMA uptake. PSMA stands for prostate-specific membrane antigen, and we have a PET scan that can look at that very specifically," Dr. Sartor explains.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-center-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Quadra-Pet-Scan-2024-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Qudra PET scan, imaging" class="wp-image-392995" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Quadra-Pet-Scan-2024-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Quadra-Pet-Scan-2024-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Quadra-Pet-Scan-2024-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Quadra-Pet-Scan-2024-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Quadra-Pet-Scan-2024-16-x-9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">A patient will undergo a PET scan to help determine eligibilty for treatment</figcaption></figure>



<p>Once eligibility is confirmed, this therapy can be considered.</p>



<p>"It's a radioactive element. It's given intravenously in a short infusion. The FDA-approved regimen is to give it once every six weeks for a maximum of six doses," says Dr. Sartor.</p>



<p>Patients with advanced prostate cancer need a personalized treatment plan. "Please remember that individualization of care is absolutely critical in this disease," he says.</p>



<p>Dr. Sartor is hopeful that this treatment will be made available to patients with prostate cancer earlier in their treatment course.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Conflict of Interest or Disclosure</strong>: Dr. Sartor is a paid consultant for Novartis, the maker of the drug Pluvicto.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-new-hope-for-patients-with-metastatic-prostate-cancer/">(Video) New hope for patients with metastatic prostate cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Patient-advanced-prostate-cancer-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Patient-advanced-prostate-cancer-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Alton Sartor]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Understanding CAR-T cell therapy for cancer: Mayo Clinic expert explains how it works</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/understanding-car-t-cell-therapy-for-cancer-mayo-clinic-expert-explains-how-it-works/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sharon Theimer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 13:22:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=393194</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>World Lymphoma Day is September 15 ROCHESTER, Minn. — For many doctors and researchers, immunotherapy that uses someone’s own immune system to target and attack cancer cells is the next and best frontier of cancer treatment. Chimeric antigen receptor T-cell therapy, or CAR-T cell therapy, is one type of immunotherapy. Sometimes likened to a “smart [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/understanding-car-t-cell-therapy-for-cancer-mayo-clinic-expert-explains-how-it-works/">Understanding CAR-T cell therapy for cancer: Mayo Clinic expert explains how it works</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="799" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Illustration-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-CAR-T-cell-immunotherapy_GettyImages-1148113630-1024x799.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-393209" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Illustration-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-CAR-T-cell-immunotherapy_GettyImages-1148113630-1024x799.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Illustration-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-CAR-T-cell-immunotherapy_GettyImages-1148113630-300x234.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Illustration-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-CAR-T-cell-immunotherapy_GettyImages-1148113630-768x600.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Illustration-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-CAR-T-cell-immunotherapy_GettyImages-1148113630.jpg 1441w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><em>World Lymphoma Day is September 15</em></p>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — For many doctors and researchers, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/discovery-translation-labs/cancer-research/cancer-immunotherapy" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">immunotherapy</a> that uses someone’s own immune system to target and attack cancer cells is the next and best frontier of cancer treatment. Chimeric antigen receptor T-cell therapy, or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/car-t-cell-therapy-program/sections/gnc-20405215" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CAR-T cell therapy</a>, is one type of immunotherapy. Sometimes likened to a “smart drug” or “living drug,” CAR-T cell therapy relies on <a href="https://mcpress.mayoclinic.org/healthy-aging/how-will-crispr-gene-editing-change-healthcare/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">genetically modified immune cells</a> to recognize and destroy cancer cells. In this expert alert, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/vile-richard-g-ph-d/bio-00027663" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Richard Vile, Ph.D.</a>, an immunologist and cancer researcher at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota, explains how CAR-T cell therapy works, including the benefits, risks and realities of treatment.</p>



<p>Over the last decade, immunotherapy-focused research has expanded, and results point toward promising, less arduous cancer treatments. Some immune system-focused drugs, for example, have shrunk or eliminated tumors — even in people with advanced cancers.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Dr.-Richard-Vile_1620847_3874783_0007-200x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-393206" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Dr.-Richard-Vile_1620847_3874783_0007-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Dr.-Richard-Vile_1620847_3874783_0007.jpg 533w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><sup>Richard Vile, Ph.D.</sup></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>“The holy grail of all cancer therapies throughout the years has been to develop a treatment that targets only cancerous cells and not normal or healthy cells,” Dr. Vile says. “One of the reasons <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/chemotherapy/about/pac-20385033" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chemotherapy</a> can be so toxic and unpleasant is that it is very rarely highly selective for the cancer cells, and as a result it can harm other cells. CAR-T cell therapy, in theory, only kills cancer cells, which makes the treatment much gentler on the body.”</p>



<p>The&nbsp;U.S. Food and Drug Administration has approved <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/car-t-cell-therapy-program/sections/gnc-20405547" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CAR-T cell therapy</a> for several conditions, including different types of B-cell <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lymphoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20352638" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymphoma</a>, some forms of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/leukemia/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20374378" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">leukemia</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/multiple-myeloma/symptoms-causes/syc-20353378" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">myeloma</a>. Research is underway at Mayo Clinic to explore CAR-T’s potential to treat diseases beyond cancer.</p>



<p>Like all immunotherapy, CAR-T cell therapy <a href="https://mcpress.mayoclinic.org/cancer/mayo-clinic-qa-podcast-immunotherapy-for-multiple-myeloma/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">harnesses the power of the immune system</a> — in this case, by using and modifying the body’s T cells. As an important part of the immune system, T cells are a type of white blood cell that helps defend the body from infection and are thought to fight cancer.</p>



<p>To prepare these cells for targeted cancer treatment, T cells are collected from the body — typically through blood work — and are genetically treated in a lab. During this process, the T cells are modified to produce special receptors called chimeric antigen receptors (CARs). These CARs change the T cells in two important ways. First, the T cells can “see” certain antigens, called markers, on cancer cells they were previously blind to. Second, the CARs activate the T cell’s ability to kill the cancer cells. In short, Dr. Vile says that CAR-T cell therapy offers the immune system a sort of honing ability on cancer cells that it otherwise wouldn’t have.</p>



<p>From there, millions of these modified T cells are infused back into the bloodstream. In some cases, other cancer treatments, such as low-dose chemotherapy, are used in tandem with CAR-T cell therapy. The process overall is complex and time intensive. The lab process alone can take several weeks to prepare the CAR-T cells, although people don’t need to be in the hospital during this process. It’s also possible that people receiving CAR-T therapy may experience a reaction when the CAR-T cells are reinfused back into the bloodstream. A reaction, if it occurs, may require treatment in a hospital.</p>



<p>CAR-T cell therapy is not yet effective for all types of cancer. Dr. Vile says this type of therapy is most effective for <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/centers-of-excellence/walmart/specialties/blood-cancers" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">blood cancers</a>, called hematological cancers, where tumors tend to be diffuse in the blood.</p>



<p>“In people, CAR-T cell therapy has been extremely successful for blood cancers, likely because the T cells are circulating in the blood, just like the cancer cells are,” says Dr. Vile. “Challenges remain for treating solid tumors, which grow in a localized place, such as in an organ. These tumor sites have evolved to become extremely hostile to immune cells.”</p>



<p>CAR-T cell therapy has been an effective treatment for some forms of cancer — particularly for hard-to-treat or recurrent cancers. In fact, one study found that 18% of people with relapsing, treatment-unresponsive <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/chronic-lymphocytic-leukemia/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352433" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chronic lymphocytic leukemia</a> (CLL) experienced <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/08/15/car-t-cell-therapy-restores-hope-for-leukemia-patient/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">full remission after a single CAR-T cell therapy treatment</a>. Additionally, CAR-T cell therapy has the potential to keep cancer in remission for many years.</p>



<p>Like most cancer therapies, CAR-T cell therapy comes with side effects, Dr. Vile says. Side effects may include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Cytokine release syndrome (CRS), a severe immune system reaction that can lead to death.</li>



<li>Noticeable, but often temporary, neurological side effects such as confusion, seizures, and difficulty speaking or walking.</li>



<li>Temporary blood conditions like anemia and low platelet count.</li>



<li>An increased risk of infection, particularly after the first few weeks of treatment.</li>
</ul>



<p>Scientists are working to develop next-generation methods that will reduce side effects, lower or even eliminate cancer recurrence, and better target treatment-resistant B-cell cancers. Critically, researchers also are focusing on expanding the scope of cancer targets to include a wider number of blood cancers, as well as solid tumors.</p>



<p>“Immunotherapy has really advanced hugely in recent years,” says Dr. Vile. “I believe future CAR-T cell treatment will involve targeting more than a single antigen in cancer cells so that the cancers can’t escape the therapy. Another major advancement would be understanding how we can put CAR-T cells into people so that the cells persist and keep people in remission for long periods of time, potentially for someone’s entire lifetime.”</p>



<p>There may be uses for CAR-T cell therapy aside from cancer treatment. Mayo Clinic researchers are studying whether CAR-T cell therapy may improve treatments for autoimmune diseases as well as reduce the risks of organ rejection in those who receive organ transplants.</p>



<p>For more information visit the <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/search/?search=car-t" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center blog</a> and <a href="https://mcpress.mayoclinic.org/cancer/#full-list" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Press</a>.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/international?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/understanding-car-t-cell-therapy-for-cancer-mayo-clinic-expert-explains-how-it-works/">Understanding CAR-T cell therapy for cancer: Mayo Clinic expert explains how it works</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Illustration-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-CAR-T-cell-immunotherapy_GettyImages-1148113630_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Illustration-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-CAR-T-cell-immunotherapy_GettyImages-1148113630_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>