<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 May 2024 20:00:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Bladder cancer: Research is driving new treatment options, better outcomes</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/bladder-cancer-research-is-driving-new-treatment-options-better-outcomes/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jessica Saenz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bladder cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Mark Tyson]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=388415</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Editor's note: May is Bladder Cancer Awareness Month. Just 10 years ago, people with bladder cancer whose cancer had not spread and didn't respond to treatment often required bladder removal, says Mark Tyson, II, M.D., a Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center urologic surgeon. "Now, we have a whole host of new drugs and clinical trials that allow [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/bladder-cancer-research-is-driving-new-treatment-options-better-outcomes/">Bladder cancer: Research is driving new treatment options, better outcomes</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="938" height="528" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Farm-couple-looking-over-fields-GettyImages-182939490_16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-388422" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Farm-couple-looking-over-fields-GettyImages-182939490_16x9.jpg 938w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Farm-couple-looking-over-fields-GettyImages-182939490_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Farm-couple-looking-over-fields-GettyImages-182939490_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 938px) 100vw, 938px" /></figure>



<p><em><strong>Editor's note: </strong>May is Bladder Cancer Awareness Month.</em></p>



<p>Just 10 years ago, people with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/bladder-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20356104" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bladder cancer</a> whose cancer had not spread and didn't respond to treatment often required bladder removal, says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/tyson-mark-d-ii-m-d-m-p-h/bio-20206454" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mark Tyson, II, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center urologic surgeon. "Now, we have a whole host of new drugs and clinical trials that allow us to offer more options," he says. Many of these options provide effective treatment while preserving the bladder. And clinical trials can provide additional options.</p>



<p>Most bladder cancers are urothelial carcinomas, which begin in the urothelial cells lining the inside of your bladder. Most are also non-muscle-invasive, meaning they have not spread beyond the bladder's muscle wall. While treatment depends on cancer type, grade, stage, the patient's overall health and other factors, Dr. Tyson says "We are, hopefully, going to be able to keep the disease at bay for the vast majority of people."</p>



<p>Dr. Tyson talks about new and developing bladder cancer treatments and what you should know when seeking bladder cancer care:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Individualized treatments and improved techniques are producing better outcomes</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Newly approved drug combination</h3>



<p>In 2023, the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approved a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/news-events/cancer-currents-blog/2023/bladder-cancer-padcev-keytruda-doubles-survival" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">two-drug combination</a>&nbsp;of enfortumab vedotin and pembrolizumab (EV/pembro) to treat locally advanced or metastatic urothelial bladder cancer. The combination was previously only approved for the significant number of people who were ineligible for first-line treatment with a type of chemotherapy called&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements/cisplatin-intravenous-route/description/drg-20062953" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cisplatin</a>.</p>



<p>"Clinical trial&nbsp;<a href="https://www.onclive.com/view/frontline-enfortumab-vedotin-plus-pembrolizumab-elicits-os-improvement-in-advanced-urothelial-carcinoma" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">results</a>&nbsp;showed that EV/pembro was better than cisplatin and cisplatin-based combination chemotherapy in the first-line setting," says Dr. Tyson. Study results also highlighted a 55% reduction in disease progression or death compared to treatment with cisplatin-based chemotherapy, making EV/pembro the first treatment for urothelial bladder cancer to outperform chemotherapy when used as a first-line treatment.</p>



<p>"EV/pembro is now&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/news-events/cancer-currents-blog/2023/bladder-cancer-padcev-keytruda-doubles-survival" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">the new standard of care</a>&nbsp;for patients with metastatic urothelial bladder cancer," says Dr. Tyson.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Single-port cystectomy (bladder removal surgery)</h3>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/cystectomy/about/pac-20385108" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cystectomy</a>&nbsp;(bladder removal) might be recommended for muscle-invasive bladder cancer and for non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer that hasn't responded to other treatments or is likely to spread. It can be done with one large incision or several small incisions using&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/minimally-invasive-surgery/about/pac-20384771" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">minimally invasive surgery</a>.</p>



<p>Dr. Tyson says Mayo Clinic is leading the way in refining a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7214961/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">single-incision robotic surgery</a>&nbsp;for bladder removal and reconstruction. This method shows potential for less pain, fewer postoperative complications and shorter hospital stays, although more research needs to be conducted.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Clinical trials testing new immunotherapy and less-invasive surveillance</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Immunotherapy for treatment-resistant non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer</h3>



<p>Immunotherapy, a drug treatment that helps your immune system fight cancer, is sometimes used to prevent the recurrence of non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer, especially when bladder preservation is a priority. A current standard-of-care immunotherapy is&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/def/bcg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bacillus Calmette-Guérin (BCG)</a>, a vaccine that uses weakened bacteria to stimulate the immune system to kill remaining cancer cells in the bladder. For high-grade, non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer that's unresponsive to BCG, a new immunotherapy called cretostimogene grenadenorepvec is on the fast track for FDA approval, says Dr. Tyson. Mayo Clinic is participating in a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/cancer-clinical-trials/about-cancer-clinical-trials" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">phase 3</a>&nbsp;clinical trial testing cretostimogene grenadenorepvec.</p>



<p>"We presented&nbsp;<a href="https://www.onclive.com/view/fda-grants-fast-track-breakthrough-therapy-designations-to-cretostimogene-grenadenorepvec-for-nmibc" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">data</a>&nbsp;at the annual meeting of the American Urological Association in 2024 showing promising results from a study conducted in patients with BCG-unresponsive, non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer," says Dr. Tyson. "As part of the trial, it's administered once a week for six weeks, and it's well tolerated, so patients don't have many side effects. Then we reassess them for three months, and if they've had a good response, they go on maintenance cretostimogene for three, six, nine, 12 and 18 months." Preliminary study results showed that out of 112 people who had completed the treatment course, 75.2% had a complete response, meaning that their cancer had not recurred. Eighty-three percent of complete responders who had one year of follow-up maintained their complete response beyond one year.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Urine test for non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer recurrence monitoring</h3>



<p>Because bladder cancer has a high recurrence rate and can progress from non-muscle-invasive to muscle-invasive disease during treatment, surveillance is important. Post-treatment monitoring often involves&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/cystoscopy/about/pac-20393694" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cystoscopy</a>, a procedure where a scope is inserted through the urethra — the tube that carries urine out of your bladder — to examine the inside of your bladder.</p>



<p>Intravesical therapy, chemotherapy given directly into the bladder through a tube passed through the urethra, is an option for people with non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer. "Patients undergoing intravesical therapy generally need surveillance cystoscopy every three to six months for a couple of years, every six months for a couple of years, and yearly thereafter," says Dr. Tyson.</p>



<p>Cystoscopies can be uncomfortable and sometimes painful, and Dr. Tyson says a less-invasive surveillance method might become an option for people after non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer treatment. "One of the exciting studies we're doing at Mayo Clinic uses a urinary biomarker from a urine sample to identify recurrence without the need for cystoscopy," he says. The study aims to learn about people's preferences, comfort level and confidence in the urine test compared to cystoscopy.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/bladder-cancer-illustration-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-388420" style="width:741px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/bladder-cancer-illustration-16x9-1.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/bladder-cancer-illustration-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Finding the most effective bladder cancer treatment for you</h2>



<p>Choosing bladder cancer treatment is a personal decision. There are many factors to consider, including bladder preservation and quality of life. Dr. Tyson says it's important to find an attentive care team that treats a high volume of people with bladder cancer and has expertise in different surgical approaches to treatment.</p>



<p>"Try to find a healthcare professional willing to spend time with you to answer your questions," says Dr. Tyson. "If you feel rushed, that's not a good thing. If you feel like your care team isn't talking to you about all the options available, you're not getting a good opinion." He says learning about and considering all the treatment options is especially important if you want to preserve your bladder.</p>



<p>Dr. Tyson also recommends talking to your healthcare team about&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials/search-results?keyword=BLADDER%20CANCER&amp;studySiteStatusesGrouped=Open/Status%20Unknown" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bladder cancer clinical trials</a>, which might be beneficial if your cancer continues to advance after treatment. "People should look for care at centers that offer clinical trials, especially if they have non-muscle-invasive disease. Clinical trials are a good opportunity to get next-generation therapies."</p>



<p>Bladder cancer treatment and survival have improved drastically over the last decade. Dr. Tyson wants people with bladder cancer to know they have more options than ever before.</p>



<p>"If you have non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer, you're unlikely to die from your disease, and it's becoming more unlikely that you will lose your bladder," he says. "For muscle-invasive bladder cancer, the landscape has totally changed with EV/pembro. There's a lot of reason for hope. There's a lot of reason to think you can beat this disease."</p>



<p>This article first appeared on the <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/05/22/bladder-cancer-research-is-driving-new-treatment-options-better-outcomes/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center blog.</a></p>



<p><strong>Additional resources:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/bladder-cancer-what-you-should-know-about-diagnosis-treatment-and-recurrence/">Bladder cancer: What you should know about diagnosis, treatment and recurrence</a></li>



<li><a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2022/05/24/bladder-cancer-patients-require-ongoing-surveillance/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bladder cancer patients require ongoing surveillance</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/bladder-cancer-research-is-driving-new-treatment-options-better-outcomes/">Bladder cancer: Research is driving new treatment options, better outcomes</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Farm-couple-looking-over-fields-GettyImages-182939490_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Farm-couple-looking-over-fields-GettyImages-182939490_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[bladder cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Mark Tyson]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: New chemotherapy approach for treating stomach cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-new-chemotherapy-approach-for-treating-stomach-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[DeeDee Stiepan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2024 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Travis Grotz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HIPEC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hyperthermic intraperitoneal chemotherapy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=364307</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Stomach cancer is caused by an uncontrolled growth of cells that starts in the stomach. Most stomach cancers are found when the disease has spread beyond the stomach, when a cure is less likely. Mayo Clinic experts are exploring new ways to help patients with late-stage cancers. A new approach to treating stomach cancers called [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-new-chemotherapy-approach-for-treating-stomach-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: New chemotherapy approach for treating stomach cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Stomach cancer is caused by an uncontrolled growth of cells that starts in the stomach. Most stomach cancers are found when the disease has spread beyond the stomach, when a cure is less likely.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic experts are exploring new ways to help patients with late-stage cancers. A new approach to treating <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stomach-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352438" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stomach cancers</a> called hyperthermic intraperitoneal chemotherapy (HIPEC) delivers heated liquid chemotherapy directly to the abdomen where it can target the cancer. In this Mayo Clinic Minute, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/grotz-travis-e-m-d/bio-20342285" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Travis Grotz</a>, a Mayo Clinic surgical oncologist, discusses how HIPEC works and the potential benefits of the treatment.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/qX9dTmQkyi4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe id="videoidhttpsyoutubeqX9dTmQkyi4"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: New chemotherapy approach for treating stomach cancer" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qX9dTmQkyi4?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:03) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please "Courtesy: Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/SCRIPT-MCM-HIPECC-Stomach-Cancer-SCRIPT-CE-draft.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>During a HIPEC treatment, the abdominal cavity is bathed with hot chemotherapy to kill any microscopic cancer cells.</p>



<p>"The chemo can stay locally in that region, the abdomen, and then it can continue to work even past the procedure. And then that allows us to use really high concentrations of the chemo directly where the cancer is," says Dr. Grotz.</p>



<p>HIPEC has been used as a treatment for other cancers for several decades, but just recently has been adapted to stomach cancer.</p>



<p>"We use the kind of a different combination of drugs that we've come up with based on other research and data and experience, and put them together and found that, in our experience, that they were more synergistic. They work together to kill the cancer cells very well. Our outcomes were quite a bit better than kind of traditional systemic chemotherapy," says Dr. Grotz.</p>



<p>The outcomes have been significantly better than those achieved with traditional chemotherapy. However, Dr. Grotz notes that more studies are ongoing. &nbsp;</p>



<p>"We want to improve survival, help people live longer, spend more time with their family, do it in a way that's safer, and has less complications and risks to patients," says Dr. Grotz.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-new-chemotherapy-approach-for-treating-stomach-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: New chemotherapy approach for treating stomach cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/HIPEC2-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/HIPEC1-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Travis Grotz]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[HIPEC]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[hyperthermic intraperitoneal chemotherapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Transforming cancer care with treatments at home</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/transforming-cancer-care-with-treatments-at-home/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Osiadacz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2024 14:46:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Clinical Trials]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Healthcare Delivery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Advanced Care at Home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bart Tragemann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Care Beyond Walls]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chemotherapy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jeremy Jones]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Roxana Dronca]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Erin Tragemann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maria Holmes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comphrehensive Cancer Center]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=388111</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Cancer is a life-altering diagnosis requiring complex care that can last months, years and, for some people, the rest of their lives. Studies show that people undergoing cancer treatment can spend as much as 10% of their time traveling to and from medical facilities and at appointments for therapies, lab work or scans. Through collaboration [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/transforming-cancer-care-with-treatments-at-home/">Transforming cancer care with treatments at home</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Cancer-Care-Beyond-Walls-MSS-Video-Still_Models_16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-388400" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Cancer-Care-Beyond-Walls-MSS-Video-Still_Models_16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Cancer-Care-Beyond-Walls-MSS-Video-Still_Models_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Cancer-Care-Beyond-Walls-MSS-Video-Still_Models_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Cancer-Care-Beyond-Walls-MSS-Video-Still_Models_16x9-1536x865.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Cancer-Care-Beyond-Walls-MSS-Video-Still_Models_16x9.jpg 1718w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Cancer is a life-altering diagnosis requiring complex care that can last months, years and, for some people, the rest of their lives. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7666754/">Studies</a> show that people undergoing cancer treatment can spend as much as 10% of their time traveling to and from medical facilities and at appointments for therapies, lab work or scans.</p>



<p>Through collaboration and innovation, Mayo Clinic's Cancer Care Beyond Walls program is transforming care delivery to allow some patients to receive part of their cancer care from the comfort of their own homes while integrating digital technology and remote patient monitoring capabilities to improve clinical outcomes.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=js_1dRlsupM" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Watch: Transforming cancer care with treatments at home</strong></a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidjs1dRlsupM"  title="Mayo Clinic&#039;s Cancer Care Beyond Walls" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/js_1dRlsupM?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>"What we have realized is that as cancer care becomes more complex, it becomes more fragmented," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/jones-jeremy-c-m-d/bio-20469882" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Jeremy Jones</a>, a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> medical oncologist. "Patients end up spending far more of their time undergoing testing and treatments, which can be a great detriment on quality of life."</p>



<p>Cancer Care Beyond Walls is built upon Mayo Clinic's <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/hospital-at-home/sections/overview/ovc-20551797" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Advanced Care at Home</a> capabilities, which replicate hospital-quality care in a patient's home. Cancer Care Beyond Walls has built upon these capabilities to create a new paradigm for outpatients that allows the care team to administer chemotherapy, perform lab draws and conduct telehealth appointments in the patient's home — addressing barriers to care, including financial constraints, time limitations or travel ability.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/dronca-roxana-s-m-d/bio-20055312" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Roxana Dronca</a>, a medical oncologist and the site deputy director of Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center in Florida, explains Cancer Care Beyond Walls is changing how patients navigate their care.</p>



<p>"Cancer Care Beyond Walls gives more people access to cancer care and to clinical trials no matter where they live, reducing the financial and time burden on patients and their families and improving quality of life," says Dr. Dronca. "Providing cancer care in the home for people who are part of this program allows other people with cancer the opportunity to receive treatment in the clinic because more infusion chairs and beds are now available. The program is also designed to reduce a participant’s number of visits to the emergency room through symptom assessment and prompt management."</p>



<p>Maria Holmes, a retired business owner living in Jacksonville, Florida, spends her day on the move. She saw Cancer Care Beyond Walls as an opportunity to stay engaged with activities she enjoys and people she loves.</p>



<p>"I'm able to be with my sister," says Maria. "It is just such a convenience that I could go off and check my time, and say, 'OK, my nurse is going to be here at 9 a.m.,' pop in, get my chemotherapy infusion, and then go back out and continue my walk."</p>



<p>The program allows Bart Tragemann to miss fewer days as an elementary school physical education instructor.</p>



<p>"This program of getting your chemotherapy at home has changed my life," says Bart. "It frees up my time and allows me to do things that I never thought I would be able to do again. My quality of life has changed significantly to a point where I never thought I'd be."</p>



<p>Bart's wife, Erin Tragemann, says treatments at home allow them to spend time with family and make plans that previously had to be arranged around visits to medical facilities.</p>



<p>"Being on this path that we're on right now — being stable right here at home and able to do all the things that we've been talking about doing and going to do them, looking forward to things and going to plan vacations and futures — it's just exciting and wonderful," says Erin.</p>



<p>For Dr. Dronca, the mission of Cancer Care Beyond Walls is personal.</p>



<p>"My daughter, my seemingly healthy 6-year-old daughter, was diagnosed with an inoperable brain tumor in 2020," says Dr. Dronca. "As an oncologist, I was convinced that we can do more. As a mom, I would have given everything, even if a few blood tests were done at home, and we would not have to travel. Even if 1 in 5 infusions were done in the home, we would not have to go through all this."</p>



<p>Dr. Dronca hopes the program will yield an improved quality of life for people with cancer and their families.</p>



<p>"After my personal experience and after my daughter losing her battle with this disease, I'm even more determined that I will fight it with everything I can," says Dr. Dronca. "I will fight it by changing the way we deliver care and making it more comfortable for our patients, and I won't stop until we cure cancer."</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/transforming-cancer-care-with-treatments-at-home/">Transforming cancer care with treatments at home</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Cancer-Care-Beyond-Walls-MSS-Video-Still_Models_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Cancer-Care-Beyond-Walls-MSS-Video-Still_Models_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Advanced Care at Home]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Bart Tragemann]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer Care Beyond Walls]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Chemotherapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jeremy Jones]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Roxana Dronca]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Erin Tragemann]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Maria Holmes]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comphrehensive Cancer Center]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Clinical trials: A significant part of cancer care</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/clinical-trials-a-significant-part-of-cancer-care/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Clinical Trials]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Translational Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Geoffrey Johnson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Judy Boughey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Block]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=388025</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A cancer diagnosis is an emotional experience. Learning that you have cancer can create feelings of hopelessness, fear and sadness. This is especially true if your cancer is advanced or available treatments are unable to stop or slow its growth. "Often, when patients are diagnosed with&#160;cancer, they feel hopeless and scared. Clinical trials are one [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/clinical-trials-a-significant-part-of-cancer-care/">Clinical trials: A significant part of cancer care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="936" height="526" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/2-Cancer-Clinical-Trials-16x9-WF2727318_0018.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-388034" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/2-Cancer-Clinical-Trials-16x9-WF2727318_0018.jpg 936w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/2-Cancer-Clinical-Trials-16x9-WF2727318_0018-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/2-Cancer-Clinical-Trials-16x9-WF2727318_0018-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 936px) 100vw, 936px" /></figure>



<p>A cancer diagnosis is an emotional experience. Learning that you have cancer can create feelings of hopelessness, fear and sadness. This is especially true if your cancer is advanced or available treatments are unable to stop or slow its growth.</p>



<p>"Often, when patients are diagnosed with&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20370588" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer</a>, they feel hopeless and scared. Clinical trials are one way patients can be proactive. They can make a choice in how their care is going to be," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/block-matthew-s-m-d-ph-d/bio-00027434" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Matthew Block, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic medical oncologist.</p>



<p>Cancer clinical trials help physician-scientists test new and better ways to control and treat cancer. During a clinical trial, participants receive specific interventions, and researchers determine if those interventions are safe and effective. Interventions studied in clinical trials might be new cancer drugs or new combinations of drugs, new medical procedures, new surgical techniques or devices, new ways to use existing treatments, and lifestyle or behavior changes.</p>



<p>Clinical trials provide access to potential treatments under investigation, giving options to people who otherwise may face limited choices. "Clinical trials open the door to a new hope that maybe we can fight their cancer back and give them a better quality of life," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/johnson-geoffrey-b-m-d-ph-d/bio-20055408" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Geoffrey Johnson, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic radiologist, nuclear medicine specialist and co-chair of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;Experimental and Novel Therapeutics Disease Group.</p>



<p>You will receive cancer treatment if you participate in a clinical trial. "I think one common misperception about clinical trials is that if you enter a clinical trial, you may not get treatment (receive a placebo). And that's actually very much not true. Most clinical trials are looking at one treatment compared to another treatment," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/boughey-judy-c-m-d/bio-00027350" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Judy C. Boughey, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic surgical oncologist, chair of Breast and Melanoma Surgical Oncology at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota, and chair of the Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center Breast Cancer Disease Group.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>"I think one common misperception about clinical trials is that if you enter a clinical trial, you may not get treatment (receive a placebo). And that's actually very much not true. Most clinical trials are looking at one treatment compared to another treatment."</p>
<cite>JUDY C. BOUGHEY, M.D.</cite></blockquote>



<p><strong>Watch this <a href="https://youtu.be/laXwkIUrBRI?si=IuoFOQpYaNDjEcMV" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">video</a> to hear the experiences of people who have participated in cancer clinical trials and to hear Drs. Block, Johnson and Boughey discuss the importance of clinical trials in cancer care:</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidlaXwkIUrBRI"  title="Enhancing Cancer Care through Clinical Trials at Mayo Clinic" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/laXwkIUrBRI?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>Clinical trials are a significant part of cancer care at Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center. Cancer care teams work together across specialties to make sure the right clinical trials are available to serve the needs of people with cancer who come to Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>"We are very particular in how we select the clinical trials that we have available for patients," says Dr. Boughey. "We want to have the best trials available for our patients. Some of the clinical trials are evaluating drugs — we are so excited about those drugs, but we can't prescribe those drugs for patients without having that trial. And so we will actually fight to try to get that trial open here to have it available as an opportunity for our patients."</p>



<p>If you choose to participate in a clinical trial, you will continue to receive cancer care. "For most patients that we evaluate, there's always the standard of care treatment option for those patients. And then, in many situations, there's also a clinical trial that the patient can participate in," says Dr. Boughey.</p>



<p>People who participate in clinical trials help make new and better cancer care available for future patients. The treatments available for cancer patients today exist because of the clinical trial participants of yesterday. "We couldn't advance medicine if it wasn't for people volunteering for trials. And the promise from our side is to say we're not going to put patients on trials or offer trials for them to consider unless we think there's a good chance that they'll get a benefit or that society at large will get a benefit," says Dr. Johnson.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>"We couldn't advance medicine if it wasn't for people volunteering for trials. And the promise from our side is to say we're not going to put patients on trials or offer trials for them to consider unless we think there's a good chance that they'll get a benefit or that society at large will get a benefit."</p>
<cite>GEOFFREY JOHNSON, M.D., PH.D.</cite></blockquote>



<p>Participating in a clinical trial may give you access to cutting-edge treatment, improve your quality of life and extend your time with loved ones.</p>



<p>"It's definitely worth reaching out to your healthcare provider and asking, 'What clinical trials could I be a potential candidate for?'" says Dr. Boughey. "And remember, you can ask this of your surgical oncologist, your medical oncologist, your radiation oncologist, or any of the physicians you're seeing because there are trials in all disciplines. There are also ongoing trials that require the collection of tissue or the donation of blood. They can also be important in trying to help future generations as we continue to work to end cancer."</p>



<p>Participating in a clinical trial is an important decision with potential risks and benefits. Explore these <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/cancer-clinical-trials/frequently-asked-questions-about-clinical-trials" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">FAQ</a> about cancer clinical trials, and ask your care team if a clinical trial might be right for you.</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/05/07/clinical-trials-a-significant-part-of-cancer-care/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/clinical-trials-a-significant-part-of-cancer-care/">Clinical trials: A significant part of cancer care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Cancer-Clinical-Trials-1x1WF2727318_0018.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/2-Cancer-Clinical-Trials-16x9-WF2727318_0018.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Geoffrey Johnson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Judy Boughey]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Block]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Who should be screened for skin cancer?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-who-should-be-screened-for-skin-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 15:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dermatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Collin Costello]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skin Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[skin cancer screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[skin check]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386714</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Skin cancer is the most common cancer in the U.S. Each year, more than 6 million adults are treated for skin cancer, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Dr. Collin Costello, a Mayo Clinic dermatologist, says anyone can get skin cancer, but some people are at higher risk. So how often should [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-who-should-be-screened-for-skin-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Who should be screened for skin cancer?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/skin-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20377605?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Skin cancer</a> is the most common cancer in the U.S. Each year, more than 6 million adults are treated for skin cancer, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/costello-collin-m-m-d/bio-20537501?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Collin Costello</a>, a Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/dermatology/sections/overview/ovc-20420526?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dermatologist</a>, says anyone can get skin cancer, but some people are at higher risk. So how often should you be screened?</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/On2CTz7Y7Go" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeOn2CTz7Y7Go"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Who should be screened for skin cancer?" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/On2CTz7Y7Go?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:05) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/MCM_Who-should-be-screened-for-skin-cancer.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>A skin check by a dermatologist usually only takes a few minutes, but that short time spent in the doctor's office could add years to your life if skin cancer is detected early.</p>



<p>"I think one of the big things with screening is, because there aren't really rigorously set national guidelines, that we really look to risk factors to help guide who needs to be screened and how frequently," says Dr. Costello.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Skin-Cancer-1-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Dr. Collin Costello checking man for skin cancer" class="wp-image-387389" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Skin-Cancer-1-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Skin-Cancer-1-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Skin-Cancer-1-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Skin-Cancer-1-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Skin-Cancer-1-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Collin Costello checks for skin cancer</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>He says it's important that everyone is familiar with their skin. And you should see a healthcare professional if you notice any changes, like suspicious moles or spots. But for anyone who is at higher risk, an annual skin exam by a dermatologist is a good idea.</p>



<p>"People with personal and family history of melanoma and then personal history of nonmelanoma skin cancers, people over the age of 65, particularly people that burn easily, you know, get sunburned easily as well as have light-colored eyes and light-colored hair — those are the people that are going to benefit the most from the skin cancer screening," says Dr. Costello.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h3>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advances-in-surgery-are-improving-survival-for-people-with-melanoma/">Advances in surgery are improving survival for people with melanoma</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-men-need-to-take-melanoma-seriously/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Men need to take melanoma seriously</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-who-should-be-screened-for-skin-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Who should be screened for skin cancer?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Skin-Caner-2-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Skin-Caner-2-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dermatology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Collin Costello]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Skin Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[skin cancer screening]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[skin check]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Fighting lymphoma: Treatment options include alternatives to chemotherapy, expert explains</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/fighting-lymphoma-treatment-options-include-alternatives-to-chemotherapy-expert-explains/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sharon Theimer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=387894</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Editor's Note: May 28 is World Blood Cancer Day ROCHESTER, Minn. — Chemotherapy is usually the first treatment doctors try to treat lymphoma, including the two most common forms: non-Hodgkin and Hodgkin. But alternatives to chemotherapy are developing, as first-line treatments and as backup options, explains Stephen Ansell, M.D., Ph.D., hematology chair and hematologic oncologist [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/fighting-lymphoma-treatment-options-include-alternatives-to-chemotherapy-expert-explains/">Fighting lymphoma: Treatment options include alternatives to chemotherapy, expert explains</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="500" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Preparing-to-biomanufacture-a-new-CAR-T.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-383215" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Preparing-to-biomanufacture-a-new-CAR-T.jpg 500w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Preparing-to-biomanufacture-a-new-CAR-T-300x180.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Editor's Note: <em>May 28 is World Blood Cancer Day</em></strong></p>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Chemotherapy is usually the first treatment doctors try to treat <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lymphoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20352638" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymphoma</a>, including the two most common forms: <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/non-hodgkins-lymphoma/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20375685" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">non-Hodgkin</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hodgkins-lymphoma/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352650" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hodgkin</a>. But alternatives to chemotherapy are developing, as first-line treatments and as backup options, explains <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/ansell-stephen-m-m-d-ph-d/bio-20053059" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stephen Ansell, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, hematology chair and hematologic oncologist at the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>.</p>



<p>Lymphoma is a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/centers-of-excellence/walmart/specialties/blood-cancers" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">blood cancer</a> that begins when a germ-fighting white blood cell, called a lymphocyte, mutates and rapidly multiplies. There were roughly a half-million new cases of non-Hodgkin lymphoma and 82,409 new cases of Hodgkin lymphoma in 2022, making them the 10<sup>th</sup> and 26<sup>th</sup> most commonly diagnosed cancers that year, respectively, according to the most recent statistics from the World Health Organization's <a href="https://acsjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.3322/caac.21834" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">International Agency for Research on Cancer</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Symptoms may include swollen lymph nodes, itchy skin, night sweats, fever, persistent fatigue, unexplained weight loss and shortness of breath.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/cancer/news/recent-findings-and-future-directions-in-non-hodgkins-lymphoma-therapy/mac-20516002" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Developing novel therapies</a> to improve lymphoma outcomes for patients is a high priority for Dr. Ansell.</p>



<p>"It's about improving outcomes while minimizing side effects — using treatments that can specifically target the cancer and have less of an impact on the body's healthy, normal cells," Dr. Ansell says. "There is a high percentage of patients whose lymphoma is cured. When people are cured, they may have to deal with long-term complications. Our idea is to have the best outcomes and minimize long-term problems."</p>



<p>Dr. Ansell's studies have included work as part of Mayo's Early Cancer Therapeutics Group. The therapeutics research group offers patients whose cancers haven't responded to chemotherapy the opportunity to join early phase clinical trials of potential new treatments.</p>



<p>People with lymphoma may receive chemotherapy alone or a combination of chemotherapy and nonchemotherapy treatments, Dr. Ansell says. Nonchemotherapy options include immunotherapy, chimeric antigen receptor-T cell therapy (CAR-T cell therapy), targeted therapy, bone marrow transplant and radiation therapy, he explains:</p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/discovery-translation-labs/cancer-research/cancer-immunotherapy" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Immunotherapy</a> uses the body's <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ot5LZrVv_7I" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">immune system to fight cancer</a>, blocking cancer cells' ability to hide from the body's attempts to attack it. There are several types of immunotherapy. Dr. Ansell's research contributed to the treatment of lymphoma with immune checkpoint therapy, drugs that help the immune system fight cancer cells without destroying healthy cells.</li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li>In <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/car-t-cell-therapy-program/home/orc-20404317" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CAR-T cell therapy</a>, some of a patient's white blood cells, including T cells, are removed and treated in the lab to produce chimeric antigen receptors, or CARs, that activate T cells' ability to recognize and kill cancer cells. The CAR-T cells are then infused back into the patient. This form of immunotherapy is considered one of the most promising areas of cancer treatment. Dr. Ansell is a member of the CAR-T Cell Therapy Program at Mayo Clinic.</li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/non-hodgkins-lymphoma/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20375685" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Targeted therapy</a> uses drugs or other substances — alone or in combination — to identify and attack abnormalities within cancer cells with less harm to normal cells. Dr. Ansell is currently researching potential new drug combinations and their side effects.</li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li>A <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bone-marrow-transplant/about/pac-20384854" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bone marrow transplant</a>, also known as a stem cell transplant, infuses healthy blood-forming stem cells into the body to replace bone marrow that's not producing enough healthy blood cells.</li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/radiation-therapy/about/pac-20385162" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Radiation therapy</a> uses high-powered energy beams, such as X-rays and protons, to kill cancer cells. For certain types of non-Hodgkin lymphoma, radiation therapy may be the only treatment you need, particularly if your lymphoma is slow growing and located in just one or two spots. More commonly, radiation is used after chemotherapy to kill any lymphoma cells that might remain.</li>
</ul>



<p>Unfortunately, there is no known way to prevent lymphoma, but a healthy diet and exercise are important. They can help patients better cope with cancer treatments and have better outcomes, Dr. Ansell says.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/international?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.  &nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact: </strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Sharon Theimer, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/fighting-lymphoma-treatment-options-include-alternatives-to-chemotherapy-expert-explains/">Fighting lymphoma: Treatment options include alternatives to chemotherapy, expert explains</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/non-hodgkin-lymphoma-cells-original_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/non-hodgkin-lymphoma-cells-original_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Melanoma in darker skin tones: Race and sex play a role, Mayo study finds</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/melanoma-in-darker-skin-tones-race-and-sex-play-a-role-mayo-study-finds/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Vincent Jacobbi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2024 13:13:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Healthcare Delivery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Black Men Black Women]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Tina J. Hieken]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skin Cancer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=387631</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A recent Mayo Clinic study reveals melanoma is often detected later in people with darker skin complexions.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/melanoma-in-darker-skin-tones-race-and-sex-play-a-role-mayo-study-finds/">Melanoma in darker skin tones: Race and sex play a role, Mayo study finds</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/melanoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20374884" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Melanoma</a>, an aggressive form of skin cancer that accounts for 75% of all skin-cancer-related deaths, is often detected later in people with darker skin complexions — and the consequences can be devastating, a Mayo Clinic <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38436625/#:~:text=Conclusions%3A%20NHB%20melanoma%20patients%20presented,and%20treatment%20may%20improve%20outcomes." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> reveals.</p>



<p>While melanoma may be found less frequently in people with darker complexions than fair ones, this potentially serious form of cancer can strike anyone. The study, which consisted of 492,597 patients with melanoma, suggests that added vigilance in early screening is particularly needed for Black men, whose cancers are often found at later stages, leading to worse outcomes compared to white patients.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="640" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Hieken_Tina_J._15589811_202308091522.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-387633" style="width:200px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Hieken_Tina_J._15589811_202308091522.jpg 640w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Hieken_Tina_J._15589811_202308091522-240x300.jpg 240w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Tina Hieken, M.D., senior author of the study.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We compared non-Hispanic Black patients to white patients and saw striking differences in how patients presented with the disease," says surgical oncologist <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/hieken-tina-j-m-d/bio-20089011" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tina Hieken, M.D.</a>, senior author of the study and a researcher at <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>. "We saw more extremity melanoma, and more later-stage disease."</p>



<p>Extremity melanoma refers to skin cancer that can develop on the arms, legs, hands and feet. Various factors, including social risk factors and biological components, could be at play, but further research is needed to help determine why these differences exist.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Revealing differences in sex-based immune response</h2>



<p>The research found that Black female patients with melanoma fared better than Black male patients.</p>



<p>Men tended to be older at diagnosis and more likely to have cancer that had spread to their lymph nodes compared to women. This translated to worse survival rates. The researchers learned that Black men with stage 3 melanoma have only a 42% chance of surviving for five years, compared to 71% for Black women.</p>



<p>Most research on melanoma hasn't focused on how race and sex affect outcomes and hasn't looked at the influence of race and ethnicity across all groups. Dr. Hieken says the study highlights the need to understand these differences better, noting that this is the first large study to confirm that sex‐based differences in melanoma outcomes exist within the non-Hispanic Black population.</p>



<p>"When we talk about later-stage melanoma patients who are female versus male in that non-Hispanic Black patient cohort who ended up doing worse, some biological things may be going on here that are interesting," says Dr. Hieken.</p>



<p>One theory centers on variations in immune response.</p>



<p>"Several immune signals suggest that women may respond better to some immunotherapies than males," says Dr. Hieken.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Identifying the need</h2>



<p>Researchers note that more studies focused on melanoma in a broader range of people, including more Black participants in clinical trials, is key to bridging this knowledge gap and potentially identifying more effective treatments.</p>



<p>"We want to broaden and deepen our reach to better understand the disease that affects all patients," says Dr. Hieken.</p>



<p>She underscores the role played by the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/education-training" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</a> in this study.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"What we've done with the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/education-training" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kern Center</a>, with this study and others, is to identify the need," says Dr. Hieken. "We have a rich, integrated, multidisciplinary clinical research practice in melanoma, and we want to address clinical needs and knowledge gaps relevant to our practice."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A wake-up call in the battle against melanoma</h2>



<p>Dr. Hieken notes that this study is a wake-up call for everyone battling to diagnose and cure melanoma, regardless of the patient's sex or skin tone.</p>



<p>She emphasizes that healthcare professionals should carefully examine areas like palms, soles and under fingernails, where melanoma might be more challenging to spot on darker skin.</p>



<p>"We can incorporate screening for skin lesions or lesions under the nails into the visit for patients as part of their regular checkups," says Dr. Hieken. "What we want to do is elevate care for our patients."</p>



<p>The <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/education-training" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/breast-melanoma-surgical-oncology/sections/overview/ovc-20535267" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Breast and Melanoma Surgical Oncology in the Department of Surgery</a> supported this research. Review the <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38436625/#:~:text=Conclusions%3A%20NHB%20melanoma%20patients%20presented,and%20treatment%20may%20improve%20outcomes.">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery </strong><br>The <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/education-training" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</a> collaborates with clinical areas across Mayo to create and evaluate data-driven solutions to transform the experience of health and healthcare for patients, staff, and communities. It drives continuous improvement of Mayo Clinic as a learning health system, enabling always safe, evidence-based, high-quality care.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.cancer.gov%2F%3Fmc_id%3Dus%26utm_source%3Dnewsnetwork%26utm_medium%3Dl%26utm_content%3Dcontent%26utm_campaign%3Dmayoclinic%26geo%3Dnational%26placementsite%3Denterprise%26invsrc%3Dother%26cauid%3D100721&amp;data=05%7C02%7CJacobbi.Vincent%40mayo.edu%7Cb12b6321231e4910a9d108dc6eaa33be%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C638506924500656520%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=yaPvGOAqgE67ywoalY08jav4AE0ejQJtWSHc9xwodkU%3D&amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining new boundaries in possibility, focusing on patient-centered care, developing novel treatments, training future generations of cancer experts and bringing cancer research to communities. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs that are changing approaches to cancer prevention, screening and treatment, and improving the lives of cancer survivors.</p>



<p><strong>Media Contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Vincent Jacobbi, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Learn more:</strong><br><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-melanoma-misconception-dark-skin-tones-at-risk-too/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Melanoma misconception — dark skin tones at risk too</a><br><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-men-need-to-take-melanoma-seriously/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Men need to take melanoma seriously</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/melanoma-in-darker-skin-tones-race-and-sex-play-a-role-mayo-study-finds/">Melanoma in darker skin tones: Race and sex play a role, Mayo study finds</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-192010801209284023-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-192010801209284023-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Black Men Black Women]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Tina J. Hieken]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Skin Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mcthumb >https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-192010801209284023-16x9-1-150x150.jpg</mayoclinic:mcthumb >	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Treating breast cancer through surgery</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treating-breast-cancer-through-surgery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Osiadacz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 14:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sarah McLaughlin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[National Women's Health Month]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Surgery]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=385952</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Editor’s Note: May is National Women’s Health Month Globally, 2.3 million women are diagnosed with breast cancer every year, according to the World Health Organization. Advances in treating breast cancer are improving care and quality of life. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute  Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:00) is in the downloads at the end of this [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treating-breast-cancer-through-surgery/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Treating breast cancer through surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Editor’s Note</strong>: May is<em> </em><a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fnationaltoday.com%2Fwomens-health-month%2F%23faqs&amp;data=05%7C02%7COsiadacz.Alexander%40mayo.edu%7Cdd0df85f33504177ee6508dc53428b2b%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C638476792487880058%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=KuVGn1eMYBhl5LKKvTE%2FDGj4teDpCcOZuyNqPZmtcHs%3D&amp;reserved=0"><em>National Women’s Health Month</em></a></p>



<p>Globally, <a href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/breast-cancer" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">2.3 million women</a> are diagnosed with breast cancer every year, according to the World Health Organization. Advances in <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/care-at-mayo-clinic/mac-20352479?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">treating</a> breast cancer are improving care and quality of life.</p>



<p><a href="https://youtu.be/kHXecY28KEk" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</strong> </a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubekHXecY28KEk"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Treating breast cancer through surgery" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kHXecY28KEk?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:00) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Mayo-Clinic-Minute-Treating-breast-cancer-through-surgery_Script.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Treating <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a> may include personalized therapies or surgery.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"There are only two surgical options: lumpectomy and mastectomy. But there are 100 reasons why women choose one thing or another," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mclaughlin-sarah-a-m-d/bio-20055048?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Sarah McLaughlin</a>, a Mayo Clinic breast surgical oncologist. "Some of that can be cancer-based, some of it can be family history and genetic, some of it can be personal peace of mind."</p>



<p>A <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/lumpectomy/about/pac-20394650?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lumpectomy</a> removes the cancerous tissue and the surrounding margin of normal breast tissue. A <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mastectomy/about/pac-20394670?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">mastectomy</a> removes the entire breast. Dr. McLaughlin explains that decades of research have shown similar long-term survival rates for both options.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-left-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Lumpectomy-Mastectomy-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Illustration of lumpectomy and mastectomy, treatments for breast cancer " class="wp-image-385928" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Lumpectomy-Mastectomy-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Lumpectomy-Mastectomy-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Lumpectomy-Mastectomy-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Lumpectomy-Mastectomy-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Lumpectomy-Mastectomy-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Lumpectomy and mastectomy are two surgical options for treating breast cancer</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"If you don't need a mastectomy, you don't do better or live longer because you do a more radical operation," says Dr. McLaughlin.</p>



<p>Surgical innovations are improving care and quality of life. Some patients no longer need lymph nodes under the armpit removed, and new techniques remove less skin while preserving the nipple and areola complex.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"That means placing the incisions remote from the actual site of cancer and then rearranging the breast tissue within what remains," says Dr. McLaughlin.</p>



<p>It's important to work with your healthcare team to determine what treatments are best for you. Considerations may include the stage of cancer, your personal preferences and overall health.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h3>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breast-cancer-predicting-individual-risk/">Breast cancer: Predicting individual risk</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/recommendations-to-begin-breast-cancer-screening-at-age-40/">Recommendations to begin breast cancer screening at age 40</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/not-all-lumps-are-breast-cancer-benign-breast-disease/">Not all lumps are breast cancer: Benign breast disease</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treating-breast-cancer-through-surgery/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Treating breast cancer through surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Dr-Sarah-McLaughlin-surgery-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Dr-Sarah-McLaughlin-surgery-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Sarah McLaughlin]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[National Women's Health Month]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Surgery]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Melanoma misconception &#8212; dark skin tones at risk, too</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-melanoma-misconception-dark-skin-tones-at-risk-too/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dark skin tones]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Dawn Davis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skin Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=365837</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The myth that people with dark skin are immune to melanoma, a type of skin cancer, has persisted for many years. It's a dangerous misconception that has caused some people not to be diligent about protecting themselves against dangerous ultraviolet (UV) rays. Dr. Dawn Davis, a Mayo Clinic dermatologist, says people with darker skin tones [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-melanoma-misconception-dark-skin-tones-at-risk-too/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Melanoma misconception &#8212; dark skin tones at risk, too</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="722" height="406" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-514411683-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-366584" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-514411683-16x9-1.jpg 722w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-514411683-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 722px) 100vw, 722px" /></figure>



<p>The myth that people with dark skin are immune to melanoma, a type of skin cancer, has persisted for many years. It's a dangerous <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/skin-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20377605?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">misconception</a> that has caused some people not to be diligent about protecting themselves against dangerous ultraviolet (UV) rays.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/davis-dawn-marie-r-m-d/bio-20054974?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Dawn Davis</a><strong>, </strong>a Mayo Clinic dermatologist, says people with darker skin tones need to be vigilant about sun protection.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/rcsfbWZm6CY" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubercsfbWZm6CY"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Melanoma misconception —  dark skin tones at risk, too" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rcsfbWZm6CY?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:57) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/SCRIPT-Melanoma-dark-skin-tones.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"Melanin is the protein component of the skin that gives our skin color," says Dr. Davis.</p>



<p>Darker skin tones have more melanin. The pigment protects against sun damage and lowers the risk of skin cancer. Some people with dark complexions think melanin shields them from getting cancer. But Dr. Davis says that's a myth.</p>



<p>"All patients, including patients who are skin of color, have a risk of melanoma. Children can also have melanoma," explains Dr. Davis.</p>



<p>When <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/melanoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20374884?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">melanoma</a> develops in people of color, it's often diagnosed at a later stage and is more aggressive. But that could be because skin cancer in people with darker skin may appear in unexposed areas.</p>



<p>"Under your armpits, in your genital area, under your nails, fingernails and toenails, and on the palms and soles," says Dr. Davis.</p>



<p>Dr. Davis says people of color, including children, should wear sunscreen and perform regular skin self-exams.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">How to reduce the risk of melanoma</h3>



<p>The longer you're exposed to the sun, the greater the risk for developing skin cancer. &nbsp;Dr. Davis says there are several things people can do to <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-importance-of-skin-">protect</a> their skin:</p>



<ul>
<li>Wear sunscreen of at least 30 SPF.</li>



<li>Perform regular skin self-exams.</li>



<li>See a healthcare professional for abnormal growths or warts.</li>



<li>Wear protective clothing.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Related posts:</strong></p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-understanding-skin-cancer-and-how-to-prevent-it/">Understanding skin cancer and how to prevent it</a></p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-men-need-to-take-melanoma-seriously/">Men need to take melanoma seriously</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-melanoma-misconception-dark-skin-tones-at-risk-too/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Melanoma misconception &#8212; dark skin tones at risk, too</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/sunscreen-pic-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/man-running-in-sun.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[dark skin tones]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Dawn Davis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Skin Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond weight loss: Bariatric surgery may reduce cancer risk</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/beyond-weight-loss-bariatric-surgery-may-reduce-cancer-risk/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bariatric surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cancer risk]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Maria Linnaus]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=387449</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>When you think about obesity, you may not connect it to cancer. However, researchers long have suspected a link between certain cancers and weight. Among those are endometrial, ovarian, colon, liver, pancreatic and postmenopausal breast cancers, which together contribute to 15 to 20% of all cancer deaths in the U.S. Cancer risk increases with obesity More than [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/beyond-weight-loss-bariatric-surgery-may-reduce-cancer-risk/">Beyond weight loss: Bariatric surgery may reduce cancer risk</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/couple-smiling-together16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-387464" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/couple-smiling-together16x9.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/couple-smiling-together16x9-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></figure>



<p>When you think about <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/mankato/services-and-treatments/bariatric-surgery/about-obesity" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">obesity</a>, you may not connect it to <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/topics/cancer" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer</a>. However, researchers long have suspected a link between certain cancers and weight. Among those are endometrial, ovarian, colon, liver, pancreatic and postmenopausal breast cancers, which together contribute to 15 to 20% of all cancer deaths in the U.S.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Cancer risk increases with obesity</h2>



<p>More than one-third of adults in the U.S. are considered obese with a&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-bmi-is-not-the-only-indicator-of-your-overall-health/" target="_blank">body mass index (BMI)</a>&nbsp;of 30 or higher. BMI is the&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/obesity/in-depth/bmi-calculator/itt-20084938" target="_blank">measure of body fat of body fat based on weight and height</a>. The number of people with severe obesity, which is a BMI of 40 or higher, has increased significantly. According to one study in the New England Journal of Medicine, if a person's BMI goes up by even five points, their cancer risk increases by 10%.</p>



<p>Those who are obese are two times more likely to develop cancer than those of optimal weight. For example, the risk for endometrial cancer increases sevenfold with a BMI of more than 40.</p>



<p>The greater risk of cancer appears to be due to excess body weight in the form of fat. Obesity causes fat cells in the body to increase. As the number of these fat cells goes up, the body's release of hormones changes. These changes tend to increase pro-inflammatory hormones and estrogen. This chronic inflammatory state can lead to damage in cells and the DNA in them, increasing the risk of certain types of cancers.</p>



<p>Researchers are studying the role body fat plays in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/want-to-ease-chronic-inflammation" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chronic inflammation</a>. In addition, hormones like estrogen and insulin resistance can lead to <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/endocrinology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chronic metabolic diseases</a>, including diabetes. By 2050, the <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/diabetes/basics/diabetes.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Centers for Disease Control</a> estimates that 1 in 3 adults will have diabetes along with its associated health complications.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Bariatric surgery and reduction of cancer risk link</h2>



<p>Researchers believe a decrease in inflammatory fat cells could reduce cancer risks, but more research is needed. And it's still unknown to what extent cancer risk is reversed with nonsurgical, also called intentional, weight loss.</p>



<p>But for anyone who has lost weight with lifestyle changes, the challenge is keeping it off. The body has many complex neurohormonal systems in place to avoid starvation, making it difficult to maintain weight loss.</p>



<p>At this time, <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/thinking-about-weight-loss-surgery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bariatric or metabolic surgery</a> is the most effective treatment for obesity available, even when compared with medications and intensive lifestyle therapy. After surgery, people typically lose 50 to 70% of their excess weight or 25 to 35% of their total body weight, which often is sustained for many years.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Continuing research</h2>



<p>Several large studies have been conducted to explore the link between weight loss through bariatric surgery and the reduction of cancer risk.</p>



<p>In a&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://journals.lww.com/annalsofsurgery/fulltext/2019/01000/bariatric_surgery_and_the_risk_of_cancer_in_a.21.aspx" target="_blank">2019 article in the Annals of Surgery</a>, more than 22,000 people who had bariatric surgery were compared with 66,000 who didn't. The study participants were matched by sex, age, study site, BMI and other factors. Statistical models were used to look at the incidence of cancer up to 10 years after bariatric surgery compared to nonsurgical participants.</p>



<p>Those who had undergone bariatric surgery had a 33% lower risk of developing any type of cancer during the follow-up period compared to those who didn't have bariatric surgery. The results were even stronger when the outcome was restricted to obesity-associated cancers.</p>



<p>A&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2793220" target="_blank">2022 study in the Journal of the American Medical Association</a>&nbsp;followed 30,000 people, all with a BMI greater than 35. The participants were divided into two groups and matched by factors including age and sex. One group of about 5,000 patients had undergone bariatric surgery; the other group of just over 25,000 patients didn't have surgery. The median follow-up period was about six years.</p>



<p>The follow-up showed that bariatric surgery was associated with a significant reduction in the risk of obesity-related and other cancers. It also showed that patients who had undergone bariatric surgery had a decrease in cancer-related deaths compared with those who didn't have the surgery.</p>



<p>Researchers continue to delve into why and how bariatric surgery is reducing the risk of cancer and diabetes, and more studies are needed to confirm these results. However, there is promise for patients struggling with obesity that bariatric surgery can decrease metabolic diseases like diabetes and possibly the risk of cancer.</p>



<p>If you're considering bariatric surgery, this new evidence about its effectiveness and benefits may help you decide. It's another topic to discuss with your primary care provider or <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/bariatric-surgery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bariatric surgery team</a>.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/maria-linnaus-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Maria Linnaus, M.D.</em></a><em>, is a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/bariatric-surgery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bariatric surgeon</a> in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/eau-claire" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Eau Claire</a>, Wisconsin.</em></p>



<p>This article originally published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/bariatric-surgery-and-cancer-risk" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/beyond-weight-loss-bariatric-surgery-may-reduce-cancer-risk/">Beyond weight loss: Bariatric surgery may reduce cancer risk</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/couple-smiling-together_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/couple-smiling-together16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[bariatric surgery]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cancer risk]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Maria Linnaus]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>