<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 13:56:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Tomorrow&#8217;s Cure: How personalized vaccines combat cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-how-personalized-vaccines-combat-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Keith Knutson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nora Disis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Saranya Chumsri]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tomorrow's Cure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[vaccines and cancer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=391993</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The new episode of Tomorrow’s Cure highlights the efforts of research scientists who are equipping a vaccine with bits of proteins that redirect the immune system's efforts to specifically fight cancer. The vaccine aims to prevent breast cancer tumors from returning, as relapsing cancer is often more aggressive and difficult to treat. The latest research [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-how-personalized-vaccines-combat-cancer/">Tomorrow&#8217;s Cure: How personalized vaccines combat cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/MCP-17395_TC_S01E05_YT-Thumbnail_Long_1_RLSD-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-391994" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/MCP-17395_TC_S01E05_YT-Thumbnail_Long_1_RLSD-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/MCP-17395_TC_S01E05_YT-Thumbnail_Long_1_RLSD-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/MCP-17395_TC_S01E05_YT-Thumbnail_Long_1_RLSD-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/MCP-17395_TC_S01E05_YT-Thumbnail_Long_1_RLSD.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The new episode of <a href="https://careinfo.mayoclinic.org/tomorrows-cure-podcast?mc_id=global&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=tcepisodefive&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=global&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=185876" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tomorrow’s Cure</a> highlights the efforts of research scientists who are equipping a vaccine with bits of proteins that redirect the immune system's efforts to specifically fight cancer. The vaccine aims to prevent breast cancer tumors from returning, as relapsing cancer is often more aggressive and difficult to treat. The latest research also seeks to understand why some breast cancer tumors evade the body's immune response.</p>



<p>Featured experts are <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/knutson-keith-l-ph-d/bio-00026672" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Keith Knutson</a>, an immunologist and cancer vaccine researcher at Mayo Clinic; <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/chumsri-saranya-m-d/bio-20114242?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=yext&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=departmentcancer&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=cancer&amp;cauid=105142&amp;y_source=1_OTE2NDc2NDktNDgzLWxvY2F0aW9uLndlYnNpdGU%3D" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Saranya Chumsri</a>, a Mayo Clinic hematologist​; and <a href="https://hemonc.uw.edu/people/nora-disis" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Nora Disis,</a> director of the University of Washington Institute of Translational Health Science and the Center for Translational Medicine in Women’s Health at University of Washington.</p>



<p>Vaccines help to protect people from deadly viruses, but can they also help fight cancer? Vaccine trials are underway to target aggressive cancers such as triple-negative and HER2-positive breast cancers. These types of cancers have a high reoccurrence rate.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe id="videoidhttpsyoutubejJxmyMIIXsM"  title="How personalized vaccines combat cancer | Tomorrow&#039;s Cure Episode 5" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jJxmyMIIXsM?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>"I think the tricky part is trying to activate our immune system to be able to recognize that particular cancer. It's different in different types of cancer," says Dr. Chumsri. "I think in breast cancer, it might be difficult for the immune system to generate <a>the</a> effective immune response, but that's what we all try to work for."</p>



<p>"We have a number of different approaches that we're using. So, for example, we have peptide vaccines that are administered with this danger signal so that we can alert the immune system to respond," explains Dr. Knutson.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Experts say, in the future, vaccines would target cancer risk factors, such as inflammation.</p>



<p>"We're actively working on vaccines targeting cancer risk factors like chronic inflammation," says Dr. Disis. "So this would potentially be able to reduce their risk of development of cancer by controlling that chronic inflammation."</p>



<p>To learn more about the progressive work being done with cancer vaccines, check out the latest episode of <a href="https://careinfo.mayoclinic.org/tomorrows-cure-podcast?mc_id=global&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=tcepisodefive&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=global&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=185876" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tomorrow’s Cure</a>. To learn more about Tomorrow's Cure and see a complete list of episodes and featured experts, visit <a href="https://careinfo.mayoclinic.org/tomorrows-cure-podcast?mc_id=global&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=tcepisodefive&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=global&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=185876" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">tomorrowscure.com</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Related posts:</strong></p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/cancer/news/cancer-vaccines-illuminate-more-personalized-treatment-and-prevention-strategies/mac-20539115" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cancer vaccines illuminate more personalized treatment and prevention strategies - Mayo Clinic</a></p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/harnessing-the-immune-system-to-fight-ovarian-cancer/">Harnessing the immune system to fight ovarian cancer</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-how-personalized-vaccines-combat-cancer/">Tomorrow&#8217;s Cure: How personalized vaccines combat cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/MCP-17395_TC_S01E05_IG_Social_Title__1080x1080_.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/MCP-17395_TC_S01E05_YT-Thumbnail_Long_1_RLSD.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Keith Knutson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nora Disis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Saranya Chumsri]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Tomorrow's Cure]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[vaccines and cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Caring for your psychological needs as an adolescent or young adult cancer survivor</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/caring-for-your-psychological-needs-as-an-adolescent-or-young-adult-cancer-survivor/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jessica Saenz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Kristine Donovan]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=390071</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The burden of cancer is different for everyone, and life stages can play a role in how it affects people. For adolescents and young adults (AYAs) ages 15 to 39, cancer is a disruptor during a time when people are experiencing personal growth, taking on new responsibilities and becoming independent. This can take a toll [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/caring-for-your-psychological-needs-as-an-adolescent-or-young-adult-cancer-survivor/">Caring for your psychological needs as an adolescent or young adult cancer survivor</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="938" height="527" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Young-African-American-woman-GettyImages-1455211526_16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390072" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Young-African-American-woman-GettyImages-1455211526_16x9.jpg 938w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Young-African-American-woman-GettyImages-1455211526_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Young-African-American-woman-GettyImages-1455211526_16x9-768x431.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 938px) 100vw, 938px" /></figure>



<p>The burden of cancer is different for everyone, and life stages can play a role in how it affects people. For adolescents and young adults (AYAs) ages 15 to 39, cancer is a disruptor during a time when people are experiencing personal growth, taking on new responsibilities and becoming independent. This can take a toll on mental health, and the emotional and psychological distress of surviving cancer during these formative years can have long-term effects.</p>



<p>Kristine Donovan, Ph.D., a clinical psychologist and co-director of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/adolescent-young-adult-cancer-program/sections/overview/ovc-20564751" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Adolescent and Young Adult Cancer Program</a>&nbsp;at Mayo Clinic, explains how cancer affects AYAs and how to cope.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Prioritize your basic needs.</h2>



<p>When you experience a life-changing event like a cancer diagnosis, fundamental needs like sleep, nutrition and exercise can suffer. Cancer and cancer treatment side effects such as pain, nausea, poor appetite and fatigue can make meeting these needs challenging, ultimately affecting treatment response, mental well-being and quality of life.</p>



<p>If you are experiencing symptoms that make caring for yourself difficult, talk to your care team and ask about cancer-specific mental health support. "Patients have better outcomes when they work with a counselor or psychiatrist who routinely works with cancer patients," says Dr. Donovan. Counselors and mental health providers can help you decide the most effective treatment for your symptoms.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>"Patients have better outcomes when they work with a counselor or psychiatrist who routinely works with cancer patients."</p>
<cite>Kristine Donovan, Ph.D.</cite></blockquote>



<p>Dr. Donovan says talk therapy, such as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/cognitive-behavioral-therapy/about/pac-20384610" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cognitive behavioral therapy</a>, and medication can be effective symptom-management tools. "If a patient is having challenges with appetite because of chemotherapy, a psychiatrist who works in&nbsp;<a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/09/28/onco-psychology-helping-people-manage-cancer-related-distress/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">onco-psychology</a>&nbsp;or the cancer space might know how to tackle more than one symptom with one medication."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Communicate with caregivers, friends and family.</h2>



<p>Understanding your needs and boundaries is an important part of preserving your mental health as a cancer patient and survivor, and Dr. Donovan says this exploration makes up much of her work with AYAs. "Helping patients communicate their needs can be helpful, especially for young adults who've had some growing independence from parents and family of origin, then they're hit with this diagnosis, and parents immediately want to protect and take care of them," she says.</p>



<p>Some people welcome support from family and friends but decide to keep parts of their cancer care and survivorship journey private. For example, you may not want your parents to have access to your health portal, but you would like them to accompany you to certain appointments. Voicing your level of comfort and preferences can help avoid frustration for you and those who support you.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Learn about the resources available to AYAs.</h2>



<p>Individual counseling, cancer support groups, social workers, and financial and career assistance might be available through your cancer care team. AYA-specific resources can also help you navigate the challenges you face.</p>



<p>"If you're 45 or 55, you tend to have more reserves — whether it's financial resources, emotional resources, or a wider network of friends or family who can help you. Younger adults are less likely to have those resources to help support them through the process," says Dr. Donovan. AYA resources are often curated with this in mind.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>"If you're 45 or 55, you tend to have more reserves — whether it's financial resources, emotional resources, or a wider network of friends or family who can help you. Younger adults are less likely to have those resources to help support them through the process."</p>
<cite>Kristine Donovan, Ph.D.</cite></blockquote>



<p>Online resources are available through organizations specializing in AYA cancer survivorship, including:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://triagecancer.org/quick-guides/finding-help-parent-cancer-checklist" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Checklist: Finding Help as a Parent with Cancer</a></li>



<li><a href="https://cancer-network.org/programs-2-3/resource-library/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National LGBT Cancer Network Resource Library</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/survivorship/be-healthy-after-treatment/returning-to-work-after-cancer-treatment.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Returning to Work After Cancer Treatment</a></li>



<li><a href="https://stupidcancer.org/resource-guide/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stupid Cancer Resource Guide</a></li>



<li><a href="https://triagecancer.org/military-veterans-cancer#mil-vet-resources" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Triage Cancer Military, Veterans &amp; Cancer Resources</a></li>



<li><a href="https://triagecancer.org/cancer-finances" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Triage Cancer Toolkit for Navigating Finances After Cancer</a></li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Focus on what you can control.</h2>



<p>During your cancer journey, you will encounter circumstances out of your control, which can lead to feeling powerless. Dr. Donovan says this is a common feeling among AYAs she works with, and it can have a negative impact on mental health and make navigating cancer care, relationships and daily life more difficult.</p>



<p>"As psychologists, sometimes we see patients right after diagnosis before their treatment plans are even in place," says Dr. Donovan. This is often when uncertainty and worry are at an all-time high.</p>



<p>Though you may not have control over your diagnosis or if your cancer will come back, Dr. Donovan says AYAs can cope and regain a sense of power by focusing on things they can control. "I tell them, 'Let's figure out what you can do between now and two weeks from now when you get your treatment plan,'" she says.</p>



<p>If you were just diagnosed with cancer and don't know what to do next, consider:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Making a list of questions for your care team. Ask about resources they can offer you.</li>



<li>Finding an ally, such as a friend or family member you can rely on for emotional support, company at appointments, advocacy or day-to-day help.</li>



<li>Connecting with peers by joining a <a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/event/aya-adolescents-and-young-adults-support-group-14-8370/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer support group</a> with members who can offer guidance.</li>



<li>Adopting habits to improve your sleep, and asking your healthcare professional for support if you continue to have trouble sleeping.</li>



<li>Eating a <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2021/12/30/7-steps-to-better-nutrition-habits-for-cancer-survivors/">well-balanced diet</a> to nourish your body before treatment.</li>



<li>Talking to a school counselor or your employer's human resources team to learn about medical leave policies and schedule flexibility.</li>
</ul>



<p>Dr. Donovan says it's also important to do things you enjoy in periods before or between treatments. "If you have two weeks before surgery, for example, how do you want to spend that time? Maybe you can finish that work project if that's important to you — or maybe you just want to relax and spend those weeks with friends and family."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Understand that it's OK to grieve.</h2>



<p>You may feel grief for many reasons, and they are all valid. Missed college experiences and career goals, prolonged family planning, and financial hurdles are just a few of the many possible effects of cancer.</p>



<p>"It's a life interrupted," says Dr. Donovan. "It's a big shift to go from being a full-time student, young parent or employee to a full-time cancer patient."</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>"It's a big shift to go from being a full-time student, young parent or employee to a full-time cancer patient."</p>
<cite>Kristine Donovan, Ph.D.</cite></blockquote>



<p>Dr. Donovan shares how she observed this shift in her own family. "My brother died of cancer at 35. When he was really sick, he would go to my parents’ house and our mother would put him in a recliner while she took care of his two-year-old daughter. So things shifted. He went from being a successful broadcaster to just being able to hang out with his mom and youngest child," she says.</p>



<p>Dr. Donovan adds that acknowledging the grief and discomfort of cancer can sometimes allow you to begin to find meaningful connections again despite your diagnosis. "Your priorities shift; I've seen this in patients. Their world shrinks, but they're able to find meaning and purpose. In my brother's case, he continued to parent to the best of his ability," she says.</p>



<p>This loss of independence, in any capacity, can feel devastating. "The thing I've found to be most meaningful for patients is just acknowledging how sad it is and how hard it is," says Dr. Donovan. "There's nothing you can say to make that better, but we can give them permission and space to express and process these feelings."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Learn more</h2>



<p>Learn more about&nbsp;<a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/04/04/qa-on-cancer-in-adolescents-and-young-adults/">adolescents and young adults with cancer</a>.</p>



<p>Join the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/adolescent-young-adult-aya-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Adolescent and Young Adult (AYA) Cancer Support Group</a>&nbsp;on&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Connect</a>, an online community moderated by Mayo Clinic for patients and caregivers.</p>



<p>Join Mayo Clinic's online&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/event/aya-adolescents-and-young-adults-support-group-14-8370/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Young Adult Cancer Support Group</a>&nbsp;based in Arizona.</p>



<p>Also, read these articles:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2022/05/12/cancer-and-mental-health-coping-with-the-burden-of-your-diagnosis/">Cancer and mental health: Coping with the burden of your diagnosis</a></li>



<li><a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/11/07/finding-balance-tips-for-managing-caregiving-and-self-care/">Finding balance: Tips for managing caregiving and self-care</a></li>



<li><a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2021/12/30/7-steps-to-better-nutrition-habits-for-cancer-survivors/">7 steps to better nutrition habits for cancer survivors</a></li>



<li><a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/03/21/sally-blackwell-no-longer-on-the-sidelines-after-life-changing-surgery-for-rectal-cancer/">Sally Blackwell 'no longer on the sidelines' after life-changing surgery for rectal cancer</a></li>
</ul>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/06/26/caring-for-your-psychological-needs-as-an-adolescent-or-young-adult-cancer-survivor/">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/caring-for-your-psychological-needs-as-an-adolescent-or-young-adult-cancer-survivor/">Caring for your psychological needs as an adolescent or young adult cancer survivor</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Young-African-American-Woman-GettyImages-1455211526_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Young-African-American-woman-GettyImages-1455211526_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Kristine Donovan]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tomorrow&#8217;s Cure: How nuclear medicine helps cancer patients</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-how-nuclear-medicine-helps-cancer-patients/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Geoffrey Johnson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. George Sgouros]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nuclear Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tomorrow's Cure]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=391726</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Nuclear medicine therapy is sometimes the best option for people who no longer respond to other cancer treatments. It is often helpful for patients with cancers that are historically hard to treat, like prostate cancer or lymphoma. On the latest episode of Tomorrow’s Cure, find out how nuclear medicine, when combined with other therapies, will [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-how-nuclear-medicine-helps-cancer-patients/">Tomorrow&#8217;s Cure: How nuclear medicine helps cancer patients</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Tomorrows-cure-Episode-4-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-391743" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Tomorrows-cure-Episode-4-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Tomorrows-cure-Episode-4-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Tomorrows-cure-Episode-4-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Tomorrows-cure-Episode-4-16x9-1.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Nuclear medicine therapy is sometimes the best option for people who no longer respond to other cancer treatments. It is often helpful for patients with cancers that are historically hard to treat, like prostate cancer or lymphoma. On the latest episode of <a href="https://careinfo.mayoclinic.org/tomorrows-cure-podcast?mc_id=global&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=tcepisodefour&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=global&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=185875" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tomorrow’s Cure</a>, find out how nuclear medicine, when combined with other therapies, will control symptoms and shrink and stabilize tumors, sometimes for years.</p>



<p>This week’s podcast episode features <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/johnson-geoffrey-b-m-d-ph-d/bio-20055408" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Geoffrey Johnson</a>, Chair of the Division of Nuclear Medicine and radiologist and nuclear medicine physician at Mayo Clinic; and <a href="https://profiles.hopkinsmedicine.org/provider/George+Sgouros/2777500" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. George Sgouros</a>, Director of Radiological Physics Division and Professor of Radiology and Radiological Science at Johns Hopkins School of Medicine.</p>



<p>"With chemotherapeutics, we never really know where these things are going. Are they targeting <a>the cancer</a> or where are they going?" Dr. Sgorous says. "[With] this new approach, we can generate images that tell us where the therapeutic agent is going, and it is no longer the black box that it has always been. That’s really a fundamental difference is this treatment."</p>



<p>"If we can give enough radiation safely to the tumors, we can kill anything," Dr. Johnson says. "We can go after any type of cancer with this type of therapy."</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidCTnahCYNooA"  title="How nuclear medicine helps cancer patients | Tomorrow&#039;s Cure Episode 4" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CTnahCYNooA?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>Both physicians are at the forefront of the nuclear medicine field, innovating to provide better cancer care. Dr. Johnson is hopeful about the future.</p>



<p>"Right now, we're treating patients who have failed everything," Dr. Johnson says. "So, we're asking right at the very beginning, 'Can we use these radiopharmaceutical therapies to stop the cancer before it spreads too far?'"</p>



<p>This innovative treatment is providing patients with more resources to fight cancer. To learn more, check out the latest episode of <a href="https://careinfo.mayoclinic.org/tomorrows-cure-podcast?mc_id=global&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=tcepisodefour&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=global&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=185875" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tomorrow’s Cure</a> wherever you get your podcasts. To learn more about Tomorrow's Cure and see a complete list of episodes and featured experts, visit <a href="https://careinfo.mayoclinic.org/tomorrows-cure-podcast?mc_id=global&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=tcepisodefour&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=global&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=185875" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">tomorrowscure.com</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Related posts:</strong><strong></strong></p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/sharing-mayo-clinic-georgia-man-with-neuroendocrine-cancer-gains-quality-of-life-thanks-to-new-nuclear-med-therapy/">Georgia man with neuroendocrine cancer gains quality of life thanks to new nuclear med therapy</a></p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-new-chemotherapy-approach-for-treating-stomach-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: New chemotherapy approach for treating stomach cancer</a></p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-researchers-invented-a-new-class-of-ai-to-improve-cancer-research-and-treatments/">Mayo researchers invented a new class of AI to improve cancer research and treatments</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-how-nuclear-medicine-helps-cancer-patients/">Tomorrow&#8217;s Cure: How nuclear medicine helps cancer patients</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Tomorrows-cure-Episode-4-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Tomorrows-cure-Episode-4-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Geoffrey Johnson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. George Sgouros]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Nuclear Medicine]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Tomorrow's Cure]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Treatment and research of glioblastoma</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treatment-and-research-of-glioblastoma/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Osiadacz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2024 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[brain cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brain Tumor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Alfredo Quinones Hinojosa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[glioblastoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=385954</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Editor's note:  Glioblastoma Awareness Day is July 17 Considered the most aggressive type of brain cancer, glioblastoma grows rapidly, destroying healthy tissue. Globally, approximately 300,000 people are diagnosed each year with glioblastoma. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:05) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treatment-and-research-of-glioblastoma/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Treatment and research of glioblastoma</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Editor's note:  Glioblastoma Awareness Day is July 17</em></p>



<p>Considered the most aggressive type of brain cancer, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/glioblastoma/cdc-20350148?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">glioblastoma</a> grows rapidly, destroying healthy tissue. Globally, approximately <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7302718/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">300,000 people</a> are diagnosed each year with glioblastoma.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/DP7p09z_mOY" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeDP7p09zmOY"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Treatment and research of glioblastoma" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/DP7p09z_mOY?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:05) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/SCRIPT-MCM-Glioblastoma.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Glioblastoma is a type of cancer affecting glial cells, which connect nerve cells and support brain function.</p>



<p>"It tends to be a tumor that also tends to grow and invade the brain," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/quinones-hinojosa-alfredo-m-d/bio-20238939?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Alfredo Quinones-Hinojosa</a>, a neurosurgeon at Mayo Clinic. "Sometimes it can be slow and steady, but it tends to grow very fast."</p>



<p>Despite significant advances in surgery, chemotherapy, immunotherapy and radiation technology, the prognosis of glioblastoma remains poor.</p>



<p>“The median survival of patients with the best therapies tends to be between 12 and 14 months,” says Dr. Quinones-Hinojosa.</p>



<p>There is no known cure for glioblastoma, but treatments may help slow the progression or help stabilize the quality of life. <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/brain-tumor-stem-cell-research/overview?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Research</a> is making strides, giving patients more options and hope.</p>



<p>“Research is crucial to find hope and healing on every corner of our operating room, in every corner of our laboratory, and to connect those two, ultimately, through our patients," says Dr. Quinones-Hinojosa.</p>



<p>Related posts:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/fighting-glioblastoma-one-of-the-deadliest-forms-of-brain-cancer/">Fighting glioblastoma — one of the deadliest forms of brain cancer</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-types-of-brain-tumors-and-treatments/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Types of brain tumors and treatments</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/discoverys-edge-battling-brain-cancers-through-genomics/">Discovery’s Edge: Battling brain cancers through genomics</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treatment-and-research-of-glioblastoma/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Treatment and research of glioblastoma</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/03/Glioblastoma-illustration-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/03/glioblastoma-illustration3-16-x-9_Fotor.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[brain cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Brain Tumor]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Alfredo Quinones Hinojosa]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[glioblastoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>A student&#8217;s approach in biomedical research aims to give others a voice</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-students-approach-in-biomedical-research-aims-to-give-others-a-voice/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kate Ledger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 15:10:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. David Lott]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=391524</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Growing up as the child of a voice instructor, Emily Hardy developed a lifelong interest in singing. But the third-year student at Mayo Clinic Alix School of Medicine never dreamed her interest in vocals would lead to research related to the first larynx transplant at Mayo Clinic. "When I first learned that Mayo Clinic was [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-students-approach-in-biomedical-research-aims-to-give-others-a-voice/">A student&#8217;s approach in biomedical research aims to give others a voice</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="575" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_9565_16x9-1024x575.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-391674" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_9565_16x9-1024x575.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_9565_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_9565_16x9-768x431.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_9565_16x9-1536x863.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_9565_16x9-2048x1151.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Growing up as the child of a voice instructor, Emily Hardy developed a lifelong interest in singing. But the third-year student at <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/mayo-clinic-alix-school-of-medicine/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Alix School of Medicine</a> never dreamed her interest in vocals would lead to research related to the first larynx transplant at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>"When I first learned that Mayo Clinic was advancing the larynx transplant, I thought the procedure is something that will be exciting for Mayo to be able to do for patients — something I couldn't even fathom," she says. "I knew I wanted to be fully involved in advancing the research in this area."</p>



<p>In addition to her medical degree, Hardy is pursuing a master's degree at <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a>. Her research project is looking at ways to make the post-laryngeal transplant regimen easier for patients. Because receiving a transplant requires lifelong immunosuppressive drugs to prevent rejection of the new organ, Hardy is investigating removing the cells of a laryngeal transplant model, looking for approaches that reduce the immune response and, hopefully, the need for medication.</p>



<p>"If we can reduce the immune response or the need for immunosuppression that could make laryngeal transplant available to more patients and improve their quality of life," she says.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Voice as a hobby and a scientific study</strong></h2>



<p>Finding joy in singing with others, Hardy participated in a choir in college, and, when she came to medical school at Mayo Clinic in Arizona, she performed with a community-based barbershop group.</p>



<p>"I've always loved anything related to the voice," she says. "When I came to medical school, I'd never thought of incorporating that into my career until I began learning about laryngology and ear nose and throat surgery and realized how those specialties matched that specific interest."</p>



<p>As a medical student also interested in conducting biomedical research, her interest in the intersection of that work and singing would put her at the cutting edge of a brand-new field of study: regenerative sciences. During her first year of medical school, as she sought opportunities to work in a lab, she found <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/lott-david-g-m-d/bio-00092606" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">David Lott, M.D.</a>, chair of the Department of Otolaryngology (ENT) - <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/head-and-neck-cancer-center/sections/overview/ovc-20457072" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Head and Neck Surgery</a>/Audiology at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/arizona" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Arizona</a>. His research applies the approaches of regenerative medicine to restoring the voices of patients who have had a laryngectomy — a surgery to remove the voice box.</p>



<p>Regenerative medicine is an approach that shifts the focus from treating disease to rebuilding health by repairing, replacing or restoring damaged tissues, cells or organs.&nbsp;As director of the Head and Neck Regenerative Medicine Lab at Mayo Clinic, Dr. Lott has focused on establishing techniques to regenerate the voice box and restore its abilities after diseases or traumas.</p>



<p>His work led to the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-marks-medical-milestone-with-worlds-first-known-successful-total-larynx-transplant-performed-in-a-patient-with-an-active-cancer-as-part-of-a-clinical-trial/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">first laryngeal transplant at Mayo Clinic</a> — actually replacing a damaged voice box with all its necessary functions. People whose voice box was damaged from injury, cancer or the residual effects of radiation treatment — as many as 60,000 people in the U.S. — can neither speak with their natural voices nor breathe through their noses. Mayo Clinic is in the process of establishing the first ongoing larynx transplant program in the country. Dr. Lott and colleagues are advancing the transplant procedure and also exploring other regenerative approaches to larynx restoration, including the use of stem cells and growth factors to help grow functional tissue.</p>



<p>As Hardy learned about the lab's various approaches to laryngeal transplant and the potential to restore function through regenerative sciences, she knew she wanted to contribute to research to further options for voice-impaired patients.</p>



<p>The field of regenerative medicine is so new that few people are versed in its principles and techniques. Mayo Clinic is at the forefront of training the workforce in this emerging field, offering doctoral and post-graduate training in Regenerative Sciences through the Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences. Hardy is an example of the future physician-scientists that Mayo is training to deliver the newest regenerative technologies and carry on the work for the next generation.</p>



<p>"Education plays a key role, complementing the research and practice components, in the laryngeal transplant," says Dr. Lott. The entire staff involved in a transplant rehearsed and trained for it, including nurses who underwent specialized in-service training and online courses. Training for the laryngeal transplant provided a unique learning opportunity for residents at<a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/residencies-and-fellowships/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"> Mayo Clinic School of Graduate Medical Education</a>, including head and neck surgical resident Payam Entezami, M.D., who assisted the surgical team.&nbsp;</p>



<p>To address patient needs following the transplant, Hardy found she could amplify her medical school training by pausing it to pursue a master's degree in regenerative sciences, attending classes about its innovative approaches and conducting research in Dr. Lott's lab. She is among Mayo's first students in the program, and says she is impressed by the topics involved — stem cells, tissue engineering, 3D bioprinting — and the vast areas of medicine it touches.</p>



<p>"There are so many different approaches within regenerative medicine and ways to apply it to specific clinical areas of interest," she says.</p>



<p>"We’re educating a specialized clinical workforce of the future, who will have the understanding to manifest the potential held within regenerative medicine," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/wyles-saranya-p-m-d-ph-d/bio-20476857" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Saranya Wyles, M.D., Ph.D.</a> a dermatologist and associate director of education at Mayo Clinic Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics. "Regenerative technologies, focused on restoring form and function, have the potential to transform standard of care. The approach begets a new set of skills."</p>



<p>Dr. Lott is enthusiastic that Hardy's research will contribute to the growing information about laryngeal transplant. He's also emphatic about the importance of the various educational opportunities emerging in regenerative medicine.</p>



<p>"We're training the next generation of scientists and clinicians who are going to be pushing the field ahead," he says. "It's one thing to be able to develop regenerative approaches for patients now. It's a whole other to establish the experts in this new field who can help patients for years and years down the road."</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-students-approach-in-biomedical-research-aims-to-give-others-a-voice/">A student&#8217;s approach in biomedical research aims to give others a voice</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/EmilyHardy-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/EmilyHardy-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. David Lott]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Teamwork and research play a key role in Mayo Clinic&#8217;s first larynx transplant</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/teamwork-and-research-play-a-key-role-in-mayo-clinics-first-larynx-transplant/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Buckles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 12:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Biotherapeutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#biomedical research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Dr. Brent Chang]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Dr. Brittany Howard]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Dr. David Lott]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Dr. Girish Mour]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Dr. Melissa Zheng]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Dr. Michael Hinni]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#larynx transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Mayo Clinic Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=391579</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Surgeons at Mayo Clinic in Arizona perform a total larynx transplant Mayo Clinic's unique culture of teamwork and collaboration, hallmarks since the days of Dr. Will and Dr. Charlie Mayo, laid the foundation for Mayo's first larynx transplant that happened February 29 in Arizona. This groundbreaking surgery, only third larynx transplant in the U.S., continues [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/teamwork-and-research-play-a-key-role-in-mayo-clinics-first-larynx-transplant/">Teamwork and research play a key role in Mayo Clinic&#8217;s first larynx transplant</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Surgeons at Mayo Clinic in Arizona perform the first total larynx transplant in a patient with cancer as part of a clinical trial." class="wp-image-391589" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><em>Surgeons at Mayo Clinic in Arizona perform a total larynx transplant</em></p>



<p>Mayo Clinic's unique culture of teamwork and collaboration, hallmarks since the days of Dr. Will and Dr. Charlie Mayo, laid the foundation for Mayo's first larynx transplant that happened February 29 in Arizona. This groundbreaking surgery, only third larynx transplant in the U.S., continues the innovative work for which the Mayo brothers were known.</p>



<p>A team of six surgeons and 20 support staff combined expertise from the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/ent-head-neck-surgery/sections/doctors/drc-20424100" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Otolaryngology</a>&nbsp;with the&nbsp;mastery of the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/home/orc-20203891" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Transplantation</a> in an extraordinary 21-hour operation. They transplanted a donor larynx in a 59-year-old patient with cancer whose damaged larynx hampered his ability to talk, swallow and breathe.</p>



<p>The <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/larynx-trachea-transplant/overview/ovc-20508897" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">larynx transplant</a> was a composite neck transplant that included at least eight different types of tissue, including the larynx, upper trachea, upper esophagus, pharynx, thyroid glands, parathyroid glands, nerves and blood vessels — commonly called the throat.&nbsp; It's a rare type of transplant known as a vascular composite allograft.&nbsp; The larynx — also called the voice box — is a delicate organ composed of tissue, cartilage and joints that must be able to move after transplantation.</p>



<p><em><a href="https://youtu.be/Z_1E_OtA88w" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Teamwork and research played a key role the first total larynx transplant at Mayo Clinic</a></em></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeZ1EOtA88w"  title="Larynx Transplant Research - Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Z_1E_OtA88w?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:56) in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/LarynxTransplantResearch.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script.</a></strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A team science approach to larynx transplantation</strong></h2>



<p>This complex surgery is an example of Mayo Clinic's team science approach, to advance research innovation to patient care.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Mayo Clinic's team science approach made it possible for us to offer this type of a transplant on a scale that was previously unattainable," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/lott-david-g-m-d/bio-00092606" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">David Lott, M.D.</a>, chair of the Arizona Department of Otolaryngologist and lead surgeon. "All transplants are complex, but there are more tissue types and moving parts with laryngeal transplantation than other transplants.</p>



<p>In any transplant, the body's immune system flags the donor organ as a foreign object and tries to reject it. A key to success is identifying the right immunosuppressant drugs that allow the body to recognize and accept the new tissue. That was exceptionally challenging in this complex surgery that required eight types of donor tissue. This first transplant will serve as a baseline for understanding the various immune responses, quality of life and long-term sustainability of the larynx transplant.</p>



<p>"Our research laid the foundation for understanding the unique immunosuppressant needs of the patient after transplanting multiple types of tissues," says Dr. Lott. "Preclinical models helped us learn which medications could regulate the immune responses of the various different donor tissue with fewest potential side effects and still be powerful enough to prevent rejection."</p>



<p>This is also the first known larynx transplant in a patient with active cancer who was part of a <a href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/study/NCT03269396?intr=larynx%20transplant&amp;rank=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">clinical trial.</a> &nbsp;Dr. Lott and the team will now conduct research aimed at establishing scientific evidence to support the first-ever clinical service line in laryngeal transplantation.</p>



<p>"Because this surgery is so rare, there are a lot of unknowns.&nbsp; We will continue our study of laryngeal transplantation in the patient's follow-up care to determine how well the new organ has restored his ability to talk, breathe and eat," says Dr. Lott. "Besides the quality-of-life issues, we want to study how well the transplanted tissues are functioning over time."</p>



<p>The initial focus of the larynx transplant study will be patients who have a voice box that is no longer functional due to previous cancer or traumatic injury. The team is not yet transplanting a donor larynx in a person who has had a total larynx removal — known as a laryngectomy. They hope to use the research to improve this surgery to make it possible for more patients, including those without a larynx, in the near future.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p>Dr. Lott is the chair of the Department of Otolaryngology in Arizona, director of the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/head-and-neck-regenerative-medicine/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Head and Neck Regenerative Medicine Lab at Mayo Clinic</a>, surgical director of the Larynx and Trachea Transplantation Program, and the associate director of the Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</a> in Arizona. His team's research and practice seek to restore laryngeal and tracheal function through 3D-bioprinted implants and full organ transplantation</p>



<p>Additional members of the transplant team are:&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/chang-brent-a-m-d/bio-20530473" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Brent Chang, M.D.</a>, otolaryngology, head and neck surgeon.<br>Payam Entezami, M.D., otolaryngology <br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/hinni-michael-l-m-d/bio-20053549" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Michael Hinni, M.D.</a>, otolaryngology, head and neck surgeon.<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/howard-brittany-e-m-d/bio-20364052" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Brittany Howard, M.D.</a>, otolaryngology, facial plastics and reconstruction surgeon.<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/zheng-melissa-m-d/bio-20555403" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Melissa Zheng, M.D.</a>, otolaryngology, laryngeal surgeon.<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mour-girish-k-m-b-b-s/bio-20392405" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Girish Mour, M.B.B.S.</a>, transplant medical director </p>



<p>###</p>



<p>Related stories:</p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-marks-medical-milestone-with-worlds-first-known-successful-total-larynx-transplant-performed-in-a-patient-with-an-active-cancer-as-part-of-a-clinical-trial/">Mayo Clinic marks medical milestone with world's first known successful total larynx transplant performed in a patient with an active cancer as part of a clinical trial</a></p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-is-laryngeal-chondrosarcoma/">What is laryngeal chondrosarcoma?</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p><a id="_msocom_1"></a></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/teamwork-and-research-play-a-key-role-in-mayo-clinics-first-larynx-transplant/">Teamwork and research play a key role in Mayo Clinic&#8217;s first larynx transplant</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#biomedical research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Dr. Brent Chang]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Dr. Brittany Howard]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Dr. David Lott]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Dr. Girish Mour]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Dr. Melissa Zheng]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Dr. Michael Hinni]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#larynx transplant]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Mayo Clinic Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Can you prevent cancer with lifestyle changes?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/can-you-prevent-cancer-with-lifestyle-changes/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[DeeDee Stiepan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 14:12:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jon Ebbert]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381968</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Nearly half of cancer deaths in the U.S. are associated with preventable risk factors — such as smoking and alcohol use — according to a new American Cancer Society study. Dr. Jon Ebbert, medical director of the Mayo Clinic Nicotine Dependence Center, says it's never too late to make lifestyle changes that can decrease your risk of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/can-you-prevent-cancer-with-lifestyle-changes/">Can you prevent cancer with lifestyle changes?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Nearly half of cancer deaths in the U.S. are associated with preventable risk factors — such as smoking and alcohol use — according to a new American Cancer Society <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Facsjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com%2Fdoi%2Ffull%2F10.3322%2Fcaac.21858&amp;data=05%7C02%7CStreed.Joel%40mayo.edu%7C1f899e6512964df08de208dca27abb8e%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C638563895216810300%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=g3uUP7KeOeidFbrOTlnm1MkrA01X3TKXu2IqEm3F%2FTI%3D&amp;reserved=0">study</a>. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/ebbert-jon-o-m-d/bio-20053361?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Jon Ebbert</a>, medical director of the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/nicotine-dependence-center/sections/overview/ovc-20457521?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Nicotine Dependence Center</a>, says it's never too late to make lifestyle changes that can decrease your risk of cancer.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/__d7F9sEcaQ" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Prevent cancer with lifestyle changes</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubed7F9sEcaQ"  title="Can you prevent cancer with lifestyle changes?" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/__d7F9sEcaQ?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:27) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/SCRIPT-Cancer-prevention.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>What do tobacco, alcohol and obesity have in common? They can all increase your risk of developing cancer. Smoked tobacco is strongly linked to cancer in almost every part of the body.</p>



<p>"Smoked tobacco produces about 7,000 chemicals, and when you inhale those chemicals in your body, they cause alterations in cells. And it's those alterations in cells that can lead to cancer," says Dr. Ebbert.</p>



<p>He says smoking also weakens your immune system, making it harder to fight cancer cells. One of the best ways to lower your cancer risk is to not use any kind of tobacco.</p>



<p>"We always say it's never too late to stop smoking. And the risk for cancer after quitting cigarette smoking, for example, goes down. But it takes some time," says Dr. Ebbert.</p>



<p>Consuming alcohol increases your risk of breast, head and neck, esophageal, and colorectal cancers.</p>



<p>"At every level of alcohol consumption, there is cancer risk, but heavier drinkers have higher cancer risk than lighter drinkers," says Dr. Ebbert.</p>



<p>Finally, packing on extra pounds can increase your risk of cancer in several ways.</p>



<p>"Excess body weight increases estrogen and insulin, which can increase the rate of cellular division, which can increase the risk for cancer. But also, excess body weight is associated with inflammation, and inflammation is a known risk factor for the development of cancer," says Dr. Ebbert.</p>



<p>Bariatric surgery has been shown to decrease risk of hormone-related cancers such as breast, endometrial and prostate, as well as pancreatic and colorectal cancers. However, there are less drastic steps people can take.</p>



<p>"Small sustainable steps toward weight loss are the most effective when we think about diet and exercise. Those are the classic approaches, but also there are new medications on the market that can help people lose weight," says Dr. Ebbert.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/can-you-prevent-cancer-with-lifestyle-changes/">Can you prevent cancer with lifestyle changes?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/shutterstock_299245511_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/shutterstock_299245511_Fotor-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jon Ebbert]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>What is laryngeal chondrosarcoma?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-is-laryngeal-chondrosarcoma/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 14:25:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chondrosarcoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[laryngeal cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=390348</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>You may have heard about a recent first at Mayo Clinic, a total larynx transplant. What you may not have heard was what precipitated that transplant. The patient developed a rare form of cancer called laryngeal chondrosarcoma.&#160; Dr. David Lott is a Mayo Clinic otolaryngologist who specializes in laryngeal cancer. He says your larynx, or [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-is-laryngeal-chondrosarcoma/">What is laryngeal chondrosarcoma?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx2-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390364" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx2-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx2-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx2-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx2-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx2-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>You may have heard about a recent first at Mayo Clinic, a <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-marks-medical-milestone-with-worlds-first-known-successful-total-larynx-transplant-performed-in-a-patient-with-an-active-cancer-as-part-of-a-clinical-trial/">total larynx transplant</a>. What you may not have heard was what precipitated that transplant. The <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-the-silence-first-known-total-larynx-transplant-on-a-patient-with-active-cancer-as-part-of-landmark-clinical-trial/">patient</a> developed a rare form of cancer called laryngeal <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/chondrosarcoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20354196" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chondrosarcoma</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/lott-david-g-m-d/bio-20055443" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. David Lott</a> is a Mayo Clinic otolaryngologist who specializes in laryngeal cancer. He says your larynx, or voice box, essentially sits in the middle of your throat. "And it has a bunch of jobs. It is the primary organ that's responsible for your ability to speak, for your ability to swallow, to eat and drink, and to breathe," says Dr. Lott.</p>



<p><a href="https://youtu.be/cXeydIJwgdA" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Watch: What is laryngeal chondrosarcoma?</strong></a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubecXeydIJwgdA"  title="What is laryngeal chondrosarcoma?" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cXeydIJwgdA?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:35) in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/What-is-laryngeal-chondrosarcoma.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script.</a></strong></p>



<p>Unfortunately, like the rest of your body, things can go wrong, including cancer.</p>



<p>"Laryngeal chondrosarcoma are cancers of the cartilage within the larynx," says Dr. Lott.</p>



<p>It's an uncommon cancer, accounting for about 1% of overall laryngeal cancers. Symptoms may include hoarseness, breathing difficulties and pain in the throat. "Laryngeal chondrosarcomas are treated a little bit differently than the typical laryngeal cancers," adds Dr. Lott.</p>



<p>Step 1, he says, is determining the grade of cancer. Is it mild or a more aggressive form?</p>



<p>"If there's a lot of destruction and the patient is having a lot of symptoms, like not being able to breathe or not being able to swallow or have lost their voice, then we need to act a little more aggressively to try to remove that tumor to try to preserve what function they have," says Dr. Lott.</p>



<p>Because of its rarity and the intricate anatomy, this cancer type needs specialized care from a team of experts, including otolaryngologists and oncologists. According to Dr. Lott, unlike many cancers, even some other laryngeal cancers, "there really isn't much that people do to get that type of a cancer. It's not strictly associated with things like smoking or alcohol use. It tends to be, honestly, just bad luck."</p>



<p><strong>Additional resources:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-marks-medical-milestone-with-worlds-first-known-successful-total-larynx-transplant-performed-in-a-patient-with-an-active-cancer-as-part-of-a-clinical-trial/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic marks medical milestone with world's first known successful total larynx transplant performed in a patient with an active cancer as part of a clinical trial&nbsp;</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-the-silence-first-known-total-larynx-transplant-on-a-patient-with-active-cancer-as-part-of-landmark-clinical-trial/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Breaking the silence: First known total larynx transplant on a patient with active cancer as part of landmark clinical trial</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/preparing-for-mayos-first-larynx-transplant/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Research prepares for Mayo's first larynx transplant</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-is-laryngeal-chondrosarcoma/">What is laryngeal chondrosarcoma?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx2-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx2-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[chondrosarcoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[laryngeal cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tomorrow&#8217;s Cure: How DNA guides cancer detection</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-how-dna-guides-cancer-detection/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 11:46:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DNA test for cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Kelly Bolton]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Mrinal Patnaik]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tomorrow's Cure]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=390372</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>What if you knew you'd get sick before you ever felt symptoms? If it was a cold, that information is useful. In the case of cancer, it is lifesaving. This week's podcast episode of Tomorrow's Cure explores how DNA could be used to detect blood cancers before they ever develop. Episode experts include Dr. Mrinal [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-how-dna-guides-cancer-detection/">Tomorrow&#8217;s Cure: How DNA guides cancer detection</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Tomorrows-Cure-episode-3-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390368" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Tomorrows-Cure-episode-3-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Tomorrows-Cure-episode-3-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Tomorrows-Cure-episode-3-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Tomorrows-Cure-episode-3.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>What if you knew you'd get sick before you ever felt symptoms? If it was a cold, that information is useful. In the case of cancer, it is lifesaving. This week's podcast episode of <a href="https://careinfo.mayoclinic.org/tomorrows-cure-podcast?mc_id=global&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=tcepisodethree&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=global&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=185874" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tomorrow's Cure</a> explores how DNA could be used to detect blood cancers before they ever develop.</p>



<p>Episode experts include <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/patnaik-mrinal-s-mbbs/bio-20055415" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Mrinal Patnaik</a>, a hematologist, internist and oncologist at Mayo Clinic; and <a href="https://oncology.wustl.edu/people/kelly-bolton-md-phd/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Kelly Bolton</a>, an oncologist at Washington University in St. Louis.</p>



<p>"We're developing tests where we can actually detect the early first step in the multistep progression to cancer," Dr. Bolton says. "That's an area where we might be able to intervene on someone's genetic changes that haven't quite led to cancer, but that are very high risk of becoming a cancer."</p>



<p>"When we detect clonal hematopoiesis, we want to nip it in the bud and prevent those high-risk patients from developing blood cancer because they are often lethal, difficult to treat. So the earlier we can effectively and safely intervene, the better for the patients,” says Dr. Patnaik.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubex7CjqdQDSbg"  title="How DNA guides cancer detection | Tomorrow&#039;s Cure Episode 3" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/x7CjqdQDSbg?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>To learn more about how these physicians are advancing cancer care, tune into a new episode of Tomorrow's Cure. The free podcast is available on all audio platforms, including <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/tomorrows-cure/id1747315251" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Apple Podcasts</a> and <a href="https://open.spotify.com/show/4TR8yPw5DUt94ETrgnWxL1?si=xW7dgSs6S5i8E2Lpipm0Jg&amp;nd=1&amp;dlsi=2aae8c8f9e8a4018" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Spotify</a>. A video version of the episode is also available on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLSWR1ylG_6JZd7nHPPgpIaoq_iRHgXRoF" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic's YouTube channel</a>.</p>



<p>The first season comprises eight episodes, with seasons 2 and 3 set to resume in early 2025. To learn more about Tomorrow's Cure and see the complete list of episode topics and featured experts, visit <a href="https://careinfo.mayoclinic.org/tomorrows-cure-podcast?mc_id=global&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=tcepisodethree&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=global&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=185874" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">tomorrowscure.com</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Related posts:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-gene-markers-detect-lynch-syndrome-associated-colorectal-cancer-mayo-clinic-study/">New gene markers detect Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer, Mayo Clinic Study</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/science-saturday-a-big-step-forward-bringing-dna-sequencing-data-to-routine-patient-care/">Science Saturday: A big step forward, bringing DNA sequencing data to routine patient care</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-how-dna-guides-cancer-detection/">Tomorrow&#8217;s Cure: How DNA guides cancer detection</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Tomorrows-Cure-episode3-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Tomorrows-Cure-episode-3.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[DNA test for cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Kelly Bolton]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Mrinal Patnaik]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Tomorrow's Cure]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Breaking the silence: First known total larynx transplant on a patient with active cancer as part of landmark clinical trial</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-the-silence-first-known-total-larynx-transplant-on-a-patient-with-active-cancer-as-part-of-landmark-clinical-trial/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. David Lott]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marty Kedian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=390113</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>On Feb. 29, Marty Kedian made history by successfully undergoing a groundbreaking surgery at Mayo Clinic that is providing hope to thousands who have lost their voice and ability to swallow and breathe on their own due to diminished laryngeal function or total loss of their larynx. This is the third known larynx transplant in [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-the-silence-first-known-total-larynx-transplant-on-a-patient-with-active-cancer-as-part-of-landmark-clinical-trial/">Breaking the silence: First known total larynx transplant on a patient with active cancer as part of landmark clinical trial</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-Gina-3-20-25_16x9-1024x577.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390220" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-Gina-3-20-25_16x9-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-Gina-3-20-25_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-Gina-3-20-25_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-Gina-3-20-25_16x9-1536x865.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-Gina-3-20-25_16x9-2048x1153.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Gina and Marty Kedian</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>On Feb. 29, Marty Kedian made history by successfully undergoing a groundbreaking surgery at Mayo Clinic that is providing hope to thousands who have lost their voice and ability to swallow and breathe on their own due to diminished laryngeal function or total loss of their larynx.</p>



<p>This is the third known larynx transplant in the U.S. and the first known case performed on a patient with an active cancer as part of a clinical trial. It is also Mayo Clinic's first total larynx transplant. The multidisciplinary team, including six surgeons, was led by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/lott-david-g-m-d/bio-20055443" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. David Lott</a>, chair of the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/ent-head-neck-surgery/sections/overview/ovc-20424084" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Otolaryngology (ENT) - Head and Neck Surgery/Audiology at Mayo Clinic in Arizona</a>. Dr. Lott also leads <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/larynx-trachea-transplant/overview/ovc-20508897" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic's Larynx and Trachea Transplant Program</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/larynx-trachea-transplant/overview/ovc-20508897">.</a></p>



<p>Experts say the larynx transplant at Mayo is a pivotal milestone in making the rare procedure available as a scientifically proven, safe and effective procedure for a wider population.</p>



<p>For Marty, it marks the beginning of his quest to break the silence on laryngeal transplantation.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="795" height="1006" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Thumbs-up-March-6-2024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390154" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Thumbs-up-March-6-2024.jpg 795w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Thumbs-up-March-6-2024-237x300.jpg 237w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Thumbs-up-March-6-2024-768x972.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 795px) 100vw, 795px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Less than a week after surgery, Marty Kedian and his team give the thumbs up</strong>  Photo courtesy: Kedian Family</figcaption></figure>



<p>A multidisciplinary team, including six surgeons, conducted the 21-hour transplant. Four months after surgery, Marty has regained use of his voice and his ability to swallow and breathe on his own, exceeding the transplant team's expectations.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H9fOyKUrDmQ" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Watch: Breaking the silence: Man achieves dream of getting his voice back in world's first known total larynx transplant on a patient with an active cancer as part of a landmark clinical trial</strong></a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeH9fOyKUrDmQ"  title="Breaking the silence: Total larynx transplant on a patient with active cancer" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/H9fOyKUrDmQ?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (5:15) in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-patient-story-video-script.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script.</a></strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Silenced by cancer</strong></h2>



<p>"I love to talk to people everywhere I go," says Marty. "I'm that guy at the baseball game who doesn't know anyone sitting around them. And by the end of the game, I'm friends with everyone in my section."</p>



<p>Marty's world changed in 2013 when he went to the doctor after noticing he was having trouble swallowing his food. "Food was getting caught in my throat. I thought I had allergies. I didn't really think anything of it," recalls Marty.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="909" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-gina-in-their-apt-1024x909.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390166" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-gina-in-their-apt-1024x909.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-gina-in-their-apt-300x266.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-gina-in-their-apt-768x682.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-gina-in-their-apt-1536x1364.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-gina-in-their-apt-2048x1818.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Marty and Gina Kedian</strong> <strong>and their dog Baxter</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>A series of tests revealed Marty had a rare form of laryngeal cancer called <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/chondrosarcoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20354196" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chondrosarcoma</a>. Doctors told Marty he needed surgery. "It was a shock," recalls Marty. "It was devastating. I wasn't going to die, but I had a job that required me to talk to people all day long." For 35 years, Marty worked at a local print shop speaking with customers in Haverhill, Massachusetts, where he lives with his wife, Gina, and their family.</p>



<p>Marty underwent his first surgery in 2014. Over the next 10 years, dozens more followed, reducing Marty's voice to a raspy whisper. No longer able to breathe on his own, Marty underwent surgery to have a tracheostomy tube inserted so he could breathe through a hole in the front of his neck.</p>



<p>"Everywhere I went, the first thing people would ask me is, 'How many cigarettes did you smoke a day?' I never smoked a cigarette in my life," says Marty. "People would immediately shut down and back away from me. After a while, I just didn't want to go out anywhere. I was alive, but I wasn't living." Marty was eventually told his last option was a total laryngectomy, or removal of his voice box. He declined. "I didn't want a laryngectomy. I wanted to find a way to get my quality of life back," says Marty.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-feeding-baby-Charlotte-768x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390142" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-feeding-baby-Charlotte-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-feeding-baby-Charlotte-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-feeding-baby-Charlotte-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-feeding-baby-Charlotte.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Marty with his granddaughter, Charlotte   Photo courtesy: Kedian Family</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>"I just had my first grandchild. I wanted to be able to talk to her with my own voice, play with her in the yard and take her to baseball games and breathe normally. Gina knew I was already depressed and out of my mind. She kept saying there had to be another way. She went online, and that's when she found Dr. Lott."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Finding hope at Mayo Clinic</h2>



<p>Thousands of miles from Marty's home, at Mayo Clinic in Phoenix, Dr. Lott was leading a team of scientists researching laryngeal restoration and transplantation. Dr. Lott is an ear, nose and throat surgeon who specializes in laryngeal surgery. For the past two decades, Dr. Lott and his team have been <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/head-and-neck-regenerative-medicine/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">investigating ways to restore and save a person's voice and laryngeal function.</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="698" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_0116-698x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390168" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_0116-698x1024.jpg 698w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_0116-204x300.jpg 204w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_0116-768x1127.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_0116-1047x1536.jpg 1047w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/IMG_0116.jpg 1284w" sizes="(max-width: 698px) 100vw, 698px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Dr. David Lott discusses laryngeal transplantation with Kedian at Mayo Clinic in Phoenix, Arizona</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>"I set my path on becoming a laryngeal surgeon and researcher to build a program that is pushing the boundaries of science forward," explains Dr. Lott.</p>



<p>"Nobody really thinks of their larynx until it's gone," says Dr. Lott. "Then your ability to speak, breathe and swallow is gone, and you are left breathing through a hole in your neck. It is very isolating, and many become a shell of who they used to be. I wanted to find a way to help restore a person's quality of life."</p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/preparing-for-mayos-first-larynx-transplant/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">In 2016, Dr. Lott's program was granted approval to conduct the first clinical trial in the U.S. on laryngeal transplantation</a>. "Until now, laryngeal transplants have been done as one-offs," says Dr. Lott. "This clinical trial allows us to conduct a true scientific investigation aimed at thoroughly researching the safety and efficacy of laryngeal transplantation as a trusted option for patients."</p>



<p>One of the biggest challenges to advancing laryngeal transplantation as an option for cancer patients like Marty has been the risk associated with the use of immunosuppressive therapy. <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/11-16-four-ways-organ-transplants-are-being-transformed-to-save-more-lives/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Transplant</a> patients are given immunosuppressive drugs to lower the body's immune response, which reduces the risk of organ rejection. However, immunosuppression also increases the risk of the cancer spreading. Marty was already on immunosuppressives due to a <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-surgeons-perform-first-robotic-assisted-kidney-transplant-in-minnesota/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">kidney transplant</a> years ago.</p>



<p>"Having a patient with an active cancer who already has his own immune suppression allowed us to do the transplant safely without introducing additional risk in a way that has rarely, if ever, been done before," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mour-girish-k-m-b-b-s/bio-20392405" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Girish Mour, M.B.B.S.,</a> medical director of the program.</p>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Inside the operating room</strong></h1>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390126" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Team-in-surgery-3-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>The 21-hour landmark transplant was performed by a multidisciplinary team of doctors that included six surgeons</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>Removing the cancer was the surgical team's main priority. "First, we removed Mr. Kedian's cancerous larynx," explains Dr. Lott. "Then, with the confidence of our team that the cancer was gone, we focused on the transplant. The entire procedure went better than we expected."</p>



<p>In addition to the larynx, surgeons transplanted the pharynx, upper trachea, upper esophagus, thyroid and parathyroid glands, blood vessels, and nerves.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="753" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-figure-1024x753.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390174" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-figure-1024x753.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-figure-300x220.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-figure-768x564.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-figure-1536x1129.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-figure-2048x1505.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Marty's road to recovery</strong></h1>



<p>Four months after his transplant, Marty regained 60% of his voice. Doctors say it will continue to improve as he heals over the next year. He has also regained the ability to swallow and breathe on his own. "It is truly amazing," says Marty. "Dr. Lott and the team at Mayo have not only given me my voice back, they've also given me my life back."</p>



<p>Speech and swallow therapy at Mayo has been a significant part of Marty's recovery.</p>



<p>"Marty's progress is remarkable," describes Dr. Lott. "He is eating hamburgers, macaroni and cheese, almost anything with no problem. His breathing also continues to steadily improve." Doctors plan to remove the tracheostomy tube when Marty regains full function of his ability to breathe on his own.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/pb/assets/raw/Health%20Advance/journals/jmcp/Lott-1720450777830.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">A paper by Dr. Lott on the case was published July 9 in the peer-reviewed medical journal Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Girish-Mour-Marty-Kedian-and-Dr.-David-Lott-post-op-in-hospital-room-1-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390141" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Girish-Mour-Marty-Kedian-and-Dr.-David-Lott-post-op-in-hospital-room-1-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Girish-Mour-Marty-Kedian-and-Dr.-David-Lott-post-op-in-hospital-room-1-300x225.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Girish-Mour-Marty-Kedian-and-Dr.-David-Lott-post-op-in-hospital-room-1-768x576.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Girish-Mour-Marty-Kedian-and-Dr.-David-Lott-post-op-in-hospital-room-1-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Girish-Mour-Marty-Kedian-and-Dr.-David-Lott-post-op-in-hospital-room-1-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Dr. Girish Mour (L), Marty and Dr. Lott one week after the transplant</strong></figcaption></figure>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>"The holy grail for managing laryngeal cancer"</strong></h1>



<p>"The case signifies a monumental breakthrough," says Dr. Marshall Strome, who performed the world's first successful larynx transplant in 1998. "It represents the future of laryngeal transplantation where every patient needing a total laryngectomy will have the option of a reconstruction that allows them to maintain their quality of life."</p>



<p>Dr. Lott did some of his early training under Dr. Strome. Since then, Dr. Strome has remained a trusted mentor to Dr. Lott. In a full circle moment, Dr. Strome was present when Dr. Lott performed the transplant at Mayo in February.</p>



<p>"With the clinical trial underway, Dr. Lott and his team are positioned to advance the field in ways no other program can currently achieve. The Mayo team has discovered the holy grail for managing laryngeal cancer, which I believe will come to fruition by the end of this decade," says Dr. Strome.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Strome-and-Dr.-Lott-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390123" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Strome-and-Dr.-Lott-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Strome-and-Dr.-Lott-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Strome-and-Dr.-Lott-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Strome-and-Dr.-Lott-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-Strome-and-Dr.-Lott-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>A full circle moment for Dr. Marshall Strome and Dr. Lott following Mayo's groundbreaking transplant</strong></figcaption></figure>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Breaking the silence on laryngeal transplantation</strong></h1>



<p>Less than five months after surgery, Marty and Gina are excited to return home to Massachusetts. "We couldn't have done this without everyone's love and support," says Gina.</p>



<p>"I will always be grateful to the team at Mayo and especially for the generosity of my organ donor and the donor family," says Marty.</p>



<p>Dr. Lott's clinical trial is approved to perform additional larynx transplants in the coming years.</p>



<p>Marty is looking forward to doing what he loves most — talking to family, friends and everyone else he meets. He is especially looking forward to talking with his granddaughter, Charlotte.</p>



<p>"I will be reading her lots of bedtime stories," says Marty. Meanwhile, Marty also is planning to share his own story to inspire others.</p>



<p>"My first job is to get better," says Marty. "My next job will be to tell everyone they can do it too."</p>



<p>Additional resources:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-marks-medical-milestone-with-worlds-first-known-successful-total-larynx-transplant-performed-in-a-patient-with-an-active-cancer-as-part-of-a-clinical-trial/">Mayo Clinic marks medical milestone with world’s first known successful total larynx transplant performed in a patient with an active cancer as part of a clinical trial&nbsp;</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/preparing-for-mayos-first-larynx-transplant/">Research prepares for Mayo's first larynx transplant</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-the-silence-first-known-total-larynx-transplant-on-a-patient-with-active-cancer-as-part-of-landmark-clinical-trial/">Breaking the silence: First known total larynx transplant on a patient with active cancer as part of landmark clinical trial</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-Gina-3-20-25_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Marty-and-Gina-3-20-25_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. David Lott]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Marty Kedian]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss><!-- Static page delivered by HubScale -->