<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 16:58:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Pass the turkey &#8212; and your family health insights &#8212; this Thanksgiving</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/pass-the-turkey-and-your-family-health-insights-this-thanksgiving/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. John Presutti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Niloy Jewel Samadder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Family Health History Day]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genomics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377654</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Thanksgiving Day is also&#160;Family Health History Day, an annual national campaign to promote awareness of hereditary health traits in families. Has your grandmother, mother, aunt or sister had breast or ovarian cancer? Has your grandfather, father or uncle had prostate, breast or pancreatic cancer? Is there a history in your family of colon cancer, diabetes [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/pass-the-turkey-and-your-family-health-insights-this-thanksgiving/">Pass the turkey &#8212; and your family health insights &#8212; this Thanksgiving</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="893" height="502" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/THANKSGIVING-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377656" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/THANKSGIVING-16x9-1.jpg 893w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/THANKSGIVING-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/THANKSGIVING-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 893px) 100vw, 893px" /></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Thanksgiving Day is also&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cdc.gov/genomics/famhistory/knowing_not_enough.htm?CDC_AA_refVal=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.cdc.gov%2Ffeatures%2Ffamilyhealthhistory%2Findex.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Family Health History Day</a>, an annual national campaign to promote awareness of hereditary health traits in families.</strong></h3>



<p>Has your grandmother, mother, aunt or sister had breast or ovarian cancer? Has your grandfather, father or uncle had prostate, breast or pancreatic cancer? Is there a history in your family of colon cancer, diabetes or high cholesterol?&nbsp;</p>



<p>If any of these scenarios resonate within your family, you could also be at risk.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Many hereditary health conditions follow patterns within families, with sometimes as high as a 50% likelihood that if one parent possesses a mutated gene, their child will inherit it. Recent Mayo Clinic&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-finds-1-in-8-patients-with-cancer-harbor-inherited-genetic-mutations/">research</a>&nbsp;shows that inherited, faulty genes cause more than 10% of all cancers.</p>



<p>"The biggest advice I would give is that if you are with your family this Thanksgiving, spend a few moments to share some of that family health history information. And if a red flag goes up, report that to your doctor. It could actually save someone's life," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/presutti-richard-john-j-d-o/bio-20053922" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">John Presutti, D.O.</a>, a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician and a researcher at the Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Predictive power of genomics</strong></h3>



<p>Dr. Presutti has integrated genomics into his everyday medical decision-making for his patients, realizing the potential for improving health outcomes.</p>



<p>"If I can help identify patients at high risk for cancer and other diseases, then I can help get them started on screening earlier and avoid the situation of metastatic cancer and early cancer deaths," he says.</p>



<p>Equally important to the discovery of a person's inherited cancer mutation is the potential for them to share the heritable cause of their disease with their blood relatives, allowing family members to pursue care for earlier disease detection and cancer management.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"The power of genetics is that we can potentially foresee the cancer that will develop in other family members," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/samadder-niloy-jewel-jewel-j-m-d/bio-20396993" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Niloy Jewel Samadder, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic gastroenterologist and cancer geneticist. "This can allow us to target cancer screening to those high-risk individuals and hopefully prevent cancer altogether in the next generation of the family."</p>



<p>Dr. Samadder emphasizes that knowing your family health history can help you, but only if you act on it.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Questions to ask family about health history</strong></h3>



<ul>
<li>Do you have chronic conditions, such as heart disease or diabetes, high blood pressure or high cholesterol?</li>



<li>Have you had serious diseases, such as cancer or stroke?</li>



<li>How old were you when each of these diseases or health conditions was diagnosed?</li>



<li>What is your family's ancestry? What countries or regions did your ancestors come from?</li>



<li>What were the causes and ages of death for relatives who have died?</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Examples of family health syndromes:</strong></h3>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/brca-gene-test/about/pac-20384815" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hereditary breast and ovarian cancer syndrome</a>&nbsp;is an inherited mutation in the BRCA1 or BRCA2 gene. Along with breast and ovarian cancer, this syndrome also can lead to male breast cancer, pancreatic cancer and prostate cancer.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lynch-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20374714" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lynch syndrome</a>&nbsp;is a cluster of mutations that can boost the risk of a wide range of cancers, including colon, rectal, endometrial, ovarian, stomach, small intestine, pancreas, kidney, brain, uterus and bile duct.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/familial-hypercholesterolemia/symptoms-causes/syc-20353755" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Familial hypercholesterolemia</a>&nbsp;is a genetic disorder characterized by high cholesterol, which can lead to premature cardiovascular disease.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Health history situations that raise a red flag</strong></h3>



<ul>
<li>A person developed cancer at an unusually young age.</li>



<li>A person has had several different types of cancer.</li>



<li>Cancer developed in both organs in a set of paired organs, such as both kidneys or both breasts.</li>



<li>Several first-degree relatives ― parents, siblings or a person's children ― have the same type of cancer. Examples might include a mother, daughter and sisters with breast cancer; multiple family members with breast or ovarian cancer; or family members with colon cancer and endometrial cancer.</li>



<li>Unusual cases of a specific cancer type, such as breast cancer in a man.</li>



<li>Being a member of a racial or ethnic group that is known to have an increased risk of having a certain inherited cancer susceptibility syndrome.</li>



<li>Several family members with cancer.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What to do with the information</strong></h3>



<p>If you have a family health history of disease, here are some steps to take:</p>



<ul>
<li>Consult a healthcare professional: Schedule a consultation with a doctor or genetic counselor to discuss your family health history and any potential risks.</li>



<li>Genetic testing: In some cases, your healthcare team may recommend genetic testing to determine whether you have specific genetic mutations or markers associated with hereditary diseases.</li>



<li>Lifestyle modifications: Make lifestyle changes to reduce risk factors, such as maintaining a healthy diet, staying physically active, and avoiding tobacco and excessive alcohol consumption.</li>



<li>Communicate: Keep open lines of communication with family members about their health histories, as it can provide valuable insights for everyone's well-being.</li>
</ul>



<p>This article first appeared on the <a href="https://individualizedmedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/11/10/pass-the-turkey-and-your-family-health-insights-this-thanksgiving/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Individualized Medicine blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/pass-the-turkey-and-your-family-health-insights-this-thanksgiving/">Pass the turkey &#8212; and your family health insights &#8212; this Thanksgiving</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/THANKSGIVING-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/THANKSGIVING-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. John Presutti]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Niloy Jewel Samadder]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Family Health History Day]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Genomics]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers demonstrate nearly 20% boost in adolescent HPV vaccination rates using comprehensive strategy</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-demonstrate-nearly-20-boost-in-adolescent-hpv-vaccination-rates-using-comprehensive-strategy/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2023 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Lila Finney Rutten]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Robert Jacobson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HPV]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HPV vaccination]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vaccine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377625</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researchers demonstrated a nearly 20% increase in human papillomavirus (HPV) vaccination rates among adolescents through a combination intervention approach, a new Mayo Clinic study finds. The strategy involved mailing reminders to parents about their child's eligibility for the HPV vaccine and simultaneously giving healthcare providers feedback about successful HPV vaccine administration among the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-demonstrate-nearly-20-boost-in-adolescent-hpv-vaccination-rates-using-comprehensive-strategy/">Mayo Clinic researchers demonstrate nearly 20% boost in adolescent HPV vaccination rates using comprehensive strategy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="vial of human papillomavirus vaccine" class="wp-image-103619" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers demonstrated a nearly 20% increase in <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hpv-infection/symptoms-causes/syc-20351596" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">human papillomavirus (HPV)</a> vaccination rates among adolescents through a combination intervention approach, a new Mayo Clinic study finds. The strategy involved mailing reminders to parents about their child's eligibility for the HPV vaccine and simultaneously giving healthcare providers feedback about successful HPV vaccine administration among the patients they had recently seen.</p>



<p>The findings, published in <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamapediatrics/fullarticle/2812161">JAMA Pediatrics</a>, suggest healthcare practices could adopt this evidence-based approach to boost HPV vaccination uptake in 11- and 12-year-olds.</p>



<p>"HPV vaccine uptake at 60% of eligible adolescents falls short of national public health goals and lags other adolescent vaccines," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/jacobson-robert-m-m-d/bio-00083020" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Robert Jacobson, M.D.</a>, a pediatrician in the Mayo Clinic Division of Community Pediatric and Adolescent Medicine. Dr. Jacobson is a co-principal investigator of the study.</p>



<p>Human papillomaviruses cause viral infections transmitted sexually through skin-to-skin contact. HPV infections may occur without symptoms or signs in late adolescence or early adulthood and affect both males and females. The virus can cause several types of cancers, including of the cervix, anus, genital area, mouth and throat.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/cancer/hpv/statistics/cases.htm" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">estimates</a> 37,000 HPV-linked cancers occur each year in the U.S., all of which may be prevented by the HPV vaccination.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For the study, the researchers evaluated their intervention strategy at six Mayo Clinic primary care practices in Southeastern Minnesota. The investigation involved 9,242 adolescents who were due to receive at least one dose of the HPV vaccine. When parents received reminders in the mail and providers were simultaneously given feedback, 39.7% of patients got their doses due in the months that followed the interventions, as contrasted to 21.9% without the interventions.</p>



<p>“Our study investigated both parent- and provider-facing interventions. By targeting parents and providers, we achieved much higher improvements in HPV vaccine uptake than the use of these strategies in isolation,” says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/rutten-lila-j-ph-d/bio-20551780" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lila Finney Rutten, Ph.D.</a>, lead author and chair of the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/departments-divisions/quantitative-health-sciences/divisions/epidemiology/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Division of Epidemiology</a>.</p>



<p>The researchers say the study not only addresses the low HPV vaccination rate but also holds the potential to reshape other public health and vaccination campaigns.</p>



<p>Review the&nbsp;study&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures, and funding.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> &nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and to providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.  &nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong>  &nbsp;</p>



<ul>
<li>Susan Murphy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>  &nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-demonstrate-nearly-20-boost-in-adolescent-hpv-vaccination-rates-using-comprehensive-strategy/">Mayo Clinic researchers demonstrate nearly 20% boost in adolescent HPV vaccination rates using comprehensive strategy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Lila Finney Rutten]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Robert Jacobson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[HPV]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[HPV vaccination]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Vaccine]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Consumer Health: What do you know about pancreatic cancer?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-what-do-you-know-about-pancreatic-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laurel Kelly]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pancreatic Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pancreatic Cancer Awareness Month]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=371506</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>November is&#160;Pancreatic Cancer Awareness Month, which makes this a good time to learn more about the risk factors for pancreatic cancer and what you can do to keep yourself safe. More than 64,000 people in the U.S. will be diagnosed with pancreatic cancer this year, and more than 50,000 people will die of the disease, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-what-do-you-know-about-pancreatic-cancer/">Consumer Health: What do you know about pancreatic cancer?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Mom-Daughter-Original-with-Ribbon-1024x683.jpg" alt="a portrait of two women, one elderly, the other middle age, perhaps a mother and daughter with a purple Pancreatic Cancer Awareness ribbon graphic" class="wp-image-352950" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Mom-Daughter-Original-with-Ribbon-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Mom-Daughter-Original-with-Ribbon-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Mom-Daughter-Original-with-Ribbon-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Mom-Daughter-Original-with-Ribbon-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Mom-Daughter-Original-with-Ribbon-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>November is&nbsp;<a href="https://www.aacr.org/patients-caregivers/awareness-months/pancreatic-cancer-awareness-month/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pancreatic Cancer Awareness Month</a>, which makes this a good time to learn more about the risk factors for pancreatic cancer and what you can do to keep yourself safe.</p>



<p>More than 64,000 people in the U.S. will be diagnosed with pancreatic cancer this year, and more than 50,000 people will die of the disease, according to the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/pancreatic-cancer/about/key-statistics.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Cancer Society</a>. Pancreatic cancer is the&nbsp;<a href="https://cancerstatisticscenter.cancer.org/?_ga=2.189398057.347593919.1602700843-1875348864.1599565997&amp;_gac=1.45345424.1602700843.EAIaIQobChMIsIfA8N207AIVksDACh2zsQq-EAAYASAAEgItfvD_BwE#!/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">third-leading cause of cancer death</a>&nbsp;in the U.S.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pancreatic-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20355421?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pancreatic cancer</a>&nbsp;begins in the tissues of your pancreas — an organ in your abdomen that lies behind the lower part of your stomach. Your pancreas releases enzymes that aid digestion and produces hormones that help manage your blood sugar.</p>



<p>Several types of growths can occur in the pancreas, including cancerous and noncancerous tumors. The most common type of cancer that forms in the pancreas is pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma, which begins in the cells that line the ducts that carry digestive enzymes out of the pancreas.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Symptoms</strong></h2>



<p>Signs and symptoms of&nbsp;pancreatic cancer&nbsp;often don't occur until the disease is advanced. This means the disease rarely is detected at its early stages when it's most curable.</p>



<p>Pancreatic cancer symptoms can include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Abdominal pain that radiates to your back.</li>



<li>Loss of appetite or unintended weight loss.</li>



<li>Yellowing of your skin and the whites of your eyes.</li>



<li>Light-colored stools.</li>



<li>Dark-colored urine.</li>



<li>Itchy skin.</li>



<li>New diagnosis of diabetes or existing diabetes that's becoming more difficult to control.</li>



<li>Blood clots.</li>



<li>Fatigue.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Risk Factors</strong></h2>



<p>Factors that can increase your risk of pancreatic cancer include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Smoking.</li>



<li>Diabetes.</li>



<li>Chronic inflammation of the pancreas, or&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pancreatitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20360227?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pancreatitis</a>.</li>



<li>Family history of genetic syndromes that can increase cancer risk, including a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/brca-gene-test/about/pac-20384815?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">BRCA2 gene mutation</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lynch-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20374714?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lynch syndrome</a>&nbsp;and familial atypical mole malignant melanoma syndrome.</li>



<li>Family history of pancreatic cancer.</li>



<li>Obesity.</li>



<li>Older age, as most people are diagnosed after 65.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Reducing your risk</strong></h2>



<p>While some of these risk factors are out of your control, here are some lifestyle choices you can make to reduce your risk:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Stop smoking.<br></strong>If you smoke, try to stop. Talk to your healthcare team about strategies to help you stop, including support groups, medications and nicotine replacement therapy. If you don't smoke, don't start.</li>



<li><strong>Maintain a healthy weight.<br></strong>If you are at a healthy weight, work to maintain it. If you need to lose weight, aim for a slow, steady weight loss — 1 to 2 pounds a week. Combine daily exercise with a diet rich in vegetables, fruit and whole grains, with smaller portions to help you lose weight.</li>



<li><strong>Choose a healthy diet.</strong><br>A diet full of colorful fruits and vegetables, and whole grains, may reduce your risk of cancer.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Treatment</strong></h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pancreatic-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20355427?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Treatment</a> for pancreatic cancer depends on the stage and location of the cancer as well as on your overall health and personal preferences. For most people, the first goal of pancreatic cancer treatment is to eliminate the cancer, when possible. When that isn't an option, the focus may be on improving your quality of life and limiting the cancer from growing or causing more harm.</p>



<p>Treatment may include surgery, radiation therapy, chemotherapy or a combination of these. When pancreatic cancer is advanced and these treatments aren't likely to offer a benefit, your healthcare professional will focus on symptom relief with palliative care to keep you as comfortable as possible for as long as possible.</p>



<p>Connect with others talking about pancreatic cancer in the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/pancreatic-cancer/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pancreatic Cancer Support Group</a> on&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Connect</a>, an online patient community moderated by Mayo Clinic.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-what-do-you-know-about-pancreatic-cancer/">Consumer Health: What do you know about pancreatic cancer?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/11/a-purple-and-white-graphic-with-written-information-that-November-is-Pancreatic-Cancer-Awareness-Month-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Mom-Daughter-Original-with-Ribbon.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Pancreatic Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Pancreatic Cancer Awareness Month]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic and Columbia University receive $10.6 million grant from NCI to advance glioblastoma research with mathematical oncology</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-and-columbia-university-receive-10-6-million-grant-from-nci-to-advance-glioblastoma-research-with-mathematical-oncology/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelley Luckstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2023 20:24:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Kristin Swanson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[glioblastoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MRI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[National Cancer Institute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377554</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center and Columbia University received a five-year, $10.6 million U54 center grant from the National Cancer Institute (NCI) to further study combining the molecular analysis of glioblastoma with MRI. Glioblastoma is a fast-growing and aggressive brain tumor that begins as a growth of cells in the brain or spinal cord. As [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-and-columbia-university-receive-10-6-million-grant-from-nci-to-advance-glioblastoma-research-with-mathematical-oncology/">Mayo Clinic and Columbia University receive $10.6 million grant from NCI to advance glioblastoma research with mathematical oncology</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="647" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Brain_NCI_Grant_Swanson-1024x647.png" alt="" class="wp-image-377584" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Brain_NCI_Grant_Swanson-1024x647.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Brain_NCI_Grant_Swanson-300x189.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Brain_NCI_Grant_Swanson-768x485.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Brain_NCI_Grant_Swanson.png 1050w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> and <a href="https://www.columbia.edu/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Columbia University</a> received a five-year, $10.6 million <a href="https://reporter.nih.gov/search/erErGjWh7k-kKXXTUi4tag/project-details/10729420details?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">U54 center grant</a> from the <a href="https://www.nih.gov/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a> (NCI) to further study combining the molecular analysis of glioblastoma with MRI.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/glioblastoma/cdc-20350148?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Glioblastoma</a> is a fast-growing and aggressive brain tumor that begins as a growth of cells in the brain or spinal cord. As it grows, it can invade and destroy healthy tissue. There is no cure, but treatments may slow the cancer's growth and reduce symptoms.</p>



<p>Glioblastoma is a diverse cancer, which means that biopsies from different regions of each patient's tumor can represent widely different tumor biology. Treatments that work for one region of the tumor may not work for others.</p>



<p>MRI provides a way to look at the whole tumor but is poor at differentiating regions of unfavorable tumor progression from regions of favorable tumor response which is often mixed with immune response and inflammation. For this reason, it can be difficult for physicians to use imaging to determine if a treatment works for all or part of the patient’s tumor.</p>



<p>This new NCI grant supports a team of researchers to develop the Mathematical Oncology Systems Analysis Imaging Center (MOSAIC). MOSAIC will combine biopsies collected at different regions of each patient’s tumor with features on patient MRIs. MOSAIC researchers rely on these patterns to build mathematical and machine learning models allowing MRI to predict tumor biology in regions that were not biopsied. In this way, MOSAIC researchers can effectively create so-called "virtual biopsies" of patient’s tumors without surgery.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Mathematical oncology is the use of mathematics, modeling and simulation in cancer biology and oncology.&nbsp;This fusion of the quantitative sciences with the study of cancer includes the development of predictive mathematical models that help bridge gaps in knowledge in the understanding of cancer or data-driven machine-learning approaches that detect patterns in cancer data that had not been identified previously.</p>



<p>"This grant is important as it will help us use MRI as a lens to more directly predict changes in the biology of each patient’s tumor during treatment when we normally have very limited access to tissue samples," says the study's co-principal investigator, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/swanson-kristin-r-ph-d/bio-20396996?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kristin Swanson, Ph.D.</a>, a mathematical oncologist at Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center.  </p>



<p>MOSAIC's image-based mathematical models will use MRI to track aspects of tumor heterogeneity previously unattainable during the course of patient care. This is particularly important as the brain is a protected organ which limits tissue sampling during rare surgical interventions. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>"This grant will allow us to better understand which of our patients are responding to treatment and to ultimately drive new clinical trials that improve patient outcomes," adds Dr. Swanson.</p>



<p>The center will be based at Mayo Clinic in Arizona with co-principal investigator <a href="https://www.pathology.columbia.edu/profile/peter-d-canoll-md#research?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Peter Canoll, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, Columbia University, and involves collaboration among multiple institutions, including Arizona State University, Columbia University, City of Hope, Inova, Mayo Clinic Rochester, MD Anderson and Washington University.</p>



<p>The grant is supported by NCI of the National Institutes of Health (NIH) under project number <a href="https://reporter.nih.gov/search/erErGjWh7k-kKXXTUi4tag/project-details/10729420details?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">1U54CA274504-01A1</a>. The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the NIH.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center<br></strong>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the <a href="https://www.cancer.gov/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining new boundaries in possibility, focusing on patient-centered care, developing novel treatments, training future generations of cancer experts, and bringing cancer research to communities. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs that are changing approaches to cancer prevention, screening and treatment, and improving the lives of cancer survivors.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contacts:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-and-columbia-university-receive-10-6-million-grant-from-nci-to-advance-glioblastoma-research-with-mathematical-oncology/">Mayo Clinic and Columbia University receive $10.6 million grant from NCI to advance glioblastoma research with mathematical oncology</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Brain_NCI_Grant_Swanson-1x1-1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Brain_NCI_Grant_Swanson-16x9-1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Kristin Swanson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[glioblastoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[MRI]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[National Cancer Institute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic expert on the importance of lung cancer screening</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-expert-on-the-importance-of-lung-cancer-screening/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2023 14:24:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cancer screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Janani Reisenauer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lung Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lung cancer prevention]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[thoracic surgery]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377052</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Screening for lung cancer can save lives, and there's an urgent need for more screening of people of color. That's one of the takeaways from the newly released "State of Lung Cancer" report from the American Lung Association. "Lung cancer is the largest (cancer) killer of adult men and women worldwide. Many of the reasons [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-expert-on-the-importance-of-lung-cancer-screening/">Mayo Clinic expert on the importance of lung cancer screening</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Screening for<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lung-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20374620" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"> lung cancer</a> can save lives, and there's an urgent need for more screening of people of color. That's one of the takeaways from the newly released <a href="https://www.lung.org/research/state-of-lung-cancer" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">"State of Lung Cancer"</a> report from the American Lung Association.</p>



<p>"Lung cancer is the largest (cancer) killer of adult men and women worldwide. Many of the reasons for that is it's so late in its stage, often, when it's diagnosed," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/reisenauer-janani-s-m-d/bio-20433096" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Janani Reisenauer</a>, a thoracic surgeon and interventional pulmonologist at Mayo Clinic. "Historical data show that 70% of lung cancers that were being diagnosed were at stage 3, which makes it much more challenging to treat and cure someone of lung cancer."</p>



<p>"Through lung cancer screening, we've been able to identify patients much earlier in their stage, which gives them more treatment options and much more hopeful chances of cure. For that reason, screening is important," she says.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W-F4QQrxZw4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Janani Reisenauer talk about lung cancer screening</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidWF4QQrxZw4"  title="Dr. Janani Reisenauer  - Lung cancer screening" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/W-F4QQrxZw4?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites with Dr. Reisenauer are available in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Name super/CG: Janani Reisenauer, M.D./Pulmonary Medicine, Thoracic Surgery/Mayo Clinic.</strong></p>



<p>The latest update from the <a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/types/lung-cancer/detection-diagnosis-staging/detection.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Cancer Society</a> recommends that people with a substantial smoking history undergo an annual low-dose CT scan for lung cancer screening. Dr. Reisenauer says the new guidelines allow a broader population to be eligible for screening.</p>



<p>"Any patient with a significant smoking history and over age 55 (are the new guidelines). It used to be just 20 years of smoking, and now we've redefined it to say the number of cigarettes per day times the number of years smoking," she says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/07/a-medical-illustration-of-lung-cancer-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a medical illustration of lung cancer" class="wp-image-196185" style="width:796px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/07/a-medical-illustration-of-lung-cancer-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/07/a-medical-illustration-of-lung-cancer-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/07/a-medical-illustration-of-lung-cancer-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/07/a-medical-illustration-of-lung-cancer-16X9.jpg 1152w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p>"Even if you were smoking for only 10 years and not 20 years, but you were smoking twice as much, you might also be a candidate under the new screening guidelines for a CT," she says.</p>



<p>Dr. Reisenauer recommends that eligible patients talk with their primary care team to let them know you are interested in screening.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/09/16-x-9-lung-CT.jpg" alt="a medical illustration of a CT lung cancer screening" class="wp-image-216708" style="width:800px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/09/16-x-9-lung-CT.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/09/16-x-9-lung-CT-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></figure>



<p><strong>How lung cancer screening works</strong></p>



<p>Screening includes a low-dose CT scan to detect suspicious lung nodules and signs of lung cancer. Detecting lung cancer in its early stages significantly increases the likelihood of successful treatment and cure.</p>



<p>If lung cancer is confirmed, Dr. Reisenauer says a patient will work with a multidisciplinary team to decide the best treatment option.</p>



<p>She says Mayo Clinic continues to pioneer lung cancer treatment through research and innovation, working for better patient outcomes.</p>



<p>"We generate patient-specific individualized custom treatments for those patients, whether it's given IV or a surgery, or something completely novel like through the robotic bronchoscope. Our understanding of how a patient gets lung cancer and how we can treat it to where it's not the No. 1 cancer killer worldwide — I think we'll make much movement there in the next 10 to 20 years," she says.</p>



<p>"And I think screening is a part of that so we can capture these patients early, understand what we're dealing with. But as we're capturing these patients, we are trying to understand how these tumors behave on a cellular, molecular and genetic level. This is very new, and it's an area of interesting science," Dr. Reisenauer says.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-expert-on-the-importance-of-lung-cancer-screening/">Mayo Clinic expert on the importance of lung cancer screening</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/03/Medical-illustration-of-lung-cancer-1-x-1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Lung-Cancer16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cancer screening]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Janani Reisenauer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Lung Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[lung cancer prevention]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[thoracic surgery]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Stomach cancer concerns</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-stomach-cancer-concerns/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2023 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Mohamad Sonbol]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gastric cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stomach cancer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=322014</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Stomach cancer, also called gastric cancer, is an abnormal growth of cells that begins in the stomach. It can affect several areas of the stomach, including the main stomach lining or where the esophagus meets the stomach. November is Stomach Cancer Awareness Month, and experts at Mayo Clinic say there is hope for patients with [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-stomach-cancer-concerns/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Stomach cancer concerns</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<span class="medically-reviewed-by">Medically reviewed by <a target="_blank" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/sonbol-mohamad-bassam-b-m-d/bio-20466252">Mohamad (Bassam) B. Sonbol, M.D.</a></span><div class="clear margin-bottom-20"></div>


<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stomach-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352438?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stomach cancer</a>, also called gastric cancer, is an abnormal growth of cells that begins in the stomach. It can affect several areas of the stomach, including the main stomach lining or where the esophagus meets the stomach.</p>



<p>November is Stomach Cancer Awareness Month, and experts at Mayo Clinic say there is hope for patients with the disease as treatments continue to improve.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/hAexmiycYOA" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubehAexmiycYOA"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Stomach cancer concerns" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hAexmiycYOA?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:20) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/10/MCM_Stomach-cancer-concerns.pdf" target="_blank">script</a>.</strong></strong>   </p>



<p>Stomach cancer is relatively rare in the U.S. It's often diagnosed at later stages in the disease, when symptoms like nausea, heartburn and feeling bloated are more pronounced.</p>



<p>"In general, when we talk about gastric cancer, we usually talk about a cancer that's arising from the lining of the stomach," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/sonbol-mohamad-bassam-b-m-d/bio-20466252?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Mohamad Sonbol</a>, a Mayo Clinic oncologist.</p>



<p>Early signs of stomach cancer vary, and can include abdominal pain, blood in the stool or just feeling tired.</p>



<p>"If you have a cancer in the stomach, it might ooze blood very slowly, and that can cause anemia, or low hemoglobin, and that can lead to fatigue," says Dr. Sonbol.</p>



<p>If you're a man, you're at higher risk for stomach cancer than a woman. Other risk factors include obesity, smoking and drinking alcohol.</p>



<p>"And then there are other risk factors, such as there are some hereditary syndromes or things that we inherit from our parents that put us at higher risk of developing gastric cancer, stomach cancer," says Dr. Sonbol.</p>



<p>Treatment options depend on the cancer's location in the stomach, its size and stage, but can include surgery, chemotherapy, radiation and immunotherapy.</p>



<p>"I tell patients who have recently been diagnosed with gastric cancer that there is definitely a hope because we've gotten significantly better in the last decade, and more specifically really, in the last year or two, where we have now many more treatment options than we had before," says Dr. Sonbol.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-stomach-cancer-concerns/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Stomach cancer concerns</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/12/shutterstock_94181905-1024x701_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/12/shutterstock_94181905-1024x701_Fotor-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Mohamad Sonbol]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[gastric cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[stomach cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mapping cell behaviors in high-grade glioma to improve treatment</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mapping-cell-behaviors-in-high-grade-glioma-to-improve-treatment/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Gerri Kelly]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Leland Hu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nhan Tran]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[high-grade glioma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neuroradiology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377191</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>High-grade gliomas are cancerous tumors that spread quickly in the brain or spinal cord. In a new study led by Mayo Clinic, researchers found invasive brain tumor margins of high-grade glioma (HGG) contain biologically distinct genetic and molecular alterations that point to aggressive behavior and disease recurrence. The findings suggest insights into potential treatments that could modify [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mapping-cell-behaviors-in-high-grade-glioma-to-improve-treatment/">Mapping cell behaviors in high-grade glioma to improve treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377192" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1.jpg 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The researchers profiled 313 tumor biopsies from 68 high-grade glioma (HGG) patients. This image is a representation of the 3-dimensional relationship of multiple tissue biopsies from a single patient’s HGG tumor. The different colors depict different versions of genetic mutations relative to the epidermal growth factor receptor gene.<br></figcaption></figure>



<p>High-grade gliomas are cancerous tumors that spread quickly in the brain or spinal cord. In a new study led by Mayo Clinic, researchers found invasive brain tumor margins of high-grade <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/glioma/symptoms-causes/syc-20350251" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">glioma</a> (HGG) contain biologically distinct genetic and molecular alterations that point to aggressive behavior and disease recurrence. The findings suggest insights into potential treatments that could modify the course of the disease.</p>



<p>The&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-023-41559-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;published in Nature Communications, profiled 313 tumor biopsies from 68 HGG patients using genomics (study of genes), transcriptomics (study of gene expression at the mRNA level) and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).</p>



<p>Glioma is a growth of cells that starts in the brain or spinal cord. The invasive margins of HGG have long remained a mystery due to the difficulties in surgical biopsy of these regions. The aggressive nature of most gliomas, and the visual and textural similarities between the affected regions and normal tissue, create a challenge for neurosurgeons during removal of the tumor. Some glioma cells may get left behind.</p>



<p>The cells in a glioma look like healthy brain cells called glial cells. As a glioma grows, it forms a mass of cells called a tumor. The tumor can grow to press on brain or spinal cord tissue, causing a range of symptoms. There are many types of glioma. Some grow slowly and aren't considered to be cancers. Others are considered cancerous. Malignant gliomas grow quickly and can invade healthy brain tissue.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Hu_Leland_S._13803611_20230703-240x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377194" style="width:198px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Hu_Leland_S._13803611_20230703-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Hu_Leland_S._13803611_20230703.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Leland Hu, M.D., a neuroradiologist at Mayo Clinic in Arizona.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/hu-leland-s-m-d/bio-20055165" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Leland Hu, M.D.</a>, a neuroradiologist at Mayo Clinic in Arizona, says the study also shows that MRI techniques, such as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/neurology-neurosurgery/news/radiogenomics-exploring-mris-potential-for-predicting-heterogeneous-tumor-biology/mac-20529911" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dynamic susceptibility contrast</a>&nbsp;and diffusion tensor imaging, can help distinguish between the genetic and molecular alterations of invasive tumors, which is important for clinically characterizing areas that are difficult to surgically biopsy.</p>



<p>"We need to understand what is driving tumor progression," says Dr. Hu. "Our results demonstrate an expanded role of advanced MRI for clinical decision-making for high-grade glioma."</p>



<p>The study also provides insight into resistance to treatment that could improve future outcomes.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Tran_Nhan_L._16076010_202106230849-250x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377195" style="width:181px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Tran_Nhan_L._16076010_202106230849-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Tran_Nhan_L._16076010_202106230849.jpg 667w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Nhan Tran, Ph.D., cancer biologist in the Department of Cancer Biology at Mayo Clinic in Arizona.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Our hope is that these clinical MRI techniques will lead to improved diagnosis, prognosis and treatment," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/tran-nhan-l-ph-d/bio-20305146" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nhan Tran, Ph.D.</a>, a cancer biologist in the Department of Cancer Biology at Mayo Clinic in Arizona. "We are looking at this research through the lens of therapeutic decision-making for patients."</p>



<p>The entire dataset, including genomics, transcriptomics and MRI, is publicly available to other groups and institutions as a resource to fuel new discoveries beyond what Dr. Hu and colleagues have reported in the initial manuscript.</p>



<p>Review the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-023-41559-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding. </p>



<p>This article originally appeared on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/11/09/mapping-cell-behaviors-in-high-grade-glioma-to-improve-treatment/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mapping-cell-behaviors-in-high-grade-glioma-to-improve-treatment/">Mapping cell behaviors in high-grade glioma to improve treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Leland Hu]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nhan Tran]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[high-grade glioma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Neuroradiology]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>A veteran&#8217;s journey from Holocaust to hope at Mayo Clinic</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-veterans-journey-from-holocaust-to-hope-at-mayo-clinic/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic News Network Video Pkg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rochester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Eugene Kwon]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Green Beret]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kurt Glover-Ettrich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[military]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Urology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Veteran]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Veterans Day]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376868</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Veterans Day is observed every year on Nov. 11 to thank and honor military veterans of the U.S. Armed Forces. After serving his country with honor for 30 years, a retired Green Beret is now serving his community as a volunteer at Mayo Clinic. And as Jason Howland reports, this American appreciates life, liberty and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-veterans-journey-from-holocaust-to-hope-at-mayo-clinic/">A veteran&#8217;s journey from Holocaust to hope at Mayo Clinic</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Veterans Day is observed every year on Nov. 11 to thank and honor military veterans of the U.S. Armed Forces. </p>



<p>After serving his country with honor for 30 years, a retired Green Beret is now serving his community as a volunteer at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>. </p>



<p>And as Jason Howland reports, this American appreciates life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness every day — for good reason.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/NgQ-VhMtUIE" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: A veteran's journey from Holocaust to hope at Mayo Clinic</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeNgQVhMtUIE"  title="A veteran&#039;s journey from Holocaust to hope at Mayo Clinic" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/NgQ-VhMtUIE?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (4:17) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/A-veterans-journey-from-Holocaust-to-hope-at-Mayo-Clinic-SCRIPT.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Millions of patients, families and visitors journey to Mayo Clinic for hope and healing — each with their own unique life story. Kurt, an 80-year-old Mayo Clinic volunteer, has a life story you need to hear.</p>



<p>"I was born in Stimmersdorf, which was within the Nazi-occupied territory of the Czech Republic," Kurt says.</p>



<p>In 1943, when Kurt was still an infant, his father was forced by the Nazis to fight for the German army on the Eastern Front, as Kurt and his mother were sent to the concentration camps.</p>



<p>"The one soldier said, 'Leutnant, ich habe zwei Juden hier.&nbsp;(Lieutenant, I've got two Jews here.)' And we were sent to Auschwitz," Kurt says.</p>



<p>A year later, sent to Dachau. As the Allies approached in spring of '45, Kurt and his mother were quickly being transported by the Nazis to another camp when the train derailed. They survived the crash and escaped.</p>



<p>"We kept going and kept going until we couldn't hear any more dogs barking, screaming, shooting," he says.</p>



<p>They spent 16 weeks on the run avoiding capture until the war ended. "We had to live off the land, so to speak," Kurt says.</p>



<p>Meanwhile, Kurt's father was a prisoner of the Soviets. "Trains would come from Russia and bring home POWs," he says.</p>



<p>And during Hanukkah 1949 at the train station, "... it was the worst, coldest winter ever recorded. We heard a faint voice, 'Ester, bist du das? (Ester is that you?)' We turned around, it was my father," Kurt says.</p>



<p>In 1956, the family immigrated to the U.S. "And we saw the Statue of Liberty," he says. </p>



<p>They settled in Albany, New York. And as a young man at 18, Kurt became an American. "Tears came down my cheek, and I was so happy," he says.</p>



<p>And he joined the Army.</p>



<p>"I wanted to give back, and I served. It was the only way I could thank this great country called the United States of America and the American people for having allowed me to come here," Kurt says.</p>



<p>He served a 30-year military career in the Army Special Forces as a Green Beret. "Freedom is such a powerful word," Kurt says. </p>



<p>He is reminded every day what freedom truly means. "Freedom gives you hope," he says.</p>



<p>A cancer diagnosis brought him to Mayo Clinic, where he's been treated for the past 23 years by a leading expert in advanced <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prostate-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353087?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">prostate cancer</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/kwon-eugene-d-m-d/bio-20054440?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Eugene Kwon</a>.</p>



<p>"They gave me my life back. He spent as much time with me as possible, and I know with him, I was always in the best of hands," Kurt says.</p>



<p>It inspired Kurt to move to Rochester, Minnesota, and volunteer at Mayo Clinic. </p>



<p>"Monday through Friday, usually from 6:45 a.m. to 11 o'clock," he says. "This was the perfect opportunity. I knew there were patients coming through here, military people coming through here that I can relate to — not only talk to these people, but uplift their spirits, and instill in them that there is hope, that they're in the right place."</p>



<p>"Positive attitude, sunshine in the heart, and I use the gray matter God put between my ears to spread the joy, the happiness and goodwill, so to speak. This is why I'm supposed to be here," Kurt says. "America gave me freedom, hope. Mayo Clinic did the same thing."</p>



<p>Read more about Kurt's cancer care <a href="https://news.mayocliniclabs.com/2023/11/13/giving-thanks-for-years-of-prostate-cancer-treatment-kurt-glover-ettrich/">here</a>.</p>



<p> </p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-veterans-journey-from-holocaust-to-hope-at-mayo-clinic/">A veteran&#8217;s journey from Holocaust to hope at Mayo Clinic</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Kurt-Glover-Ettrich-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Kurt-Glover-Ettrich-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Eugene Kwon]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Green Beret]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Kurt Glover-Ettrich]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[military]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Urology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Veteran]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Veterans Day]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[volunteer]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic study suggests lower extremity lymphedema is a risk factor for multiple types of skin cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-suggests-lower-extremity-lymphedema-is-a-risk-factor-for-multiple-types-of-skin-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jay Furst]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[basal cell carcinoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dermatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lymphedema]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Proceedings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skin Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[squamous cell carcinoma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377039</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — New research from Mayo Clinic finds that patients with lymphedema —swelling of the limbs caused by the accumulation of protein-rich fluids of the immune system — had twice the risk of developing skin cancer than patients without lymphedema. Patients with lymphedema had a significantly higher frequency of developing basal cell carcinomas and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-suggests-lower-extremity-lymphedema-is-a-risk-factor-for-multiple-types-of-skin-cancer/">Mayo Clinic study suggests lower extremity lymphedema is a risk factor for multiple types of skin cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="682" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Physician-puts-compression-wrap-on-patient_WF2635704_0183-1024x682.jpg" alt="Physician puts compression wrap on patient" class="wp-image-377059" style="aspect-ratio:16/9;object-fit:cover" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Physician-puts-compression-wrap-on-patient_WF2635704_0183-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Physician-puts-compression-wrap-on-patient_WF2635704_0183-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Physician-puts-compression-wrap-on-patient_WF2635704_0183-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Physician-puts-compression-wrap-on-patient_WF2635704_0183-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Physician-puts-compression-wrap-on-patient_WF2635704_0183.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — New research from <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> finds that patients with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lymphedema/symptoms-causes/syc-20374682?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymphedema</a> —swelling of the limbs caused by the accumulation of protein-rich fluids of the immune system — had twice the risk of developing skin cancer than patients without lymphedema.</p>



<p>Patients with lymphedema had a significantly higher frequency of developing <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/basal-cell-carcinoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20354187?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">basal cell carcinomas</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/squamous-cell-carcinoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20352480?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">squamous cell carcinomas</a> on the lower extremities, according to the retrospective study published in <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/article/S0025-6196(23)00117-9/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a>. The study contributes to growing information linking lymphedema to localized changes in immunity and a predisposition for cancer.</p>



<p>The study reviewed data from 4,437 patients who were diagnosed with lower extremity lymphedema at Mayo Clinic in Rochester from 2000 to 2020. Compared with a matched control group, the group with lymphedema had an increased risk of skin cancer, and for patients who had lymphedema in one leg, that extremity was nearly three times as likely to have skin cancer compared with the other leg.</p>



<p>Lymphedema can be caused by surgery or cancer treatments that remove or damage the lymph nodes, which carry fluids of the immune system. Less commonly, lymphedema can be caused by inherited conditions.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Alavi-Afsaneh_30007478_202008311058-250x300.jpg" alt="portrait of Dr. Afsaneh Alavi" class="wp-image-377062" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Alavi-Afsaneh_30007478_202008311058-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Alavi-Afsaneh_30007478_202008311058-854x1024.jpg 854w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Alavi-Afsaneh_30007478_202008311058-768x921.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Alavi-Afsaneh_30007478_202008311058.jpg 938w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Afsaneh Alavi, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Patients with lymphedema are not screened routinely by dermatologists, and inadequate screening may lead to delayed diagnosis and treatment," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/alavi-afsaneh-m-d/bio-20492616?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Afsaneh Alavi, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic dermatologist and the study's senior author. "Our findings suggest the need for a relatively high degree of suspicion of skin cancer at sites with lymphedema. There is a need for raising awareness in clinicians seeing patients with lymphedema, and these patients may need regular skin cancer screenings, since early detection of skin cancer is critical."</p>



<p>View this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wPfNerwjd6I" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">video</a> of Dr. Alavi discussing the findings.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/skin-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20377605?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Skin cancer</a> is the most common cancer worldwide, but few studies have looked at the prevalence of lower extremity skin cancer, according to the article. The study found that all common forms of skin cancer, including squamous cell carcinoma, basal cell carcinoma, melanoma and angiosarcoma, were more common in patients with lower extremity lymphedema.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Proceedings</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a> is a monthly, peer-reviewed journal that publishes original articles and reviews on clinical and laboratory medicine, clinical research, basic science research and clinical epidemiology. The journal, sponsored by Mayo Foundation for Medical Education and Research as part of its commitment to physician education, has been published for 97 years and has a circulation of 127,000.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Jay Furst, Mayo Clinic Research and Education Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-suggests-lower-extremity-lymphedema-is-a-risk-factor-for-multiple-types-of-skin-cancer/">Mayo Clinic study suggests lower extremity lymphedema is a risk factor for multiple types of skin cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Physician-puts-compression-wrap-on-patient_WF2635704_0183_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Physician-puts-compression-wrap-on-patient_WF2635704_0183_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[basal cell carcinoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dermatology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Lymphedema]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Proceedings]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[screening]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Skin Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[squamous cell carcinoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>A new smartphone application aims to predict the safety of liver surgery</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-new-smartphone-application-aims-to-predict-the-safety-of-liver-surgery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelley Luckstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2023 17:42:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[APRI+ALBI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Patrick Starlinger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Liver Failure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[liver surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk prediction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[smartphone app]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377042</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — An international research team led by Dr. Patrick Starlinger, a hepatobiliary and pancreas surgeon from Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, developed a risk prediction model that can be calculated with a smartphone app. It provides an individualized risk assessment for patients before liver resection to evaluate the safety of liver surgery. Compared [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-new-smartphone-application-aims-to-predict-the-safety-of-liver-surgery/">A new smartphone application aims to predict the safety of liver surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/03/a-medical-illustration-of-liver-cancer-16X9.jpg" alt="a medical illustration of liver cancer" class="wp-image-186274" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/03/a-medical-illustration-of-liver-cancer-16X9.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/03/a-medical-illustration-of-liver-cancer-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. —<strong> </strong>An international research team led by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/starlinger-patrick-p-m-d-ph-d/bio-20533712">Dr. Patrick Starlinger</a>, a hepatobiliary and pancreas surgeon from <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/starlinger-patrick-p-m-d-ph-d/bio-20533712" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>, developed a risk prediction model that can be calculated with a smartphone app. It provides an individualized risk assessment for patients before liver resection to evaluate the safety of liver surgery. Compared to standard preoperative tests, the research suggests the model offers a predictive model for postoperative liver failure.</p>



<p>The model's effectiveness is documented in a paper that involved more than 14,000 patients from 10 different institutions and the <a href="https://www.facs.org/quality-programs/data-and-registries/acs-nsqip/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Surgery Quality Improvement Program</a> (NSQIP), an algorithm-based database from the U.S. The study is published in the <a href="https://journals.lww.com/annalsofsurgery/abstract/9900/an_apri_albi_based_multivariable_model_as.676.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Annals of Surgery</a>.</p>



<p>Surgical removal of parts of the liver remains the only curative approach for patients with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/liver-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353659" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">liver-specific cancer</a>. Normally, the liver can tolerate the surgical removal, also known as resection, of up to 75% of its volume and maintain its functions after surgery. However, depending on the underlying chronic liver disease, the type of cancer or the extent of resection, patients may be at higher risk of inadequate postoperative liver regeneration or even postoperative liver failure, the main cause of mortality after liver surgery.</p>



<p>The team of researchers developed a multivariable risk prediction model using basic patient characteristics such as age, sex, tumor type and planned type of liver resection, as well as the APRI+ALBI score. The APRI+ALBI score is an established liver function test, calculated using only routine laboratory parameters (aspartate aminotransferase (AST), platelets, albumin, bilirubin). It has already been shown to be closely related to preoperative liver function and chemotherapy-induced liver injury, and it has significant predictive potential for the development of postoperative liver failure. The APRI+ALBI score provides a comprehensive assessment of liver function, especially compared to classic liver function tests, which usually only assess the excretory capacity of the liver.</p>



<p>"We have taken an important step in translating this into clinical practice by developing a freely available smartphone application that allows us to calculate our score and thus individualize the risk assessment of patients before liver resection," says Dr. Starlinger, senior author of the study. "This sets a new standard in preoperative risk assessment and will significantly increase the safety of liver surgery for patients worldwide."</p>



<p>Details about the app and a full list of centers involved in the research are available in the <a href="https://www.meduniwien.ac.at/web/en/about-us/news/2023/news-in-november-2023/smart-phone-application-to-increase-safety-in-liver-surgery/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">news release</a> by the Medical University of Vienna. &nbsp;</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive&nbsp;Cancer Center</strong><strong><br></strong>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;is defining new boundaries in possibility, focusing on patient-centered care, developing novel treatments, training future generations of cancer experts, and bringing cancer research to communities. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs that are changing approaches to cancer prevention, screening, and treatment and improving the lives of cancer survivors.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-new-smartphone-application-aims-to-predict-the-safety-of-liver-surgery/">A new smartphone application aims to predict the safety of liver surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/03/a-medical-illustration-of-liver-cancer-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/03/a-medical-illustration-of-liver-cancer-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[APRI+ALBI]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Patrick Starlinger]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Liver Failure]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[liver surgery]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[risk prediction]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[smartphone app]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>