<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 11:31:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>A silent tumor, precancerous polyps and the power of genetic screening</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-silent-tumor-precancerous-polyps-and-the-power-of-genetic-screening/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Christina Wu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Konstantinos Lazaridis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Niloy Jewel Samadder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lynch Syndrome]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tammy LeDoux]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381552</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Tammy LeDoux could never have imagined she had a tumor the size of a pineapple growing on her left ovary. Or that precancerous polyps were lurking in her stomach and colon.&#160; "I never had any cramping. I never had any pain. I never felt anything hard or lumpy in my abdomen or down in my [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-silent-tumor-precancerous-polyps-and-the-power-of-genetic-screening/">A silent tumor, precancerous polyps and the power of genetic screening</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/TAMMY9-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381550" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/TAMMY9-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/TAMMY9-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/TAMMY9-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/TAMMY9-16x9-1.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Tammy LeDoux could never have imagined she had a tumor the size of a pineapple growing on her left ovary. Or that precancerous polyps were lurking in her stomach and colon.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"I never had any cramping. I never had any pain. I never felt anything hard or lumpy in my abdomen or down in my pelvic area. I never knew anything was there," says Tammy, an information technology analyst who lives in Wisconsin.</p>



<p>The surprising discoveries came after Tammy underwent genetic screening via the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine</a>, which revealed she has <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lynch-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20374714" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lynch syndrome.</a> The disorder is associated with an 80% risk of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353669" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colorectal cancer</a> and 50% risk of uterine and endometrial cancer.</p>



<p>"I honestly feel like knowing these genetic results has saved my life," Tammy says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Tammy's experience mirrors that of many other patients who, prior to participating in the Center’s DNA sequencing research study, called Tapestry, were unaware of their disease risk.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Overall, nearly 1.3 million Mayo Clinic patients like Tammy were invited to join Tapestry, which screened for three hereditary conditions: familial hypercholesterolemia (hereditary high cholesterol), hereditary breast and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/ovarian-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20375941" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ovarian cancer</a> (BRCA1 and BRCA2), and Lynch syndrome. Of those, roughly 100,000 chose to participate.</p>



<p>Based on existing literature, the study anticipated nearly 2% of participants would receive a positive result.</p>



<p>"What keeps me up at night is the fact that 1.2 million patients chose <em>not</em> to participate in the study, and this means around 20,000 of them likely have an undiagnosed hereditary risk or condition when considering the 2 percent rate of a positive result," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine/about/director-insights" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Konstantinos Lazaridis,</a> the Carlson and Nelson Endowed Executive Director for Mayo Clinic's Center for Individualized Medicine.</p>



<p>"We need to do better job of educating people about the value of genetic screening for rare but preventable conditions," he says.</p>



<p>Dr. Lazaridis says Mayo Clinic is advancing the idea of bringing genetic screening to routine patient care to help identify patients at high risk for cancer and other diseases, enabling earlier screening and mitigating the risk of cancer, the need to use expensive and limited therapies for advanced disease, and reducing premature deaths.</p>



<p>Beyond disease prevention, Mayo Clinic researchers are investigating volumes of Tapestry data to drive forward medical discoveries that enhance novel diagnostics and treatments.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Launching the Mayo Clinic Early Onset and Hereditary GI Cancers Program</strong></h2>



<p>In tandem with these efforts, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/samadder-niloy-jewel-m-d/bio-20396993">Dr. Niloy Jewel Samadder</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/wu-christina-s-m-b-b-ch-m-d/bio-20529971" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Christina Wu,</a> physician scientists in the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>, launched a new program in February 2024 to address the significant rise of colorectal and other gastrointestinal cancers in young people.</p>



<p>The Mayo Clinic Early Onset and Hereditary Gastrointestinal Cancers Program is dedicated to patients under the age of 55 who are diagnosed with colorectal, gastric, esophageal, liver, bile duct or pancreatic cancer.</p>



<p>This patient-centric program creates an integrated network of services involving gastroenterology, gynecology, oncology, colorectal surgery, infertility, pathology, genetics and adolescent and young adult specialists.</p>



<p>In 2022, Mayo Clinic's three campuses in Arizona, Florida and Minnesota reported over 2,000 newly diagnosed cases of gastrointestinal cancers among people under the age of 55. The marked rise in young-onset colorectal and other gastrointestinal cancers underscores a pressing health issue. The new program aims to provide accelerated access to top-tier care.</p>



<p>Dr. Samadder emphasizes that encircling patients with a multidisciplinary team of specialists will help provide the best possible outcomes.</p>



<p>"Our goal is to put the patient at the center of a collaborative framework of experts from diverse fields working seamlessly together," says Dr. Samadder, a Mayo Clinic gastroenterologist and cancer geneticist.</p>



<p>"The program also incorporates translational discoveries such as immunology and cancer evolution, as well as a clinical trial menu, research initiatives and a multi-omics approach that connects to a patient's unique biological datasets,” Dr. Samadder says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Tammy’s journey to the Tapestry study</strong></h2>



<p>Tammy’s initial motivation to participate in the Tapestry DNA research study was her curiosity about her ancestral heritage — another aspect of the study.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Upon receiving her genetic screening results, Tammy's team of genetic counselors and physicians moved quickly to educate her on Lynch Syndrome and help her schedule various screenings, including a colonoscopy, urine biopsy and ultrasound.&nbsp;</p>



<p>These screenings uncovered 10 polyps in her colon and stomach, some with precancerous characteristics, and two concerning moles on her skin. Soon after, Tammy made the proactive decision to undergo a hysterectomy to reduce her cancer risk. It was during this procedure that surgeons discovered and removed the sizable benign tumor.</p>



<p>"I couldn’t believe it. I’m beyond grateful," Tammy says. "I've been through the ringer, but now I have peace of mind knowing I've reduced my risks for cancer, and I can go in every couple years to check for any new polyps."</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is dedicated to shaping a future where cancers and other diseases can be prevented altogether, or identified at earlier stages, allowing for more precise treatment by a collaborative team of specialists.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-silent-tumor-precancerous-polyps-and-the-power-of-genetic-screening/">A silent tumor, precancerous polyps and the power of genetic screening</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/TAMMY9_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/TAMMY9-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Christina Wu]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Konstantinos Lazaridis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Niloy Jewel Samadder]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Lynch Syndrome]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Tammy LeDoux]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Treating stomach cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-treating-stomach-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2024 15:58:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gastric cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stomach cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stomach Cancer Awareness Month]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=351405</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>More than 26,000 people in the U.S. will be diagnosed with stomach cancer this year, and nearly 11,000 people will die of the disease, according to the American Cancer Society. Stomach cancer accounts for about 1.5% of all new cancers diagnosed in the U.S. each year. Stomach cancer, also known as gastric cancer, can affect any [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-treating-stomach-cancer/">Treating stomach cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-portrait-of-a-smiling-middle-aged-woman-seated-with-her-chin-resting-on-her-hand-original-1024x683.jpg" alt="a portrait of a smiling middle-aged woman, seated, with her chin resting on her hand" class="wp-image-101627" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-portrait-of-a-smiling-middle-aged-woman-seated-with-her-chin-resting-on-her-hand-original-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-portrait-of-a-smiling-middle-aged-woman-seated-with-her-chin-resting-on-her-hand-original-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-portrait-of-a-smiling-middle-aged-woman-seated-with-her-chin-resting-on-her-hand-original-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<p>More than 26,000 people in the U.S. will be diagnosed with stomach cancer this year, and nearly 11,000 people will die of the disease, according to the <a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/stomach-cancer/about/key-statistics.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Cancer Society</a>. Stomach cancer accounts for about 1.5% of all new cancers diagnosed in the U.S. each year.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stomach-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352438?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stomach cancer</a>, also known as gastric cancer, can affect any part of the stomach.&nbsp;In most of the world, stomach cancers form in the main part of the stomach. In the U.S., stomach cancer is more likely to affect the area where the esophagus meets the stomach. Where the cancer occurs in the stomach is one factor health care professionals consider when determining treatment options.</p>



<p>Signs and symptoms of stomach cancer can include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Trouble swallowing.</li>



<li>Belly pain.</li>



<li>Feeling bloated after eating.</li>



<li>Feeling full after eating small amounts of food.</li>



<li>Not feeling hungry when you would expect to be hungry.</li>



<li>Heartburn.</li>



<li>Indigestion.</li>



<li>Nausea.</li>



<li>Vomiting.</li>



<li>Unintentional weight loss.</li>



<li>Fatigue.</li>



<li>Black stools.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Treatment</strong></h2>



<p>If you've been diagnosed with stomach cancer, your&nbsp;health care professional will consider the stage and location of your cancer, as well as your overall health and personal preferences, to determine your&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stomach-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352443?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">treatment</a>&nbsp;plan. </p>



<p>Treatment can include:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Surgery.</strong><br>The goal of surgery for stomach cancer is to remove all of the cancer. For small stomach cancers, surgery might be the first treatment. Other treatments might be used first if the stomach cancer grows deeper into the stomach wall or spreads to the lymph nodes.</li>



<li><strong>Chemotherapy.</strong><br>Chemotherapy is a drug treatment that uses chemicals to kill cancer cells. Chemotherapy often is used before surgery to treat stage 2 and stage 3 stomach cancers. Systemic chemotherapy can shrink the cancer so that it's easier to remove. Systemic chemotherapy may be used after surgery if there's a risk that some cancer cells were left behind. If surgery isn't an option, systemic chemotherapy may be recommended instead. It can be used if the cancer is too advanced or if you're not healthy enough to have surgery. Chemotherapy also can help control cancer symptoms.</li>



<li><strong>Radiation therapy.</strong><br>Radiation therapy uses high-powered beams of energy to kill cancer cells. The beams can come from X-rays, protons or other sources. Radiation sometimes is used before surgery to treat stage 2 and stage 3 stomach cancers. It can shrink the cancer so that it's easier to remove. Radiation therapy may be used after surgery if the cancer can't be removed completely. Radiation can help relieve stomach cancer symptoms if the cancer is advanced or surgery isn't possible.</li>



<li><strong>Targeted therapy.</strong><br>Targeted treatments use medicines that attack specific chemicals present within cancer cells. By blocking these chemicals, targeted treatments can cause cancer cells to die. Your cancer cells are tested to see if targeted therapy is likely to work for you. Targeted therapy typically is used for advanced stomach cancer. This may include stage 4 stomach cancer and cancer that comes back after treatment.</li>



<li><strong>Immunotherapy.</strong><br>Immunotherapy is a treatment with medicine that helps your body's immune system kill cancer cells. Your immune system fights off diseases by attacking germs and other cells that shouldn't be in your body. Cancer cells survive by hiding from the immune system. Immunotherapy helps the immune system cells find and kill the cancer cells. Immunotherapy sometimes is used to treat advanced cancer. This may include stage 4 stomach cancer or cancer that comes back after treatment.</li>
</ul>



<p>Connect with others talking about stomach cancer in the <a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/cancer/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cancer</a> support group on&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Connect</a>, an online patient community moderated by Mayo Clinic</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-treating-stomach-cancer/">Treating stomach cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-portrait-of-a-smiling-middle-aged-woman-seated-with-her-chin-resting-on-her-hand-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/a-portrait-of-a-smiling-middle-aged-woman-seated-with-her-chin-resting-on-her-hand-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[gastric cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[stomach cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Stomach Cancer Awareness Month]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>World Cancer Day: Making a commitment to close the cancer care gap</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/world-cancer-day-making-a-commitment-to-close-the-cancer-care-gap/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2024 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer care gap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Rick Bold]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381393</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Union for International Cancer Control (UICC) recognizes&#160;World Cancer Day&#160;annually on February 4. The UICC's 2024 theme for World Cancer Day is "Close the Care Gap." The care gap is the gap between people who can obtain healthcare related to the prevention, early detection, diagnosis and treatment of cancer and those who cannot. The factors [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/world-cancer-day-making-a-commitment-to-close-the-cancer-care-gap/">World Cancer Day: Making a commitment to close the cancer care gap</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="1017" height="572" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381396" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_16x9.jpg 1017w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1017px) 100vw, 1017px" /></figure>



<p>The Union for International Cancer Control (UICC) recognizes&nbsp;<a href="https://www.worldcancerday.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">World Cancer Day</a>&nbsp;annually on February 4. The UICC's 2024 theme for World Cancer Day is "Close the Care Gap." The care gap is the gap between people who can obtain healthcare related to the prevention, early detection, diagnosis and treatment of cancer and those who cannot.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Bold-Rick-J._30304260_20231002-819x1024-1-240x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381394" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Bold-Rick-J._30304260_20231002-819x1024-1-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Bold-Rick-J._30304260_20231002-819x1024-1-768x960.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Bold-Rick-J._30304260_20231002-819x1024-1.jpg 819w" sizes="(max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /></figure></div>


<p>The factors that create this gap include income, education and geographical location barriers. Discrimination based on ethnicity, race, gender, sexual orientation, age, disability and lifestyle can also be a barrier. Some people are also more likely to be exposed to factors that increase cancer risk, such as environmental hazards, unhealthy diet and tobacco.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic joins the UICC in breaking down barriers that stand in the way of cancer care. In this Q&amp;A,&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/richard-bold-m-d-named-site-director-mayo-clinic-comprehensive-cancer-center-in-arizona/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Rick Bold, M.D.</a>, site deputy director for&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;in Arizona, discusses Mayo Clinic's commitment to closing the cancer care gap:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What does World Cancer Day mean to Mayo Clinic?</h2>



<p>It means understanding the gaps in our cancer care and our cancer outcomes. It means recognizing those gaps by intentionally trying to close and eliminate them. There are different ways to define the gap; it may be related to the incidence of cancer, it may be related to the outcomes of cancer, and it may be related to access to cancer care. Each of these is a different gap that affects how people cope with cancer, how people survive cancer, and how people are diagnosed with cancer. We should strive to close and eliminate each of these gaps.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What is Mayo Clinic doing to help close the cancer care gap?</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20370588" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cancer</a> is not just one disease. For example, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a> is different for each person. Understanding why breast cancer developed at an individualized level — personalized or precision medicine — helps us determine the proper treatment for that patient and leads to better outcomes. Maybe a woman's genes caused cancer to develop. Perhaps it's where she lived — her environmental history or what she ate. We're doing <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials/search-results?studySiteStatusesGrouped=Open/Status%20Unknown&amp;pocId=CON-20167633" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">studies</a> reaching out to women across different communities, ethnic backgrounds and age groups to understand how <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/breast-cancer-risk-assessment/about/pac-20393195" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer risk</a> is determined. If every person is different, we need to understand that their cancer is different based on who they are. That's one effort that's helping to close the cancer care gap.</p>



<p>Another effort to close the gap is improving access to screening. Cancer screening is one of the most effective tools to reduce the burden of cancer in our communities. However, only some people have access to screening. Mayo Clinic is asking: How can we help everyone get access? How can we make screening easier? For example, can we detect&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353669" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colon cancer</a>&nbsp;with a blood test instead of a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/colonoscopy/about/pac-20393569" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colonoscopy</a>? Can we detect it&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/fecal-occult-blood-test/multimedia/fecal-occult-blood-test-kit/img-20007541" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">with a stool sample</a>&nbsp;collected in a person's home without time away from work or family or disrupting intestinal function by drinking a solution to cleanse the colon for a colonoscopy? Mayo Clinic is researching cancer screening tools that can be made available to more people conveniently at a lower cost. These efforts can help us close the gap by detecting more cancers at their earliest stage, which is when cures happen.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is also using technology to close the gap. One example of this is&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/sections/overview/ovc-20185491" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">proton beam therapy</a>&nbsp;for radiation. Mayo Clinic has two proton therapy units, one in Scottsdale, Arizona, and one in Rochester, Minnesota. We've studied how to deliver proton beam therapy in a way that improves patient outcomes. Some people can't take the time to get radiation, which may last weeks or months. Using proton beam therapy, we can shorten treatment time, broadening access by making it more convenient for people to get treatment in a minimally disruptive way.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What is Mayo Clinic doing to reach out to underserved and rural communities facing cancer care barriers?</h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic is developing cancer screening techniques that can be implemented internationally while recognizing that even in the U.S., not everybody has a hospital or a cancer center nearby. Many people are geographically isolated from healthcare or may lack insurance that pays for screening. We're trying to identify methods that could detect a variety of cancers early in a patient-friendly fashion, no matter what environment a person is living in and no matter what resources they have.</p>



<p>All Mayo Clinic locations see themselves as serving the community around them. We are developing strategic partnerships and relationships to elevate access to care in those communities and share our clinical expertise. This moves our care beyond the walls of our hospitals and clinics. Moving cancer care into patients' homes is becoming a national concept. We're starting to delve into that model of care. This will expand our ability to serve a broader population, not just in our local communities but nationally or internationally.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What is Mayo Clinic's goal for the future of cancer care?</h2>



<p>The ideal goal would be to eliminate cancer or turn cancer into a disease nobody needs to worry about. That's a long-term goal, and maybe we will get there.</p>



<p>In the shorter term, the goal is to achieve equitable cancer care that provides the best outcomes in a way that doesn't significantly disrupt the lives of patients and their families while respecting their individuality and their role in decision-making. We want to put all those things together and then always keep working on improving outcomes.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is committed to eliminating care gaps so every patient, regardless of where they live or who they are, receives the same cancer care and experiences the same positive outcomes. Mayo Clinic is here to serve patients. That's our primary mission.</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/02/01/world-cancer-day-making-a-commitment-to-close-the-cancer-care-gap/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center Blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/world-cancer-day-making-a-commitment-to-close-the-cancer-care-gap/">World Cancer Day: Making a commitment to close the cancer care gap</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer care gap]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Rick Bold]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Closing the gaps in cancer care</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-closing-the-gaps-in-cancer-care/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#breastcancerscreening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Care]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cancer prevention]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cancer treatment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Richard Bold]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[early detection]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Endometrial Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health disparities]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health Equity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kidney cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381211</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>2024 could mark a grim milestone in the battle against cancer. In January, the&#160;American Cancer&#160;Society&#160;announced that, for the first time ever, new cancer cases could exceed the 2 million mark. Early detection and the right treatment are among the best weapons to fight cancer. However, today many people don't have equitable access to cancer care [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-closing-the-gaps-in-cancer-care/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Closing the gaps in cancer care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>2024 could mark a grim milestone in the battle against cancer.</p>



<p>In January, the&nbsp;<a href="https://pressroom.cancer.org/acs-cff-2024">American Cancer&nbsp;</a><a href="https://pressroom.cancer.org/acs-cff-2024" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Society</a>&nbsp;announced that, for the first time ever, new cancer cases could exceed the 2 million mark.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1000" height="563" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/a-close-up-of-the-word-Cancer-with-a-partial-definition-styled-to-look-like-a-dictionary-entry-16X9.jpg" alt="a close-up of the word 'Cancer' with a partial definition, styled to look like a dictionary entry" class="wp-image-361458" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/a-close-up-of-the-word-Cancer-with-a-partial-definition-styled-to-look-like-a-dictionary-entry-16X9.jpg 1000w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/a-close-up-of-the-word-Cancer-with-a-partial-definition-styled-to-look-like-a-dictionary-entry-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/a-close-up-of-the-word-Cancer-with-a-partial-definition-styled-to-look-like-a-dictionary-entry-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" /></figure>



<p>Early detection and the right treatment are among the best weapons to fight cancer.</p>



<p>However, today many people don't have equitable access to cancer care because of systemic barriers and health disparities.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is working to change that with strategic initiatives aimed at health equity.</p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/richard-bold-m-d-named-site-director-mayo-clinic-comprehensive-cancer-center-in-arizona/">Dr. Rick Bold</a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/richard-bold-m-d-named-site-director-mayo-clinic-comprehensive-cancer-center-in-arizona/">.,</a>&nbsp;a site deputy director with&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center">Mayo Clinic&nbsp;</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Comprehensive</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center">&nbsp;</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cancer</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center">&nbsp;Center</a>, discusses Mayo's commitment to eliminating health disparities and closing the gaps in cancer care.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/q11i3iP04C4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeq11i3iP04C4"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Closing the gaps in cancer care" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/q11i3iP04C4?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:10) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the </strong><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Closing-the-gaps-on-cancer-care-FINAL-1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>script</strong></a><strong><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/CLOSING-THE-GAPS-IN-CANCER-CARE-FINAL.pdf">.</a></strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What are health disparities?</h2>



<p><a href="https://health.gov/healthypeople/priority-areas/health-equity-healthy-people-2030">The U.S.&nbsp;</a><a href="https://health.gov/healthypeople/priority-areas/health-equity-healthy-people-2030" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department</a><a href="https://health.gov/healthypeople/priority-areas/health-equity-healthy-people-2030">&nbsp;of&nbsp;</a><a href="https://health.gov/healthypeople/priority-areas/health-equity-healthy-people-2030" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Health</a><a href="https://health.gov/healthypeople/priority-areas/health-equity-healthy-people-2030">&nbsp;and&nbsp;</a><a href="https://health.gov/healthypeople/priority-areas/health-equity-healthy-people-2030" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Human</a><a href="https://health.gov/healthypeople/priority-areas/health-equity-healthy-people-2030">&nbsp;Services</a>&nbsp;defines health disparities as "a particular type of health difference that is closely linked with social, economic, and/or environmental disadvantage."</p>



<p>According to the agency, health disparities also "adversely affect groups of people who have systematically experienced greater obstacles to health based on their racial or ethnic group, religion, socioeconomic status, gender, age, mental health, cognitive, sensory or physical disability, sexual orientation or gender identity, geographic location, or other characteristics historically linked to discrimination or exclusion."</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="662" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Joyce-feet-1024x662.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381379" style="width:858px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Joyce-feet-1024x662.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Joyce-feet-300x194.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Joyce-feet-768x496.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Joyce-feet-1536x993.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Joyce-feet-2048x1324.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>"Native American Indians, African American patients, Hispanic patients — there are differences that can impact health outcomes," says Dr. Bold. "We have a commitment to eliminate those differences across groups so that every patient, regardless where they live or who they are, have the same anticipated outcome from cancer."</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p>"<strong>We are here to serve patients. That's our primary mission.<br>We are committed to the elimination of inequality in all aspects of cancer care</strong>."</p><cite>Rick Bold, M.D.<br>Mayo Clinic comprehensive cancer center</cite></blockquote></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Moving Mayo's care beyond its four walls</h2>



<p>Dr. Bold, who is also a surgical oncologist and a specialist in endocrine surgery, says many patients in need of cancer care find themselves geographically isolated.</p>



<p>"Even here in the United States, not everyone has a hospital or even a cancer center within 15 minutes or 30 minutes," says Dr. Bold.</p>



<p>"All of the Mayo hospitals see themselves serving the community around them and elevating access to care by developing partnerships and relationships that takes our outcomes and clinical expertise and pushes it out into the community. This moves our care beyond our four walls," adds Dr. Bold.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/10/prostate_cancer_surgery_operating_room_16x9_3614812_0006-1024x576.jpg" alt="prostate cancer surgery in the operating room" class="wp-image-175724" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/10/prostate_cancer_surgery_operating_room_16x9_3614812_0006-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/10/prostate_cancer_surgery_operating_room_16x9_3614812_0006-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/10/prostate_cancer_surgery_operating_room_16x9_3614812_0006-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Increasing access to cancer screenings</h2>



<p>According to the<a href="https://pressroom.cancer.org/">&nbsp;American Cancer&nbsp;</a><a href="https://pressroom.cancer.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Society</a>&nbsp;January report, the risk of dying from cancer has steadily declined in the last 30 years.</p>



<p>However, the&nbsp;<a href="https://pressroom.cancer.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">report</a>&nbsp;also indicated there has been a rise in diagnoses of six of the 10 most common cancers, including&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-black-women-should-consider-screening-for-breast-cancer-earlier/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/prostate-cancer-screening-and-treatment/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">prostate</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-understanding-endometrial-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">endometrial</a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-understanding-endometrial-cancer/">,</a>&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-advancing-pancreatic-cancer-treatment-with-total-robotic-whipple-surgery/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pancreatic</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-is-kidney-cancer-treated/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">kidney</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-melanoma-misconception-dark-skin-tones-at-risk-too/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">melanoma</a>.</p>



<p>Early detection is critical in the fight against cancer by significantly improving the chances of successful treatment and long-term survival. Dr. Bold says research is underway to develop cancer screening tools that are more convenient and less costly for patients.</p>



<p>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-cancer-screenings-for-the-lgbtq-community-are-important/">Cancer&nbsp;</a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-cancer-screenings-for-the-lgbtq-community-are-important/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">screening</a>&nbsp;is probably one of the biggest things we have to reduce the burden of cancer in our communities, but not everyone has access to screening," explains Dr. Bold. "How can we make that better and easier for patients? This would really help us close the gap in our health disparities related to cancer detection in its earliest stage, which is where cures happen."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Personalized medicine</h2>



<p>Doctors at Mayo Clinic are also working on closing gaps in cancer care with&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-and-oxford-nanopore-announce-collaboration-to-advance-precision-medicine-for-cancer-and-genetic-disorders/">personalized or&nbsp;</a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-and-oxford-nanopore-announce-collaboration-to-advance-precision-medicine-for-cancer-and-genetic-disorders/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">precision</a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-and-oxford-nanopore-announce-collaboration-to-advance-precision-medicine-for-cancer-and-genetic-disorders/">&nbsp;</a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-and-oxford-nanopore-announce-collaboration-to-advance-precision-medicine-for-cancer-and-genetic-disorders/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">medicine</a>.</p>



<p>Dr. Bold says this approach can help better identify the right treatment for the right patient.</p>



<p>"Let's take breast cancer, for example. Each woman is very different. Understanding why the cancer developed at an individualized level is something that will help us determine better outcomes," says Dr. Bold. "Maybe it's a woman's genes. Maybe it's where she lived. Maybe her environmental history or what she ate."</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/Patient-radiation-therapy-mask-showing-laser-lines-for-targeting-cancer-cells-in-the-brain_shutterstock_621261359.jpg" alt="" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Proton beam therapy targets and destroys cancer cells with highly advanced precision</strong></figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Innovation transforming cancer care</h2>



<p>Dr. Bold says the intersection of innovative technology and health outcomes is helping eliminate barriers to cancer care.</p>



<p>"Radiation therapy, for example, can last for weeks, even months, which can pose a challenge for patients traveling from rural communities or far from home," says Dr. Bold.</p>



<p>At Mayo Clinic, patients can receive&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-study-reveals-proton-beam-therapy-may-shorten-breast-cancer-treatment/">proton&nbsp;</a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-study-reveals-proton-beam-therapy-may-shorten-breast-cancer-treatment/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">beam&nbsp;</a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-study-reveals-proton-beam-therapy-may-shorten-breast-cancer-treatment/">therapy</a>, a highly advanced cancer treatment that targets cancer cells painlessly and with more precision.</p>



<p>Proton therapy can be a game-changer for many patients because of the benefits it offers over traditional radiation therapy.</p>



<p>"Not everybody has the ability to move or separate themselves from their local environment, family and friends, and leave their home to receive cancer treatment," explains Dr. Bold.</p>



<p>"By using proton beam therapy, we can shorten their treatment time so we are broadening access and making it more convenient for patients to get treatments that are just as good, if not better, but in a way that's minimally disruptive for their lives," he adds.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p>"<strong>The impact of cancer treatment on patients can be disruptive. Technology allows us to offer treatments that are faster, shorter, more efficient and better ultimately for society.</strong>"</p><cite>Rick Bold, M.D.<br>MAYO CLINIC COMPREHENSIVE CANCER CENTER</cite></blockquote></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The future of cancer care</h2>



<p>Eliminating disparities and barriers to cancer care is part of Mayo Clinic's overall commitment to improving health outcomes by advancing health equity, inclusion and diversity.</p>



<p>"Our goal and hope for the future is eliminating cancer, period, so that it's no longer a disease anybody has to think about. That is our long-term goal." says Dr. Bold.</p>



<p>"In the short term, we would like to achieve equitable cancer care that provides the best outcomes for every patient."</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-closing-the-gaps-in-cancer-care/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Closing the gaps in cancer care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Screenshot-2024-02-02-at-12.35_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/GettyImages-1290137773-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#breastcancerscreening]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer Care]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cancer prevention]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cancer treatment]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Richard Bold]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[early detection]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Endometrial Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[health disparities]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Health Equity]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[innovation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[kidney cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mcthumb >https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Dr.-Patel-150x150.jpg</mayoclinic:mcthumb >	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: How precise diagnosis of lymphoma offers patients best treatment options</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-precise-diagnosis-of-lymphoma-offers-patients-best-treatment-options/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Lisa Rimsza]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lymphoma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=379901</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Dr. Lisa Rimsza&#160;is a pathologist, director of the&#160;Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory&#160;and researcher with the&#160;Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center. Her research specializes in&#160;lymphoma,&#160;with a focus on developing tests for accurate patient diagnoses and assessing disease aggressiveness. Dr. Rimsza has made significant advances in this field of research.&#160;She says having a precise diagnosis allows physicians to [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-precise-diagnosis-of-lymphoma-offers-patients-best-treatment-options/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How precise diagnosis of lymphoma offers patients best treatment options</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/rimsza-lisa-m-m-d/bio-20185498?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Lisa Rimsza</a>&nbsp;is a pathologist, director of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/laboratory-medicine-pathology/overview/specialty-groups/laboratory-genetics/molecular-genetics-laboratory?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory</a>&nbsp;and researcher with the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>. Her research specializes in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lymphoma/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352642" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymphoma,</a>&nbsp;with a focus on developing tests for accurate patient diagnoses and assessing disease aggressiveness.</p>



<p>Dr. Rimsza has made significant advances in this field of research.&nbsp;She says having a precise diagnosis allows physicians to provide patients with the best possible treatment.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/M6ARKpwlWYU" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeM6ARKpwlWYU"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Why precision diagnosis is crucial for patients" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/M6ARKpwlWYU?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:05) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: “Mayo Clinic News Network.” Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Script-MCM-Precision-diagnosis.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"My lab focuses on&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-what-is-lymphoma/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymphoma</a>, which is a group of diseases and cancers that arise from the lymphatic systems," says Dr. Rimsza.<br><br>"We specialize in developing new tests to make sure we can get the most accurate diagnosis for the patient, and also figure out whether their disease is likely to be more or less aggressive," she says.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Lisa Rimsza, M.D., in the Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory" class="wp-image-380355" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Lisa Rimsza, M.D., in the Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory</figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>"We've been working with an interesting platform, or technology platform, which actually is able to use the tissue that is most commonly available from patient biopsies when a biopsy is taken out. It's put in formaldehyde and then in paraffin wax," she says. "We've been using a technology that actually is able to work with that tissue and get good information about genes and expression."</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Lisa Rimsza, M.D., and team in the Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory. Front row, from left: Charlie Kern, Colleen Ramsower and Dr. Rimsza. Back row, from left: Lindsey Armitage, Lee Wisner, Jon Ocal, Katie Zellner." class="wp-image-380360" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Lisa Rimsza, M.D., and team in the Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory. Front row, from left: Charlie Kern, Colleen Ramsower and Dr. Rimsza. Back row, from left: Lindsey Armitage, Lee Wisner, Jon Ocal, Katie Zellner.</figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>"It's absolutely important that the patient has the most accurate diagnosis as possible. And what we're doing is going through the most common types of lymphomas, and trying to build a series of assays that will answer several different diagnostic questions," says Dr. Rimsza.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Learn more about Dr. Rimsza's work:</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f4yhqxCY7mk" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Lisa Rimsza - 2023 Arizona Bioscience Research of the Year</a></li>



<li><a href="https://news.mayocliniclabs.com/2023/11/14/rna-test-identifies-large-b-cell-lymphoma-subtypes-lisa-rimsza-m-d/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">RNA test identifies large B-cell lymphoma subtypes</a></li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-understanding-treating-lymphoma/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Understanding, treating lymphoma</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-treating-leukemia-and-lymphoma/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Consumer Health: Treating leukemia and lymphoma</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-precise-diagnosis-of-lymphoma-offers-patients-best-treatment-options/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How precise diagnosis of lymphoma offers patients best treatment options</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-researcher-lab-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-microscope-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Lisa Rimsza]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[lymphoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Why Black women need to be screened for cervical cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-black-women-need-to-be-screened-for-cervical-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Black women]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cancer screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cervical Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DeeDee Stiepan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Olivia Cardenas-Trowers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health disparity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HPV]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HPV vaccine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pap test]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=328526</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>While all women can develop cervical cancer, non-Hispanic Black women are more likely to be diagnosed and die of cervical cancer, compared to white women in the U.S. This disparity is not due to genetic differences among white, Black or Hispanic women, but rather related to systemic racism, access to healthcare and socioeconomic factors, says [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-black-women-need-to-be-screened-for-cervical-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Why Black women need to be screened for cervical cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>While all women can develop <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cervical-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352501?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cervical cancer</a>, non-Hispanic Black women are more likely to be diagnosed and die of cervical cancer, compared to white women in the U.S.<br><br>This <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/departments-divisions/department-cancer-biology/research/cancer-disparities?_ga=2.130698383.1605638451.1641152617-1403141615.1638192781?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">disparity</a> is not due to genetic differences among white, Black or Hispanic women, but rather related to systemic racism, access to healthcare and socioeconomic factors, says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/cardenas-trowers-olivia-o-m-d/bio-20519852?_ga=2.35147681.1605638451.1641152617-1403141615.1638192781?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">Dr. Olivia </a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/cardenas-trowers-olivia-o-m-d/bio-20519852?_ga=2.35147681.1605638451.1641152617-1403141615.1638192781?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cardenas-Trowers</a>, a Mayo Clinic urogynecologist. That is why she encourages women to learn more about this often-avoidable cancer and get screened, usually starting at 21 for average-risk women.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/Zvh20yQqeK4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeZvh20yQqeK4"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Why Black women need to get screened for cervical cancer" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Zvh20yQqeK4?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:15) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/01/Script-MCM-Cervical-Cancer22.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cervical-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352506?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Screening</a> for cervical cancer often starts with a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/pap-smear/multimedia/pap-test/img-20007025?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pap test</a> or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/pap-smear/about/pac-20394841?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">smear.</a><br><br>"Cervical cancer is diagnosed with tissue sampling, so like with a biopsy, but abnormal cells can be picked up with a screening exam like a Pap smear, which can lead to being able to diagnose cervical cancer," says Dr. Cardenas-Trowers.</p>



<p>Early stage cervical cancer may produce no distinct symptoms, making these regular screenings lifesaving.<br><br>"It's really in later-stage cervical cancer where you can see things like abnormal vaginal bleeding and pain, in general or with intercourse," she says.</p>



<p>The biggest risk factor for developing cervical cancer —<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hpv-infection/symptoms-causes/syc-20351596?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"> HPV infection</a> — can be prevented with a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hpv-infection/in-depth/hpv-vaccine/art-20047292?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">vaccine</a>.</p>



<p>"There is a vaccine out there that can be given as early as 9 years old and up to 45 years old. It is very important to know it's not only for women, but actually also for men," says Dr. Cardenas-Trowers.</p>



<p>Access to healthcare and establishing trust is essential to help reduce the cervical cancer mortality rate for Black women, says Dr. Cardenas-Trowers. Her advice for all women is to establish care with a primary care clinician, undergo the recommended screening and get the HPV vaccine for yourself, if you're eligible, and for your children.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-black-women-need-to-be-screened-for-cervical-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Why Black women need to be screened for cervical cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/04/an-African-American-woman-sitting-at-a-desk-near-a-window-with-the-light-coming-in-and-resting-her-head-on-her-hands-in-a-prayer-like-position-perhaps-worried-or-stressed-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/04/an-African-American-woman-sitting-at-a-desk-near-a-window-with-the-light-coming-in-and-resting-her-head-on-her-hands-in-a-prayer-like-position-perhaps-worried-or-stressed-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Black women]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cancer screening]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cervical Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[DeeDee Stiepan]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Olivia Cardenas-Trowers]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[health disparity]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[HPV]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[HPV vaccine]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Pap test]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Toolkit for reducing cervical cancer risk</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/toolkit-for-reducing-cervical-cancer-risk/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nicole Ferrara]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cervical Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=380577</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Cervical cancer is the&#160;fourth most common cancer&#160;in women globally, particularly in low- and middle-income countries. In the U.S., cervical cancer is no longer a common cause of cancer death because of the use of a screening test called a&#160;Pap smear, which detects changes in cervical cells. While the overall rate of&#160;cervical cancer&#160;in the U.S. is [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/toolkit-for-reducing-cervical-cancer-risk/">Toolkit for reducing cervical cancer risk</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/a-medical-illustration-of-cervical-cancer-16X9.jpg" alt="a medical illustration of cervical cancer" class="wp-image-220475" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/a-medical-illustration-of-cervical-cancer-16X9.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/a-medical-illustration-of-cervical-cancer-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></figure>



<p>Cervical cancer is the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/cervical-cancer#:~:text=Cervical%20cancer%20is%20the%20fourth,%2D%20and%20middle%2Dincome%20countries." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">fourth most common cancer</a>&nbsp;in women globally, particularly in low- and middle-income countries. In the U.S., cervical cancer is no longer a common cause of cancer death because of the use of a screening test called a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/pap-smear/about/pac-20394841" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pap smear</a>, which detects changes in cervical cells.</p>



<p>While the overall rate of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cervical-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352501" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cervical cancer</a>&nbsp;in the U.S. is declining, the number of people diagnosed with late-stage cervical cancer is&nbsp;<a href="https://ijgc.bmj.com/content/32/9/1115" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">increasing</a>, and rates among Black women are disproportionately high.&nbsp;<a href="https://ijgc.bmj.com/content/32/9/1115" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Research</a>&nbsp;also indicates that many women still are not being screened for cervical cancer.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/butler-kristina-a-m-d-m-s/bio-20110364" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kristina Butler, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic gynecologic oncologist, discusses the tools available to reduce your cervical cancer risk, including a trusted healthcare professional, the HPV vaccine and regular screening:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Tool No. 1: Find a healthcare professional you trust.</h2>



<p>Many people in the U.S. don't have a healthcare professional they see regularly. The causes are complicated and include being underinsured, barriers related to cost and transportation, and mistrust in the healthcare system — all of which can lead to late-stage cervical cancer diagnoses and poorer outcomes.</p>



<p>"People need to find a care professional they're comfortable with. Catching changes in the cervix and cancers early improves long-term outcomes," says Dr. Butler.</p>



<p>If you don’t visit a healthcare professional regularly due to cost or lack of insurance, you may be eligible for free or low-cost screening through the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cdc.gov/cancer/nbccedp/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Breast and Cervical Cancer Early Detection Program</a> NBCCEDP). A program of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), the NBCCEDP helps people with low incomes who do not have adequate insurance gain access to breast and cervical cancer screening, diagnosis and treatment.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cdc.gov/cancer/nbccedp/screenings.htm" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Find a screening program near you</a>.</p>



<p>Your local health department or women's clinic may also provide free or low-cost options for screening. The&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cdc.gov/publichealthgateway/healthdirectories/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CDC website</a>&nbsp;offers lists of health departments that you can search to find resources in your area.</p>



<p>Dr. Butler recommends establishing a relationship with a healthcare professional you see for a checkup once a year — a primary care provider or a gynecologist, a doctor who specializes in female reproductive health. "During that visit, it’s important to discuss symptoms and anything you think may be out of the ordinary related to the genital area. That discussion might prompt the need for a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/pelvic-exam/about/pac-20385135" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pelvic exam</a>. A person should be comfortable requesting an exam because, in many instances, it's hard to define normal."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Tool No. 2: Get the HPV vaccine for yourself and your children.</h2>



<p>Nearly all cervical cancers are caused by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hpv-infection/symptoms-causes/syc-20351596" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">HPV</a>&nbsp;(human papillomavirus) infection, which can also cause cancers of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/vaginal-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352447" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">vagina</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/vulvar-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20368051" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">vulva</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/anal-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20354140" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">anus</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/mens-health/in-depth/penis-health/art-20046175" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">penis</a>, and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/head-and-neck-cancers/symptoms-causes/syc-20354171" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">head and neck</a>. Getting vaccinated against HPV is your best protection against HPV infection and cervical cancer.</p>



<p>"You can receive the vaccine at age 9, and you may still get some protection if you get it up to age 45. With this vaccine, we're hoping to eradicate cervical cancer and other HPV-related cancers," says Dr. Butler.</p>



<p>The CDC<a>&nbsp;</a><a href="https://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/vpd/hpv/hcp/recommendations.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">recommends</a>&nbsp;the HPV vaccine for children aged 11 and those under age 26 who were not vaccinated. People younger than 15 can be vaccinated with two doses, six to 12 months apart. People who start the vaccine series later, after age 15, should get three vaccine doses over six months.</p>



<p><a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2022/03/02/dear-mayo-clinic-adults-up-to-age-45-and-at-risk-for-hpv-infection-can-get-vaccine/">Adults 27 to 45</a>&nbsp;who were not vaccinated should talk to their healthcare professional about the HPV vaccine. Dr. Butler says the vaccine can provide benefits even after you have been diagnosed with changes to cells in your cervix that make them more likely to develop into cancer or you have been exposed to HPV.</p>



<p>"The HPV vaccine is exciting because it gives us an opportunity to prevent cancer," says Dr. Butler. “We can reduce the risk of several cancers with this vaccine."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Tool No. 3: Start cervical cancer screening at age 21 and follow a schedule.</h2>



<p>"At Mayo Clinic, we recommend that cervical cancer screening start at age 21 and continue every three to five years, depending on the type of screening performed," says Dr. Butler. "At the time of screening, we do a thorough examination to evaluate multiple areas. We are looking at the vulva, the vagina, the urethral area and the anal area for anything unusual."</p>



<p>In addition to a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/pelvic-exam/about/pac-20385135" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pelvic exam</a>, your healthcare professional will conduct a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/pap-smear/about/pac-20394841" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pap smear</a>, which involves collecting cells from your cervix to detect any changes. Mayo Clinic recommends repeating Pap testing every three years for women ages 21 to 65.</p>



<p>Dr. Butler says you should continue screening following&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/menopause/symptoms-causes/syc-20353397" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">menopause</a>, particularly if you have any bleeding. "At 65, if you have had normal screening test results for quite some time, you can have a discussion with your healthcare professional about discontinuing," she says. "But we know that 16% of cervical cancer happens in women over the age of 65."</p>



<p>Women age 30 or older can consider Pap testing every five years if the procedure is combined with an&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/hpv-test/about/pac-20394355" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">HPV test</a>. Knowing whether you have a type of HPV that puts you at high risk of cervical cancer allows you and your care team to decide on the next steps, which may include monitoring or further testing.</p>



<p>Your healthcare professional may recommend a different screening schedule depending on your risk factors and history of screening results. "A patient may have high-risk factors that require more frequent screening. Examples include people with weakened immune systems or people with a history of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cervical-cancer/expert-answers/cervical-dysplasia/faq-20058142" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cervical dysplasia</a>," says Dr. Butler. "Following hysterectomy, most people no longer need cervical cancer screening. But if they have high-risk factors, they should speak to their doctor because they might need screening with a Pap smear that can be performed in the vaginal area since there is no longer a cervix."</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/GTvtELLCdss" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidGTvtELLCdss"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Cervical cancer screening" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/GTvtELLCdss?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Kristina Butler talks about cervical cancer in this Mayo Clinic Minute</figcaption></figure>



<p>If you've been diagnosed with cervical cancer, Dr. Butler says new&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cervical-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352506" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">treatments</a>&nbsp;are giving more people hope.</p>



<p>"For people with advanced and recurrent cervical cancer, we use chemotherapy and a targeted therapy drug called&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/bevacizumab" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bevacizumab</a>, which works by blocking a protein called VEGF," she says. "For some people whose cancer has markers for the protein PD-L1, we're able to use&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/pembrolizumab" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pembrolizumab</a>&nbsp;— an immunotherapy drug called an&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy/checkpoint-inhibitors" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">immune checkpoint inhibitor</a>." Pembrolizumab works by binding to the protein PD-1 on the surface of T cells (a type of immune cell). This prevents the cancer cells from weakening the immune system, which can then kill the cancer cells.</p>



<p>"The development of these additional drugs has absolutely improved outcomes," says Dr. Butler.</p>



<p><em>Story originated from the <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/01/16/your-toolkit-for-reducing-cervical-cancer-risk/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center blog</a>.</em></p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h4>



<ul>
<li>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-cervical-cancer-and-hpv-whats-the-connection/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cervical cancer and HPV — what’s the connection?</a>"</li>



<li>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-cervical-cancer-screening/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Cervical Cancer Screening</a></li>



<li>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-preventing-cancer-for-future-generations-of-black-families/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Preventing cancer for future generations of Black families</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/toolkit-for-reducing-cervical-cancer-risk/">Toolkit for reducing cervical cancer risk</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/a-medical-illustration-of-cervical-cancer-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/a-medical-illustration-of-cervical-cancer-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cervical Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Prostate cancer: screening and treatment options</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/prostate-cancer-screening-and-treatment/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 22:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Carlos Vargas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Prostate Specific Antigen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Proton Beam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Radiation Therapy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[screening]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=348086</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Prostate cancer is one of the most common cancers in the world. While many prostate cancers grow slowly and remain localized, other types are aggressive and spread quickly. That's why Dr. Carlos Vargas, a Mayo Clinic radiation oncologist, encourages regular screening. He says the goal of screening is to detect prostate cancer early, when it's [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/prostate-cancer-screening-and-treatment/">Prostate cancer: screening and treatment options</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/middle-aged-black-man-gazing-out-windowGettyImages-1171712738_16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="middle-aged man gazing out window" class="wp-image-343228" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/middle-aged-black-man-gazing-out-windowGettyImages-1171712738_16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/middle-aged-black-man-gazing-out-windowGettyImages-1171712738_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/middle-aged-black-man-gazing-out-windowGettyImages-1171712738_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/middle-aged-black-man-gazing-out-windowGettyImages-1171712738_16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/middle-aged-black-man-gazing-out-windowGettyImages-1171712738_16x9.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p></p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prostate-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353087?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Prostate cancer</a> is one of the most common cancers in the world. While many prostate cancers grow slowly and remain localized, other types are aggressive and spread quickly. That's why <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/vargas-carlos-e-m-d/bio-20123913?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Carlos Vargas</a>, a Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/radiation-oncology/sections/overview/ovc-20188591" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">radiation oncologist</a>, encourages regular <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/psa-test/in-depth/prostate-cancer/art-20048087">screening</a>. He says the goal of screening is to detect prostate cancer early, when it's still confined to the prostate gland and has the best chance for successful treatment.</p>



<p>"It's important to get adequate screening, and screening for prostate cancer is relatively simple. You can have a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/psa-test/about/pac-20384731?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">prostate-specific antigen, or PSA, test</a> with your primary care doctor once a year, and with this, you can tailor adequate procedures based on your age and other risk factors," says Dr. Vargas.</p>



<p>The prostate-specific antigen test is a blood test used to measure the amount of prostate-specific antigen in your blood. High levels may indicate the presence of cancer. Other conditions also may increase this level. It's important to discuss with your healthcare professional if the prostate-specific antigen test is right for you based on your personal risk level and age.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/EJKL5mjYHaU" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Carlos Vargas discusses prostate cancer screening and treatment.</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeEJKL5mjYHaU"  title="Dr. Carlos Vargas - Prostate cancer - Screening and treatment options" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EJKL5mjYHaU?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video is available in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy</strong>:<strong> Mayo Clinic News Network. Name super/CG: Carlos Vargas,  M.D/Radiation Oncology/Mayo Clinic</strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Who is at risk?</h2>



<p>Risk factors include age, family history and race. The most common age is around 50 or older.</p>



<p>If you have a blood relative who has or has had prostate cancer or a family history of genes that increase the risk of breast cancer — BRCA1 or BRCA2 — or a strong family history of breast cancer, your risk of prostate cancer may be higher. In the U.S., prostate cancer is deadlier for Black men than men of other races, according to the <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/cancer/prostate/prostate-cancer-health-tip-sheet.htm" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</a>. They are more likely to get prostate cancer and more than twice as likely to die from prostate cancer than other men.</p>



<p>"Early detection is very important. If we can find prostate cancer early, it is treatable and curable, " says Dr. Vargas.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Active surveillance</h2>



<p>Not all prostate cancers need to be treated, says Dr. Vargas. Some cancers can remain under <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/active-surveillance-for-prostate-cancer/about/pac-20384946?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">active surveillance</a>.</p>



<p>"When we find very early prostate cancer, we can watch it for many years. And in case that prostate cancer becomes more aggressive, then we can treat it there. The problem is when you are not screened, and then you find a very aggressive prostate cancer that is still localized or it has already metastasized, in which case, the chances of controlling the cancer, curing you and saving your life are much lower."</p>



<p>In active surveillance, regular follow-up tests may be performed to monitor the progression of your cancer.</p>



<p>"That's why screening is very important and why we encourage screening for prostate cancer. It doesn't mean that you must be treated. If prostate cancer is found, we can then determine what is the most appropriate course of action for your prostate cancer based on your age and your risk group."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="611" height="344" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/04/Prostate-cancer-16-x-9.png" alt="Medical illustration of normal prostate and cancerous prostate" class="wp-image-119143" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/04/Prostate-cancer-16-x-9.png 611w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/04/Prostate-cancer-16-x-9-300x169.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 611px) 100vw, 611px" /></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Treatment options</h2>



<p>Along with active surveillance, a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prostate-cancer/care-at-mayo-clinic/mac-20353097?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">full range</a> of treatments for prostate cancer is available, including radiation therapy; hormone therapy; cryosurgery; chemotherapy; and surgery, including robotic prostatectomy.</p>



<p><strong>"</strong>One of the things that has really changed over the last few years is the management of radiation with patients with metastatic prostate cancer," says Dr. Vargas. "We have found that many patients with metastatic prostate cancer still benefit from radiation to the prostate."</p>



<p>"And we have also found that many patients who have just a few sites of metastatic disease, meaning that the cancer is not widely spread, can also benefit from aggressive treatment where we do a combination of radiation therapy and systematic therapy to put you back in remission where disease cannot be found, and extend your life."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="700" height="394" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/Mayo-Clinic-Proton-Beam-treatment-room-16x9-1.jpg" alt="Mayo Clinic Proton Beam treatment room" class="wp-image-315559" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/Mayo-Clinic-Proton-Beam-treatment-room-16x9-1.jpg 700w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/Mayo-Clinic-Proton-Beam-treatment-room-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 700px) 100vw, 700px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><sub>A Mayo Clinic proton beam treatment room</sub></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Another radiation technique includes intensity-modulated <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/home/orc-20185488">proton b</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/home/orc-20185488?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">e</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/home/orc-20185488" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">am therapy</a> with pencil beam scanning. Dr. Vargas says proton therapy is effectively used to treat patients with prostate cancer.</p>



<p>"It's a very localized treatment that allows us to treat the prostate, localizing the treatment to the prostate, hoping to minimize significant adverse events that may happen from the treatment," says Dr. Vargas.</p>



<p>Talk with your healthcare professional to learn more about prostate cancer screening and if it's right for you.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Related posts:</strong></h3>



<ul>
<li>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-importance-of-exercise-for-men-with-prostate-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Importance of exercise for men with prostate cancer</a>."</li>



<li>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-new-prostate-biopsy-technique-reduces-infection-risk/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Prostate biopsy technique reduces infection risk</a>."</li>



<li>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-podcast-living-as-a-prostate-cancer-survivor/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A podcast: Living as a prostate cancer survivor</a>."</li>
</ul>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/prostate-cancer-screening-and-treatment/">Prostate cancer: screening and treatment options</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/PensiveMan1x1.jpeg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/PensiveMan16x9.jpeg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Carlos Vargas]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Prostate Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Prostate Specific Antigen]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Proton Beam]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Radiation Therapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[screening]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>FISH testing helps detect unseen cancer cells</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/fish-testing-helps-detect-unseen-cancer-cells/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[C.J. Bahnsen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2024 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Laboratories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[acute myeloid leukemia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Mithun Shah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Naseema Gangat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Shannon Camlek]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tim Camlek]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=380381</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>On the brink of losing her battle with acute myeloid leukemia, Shannon Camlek arrived at Mayo Clinic as a last hope. Her chances didn’t look good, but with the help of specialized genetic testing, particularly FISH (fluorescence in situ hybridization) studies, doctors were able to detect the specific gene mutations responsible for her symptoms and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/fish-testing-helps-detect-unseen-cancer-cells/">FISH testing helps detect unseen cancer cells</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Tim-Shannon-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-380390" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Tim-Shannon-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Tim-Shannon-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Tim-Shannon-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Tim-Shannon-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Tim-Shannon-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h5 class="wp-block-heading"><em>On the brink of losing her battle with acute myeloid leukemia, Shannon Camlek arrived at Mayo Clinic as a last hope. Her chances didn’t look good, but with the help of specialized genetic testing, particularly FISH (fluorescence in situ hybridization) studies, doctors were able to detect the specific gene mutations responsible for her symptoms and disease. The test results also helped Shannon’s care team target her treatment accordingly, and finally put an end to what Shannon likens as starring in her own personal horror movie while in search of hope and healing.</em></h5>



<p>"Her white blood cell count was very high and there were all these leukemia cells (blasts) in her blood." This is how&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/gangat-naseema-m-b-b-s/bio-20055150" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Naseema Gangat, M.B.B.S.</a>, a consultant in Mayo Clinic’s Division of Hematology, describes patient Shannon Camlek’s condition when she first arrived at Mayo Clinic’s Rochester campus. It was April of 2018, and Shannon had been diagnosed with acute myeloid leukemia (AML). Her condition had deteriorated so dramatically that Shannon’s care team at Sacred Heart Hospital in Eau Claire, Wisconsin, urged her to come to Mayo Clinic as a last-ditch effort to extend her life.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="264" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr_Gangat_and_Shannon-264x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-380392" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr_Gangat_and_Shannon-264x300.jpg 264w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr_Gangat_and_Shannon-901x1024.jpg 901w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr_Gangat_and_Shannon-768x873.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr_Gangat_and_Shannon-1352x1536.jpg 1352w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr_Gangat_and_Shannon.jpg 1671w" sizes="(max-width: 264px) 100vw, 264px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Gangat and Shannon</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>To determine the appropriate treatment for Shannon, Dr. Gangat ordered a second bone marrow biopsy, posthaste, after the first one was lost in transit from Sacred Heart. "I was not in good shape," says Shannon, 55, who resides in Fall Creek, Wisconsin, with her husband Tim. "My platelets were down, my white blood cell count up. I was in what they call ‘blast crisis,’ and the genetic tests from the bone marrow sample held the answers to my treatment plan. So, getting those results was a matter of life and death."</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>DR. GANGAT ADDS, “WE NEEDED THE BONE MARROW RESULTS TO ACCURATELY PROGNOSTICATE OR RISK-CLASSIFY THE DISEASE. IN SHANNON’S CASE, THE CHROMOSOME TESTS WERE NORMAL, BUT HER FISH STUDY, WHICH IS ANOTHER GENETIC TEST, REVEALED AN ABNORMALITY WITH THREE COPIES OF THIS GENE CALLED KAT6A, AND MUTATION ANALYSIS HAD THE FLT3-ITD MUTATION.”</p>
</blockquote>



<p>The FISH (fluorescence in situ hybridization) study is a highly sensitive test done in Mayo Clinic’s Genomics Laboratory. The test performed on Shannon ran 16 different probe sets, including the gene region KAT6A, which is how the third copy of the mutation was discovered (the norm is two copies).</p>



<p>The FLT3-ITD mutation put Shannon’s leukemia in the high-risk category, which meant a stem cell transplant was her only viable treatment option. The presence of the FLT3-ITD mutation also provided the opportunity to use FLT3-directed medications. Foremost, given Shannon’s presentation with "blast crisis," Dr. Gangat ordered a&nbsp;<a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/treatments/22926-leukapheresis">leukapheresis</a>, a procedure to remove white blood cells and help prevent organ damage. Shannon was then moved into an induction chemotherapy program consisting of cytarabine (7) + daunorubicin (3) plus.</p>



<p>"We performed disease assessment about a month after treatment was started," Dr. Gangat says. "And there still were about 4% of leukemia cells remaining, which we call ‘persistent AML.’ So, we did another round of the same treatment to enable the eradication of all leukemia cells. The stem cell transplant doesn't work as well if you go into it when disease is still present, because it means you are more likely to relapse."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A horror movie that won’t end</strong></h2>



<p>The second round of chemo meant even more risk to Shannon’s chances of survival. "I got real sick in that second round," she says. "I ended up in ICU with a lung hemorrhage. I got so bad we made plans for a funeral. I mean, it was like a horror movie. I look back and I think, ‘Was all this a dream? Did I really go through that and make it out the other side?’"&nbsp;</p>



<p>Once Shannon recovered from the second round of chemo and the ensuing complications, a donor was sought for her stem cell transplant. Siblings are often ideal candidates because there is a higher chance of matching more of the human leukocyte antigen (HLA) antigens — there are over 100 different types of these special white blood cells, which are part of the genetic makeup in each person’s immune system. A higher match of these antigens makes for a better engraftment of the donated bone marrow. Fortunately for Shannon, testing reveled her brother Pat to be a perfect match.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="225" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Shannon_and_Dr._Shah_-1-225x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-380402" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Shannon_and_Dr._Shah_-1-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Shannon_and_Dr._Shah_-1-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Shannon_and_Dr._Shah_-1-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Shannon_and_Dr._Shah_-1-1536x2048.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Shannon and Dr. Shah</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>For this phase of her treatment, Shannon came under the care of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/shah-mithun-v-m-d-ph-d/bio-20436105">Mithun Shah, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, a hematologist and consultant in Mayo’s Division of Hematology. A big fear for Dr. Shah was that Shannon might have recurrent bleeding in her lungs during the transplant procedure. To prepare for that possibility, he and his team had to make sure there was a source of donated blood ready if needed — and not just any blood, but HLA antibody platelets. "That makes it very difficult for us to just randomly select donors for these specific platelets," Dr. Shah says. "So, we had to talk to the transfusion team and make sure we had planned donors who would be ready to come in and donate on short notice."&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>In August of 2018, Shannon underwent a stem cell transplant at Mayo Clinic. It was a complete success. "We had to use very minimal transfusion support, which is quite remarkable and very rarely seen in transplant," Dr. Shah says. "And then, post-transplant, her counts recovered well, and Shannon came through it like a champ."&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A relapse doesn’t always mean "game over</strong>"</h2>



<p>Even so, about nine months after her transplant, Shannon relapsed. And this is where Mayo’s specialized FISH testing, again, helped inform and guide the next stage of her treatment.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>"WE DID A BONE MARROW BIOPSY, NOT EXPECTING ANY PROBLEMS TO BE THERE," DR. SHAH SAYS. "BUT THEN WHEN WE RAN A MORE SPECIALIZED FLUORESCENCE IN SITU HYBRIDIZATION TEST, WE WERE ABLE TO SEE THAT LEUKEMIA CELLS HAD COME BACK. AND THAT WAS A UNIQUE PART OF HER STORY BECAUSE, USUALLY, WE DON'T HAVE TO RUN FISH TESTS FOR LEUKEMIA PATIENTS OVER AND OVER AGAIN. WE ARE USUALLY IN THE CYTOGENETICS LAB, AND THAT’S WHERE WE STOP. BUT IN SHANNON’S CASE, WE WENT FOR THE FISH STUDY WHERE THEY FOUND RELAPSE SOLELY BASED ON THAT TEST, MEANING HER LEUKEMIA WAS COMING BACK AT A VERY, VERY LOW LEVEL. SO THAT AGAIN INFORMED OUR DECISION TO COME DOWN ON IMMUNOSUPPRESSIVE MEDICATION."</p>
</blockquote>



<p>In accordance to the results of her testing, Shannon was put on targeted medication to address the leukemia cells that had returned to her body. After two years, however, she was able to discontinue the meds and has been in remission ever since. "I've been in remission for four years," she says. "My husband has been my rock through it all."</p>



<p>Both Shannon and Tim do not take lightly the role that the Genomics Lab and other labs at Mayo Clinic played in her treatment.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>&nbsp;"THE PEOPLE DOING THE TESTING IN THE LABS HAVE ALWAYS BEEN AT THE HEART OF MY CARE," SHE SAYS. "IT STARTS WITH THEM. WE WERE AMAZED BY THE WORK THEY DO, AND WHAT HAPPENS BECAUSE OF THE WORK THEY DO. THE DOCTORS GET ALL THE GLORY AND THE PAIN. BUT WE SAW FIRSTHAND THAT IT’S WHAT HAPPENS AT THE CELLULAR LEVEL THAT REALLY DRIVES THIS ORGANIZATION AND PATIENT CARE."</p>
</blockquote>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="861" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr_Shah_Tim_and_Shannon-861x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-380393" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr_Shah_Tim_and_Shannon-861x1024.jpg 861w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr_Shah_Tim_and_Shannon-252x300.jpg 252w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr_Shah_Tim_and_Shannon-768x914.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr_Shah_Tim_and_Shannon-1291x1536.jpg 1291w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr_Shah_Tim_and_Shannon-1721x2048.jpg 1721w" sizes="(max-width: 861px) 100vw, 861px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Shah, Shannon and Tim</figcaption></figure>



<p>Tim shares his wife’s appreciation for Mayo Clinic’s lab staff. "I’m a sixth-grade science teacher, and I was amazed by the amount of elementary, middle, and high school science that goes on inside a workplace like Mayo Clinic," he says. "And a theme that comes through in our narrative is those connections between the lab people, from a microscope and cellular level, on up to the doctors, and how that all works together. It’s changed how we look at medicine."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The lesser-known “cost” of long-term cancer treatment</strong></h2>



<p>In all, Shannon and Tim ended up shuttling from Wisconsin to Rochester for eight months to get through all her treatments and follow-ups. For five of those months, they needed to live on Mayo’s campus in downtown Rochester, but Shannon’s insurance didn’t cover the additional expense of housing. And because of her medical issues, she had to give up her beloved 28-year career as a schoolteacher (third and sixth grades). The financial strain caused additional stress they didn’t need during that time.</p>



<p>Because Shannon doesn’t want other cancer patients to have to go through the financial headaches and worries her family did over patient housing, she and a friend cofounded&nbsp;<a href="https://home4healing.org/#/">Home 4 Healing</a>, an organization that helps make housing more affordable and accessible for patients whose treatment necessitates extended stays near the Mayo Clinic campus.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Dr. Gangat has been a key inspiration in helping me start Home 4 Healing," Shannon says. "She actually said to me, ‘We need this. We need to be able to offer people a place to go when we tell them they have to be here for long periods of time.’"</p>



<p>Shannon, meanwhile, remains under the care of Dr. Shah, who is optimistic about her future. "We try not to use the word ‘cure’ for leukemia," he says. "But every time I meet with Shannon, I tell her the chances of the leukemia coming back get smaller and smaller the longer she’s in remission. So, for all practical purposes, we hope, and we think, that she may be cured."</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://news.mayocliniclabs.com/2024/01/08/fish-testing-helps-detect-unseen-cancer-cells-shannon-camlek/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Laboratories blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/fish-testing-helps-detect-unseen-cancer-cells/">FISH testing helps detect unseen cancer cells</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Tim-Shannon-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Tim-Shannon-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[acute myeloid leukemia]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Mithun Shah]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Naseema Gangat]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Laboratories]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Shannon Camlek]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Tim Camlek]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Advancing pancreatic cancer treatment with total robotic Whipple surgery</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-advancing-pancreatic-cancer-treatment-with-total-robotic-whipple-surgery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Zhi Fong]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pancreatic Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whipple Procedure]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=378750</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>New technologies are improving pancreatic cancer treatment, offering hope to patients facing one of the least survivable forms of cancer. The Whipple procedure, a complex surgery for localized pancreatic cancer, can now be done robotically.&#160;&#160; Dr.&#160;Zhi Ven Fong, a Mayo Clinic surgical oncologist, says innovations in technology allow surgeons to do this highly complex operation [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-advancing-pancreatic-cancer-treatment-with-total-robotic-whipple-surgery/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Advancing pancreatic cancer treatment with total robotic Whipple surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>New technologies are improving <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/long-term-pancreatic-cancer-survivors-report-excellent-post-surgery-quality-of-life/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pancreatic cancer treatment</a>, offering hope to patients facing one of the least survivable forms of cancer. The <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/whipple-procedure/about/pac-20385054">Whipple procedure</a>, a complex surgery for localized pancreatic cancer, can now be done robotically.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/fong-zhi-m-d/bio-20555871" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr.&nbsp;Zhi Ven Fong</a>, a Mayo Clinic surgical oncologist, says innovations in technology allow surgeons to do this highly complex operation in a minimally invasive way. And that helps the patient.  Dr. Fong explains what happens during a total robotic Whipple procedure.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/4NuFnrsZyZ4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutube4NuFnrsZyZ4"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Advancing pancreatic cancer treatment with total robotic Whipple surgery" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4NuFnrsZyZ4?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:09) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Script-MCM-Robotic-Whipple-procedure_78.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script.</a></strong></p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>The Whipple procedure involves removing the head of the pancreas, part of the small intestine, gall bladder and bile duct.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="903" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Whipple-Procedure-image-1024x903.jpg" alt="Before a Whipple operation. Areas shown in gray typically will be removed. Right: After reconstruction is done during a Whipple operation." class="wp-image-379877" style="width:428px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Whipple-Procedure-image-1024x903.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Whipple-Procedure-image-300x264.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Whipple-Procedure-image-768x677.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Whipple-Procedure-image.jpg 1276w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p>"With the robotic approach, we believe that the incisions are smaller, the recoveries quicker and less pain," says Dr. Fong.</p>



<p>During surgery, Dr. Fong looks into a 3D camera while guiding the robot from a console.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Fong-robot-surgery-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Dr. Zhi Fong, total robotic Whipple surgery" class="wp-image-380040" style="width:820px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Fong-robot-surgery-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Fong-robot-surgery-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Fong-robot-surgery-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Fong-robot-surgery-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Fong-robot-surgery-16x9-1.jpg 1946w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Zhi Fong guides the robot's arms during a total robotic Whipple surgery</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"It provides me a three-dimensional image of the actual patient's abdomen through the camera," he says.</p>



<p>Dr. Fong can then control the robotic arms that perform the intricate procedure.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Fong-Hands-Operating-Robot-1024x683.jpg" alt="Dr. Zhi Fong closeup up total robotic Whipple surgery" class="wp-image-380070" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Fong-Hands-Operating-Robot-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Fong-Hands-Operating-Robot-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Fong-Hands-Operating-Robot-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Fong-Hands-Operating-Robot-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Fong-Hands-Operating-Robot.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Closeup of Dr. Zhi Fong's hands during a total robotic Whipple surgery</figcaption></figure>



<p>The robotic surgery may take longer than traditional surgery, but it offers additional advantages including shorter length of stay and less long-term wound complications.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr-Nabil-Wasif-Total-Whipple-Surgery-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Dr Nabil Wasif in surgery, Total Robotic Whipple Surgery" class="wp-image-380039" style="width:820px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr-Nabil-Wasif-Total-Whipple-Surgery-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr-Nabil-Wasif-Total-Whipple-Surgery-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr-Nabil-Wasif-Total-Whipple-Surgery-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr-Nabil-Wasif-Total-Whipple-Surgery-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr-Nabil-Wasif-Total-Whipple-Surgery-16x9-1.jpg 1946w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr Nabil Wasif works in tandem with Dr. Zhi Fong during total robotic Whipple surgery</figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Candidate for robotic Whipple surgery</h3>



<p>The best candidate for the surgery depends on the person and the cancer.</p>



<p>"Typically, patients have a lower BMI and the pancreatic cancers that don't involve the main visceral vessels that passes through the pancreas," says Dr. Fong.</p>



<p>If you have been diagnosed with pancreatic cancer, your healthcare team will talk with you about treatment options. </p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">More about pancreatic cancer</h3>



<p>Pancreatic cancer usually doesn't show symptoms until it's advanced. </p>



<p>Treatment options for pancreatic cancer depend on the type, stage, and other factors and may include surgery, radiation, chemotherapy or a combination of these.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/researchers-make-unexpected-discovery-in-how-pancreatic-cancer-spreads/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Researchers make unexpected discovery in how pancreatic cancer spreads</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-innovation-inspires-hope-in-early-detection-of-pancreatic-cancer/">Mayo Clinic’s AI innovation inspires hope in early detection of pancreatic cancer</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-advancing-pancreatic-cancer-treatment-with-total-robotic-whipple-surgery/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Advancing pancreatic cancer treatment with total robotic Whipple surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Robot-Arms-and-Dr.-Wasif-surgery-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Robot-Arms-and-Dr.-Wasif-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Zhi Fong]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Pancreatic Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Whipple Procedure]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss><!-- Static page delivered by HubScale -->