<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Cancer - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cancer/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 16:20:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.4</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Advances in medulloblastoma treatment for children</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advances-in-medulloblastoma-treatment-for-children/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nicole Ferrara]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jonathan Schwartz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medulloblastoma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=388616</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>By Nicole Brudos Ferrara Though rare, medulloblastoma is the most common cancerous brain tumor in children. These tumors begin in the lower back part of the brain called the&#160;cerebellum, which is important for balance, coordination and movement. Medulloblastomas are&#160;embryonal tumors&#160;that grow from embryonal cells left over from fetal development. "Of all the tumors we see [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advances-in-medulloblastoma-treatment-for-children/">Advances in medulloblastoma treatment for children</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="938" height="528" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Medulloblastoma-GettyImages-1214951851-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-388617" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Medulloblastoma-GettyImages-1214951851-16x9-1.jpg 938w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Medulloblastoma-GettyImages-1214951851-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Medulloblastoma-GettyImages-1214951851-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 938px) 100vw, 938px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<p><em>By Nicole Brudos Ferrara</em></p>



<p>Though rare, medulloblastoma is the most common cancerous brain tumor in children. These tumors begin in the lower back part of the brain called the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/ataxia/multimedia/cerebellum-and-brainstem/img-20007645" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cerebellum</a>, which is important for balance, coordination and movement. Medulloblastomas are&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/embryonal-tumor/cdc-20367985" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">embryonal tumors</a>&nbsp;that grow from embryonal cells left over from fetal development.</p>



<p>"Of all the tumors we see in pediatrics, 20% are medulloblastoma," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/schwartz-jonathan-d-d-o-m-p-h/bio-20471630" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jonathan Schwartz, D.O.</a>, a Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center pediatric neuro-oncologist. About&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.net/cancer-types/medulloblastoma-childhood/statistics" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">500 children</a>&nbsp;in the U.S. are diagnosed with medulloblastoma each year. "The peak age is between 5 and 7 years of age, and it's slightly more common in males," he says.</p>



<p>Medulloblastomas are fast-growing, aggressive tumors, but Dr. Schwartz says a better understanding of their biology, new drugs, technology and treatment techniques have improved <a href="https://braintumourresearch.org/en-us/blogs/faq/what-is-the-life-expectancy-of-a-child-with-medulloblastoma#:~:text=Average%205%2Dyear%20survival%20rate,5%20years%20after%20their%20diagnosis." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">outcomes for children</a>.</p>



<p>Dr. Schwartz explains how medulloblastoma is treated, the latest treatment advances and what families should look for in a care team:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How is medulloblastoma treated in children?</h2>



<p>Medulloblastoma treatment depends on tumor type and your child's age. "Treatment usually involves safely removing as much of the tumor as possible, followed by radiation therapy and chemotherapy," says Dr. Schwartz.</p>



<p>In children younger than 4, Dr. Schwartz says care teams use radiation-sparing techniques, which reduce damage to healthy tissue, and high doses of chemotherapy followed by stem cell transplant (<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bone-marrow-transplant/about/pac-20384854" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bone marrow transplant</a>). In children older than 4, treatment also depends on whether the tumor is average or high risk.</p>



<p>Medulloblastoma is considered average risk if it has not spread to other parts of the body and can be completely or almost completely removed with surgery. If the tumor has spread to other parts of the brain, spinal cord or body and cannot be completely removed with surgery, it is high risk. "If you leave more than 1.5 cubic centimeters of residual disease, we call that high risk. If it's metastatic and has spread anywhere else, it's high risk," says Dr. Schwartz.</p>



<p>Medulloblastoma spreads through the fluid surrounding and protecting the brain and spinal cord. "The spinal cord is like the top of a waterfall," says Dr. Schwartz. "If tumor cells circulate, they could go anywhere around the brain or spine. We always look at the full brain and spine when imaging during treatment and follow-up because the tumor cells can drop and sit at the bottom of the spinal cord. We deliver chemotherapy and radiation to the whole brain and spine to reduce the likelihood of recurrence."</p>



<p>If medulloblastoma recurs, Dr. Schwartz says care teams turn to other aggressive treatments, including chemotherapy and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">clinical trials</a>&nbsp;for vaccines,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/car-t-cell-therapy-program/sections/overview/ovc-20404319" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chimeric antigen receptor (CAR)-T cell therapy</a>, and other viral therapies. "It's an aggressive disease. That's why we treat it aggressively. If medulloblastoma recurs, we know treatment is generally not curative," he says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" width="632" height="510" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Medulloblastoma-illustration-1710635_3802786-003-0-72ppi.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-388619" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Medulloblastoma-illustration-1710635_3802786-003-0-72ppi.jpg 632w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Medulloblastoma-illustration-1710635_3802786-003-0-72ppi-300x242.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 632px) 100vw, 632px" /></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What are the latest advances in medulloblastoma treatment?</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Medulloblastomas are now diagnosed using molecular analysis.</h3>



<p>"The world of neuro-oncology has changed dramatically — in a positive way — in 15 years," says Dr. Schwartz. He says one of the biggest medulloblastoma treatment advances is the shift from diagnosing medulloblastoma based on tissue examination under a microscope (histologic diagnosis) to analysis of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/def/molecular-diagnostics" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">molecules</a>, such as DNA, RNA and proteins, from a tissue or fluid sample (molecular diagnosis).</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>"The world of neuro-oncology has changed dramatically — in a positive way — in 15 years."DR. JONATHAN SCHWARTZ</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Based on molecular diagnostic tests, medulloblastoma tumors are now categorized into four subgroups, and healthcare professionals understand that each requires a different treatment approach. "We now know that you shouldn't treat them all the same. We know that the five-year overall survival for&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/rare-brain-spine-tumor/tumors/medulloblastoma" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">WNT-activated medulloblastoma</a>&nbsp;is 100%. Other subgroups have lower survival or are likely to recur," says Dr. Schwartz.</p>



<p>Understanding these differences between medulloblastoma tumors has helped care teams tailor treatment plans for each child and their tumor type and improve survival and quality of life.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Researchers are studying radiation and chemotherapy dose reduction.</h3>



<p>Dr. Schwartz is conducting a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials/cls-20403517" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">clinical trial</a>&nbsp;to study whether reduced doses of radiation therapy and chemotherapy can effectively treat patients with newly diagnosed medulloblastoma tumors in WNT-driven medulloblastoma, the least aggressive tumor subgroup. "If someone has 100% chance of survival, can we de-escalate the therapy? That's the question we're asking in a clinical trial through the Children's Oncology Group," he says.</p>



<p>"Recent studies have shown radiation and chemotherapy to be effective in treating patients with WNT medulloblastoma, but we're concerned about the late effects of treatment, which can include learning difficulties, reduced amounts of hormones and other problems," says Dr. Schwartz.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/in-depth/cancer-survivor/art-20045524" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Late effects</a>&nbsp;of cancer treatment appear after treatment ends. Children who undergo cancer treatment may be at risk for more late effects than adults because their bones, tissues and organs grow quickly, and cancer treatment can interfere with that growth.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Protection against chemotherapy-related hearing loss.</h3>



<p>Cisplatin, a chemotherapy drug effective in treating medulloblastoma, is associated with hearing loss.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/news-events/cancer-currents-blog/2018/cisplatin-hearing-loss" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Research</a>&nbsp;has shown this may be due to the drug's accumulation in the inner ear. "Most patients who had cisplatin to treat medulloblastoma wear hearing aids," says Dr. Schwartz.</p>



<p>Care teams now have a tool to protect children with medulloblastoma from chemotherapy-related hearing loss. In 2022, the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/resources-information-approved-drugs/fda-approves-sodium-thiosulfate-reduce-risk-ototoxicity-associated-cisplatin-pediatric-patients" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">FDA approved</a>&nbsp;the use of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements/sodium-thiosulfate-intravenous-route/side-effects/drg-20066076?p=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">sodium thiosulfate</a>&nbsp;to reduce the risk of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements/cisplatin-intravenous-route/description/drg-20062953" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cisplatin</a>-associated hearing loss in children one month and older who have solid tumors that have not spread. Sodium thiosulfate is given to patients as an IV infusion following cisplatin infusion.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What should families look for in a medulloblastoma care team?</h2>



<p>Dr. Schwartz says families should seek care from healthcare professionals who can offer a comprehensive team approach and the latest technology. He says a team of brain tumor specialists who have cared for a high volume of children with medulloblastoma can offer the best possible diagnosis, care and outcomes.</p>



<p>"We have a team approach at Mayo Clinic. We start with oncology, neurology, neurosurgery, social work and radiology. Because we have a high volume of tumor patients, we're experts at seeing the right, the wrong, the middle, and the weird complications and tumors with atypical neuropathology. We have excellent neuropathologists. Their work is critical to getting the right diagnosis so we know how to treat the tumor appropriately. You need a skilled neurosurgeon who knows how to operate on these tumors and give kids the best chance at survival."</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>"You need a skilled neurosurgeon who knows how to operate on these tumors and give kids the best chance at survival."DR. JONATHAN SCHWARTZ</p>
</blockquote>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/sections/overview/ovc-20185491" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Proton beam therapy</a>, which delivers precise radiotherapy with lower doses of radiation to healthy tissue, is also important for children whose organs are still developing, says Dr. Schwartz. "With proton radiation, we can outline exactly where to treat. And that energy goes to that area and drops off — virtually none goes beyond the tumor. With&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/radiation-therapy/about/pac-20385162#:~:text=Radiation%20therapy%2C%20also%20called%20radiotherapy,therapy%20exist%2C%20including%20proton%20radiation." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">traditional X-ray radiation</a>&nbsp;in young children, there's radiation scatter, so you're radiating the heart, lungs, liver, diaphragm, kidneys, abdominal organs and other critical brain areas," he says.</p>



<p>If your child has been diagnosed with medulloblastoma, Dr. Schwartz wants you to know there is hope and help available. "There's always hope until there isn't. The question is: How do we give this family the best possible journey? How do we best take care of these patients?"</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Learn more</h2>



<p>Learn more about&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/medulloblastoma/cdc-20363524" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">medulloblastoma</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">find a clinical trial</a>&nbsp;at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>Join the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/brain-tumor-support-group/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Brain Tumor Support Group</a>&nbsp;or the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/caregivers/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Caregivers Support Group</a>&nbsp;on&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Connect</a>, an online community moderated by Mayo Clinic for patients and caregivers.</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/05/29/advances-in-medulloblastoma-treatment-for-children/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advances-in-medulloblastoma-treatment-for-children/">Advances in medulloblastoma treatment for children</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Medulloblastoma-GettyImages-1214951851-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Medulloblastoma-GettyImages-1214951851-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jonathan Schwartz]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[medulloblastoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lymphedema: A lesser-known breast cancer treatment side effect with lifelong impacts</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/lymphedema-a-little-known-breast-cancer-treatment-side-effect-with-lifelong-impacts/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[DeeDee Stiepan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2024 13:29:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=388850</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The journey of a cancer survivor often extends far beyond the triumphant ringing of a brass bell, signaling the end of treatment. Sonya Goins received treatment at Mayo Clinic for HER-2-positive breast cancer in 2020. Since sharing her story of survival with the Mayo Clinic News Network, a lot has changed in Sonya's life. She [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/lymphedema-a-little-known-breast-cancer-treatment-side-effect-with-lifelong-impacts/">Lymphedema: A lesser-known breast cancer treatment side effect with lifelong impacts</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The journey of a cancer survivor often extends far beyond the triumphant ringing of a brass bell, signaling the end of treatment. Sonya Goins received treatment at Mayo Clinic for HER-2-positive breast cancer in 2020. Since sharing her <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/dancing-through-complex-care-during-covid-19/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">story of survival</a> with the Mayo Clinic News Network, a lot has changed in Sonya's life. She became a Mayo Clinic employee, working in the Communications Department. She also continues to confront post-cancer health challenges, including being diagnosed with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lymphedema/symptoms-causes/syc-20374682" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymphedema</a>. &nbsp;</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/Hv8Qp6az4mE" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Lymphedema: A lesser-known breast cancer side effect with lifelong impacts</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe id="videoidhttpsyoutubeHv8Qp6az4mE"  title="Lymphedema: A lesser-known breast cancer treatment side effect with lifelong impacts" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Hv8Qp6az4mE?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (2:39) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/SCRIPT-Patient-Story-Lymphedema-PKG-script-FINAL.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"I thought once I rang that bell, it was over. But it wasn't over," says Sonya.</p>



<p>A few months after completing targeted radiation treatment for breast cancer, Sonya noticed swelling in her lower arm.</p>



<p>"I wasn't sure what it was. And they told me, 'Hey, you need to come into the emergency room. It might be an infection.' And (I) went to the emergency room, and they're like, 'No, it's lymphedema,'" says Sonya.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Sonya-Goins-bell-ringing-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Sonya Goins rings bell after completing treatment for breast cancer" class="wp-image-388907" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Sonya-Goins-bell-ringing-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Sonya-Goins-bell-ringing-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Sonya-Goins-bell-ringing-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Sonya-Goins-bell-ringing-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Sonya-Goins-bell-ringing-16-x-9.jpg 1824w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Sonya Goins rings the bell after completing treatment for breast cancer</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Lymphedema is a chronic and debilitating disease in which tissue swelling is caused by an accumulation of fluid that's usually drained through the lymphatic system.</p>



<p>About 40% of people who undergo breast cancer surgery where their lymph nodes are removed will develop lymphedema.</p>



<p>"It was painful. It was hard to sleep because it just felt like my arm was thumping all the time. I noticed, particularly at the end of the day, like, I typed a lot for my job. And I noticed my arm at the end of the day would swell up," says Sonya.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized is-style-center-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Lymphedema-hands-patient-16-x-9-1024x576.png" alt="Patient with lymphedema after breast cancer" class="wp-image-388888" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Lymphedema-hands-patient-16-x-9-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Lymphedema-hands-patient-16-x-9-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Lymphedema-hands-patient-16-x-9-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Lymphedema-hands-patient-16-x-9-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Lymphedema-hands-patient-16-x-9.png 1824w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Sonya Goins experienced lymphedema after breast cancer treatment</figcaption></figure>



<p>"To be honest with you, it was a little disheartening because I thought, 'Hey, this is over because, you know, you got the cancer. The cancer is gone, but now you have to live with the aftereffects.'"</p>



<p>But she didn't have to live with it. Sonya did some research and reached out to her Mayo Clinic care team. She found out about a surgery to help patients with lymphedema.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Dr-marks-arm-prior-to-surgery-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Patient with lymphedema after breast cancer treatment, arms marked prior to surgery" class="wp-image-388881" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Dr-marks-arm-prior-to-surgery-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Dr-marks-arm-prior-to-surgery-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Dr-marks-arm-prior-to-surgery-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Dr-marks-arm-prior-to-surgery-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Dr-marks-arm-prior-to-surgery-16-x-9.jpg 1824w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Being prepped for surgery</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"When I met Sonya, she already had stage 2 disease," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/fahradyan-vahe-m-d/bio-20521873" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Vahe Fahradyan</a>, a Mayo Clinic plastic surgeon who specializes in breast reconstruction and lymphatic reconstruction. "In her particular case, because she had some remaining functional lymphatic vessels, we decided that we're going be able to do lymphovenous bypass surgery."&nbsp;</p>



<p>Using special dye to identify the lymphatic pathways, surgeons use small incisions to reroute the lymphatic system by connecting tiny lymphatic vessels to tiny veins, creating a detour around the damaged part of the lymphatic system. This new connection restores the body's ability to drain lymphatic fluids.</p>



<p>While lymphedema is considered an incurable disease, getting outcomes like Sonya's, where patients can easily manage the symptoms and improve their quality of life, is the ultimate goal.</p>



<p>"My symptoms are so minimal, says Sonya. "I've gotten back to working out, and I'm able to swing kettlebells, which I couldn't do before. And my arm does not swell up at the end of the day. So that's amazing to be able to sleep and sleep better, and there's no more pain."</p>



<p>Dr. Fahradyan says one major key to achieving that is early diagnosis.</p>



<p>"The message is that if you notice that you have arm swelling or breast swelling or the lower extremities, it is not normal. You don't have to live like this," he says.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/lymphedema-a-little-known-breast-cancer-treatment-side-effect-with-lifelong-impacts/">Lymphedema: A lesser-known breast cancer treatment side effect with lifelong impacts</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Lymphedema-hands-patient-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Lymphedema-hands-patient-16-x-9.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic video stories earn Telly Awards</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-video-stories-earn-telly-awards/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Barber Lindquist]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 13:53:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=388964</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Two Mayo Clinic video stories related to World War II earned global recognition from the 45th annual Telly Awards honoring outstanding video and television projects. A patient story published on the Mayo Clinic News Network, "A veteran's journey from Holocaust to hope at Mayo Clinic," received a Silver Telly Award in the category of Television, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-video-stories-earn-telly-awards/">Mayo Clinic video stories earn Telly Awards</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.tellyawards.com/winners/2024/television/general-biography/a-veteran’s-journey-from-holocaust-to-hope-at-mayo-clinic/315598" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Telly-Awards-Images-1920x1080-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Image includes Telly Awards logo and images from two WWII video stories" class="wp-image-388971" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Telly-Awards-Images-1920x1080-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Telly-Awards-Images-1920x1080-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Telly-Awards-Images-1920x1080-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Telly-Awards-Images-1920x1080-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Telly-Awards-Images-1920x1080-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<p>Two Mayo Clinic video stories related to World War II earned global recognition from the 45<sup>th</sup> annual <a href="https://www.tellyawards.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Telly Awards</a> honoring outstanding video and television projects.</p>



<p>A patient story published on the Mayo Clinic News Network, "<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-veterans-journey-from-holocaust-to-hope-at-mayo-clinic/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">A veteran's journey from Holocaust to hope at Mayo Clinic</a>," received a Silver Telly Award in the category of <a href="https://www.tellyawards.com/winners/2024/television/general-biography" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Television, General, Biography</a>.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic's Jason Howland, reporter; Kevin Sullivan, videographer; Tammy Goemaat, producer; and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/kwon-eugene-d-m-d/bio-20054440" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Eugene Kwon, M.D.</a>, urologist and supervising physician, were recognized for their work. They shared the story of an 80-year-old Holocaust survivor, retired Green Beret of the <a>U.S</a>. Army Special Forces, and prostate cancer survivor who volunteers at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>"We are proud to be recognized for this beautiful story of hope and resilience, representing Mayo Clinic values of compassion and healing," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/gazelka-halena-m-m-d/bio-20055416" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Halena Gazelka, M.D.</a>, medical director for Mayo Clinic Communications.</p>



<p>Watch online via the Mayo Clinic News Network website, <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org</a>.</p>



<p>"<a href="https://history.mayoclinic.org/books-films/heritage-films/rising-to-the-challenge-the-mayo-aero-medical-unit-in-world-war-ii/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Rising to the Challenge: The Mayo Aero Medical Unit in World War II</a>" earned a Gold Telly Award in the category of <a href="https://www.tellyawards.com/winners/2024/non-broadcast/general-history" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Non-Broadcast, General, History</a> and a Silver Telly Award for <a href="https://www.tellyawards.com/winners/2024/non-broadcast/craft-use-of-archival-footage" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Non-Broadcast, Craft, Use of Archival Footage</a>.</p>



<p>The Mayo Clinic Heritage Film tells the story of Mayo's innovative work to protect WWII pilots from the deadly effects of high altitude and g-force. In the process, the Mayo team opened new horizons for human flight.</p>



<p>Heritage Films are produced by Mayo Clinic Media Support Services and the Mayo Clinic Heritage Program with the collaboration of internal and external specialists. The film is made possible with leadership support from John T. and Lillian G. Mathews, founding benefactors of Mayo Clinic Heritage Hall.</p>



<p>&nbsp;"The Mayo Aero Medical Unit is a classic example of Mayo's value of teamwork — physicians, scientists and allied health professionals coming together under wartime conditions to serve the nation and advance medical science in protecting humans in challenging environments," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/stepanek-jan-m-d-m-p-h/bio-20054420" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jan Stepanek, M.D.</a>, program director of the Mayo Clinic Aerospace Medicine Program in Arizona, and a subject matter specialist for the film.</p>



<p>Watch online through the Mayo Clinic History and Heritage website, <a href="https://history.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">history.mayoclinic.org</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-video-stories-earn-telly-awards/">Mayo Clinic video stories earn Telly Awards</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Telly-Awards-badge-1x1-1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Telly-Awards-Images-1920x1080-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Types of brain tumors and treatments</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-types-of-brain-tumors-and-treatments/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Osiadacz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2024 14:28:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brain Tumor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brain Tumor Awareness Month]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Alfredo Quiñones-Hinojosa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[glioblastoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meningioma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=385956</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A brain tumor can significantly affect a person's quality of life, not just length of life. In 2023, approximately 25,000 people living in the U.S. were diagnosed with a brain tumor. There are different types of brain tumors and ways to treat them that a healthcare team may consider. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute Journalists: [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-types-of-brain-tumors-and-treatments/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Types of brain tumors and treatments</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>A brain tumor can significantly affect a person's quality of life, not just length of life. In 2023, approximately <a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/types/brain-spinal-cord-tumors-adults/about/key-statistics.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">25,000 people</a> living in the U.S. were diagnosed with a brain tumor. There are different types of brain tumors and ways to treat them that a healthcare team may consider.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/z2n3l_iZXBc" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubez2n3liZXBc"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Types of brain tumors and treatments" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/z2n3l_iZXBc?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:05) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/SCRIPT-MCM-Types-of-brain-tumors-and-treatments.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Primary brain tumors are those that originate in the brain, like <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/glioblastoma/cdc-20350148?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">glioblastoma</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/meningioma/symptoms-causes/syc-20355643?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">meningioma</a>, or others. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/brain-metastases/symptoms-causes/syc-20350136" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Metastatic brain tumors</a> originate in other parts of the body but migrate to the brain or spinal cord.</p>



<p>"Patients that present with brain tumors can present sometimes with a long history of headaches, and the headaches, instead of improving, keep getting worse and worse," <a>says </a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/quinones-hinojosa-alfredo-m-d/bio-20238939?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. </a><a href="http://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/quinones-hinojosa-alfredo-m-d/bio-20247553" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alfredo Quiñones-Hinojosa</a>, a neurosurgeon at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/seizure/symptoms-causes/syc-20365711?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Seizures</a> and sudden collapse are other symptoms of brain tumors that warrant immediate medical attention.</p>



<p>Diagnosis requires brain imaging with an MRI brain scan and an exam by a neurologist or neurosurgeon.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/06/mss_0001598893_Fotor-16x9.jpg" alt="Dr. Alfredo Quinones-Hinojosa, Dr. Q in an operating room with a neurosurgery team doing brain surgery" class="wp-image-193860" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/06/mss_0001598893_Fotor-16x9.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/06/mss_0001598893_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/06/mss_0001598893_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Alfredo Quinones-Hinojosa in an operating room with a neurosurgery team doing brain surgery</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"The <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/brain-tumor-program/home/orc-20439723?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">treatment</a> of brain tumor is a combination of first, the diagnosis, second, a multidisciplinary discussion," says Dr. Quiñones-Hinojosa. "And all together, we have a discussion, and we try to implement a therapy and a management that is personalized for that patient."</p>



<p>Dr. Quiñones-Hinojosa says treatment can include surgery, chemotherapy, radiation therapy or a combination. For surgical removal of a brain tumor, he explains that a patient may remain awake depending on the location of the tumor and symptoms.</p>



<p>"If they're near speech or motor function, we can map those regions of the brain," says Dr. Quiñones-Hinojosa. "We can keep the patient awake and do very significant and safe resections."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Related post:</h2>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treatment-and-research-of-glioblastoma/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Treatment and research of glioblastoma</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-types-of-brain-tumors-and-treatments/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Types of brain tumors and treatments</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/06/mss_0001598893_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/06/mss_0001598893_Fotor-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Brain Tumor]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Brain Tumor Awareness Month]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Alfredo Quiñones-Hinojosa]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[glioblastoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[meningioma]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>8 innovations in neuroscience and brain research at Mayo Clinic</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/8-innovations-in-neuroscience-and-brain-research-at-mayo-clinic/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2024 13:38:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Aging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Discovery Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Healthcare Delivery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rochester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Alfredo Quiñones-Hinojosa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Gregg Day]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Joan Griffin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Leland Hu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Melissa Murray]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nilufer Ertekin-Taner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Owen Ross]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jordan Marks]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=388778</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researchers lead discoveries into many conditions, including cancer, Alzheimer's disease and other forms of dementia, as well as how the brain fundamentally works.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/8-innovations-in-neuroscience-and-brain-research-at-mayo-clinic/">8 innovations in neuroscience and brain research at Mayo Clinic</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The brain is a critical, complex organ and intricate diseases affect it. Mayo Clinic researchers are leading discoveries into many conditions, including cancer, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/alzheimers-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350447" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alzheimer's disease</a> and other forms of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/dementia/symptoms-causes/syc-20352013" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dementia</a>, as well as how the brain fundamentally works. Eight research advancements led by neuroscience experts include:</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="169" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-medium-shot-of-a-white-woman-sitting-at-a-table-with-a-jigsaw-puzzle-holding-a-puzzle-piece-16x9-1-300x169.jpg" alt="a medium shot of a white woman sitting at a table with a jigsaw puzzle holding a puzzle piece" class="wp-image-309354" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-medium-shot-of-a-white-woman-sitting-at-a-table-with-a-jigsaw-puzzle-holding-a-puzzle-piece-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-medium-shot-of-a-white-woman-sitting-at-a-table-with-a-jigsaw-puzzle-holding-a-puzzle-piece-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-medium-shot-of-a-white-woman-sitting-at-a-table-with-a-jigsaw-puzzle-holding-a-puzzle-piece-16x9-1.jpg 773w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/researchers-discover-new-molecular-drug-targets-for-progressive-neurological-disorder/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Researchers discover new molecular drug targets for progressive neurological disorder</strong></a></h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/progressive-supranuclear-palsy/symptoms-causes/syc-20355659" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Progressive supranuclear palsy (PSP)</a> is an uncurable brain disorder marked by walking and balance difficulties. Its symptoms mimic Parkinson's disease and dementia.&nbsp;Mayo researchers and collaborators <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-023-42626-3" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">have outlined</a> new therapeutic targets that may lead to future treatments for PSP as well as&nbsp;Alzheimer's disease&nbsp;and related disorders. </p>



<p>"This research enhances our understanding of progressive supranuclear palsy and other related, incurable neurological disorders," says the study's senior author,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/ertekin-taner-nilufer-m-d-ph-d/bio-00027318" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nilufer&nbsp;Ertekin-Taner, M.D., Ph.D.,</a>&nbsp;a Mayo Clinic neurologist and neuroscientist. "Moving forward, we can target these specific genes or others that are biologically related to them to develop a potential treatment for this untreatable disease."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="169" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1-300x169.jpg" alt="The researchers profiled 313 tumor biopsies from 68 high-grade glioma (HGG) patients. This image is a representation of the 3-dimensional relationship of multiple tissue biopsies from a single patient’s HGG tumor. The different colors depict different versions of genetic mutations relative to the epidermal growth factor receptor gene." class="wp-image-377192" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1.jpg 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mapping-cell-behaviors-in-high-grade-glioma-to-improve-treatment/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Mapping cell behaviors in high-grade glioma to improve treatment</strong></a></h2>



<p>High-grade gliomas are cancerous tumors that spread quickly in the brain or spinal cord. Mayo Clinic researchers <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-023-41559-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">found invasive brain tumor margins</a> of high-grade <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/glioma/symptoms-causes/syc-20350251" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">glioma</a> contain biologically distinct genetic and molecular alterations that indicate aggressive behavior and disease recurrence. They also found that MRI techniques, such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/neurology-neurosurgery/news/radiogenomics-exploring-mris-potential-for-predicting-heterogeneous-tumor-biology/mac-20529911" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dynamic susceptibility contrast</a> and diffusion tensor imaging, can help distinguish between the genetic and molecular alterations of invasive tumors, which is important for clinically characterizing areas that are difficult to surgically biopsy.</p>



<p>"We need to understand what is driving tumor progression," says lead author <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/hu-leland-s-m-d/bio-20055165" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Leland Hu, M.D.</a>, a neuroradiologist at Mayo Clinic. "Our results demonstrate an expanded role of advanced MRI for clinical decision-making for high-grade glioma."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="169" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/MRI_brain_scans_GettyImages-1158800046-16x9-1-300x169.jpg" alt="Physician, holding a pencil, viewing medical images of brain scans on a monitor." class="wp-image-376958" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/MRI_brain_scans_GettyImages-1158800046-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/MRI_brain_scans_GettyImages-1158800046-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/MRI_brain_scans_GettyImages-1158800046-16x9-1.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/researchers-identify-new-criteria-to-detect-rapidly-progressive-dementia/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Researchers identify new criteria to detect rapidly progressive dementia</strong></a></h2>



<p>Rapidly progressive dementia (RPD) is caused by several disorders that quickly impair intellectual functioning and interfere with normal activities and relationships. If patients' symptoms appear suddenly causing rapid decline, a physician may diagnose RPD. These patients can progress from initial symptoms of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/dementia/symptoms-causes/syc-20352013" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dementia</a>&nbsp;to complete incapacitation, requiring full-time care, in less than two years. Mayo Clinic researchers have <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ana.26812" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">identified new scoring criteria</a> allowing for the detection of treatable forms of RPD with reasonably high confidence during a patient's first clinical visit. This scoring criteria may allow physicians to substantially reduce the time it takes to begin treatment.&nbsp; </p>



<p>"Many conditions that cause rapidly progressive dementia can be treated and even reversed. We found that more than half of the patients in our study with rapidly progressive dementia had a treatable underlying condition. We may be able to identify many of these patients early in the symptomatic course by intentionally searching for key clinical symptoms and exam findings and integrating these with results of a brain MRI and spinal tap," says the study's senior author,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/day-gregory-gregg-s-m-d/bio-20545897" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gregg Day, M.D.</a>, a clinical researcher at&nbsp;Mayo Clinic.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="169" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Ross-Lab-1706271_3983114_0015_16x9-300x169.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-386357" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Ross-Lab-1706271_3983114_0015_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Ross-Lab-1706271_3983114_0015_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Ross-Lab-1706271_3983114_0015_16x9.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/global-consortium-to-study-picks-disease-rare-form-of-early-onset-dementia/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Global consortium to study Pick’s disease, rare form of early-onset dementia</a></strong></h2>



<p><a href="https://www.alzheimers.net/what-is-picks-disease" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pick's disease</a>, a neurodegenerative disease of unknown genetic origin, is a rare type of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/frontotemporal-dementia/symptoms-causes/syc-20354737?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">frontotemporal dementia</a>&nbsp;that affects people under the age of 65. The condition causes changes in personality, behavior and sometimes language impairment. In patients with the disease, tau proteins build up and form abnormal clumps called Pick bodies, which restrict nutrients to the brain and cause neurodegeneration.&nbsp;Researchers at Mayo Clinic and collaborators worldwide have established the Pick's Disease International Consortium <a href="https://sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1474442224000838?utm_campaign=STMJ_219742_AUTH_SERV_PA&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_acid=81527593&amp;SIS_ID=&amp;dgcid=STMJ_219742_AUTH_SERV_PA&amp;CMX_ID=&amp;utm_in=DM467488&amp;utm_source=AC_" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">to study a specific&nbsp;MAPT&nbsp;gene variation known as&nbsp;MAPT&nbsp;H2</a> that makes the tau protein and acts as a driver of disease. They investigated a connection between the gene and disease risk, age at onset and duration of Pick's disease.&nbsp;<br><br>"We found that the&nbsp;MAPT&nbsp;H2 genetic variant is associated with an increased risk of Pick's disease in people of European descent," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/ross-owen-a-ph-d/bio-00093014" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Owen Ross, Ph.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic neuroscientist and senior author of the paper. "We were only able to determine that because of the global consortium, which greatly increased the sample size of pathology cases to study Pick's disease."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="169" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/hands-holding-hands-16x9-1-300x169.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-388786" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/hands-holding-hands-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/hands-holding-hands-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/hands-holding-hands-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/hands-holding-hands-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/hands-holding-hands-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/understanding-lucid-episodes-in-dementia/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Moments of clarity in the fog of dementia</strong></a></h2>



<p>Researchers define lucid episodes as unexpected, spontaneous, meaningful and relevant communication from a person who is assumed to have permanently lost the capacity for coherent interactions, either verbally or through gestures and actions. A <a href="https://alz-journals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/alz.13667" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> surveyed family caregivers of people living with dementia and asked them about witnessing lucid episodes.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"We have found in our research and stories from caregivers that these kinds of episodes change how they interact with and support their loved ones — usually for the better," says lead author&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/griffin-joan-m-ph-d/bio-20094571" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Joan Griffin, Ph.D.</a> "These episodes can serve as reminders that caregiving is challenging, but we can always try to care with a little more humanity and grace."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="169" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/TMEM16x9-300x169.jpg" alt="Microscopy image of TMEM106B with protein in green, cell nuclei in blue and neurons in red." class="wp-image-384907" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/TMEM16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/TMEM16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/TMEM16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/TMEM16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/TMEM16x9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/untangling-the-threads-of-early-onset-dementia/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Untangling the threads of early-onset dementia</strong></a></h2>



<p>Changes in personality, behavior and language are hallmarks of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/frontotemporal-dementia/symptoms-causes/syc-20354737" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">frontotemporal dementia (FTD)</a>, the most common form of dementia in patients under the age of 65. <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/epdf/10.1126/scitranslmed.adf9735" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">New research</a> provides insight into the role a specific gene and the protein it produces play in the development and progression of FTD, which is associated with degeneration of the frontal and temporal lobes of the brain. The researchers think the key may lie in the formation of fibrils, or tiny fiber-like structures produced by part of this protein, that sometimes get tangled up in the brain. </p>



<p>"We also think that these fibrils could one day serve as biomarkers to help clinicians determine FTD prognosis or severity, " says Jordan Marks, an M.D.–Ph.D. student with the&nbsp;<a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a>.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="169" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/GettyImages-1175464489-1-300x169.jpg" alt="A brain imaging MRI scan is shown with a blue and red reflection covering half." class="wp-image-386525" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/GettyImages-1175464489-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/GettyImages-1175464489-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/GettyImages-1175464489-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/GettyImages-1175464489-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/GettyImages-1175464489-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-new-tool-links-alzheimers-disease-types-to-rate-of-cognitive-decline/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Mayo Clinic researchers' new tool links Alzheimer's disease types to rate of cognitive decline</strong></a></h2>



<p>Through a new corticolimbic index tool that identifies changes in specific areas of the brain, Mayo Clinic researchers discovered a series of brain changes characterized by unique clinical features and immune cell behaviors for <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/alzheimers-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350447" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alzheimer's disease</a>, a leading cause of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/dementia/symptoms-causes/syc-20352013" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dementia</a>. </p>



<p>"By combining our expertise in the fields of neuropathology, biostatistics, neuroscience, neuroimaging and neurology to address Alzheimer's disease from all angles, we've made significant strides in understanding how it affects the brain," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/murray-melissa-e-ph-d/bio-00028171" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Melissa E. Murray, Ph.D.</a>, a translational neuropathologist at Mayo Clinic. "The corticolimbic index is a score that could encourage a paradigm shift toward understanding the individuality of this complex disease and broaden our perspective. This study marks a significant step toward personalized care, offering hope for more effective future therapies."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="169" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/brain_cancer_16x9-300x169.jpg" alt="The brain is a critical, complex organ and intricate diseases affect it." class="wp-image-388659" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/brain_cancer_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/brain_cancer_16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/brain_cancer_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/brain_cancer_16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/brain_cancer_16x9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-research-platform-assesses-brain-cancer-mutations-during-surgery/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>New research platform assesses brain cancer mutations during surgery</strong></a></h2>



<p>Brain cancer is difficult to treat when it starts growing, and a prevalent type, known as a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/glioma/symptoms-causes/syc-20350251" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">glioma</a>, has a poor five-year survival rate. Mayo Clinic researchers <a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2318843121" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">report</a> on a new surgical platform used during surgery that informs critical decision-making about tumor treatment within minutes. Time is of the utmost importance when dealing with aggressive malignant tumors.</p>



<p>The researchers say that, in addition to enabling real-time diagnosis, the platform allows surgeons to determine a patient's prognosis and perform tumor resection to improve patient outcomes.</p>



<p>“We will be able to bring the fight against cancer to the operating room, before chemotherapy and radiation treatments begin, and before the disease has progressed and invaded further," says the study's senior author, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/quinones-hinojosa-alfredo-m-d/bio-20247553" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alfredo Quiñones-Hinojosa, M.D.</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/8-innovations-in-neuroscience-and-brain-research-at-mayo-clinic/">8 innovations in neuroscience and brain research at Mayo Clinic</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-1410795105.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-1410795105-16x9-template.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Alfredo Quiñones-Hinojosa]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Gregg Day]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Joan Griffin]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Leland Hu]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Melissa Murray]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nilufer Ertekin-Taner]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Owen Ross]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Jordan Marks]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center to highlight key studies at ASCO 2024</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-comprehensive-cancer-center-to-highlight-key-studies-at-asco-2024/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelley Luckstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 21:36:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ASCO2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Andrea Cheville]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Brad Stish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Grace Choong]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Robert Foote]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[palliative care]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[proton therapy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=388719</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Researchers from the Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center are set to present key research findings, including two late-breaking abstracts, during the 2024 American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) Annual Meeting in Chicago May 31-June 4. These studies shed light on critical aspects of cancer treatment and management. Below are the highlights: The [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-comprehensive-cancer-center-to-highlight-key-studies-at-asco-2024/">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center to highlight key studies at ASCO 2024</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="682" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Doctor-concentrating-on-computer-monitor_GettyImages-1364382009-1024x682.jpg" alt="Doctor concentrating on computer monitor" class="wp-image-388750" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Doctor-concentrating-on-computer-monitor_GettyImages-1364382009-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Doctor-concentrating-on-computer-monitor_GettyImages-1364382009-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Doctor-concentrating-on-computer-monitor_GettyImages-1364382009-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Doctor-concentrating-on-computer-monitor_GettyImages-1364382009-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Doctor-concentrating-on-computer-monitor_GettyImages-1364382009.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Researchers from the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> are set to present key research findings, including two late-breaking abstracts, during the 2024 <a href="https://conferences.asco.org/am/attend" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) Annual Meeting</a> in Chicago May 31-June 4. These studies shed light on critical aspects of cancer treatment and management. Below are the highlights:</p>



<p><strong>The impact of adjuvant endocrine therapy (AET) omission in estrogen receptor (ER)-low (1%-10%) early-stage breast cancer</strong> (<a href="https://meetings.asco.org/abstracts-presentations/233537" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Abstract: 513</a>)</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Presenter:</strong> <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/choong-grace-m-m-d/bio-20549783" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Grace Choong, M.D.</a>, medical oncologist</li>



<li><strong>Key Insight:</strong> In patients with ER-low breast cancer, omission of AET in patients treated with chemotherapy is associated with a 25% higher risk of death than those who receive AET. The impact of AET omission was most pronounced in patients with residual disease after neoadjuvant chemotherapy. Therefore, AET should be recommended in patients with ER-low breast cancer until further studies can be performed.</li>



<li><strong>Day and Time</strong>: May 31, 3:15–3:21 p.m. CDT</li>



<li><strong>Location:</strong> E451 |&nbsp;On Demand</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Final results of a phase 2 study of tucatinib and trastuzumab for HER2-positive mCRC (MOUNTAINEER) </strong>(<a href="https://meetings.asco.org/abstracts-presentations/231646" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Abstract: 3509</a>)</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Senior Author</strong>: <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/bekaii-saab-tanios-s-m-d/bio-20396570" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tanios Bekaii-Saab, M.D.</a>, medical oncologist</li>



<li><strong>Key Insight</strong>: This presentation includes the final analysis of the MOUNTAINEER trial and reaffirms the clinically meaningful anti-tumor activity and favorable tolerability of tucatinib plus trastuzumab, a chemotherapy-free treatment option for patients with HER2+ mCRC, the first regimen to be approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration for this indication.</li>



<li><strong>Day and Time</strong>: June 3, 1:15–1:21 p.m. CDT</li>



<li><strong>Location</strong>: Arie Crown Theater |&nbsp;Live Stream</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Phase 3 randomized trial of intensity-modulated proton therapy (IMPT) versus intensity-modulated photon therapy (IMRT) for the treatment of head and neck oropharyngeal carcinoma (OPC)</strong> (<a href="https://meetings.asco.org/abstracts-presentations/234877" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Abstract: 6006</a>) &nbsp;</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Senior Author</strong>: Robert Foote, M.D., radiation oncologist</li>



<li><strong>Key Insight:</strong> Intensity-modulated proton therapy (IMPT) is non-inferior to intensity modulated-photon therapy (IMRT) as measured by progression-free survival at three years and has emerged as a standard of care chemoradiotherapy treatment for oropharyngeal cancer. More patients treated with IMPT maintained their weight and fewer required gastrostomy tubes compared to patients treated with IMRT. IMPT is recommended for oropharyngeal cancer because it minimizes radiation to important organs while effectively treating the cancer.</li>



<li><strong>Day and Time:</strong> June 4, 11:45–11:57 a.m. CDT</li>



<li><strong>Location:</strong> S100a |&nbsp;Live Stream</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Late-breaking abstract: Alliance A222001: A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase 2 study of oxybutynin versus placebo for the treatment of hot flashes in men receiving androgen deprivation therapy </strong>(Abstract: <a href="https://meetings.asco.org/abstracts-presentations/232439" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">LBA12004</a>)</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Presenter</strong>: <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/stish-brad-j-m-d/bio-20340352" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Brad Stish, M.D.</a>, radiation oncologist, will share the results during the <a href="https://meetings.asco.org/2024-asco-annual-meeting/15800?presentation=232437#232437" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Symptom Science and Palliative Care track</a>.</li>



<li><strong>Key insights</strong>: The abstract becomes available at the time of the presentation. &nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>Day and Time</strong>: June 2, 9:12–9:24 a.m. CDT</li>



<li><strong>Location: </strong>S100a |&nbsp;Live Stream</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Late-breaking abstract: Primary outcomes of the enhanced, EHR-facilitated cancer symptom control (E2C2) cluster-randomized, stepped wedge, pragmatic trial</strong> (Abstract: <a href="https://meetings.asco.org/abstracts-presentations/232437" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">LBA12006</a>)</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Presenter</strong>: <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/cheville-andrea-l-m-d/bio-20054964" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Andrea Cheville, M.D.</a>, pain, rehabilitation and palliative care physician, will share findings during the <a href="https://meetings.asco.org/2024-asco-annual-meeting/15800?presentation=232437#232437" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Symptom Science and Palliative Care track</a>.</li>



<li><strong>Key insights</strong>: The abstract becomes available at the time of the presentation. &nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>Day and Time:</strong> June 2, 10–10:12 a.m. CDT</li>



<li><strong>Location</strong>: S100a |&nbsp;Live Stream</li>
</ul>



<p>In addition, Dr. Cheville's research extends to the following posters presented by Mayo Clinic researchers, all based on data from the E2C2 trial:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>SPPADE symptom prevalence and severity in a diverse sample of patients living with metastatic cancers</strong>, presented by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/pachman-deirdre-r-m-d/bio-20458001" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Deirdre Pachman, M.D.</a>, palliative fellow. (<a href="https://meetings.asco.org/abstracts-presentations/233216" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Abstract: 11108 / Poster: 303</a>)</li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li><strong>Symptom burden in adolescents and young adults with cancer: A subgroup analysis of the enhanced, EHR-facilitated cancer symptom control (E2C2) trial</strong>, presented by <a href="https://communityhealth.mayoclinic.org/providers/michael-storandt-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Michael Storandt, M.D.</a>, internal medicine resident. (<a href="https://meetings.asco.org/abstracts-presentations/233400" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Abstract: 12065 / Poster: 194</a>)</li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li><strong>Proactive, automated monitoring of uncontrolled symptoms in prostate cancer survivors across the cancer control continuum</strong> (<a href="https://meetings.asco.org/abstracts-presentations/231364" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Abstract: 12079 / Poster: 208</a>)</li>
</ul>



<p>Additional abstracts, posters and presentations featuring Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center researchers can be found <a href="https://meetings.asco.org/abstracts-presentations/search?query=*&amp;q=mayo%20clinic&amp;sortBy=Relevancy&amp;filters=%7B%22meetingTypeName%22:%5B%7B%22key%22:%22ASCO%20Annual%20Meeting%22%7D%5D,%22meetingYear%22:%5B%7B%22key%22:2024%7D%5D,%22mediaType%22:%5B%7B%22key%22:%22Abstracts%22%7D%5D%7D&amp;intcmp=cc_ascoorg_am_abstractsrelease_site_meeting-carousel_all__glob_052324__carousel_viewnow_aware_text_" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive&nbsp;Cancer Center</strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;is defining new boundaries in possibility, focusing on patient-centered care, developing novel treatments, training future generations of cancer experts and bringing cancer research to communities. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs that are changing approaches to cancer prevention, screening and treatment, and improving the lives of cancer survivors.</p>



<p><strong>Media Contacts:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Onsite at ASCO: Audrey Laine Seymour, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>



<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-comprehensive-cancer-center-to-highlight-key-studies-at-asco-2024/">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center to highlight key studies at ASCO 2024</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Doctor-concentrating-on-computer-monitor_GettyImages-1364382009_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Doctor-concentrating-on-computer-monitor_GettyImages-1364382009_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[ASCO2024]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Andrea Cheville]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Brad Stish]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Grace Choong]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Robert Foote]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[palliative care]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[proton therapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New research platform assesses brain cancer mutations during surgery</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-research-platform-assesses-brain-cancer-mutations-during-surgery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lynda De Widt]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 12:28:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[brain cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=388613</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. — Brain cancer is difficult to treat when it starts growing, and a prevalent type, known as a glioma, has a poor five-year survival rate. In a new study published in Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, Mayo Clinic researchers report on a new surgical platform used during surgery that informs critical [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-research-platform-assesses-brain-cancer-mutations-during-surgery/">New research platform assesses brain cancer mutations during surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="677" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/brain_cancer-1024x677.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-388658" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/brain_cancer-1024x677.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/brain_cancer-300x198.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/brain_cancer-768x508.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/brain_cancer-1536x1016.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/brain_cancer-2048x1354.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. — Brain cancer is difficult to treat when it starts growing, and a prevalent type, known as a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/glioma/symptoms-causes/syc-20350251" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">glioma</a>, has a poor five-year survival rate. In a <a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2318843121" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">new study</a> published in Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, Mayo Clinic researchers report on a new surgical platform used during surgery that informs critical decision-making about tumor treatment within minutes. Time is of the utmost importance when dealing with aggressive malignant tumors.</p>



<p>The platform uses mass spectrometry to identify a key gene mutation in brain cancer, known as isocitrate dehydrogenase (IDH) mutations, in real time. Mass spectrometry is a sensitive technique used to analyze substances in tissue samples, including those altered in cancer.</p>



<p>The study involved more than 240 small tissue biopsies from patients undergoing asleep and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/awake-brain-surgery/about/pac-20384913" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">awake brain surgery</a> for suspected glioma at Mayo Clinic between 2021 and 2023, and an additional 137 biopsies from an international collaborator. Neurosurgeons collected biopsy samples from the core of the tumor to identify the mutations, as well as from areas around it, to assess if the tumor had spread.</p>



<p>Each tissue sample was placed on a glass slide steps away from the patients during ongoing surgery. The samples were analyzed through the mass spectrometer, which allowed researchers to rapidly assess — within two minutes — whether an IDH mutation was present.</p>



<p>The researchers say that, in addition to enabling real-time diagnosis, the platform allows surgeons to determine a patient's prognosis and perform tumor resection to improve patient outcomes. In the future, the new platform will help surgeons take advantage of the window of opportunity in the operating room to tailor treatment to the molecular features of a tumor, a more personalized approach to medicine.</p>



<p>Researchers hope new therapies developed to target IDH mutations can be delivered in the operating room at the time of surgery.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Dr-Q-WF1453100_-10-200x300.jpg" alt="portrait of Dr. Quinones" class="wp-image-388663" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Dr-Q-WF1453100_-10-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Dr-Q-WF1453100_-10.jpg 533w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><sup>Alfredo Quiñones-Hinojosa, M.D.</sup></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"The ability to identify this mutation during brain surgery means that one day in the future we may be able to treat patients with this specific mutation locally before they leave the operating room," says the study's senior author, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/quinones-hinojosa-alfredo-m-d/bio-20247553" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alfredo Quiñones-Hinojosa, M.D.</a>, dean of research and chair of the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/neurosurgery/home/orc-20117096" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Neurosurgery</a> at Mayo Clinic in Florida.</p>



<p>"Therefore, we will be able to bring the fight against cancer to the operating room, before chemotherapy and radiation treatments begin, and before the disease has progressed and invaded further." Dr. Quiñones-Hinojosa is also director of the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/brain-tumor-stem-cell-research/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Brain Tumor Stem Cell Research Laboratory</a>.</p>



<p>In the study, researchers were able to diagnose IDH gene mutations with 100% accuracy. They are conducting more research to find other signatures in tumors where the&nbsp;mutation is absent. In addition, they plan to broaden their discoveries to include other types of brain cancers.</p>



<p>This study was supported in part by the National Cancer Institute of the National Institutes of Health under award number R33CA240181. For a full list of authors, funding and disclosures, see the <a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2318843121" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">paper</a>.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> <br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong> </p>



<ul>
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-research-platform-assesses-brain-cancer-mutations-during-surgery/">New research platform assesses brain cancer mutations during surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/brain_cancer_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/brain_cancer_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[brain cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: No &#8216;lesser evil&#8217; when it comes to tobacco use</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-no-lesser-evil-when-it-comes-to-tobacco-use/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[DeeDee Stiepan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2024 15:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jon Ebbert]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=388487</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Editors note: May 31 is World No Tobacco Day From the traditional cigarette to the modern electronic cigarette, from the communal hookah to the discreet pinch of smokeless tobacco, each has proven to be detrimental to a person's health. In this Mayo Clinic Minute, Dr. Jon Ebbert,&#160;medical director of the&#160;Mayo Clinic Nicotine Dependence Center, discusses [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-no-lesser-evil-when-it-comes-to-tobacco-use/">Mayo Clinic Minute: No &#8216;lesser evil&#8217; when it comes to tobacco use</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em><strong>Editors note: </strong> May 31 is World No Tobacco Day</em></p>



<p>From the traditional cigarette to the modern electronic cigarette, from the communal hookah to the discreet pinch of smokeless tobacco, each has proven to be detrimental to a person's health. In this Mayo Clinic Minute, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/ebbert-jon-o-m-d/bio-20053361?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Jon Ebbert</a>,&nbsp;medical director of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/nicotine-dependence-center/sections/overview/ovc-20457521?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Nicotine Dependence Center</a>, discusses why there is no "lesser evil" when it comes to tobacco use.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/kxzK24axr0c" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubekxzK24axr0c"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: No &#039;lesser evil&#039; when it comes to tobacco use" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kxzK24axr0c?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:10) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/SCRIPT-MCM-Tobacco-use-SCRIPT-final.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Smoked tobacco has the strongest association with cancer, and it goes beyond cigarettes.</p>



<p>"Hookah, which is a smoked and inhaled tobacco, has a similar cancer risk because it's the process of smoking and inhaling those 7,000 chemicals that increases the risk for cancer," says Dr. Ebbert.</p>



<p>There's no safe, or safer, way to consume tobacco. A common misconception is that cigars are less harmful than cigarettes.</p>



<p>"All the same risks that you get with cigars that you inhale are exactly the same risks you have with conventional cigarettes," says Dr. Ebbert.</p>



<p>He says even cigar users, who tend not to inhale, are still at risk.</p>



<p>"If you smoke a cigar and just hold it in your mouth and exhale, all the tissues in your mouth that are exposed to the cigar smoke have an increased risk for cancer," says Dr. Ebbert.</p>



<p>Head and neck cancers are more common in people who smoke cigars as well as those who use smokeless tobacco, which is also associated with pancreatic and kidney cancer.</p>



<p>"With electronic cigarettes specifically, we don't have enough longitudinal data to know whether those products are associated strongly with cancer," says Dr. Ebbert. "But we do know that those products result in the release of carbonyls and heavy metals. And those are known, theoretically, to lead to cancer."</p>



<p>No Tobacco Day is recognized this year on May 31 to inform the public of the dangers of using tobacco. All forms of tobacco consumption carry significant health risks and can lead to cancer.</p>



<p>"We always say it's never too late to stop smoking, and the risk for cancer after quitting cigarette smoking, for example, goes down. But it takes some time. So, if you think about reductions in cancer risk for lung cancer, in about 15 years, you have half the risk of cancer that you would if you had continued to smoke. So it takes some time, but it's never too late to stop smoking," says Dr. Ebbert.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-no-lesser-evil-when-it-comes-to-tobacco-use/">Mayo Clinic Minute: No &#8216;lesser evil&#8217; when it comes to tobacco use</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/person-smoking-and-puffing-cigarette-smoke-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/person-smoking-and-puffing-cigarette-smoke-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jon Ebbert]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Common types of skin cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-common-types-of-skin-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 15:11:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Collin Costello]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skin Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386647</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Skin cancer is the most common cancer in the U.S., affecting millions worldwide. This cancer comes in two main types:&#160;melanoma, which is less common but more deadly, and&#160;nonmelanoma&#160;skin cancers, which include&#160;basal cell carcinoma&#160;and&#160;squamous cell carcinoma.&#160; Dr. Collin Costello, a Mayo Clinic&#160;dermatologist, says these nonmelanoma skin cancers are more prevalent – and with early diagnosis and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-common-types-of-skin-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Common types of skin cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Skin cancer is the most common cancer in the U.S., affecting millions worldwide. This cancer comes in two main types:&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/melanoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20374884?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">melanoma</a>, which is less common but more deadly, and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/nonmelanoma-skin-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20355397?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">nonmelanoma&nbsp;</a>skin cancers, which include&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/basal-cell-carcinoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20354187?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">basal cell carcinoma</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/squamous-cell-carcinoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20352480?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">squamous cell carcinoma</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/costello-collin-m-m-d/bio-20537501?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Collin Costello</a>, a Mayo Clinic&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/dermatology/sections/overview/ovc-20420526?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dermatologist</a>, says these nonmelanoma skin cancers are more prevalent – and with early diagnosis and treatment, the prognosis is good.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d57yn6wPCDs" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidd57yn6wPCDs"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - The most common types of skin cancer" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/d57yn6wPCDs?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:00) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/SCRIPT-MCM-Most-common-types-of-skin-cancer.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">&nbsp;script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"Both basal and squamous cell carcinoma are often slow-growing skin cancers. They're both caused mostly by the sun," says Dr. Costello.</p>



<p>These cancers are predominantly found on sun-exposed areas, like the face, scalp, neck and ears.</p>



<p>Basal cell carcinoma often appears as a change in the skin, such as a growth or a sore that won't heal, or a slightly transparent bump on the skin.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/06/shutterstock_685947193_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a closeup of a basal cell carcinoma, a nonmelanoma skin cancer" class="wp-image-240640" style="width:841px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/06/shutterstock_685947193_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/06/shutterstock_685947193_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/06/shutterstock_685947193_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Closeup of a basal cell carcinoma, a nonmelanoma skin cancer</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"For basal cells, they're often a pink bump that slowly enlarges with time. And sometimes they can bleed and be a little tender," Dr. Costello says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/squamous-cell-carcinoma-nonmelanoma-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Photograph of squamous cell carcinoma on elbow" class="wp-image-387172" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/squamous-cell-carcinoma-nonmelanoma-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/squamous-cell-carcinoma-nonmelanoma-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/squamous-cell-carcinoma-nonmelanoma-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/squamous-cell-carcinoma-nonmelanoma-16-x-9.jpg 1045w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">A squamous cell carcinoma on an elbow</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Squamous cell carcinoma may look like a skin-colored bump and can start anywhere on the skin. It’s typically found on sun-exposed areas in sunburn-prone people. However, in those with darker skin tones, it can appear on sun-protected areas, including the genitals or toes.</p>



<p>"Sometimes they can get painful and ulcerated or be almost like a nonhealing wound," he says.</p>



<p>Early diagnosis and treatment for these nonmelanoma cancers are crucial. See a dermatologist if you notice spots changing or growing.</p>



<p>"The majority of the time both basal cell and squamous cell carcinoma are treated with&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treating-skin-cancer-with-mohs-surgery/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mohs surgery</a>, particularly when it's on the face, scalp and neck," Dr. Costello says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Reduce your risk of skin cancer </h2>



<p>Use sunscreen daily to help prevent exposure to dangerous ultraviolet rays.</p>



<ul>
<li>Wear sunscreen of at least 30 SPF.</li>



<li>Perform regular skin self-exams.</li>



<li>See a healthcare professional for abnormal growths or warts.</li>



<li>Wear protective clothing.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h3>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-skin-cancer-concerns-for-people-with-darker-skin/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Skin cancer concerns for people with darker skin</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-the-a-b-c-d-and-es-of-skin-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: The A, B, C, D and Es of skin cancer</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-common-types-of-skin-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Common types of skin cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/07/a-medical-illustration-of-three-types-of-skin-cancer-squamous-cell-basal-cell-and-melanoma-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Skin-Cancer-1-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Collin Costello]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Skin Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Tips for protecting babies from harmful UV rays</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/draft-5-3-mayo-clinic-minute-tips-for-protecting-babies-from-harmful-uv-rays/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[DeeDee Stiepan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Megha Tollefson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skin Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sunburn]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sunscreen for babies]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=365529</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Skin cancer is the most common cancer in the U.S., and it only takes one blistering sunburn during childhood or adolescence to nearly double a person's chance of developing melanoma later in life, according to the American Academy of Dermatology Association. Since babies are much more prone to sunburn than older kids, it's especially important [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/draft-5-3-mayo-clinic-minute-tips-for-protecting-babies-from-harmful-uv-rays/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Tips for protecting babies from harmful UV rays</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Skin cancer is the most common cancer in the U.S., and it only takes one blistering sunburn during childhood or adolescence to nearly double a person's chance of developing <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/melanoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20374884?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">melanoma</a> later in life, according to the American Academy of Dermatology Association. Since babies are much more prone to sunburn than older kids, it's especially important to protect them from the sun's harmful ultraviolet (UV) rays. </p>



<p>May is Melanoma and Skin Cancer Awareness Month. In this Mayo Clinic Minute, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/tollefson-megha-m-m-d/bio-20054866?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Megha Tollefson</a>, a Mayo Clinic pediatric dermatologist, offers tips for keeping babies safe outdoors.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/4ebwTy3pSxo" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutube4ebwTy3pSxo"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Tips for protecting babies from harmful UV rays" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4ebwTy3pSxo?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:59) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/SCRIPT-MCM-Sun-protection.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"Sunburns can be very painful," explains Dr. Tollefson. They can be a setup for infection if they're fairly severe."</p>



<p>While sunburns are thought to be short-term concerns, there are also long-term risks to sun exposure.</p>



<p>"The more UV exposure a child gets — especially the younger in life that it starts — and the more sunburns they have, the higher their risk for <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/skin-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20377605?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">skin cancer</a> later in life," says Dr. Tollefson.</p>



<p>Sun protection in the first 20 years of life is the most crucial for protecting against long-term skin cancer risk.</p>



<p>For infants, it's best to avoid peak sun hours from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. If that's not possible, cover the baby with shade or long-sleeved clothing and a hat.</p>



<p>Dr. Tollefson also recommends using sunscreen on areas of exposed skin.</p>



<p>"We would recommend that, at that age, parents use the sunscreens that have physical blockers rather than chemical blockers because they're better for sensitive skin," she says.</p>



<p>Look for these ingredients when selecting a sunscreen for baby:</p>



<ul>
<li>Titanium dioxide</li>



<li>Zinc oxide</li>
</ul>



<p>Remember to reapply sunscreen every two hours or right after swimming or sweating.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Additional resources:</h3>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-the-importance-of-sunscreen-sunglasses-and-protective-clothing-for-adults-and-children/">Consumer Health: The importance of sunscreen, sunglasses and protective clothing for adults and children</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-3-things-you-might-not-know-about-sunscreen/">Mayo Clinic Minute: 3 things you might not know about sunscreen</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/draft-5-3-mayo-clinic-minute-tips-for-protecting-babies-from-harmful-uv-rays/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Tips for protecting babies from harmful UV rays</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Sun-protection-for-babies-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Sun-protection-for-babies-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Megha Tollefson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Skin Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[sunburn]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[sunscreen for babies]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mcthumb >https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/sun-protection-150x150.jpg</mayoclinic:mcthumb >	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>