<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Cardiovascular - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cardiovascular-2/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cardiovascular-2/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 May 2024 13:31:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Teasing apart sex differences in heart disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/teasing-apart-sex-differences-in-heart-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kate Ledger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2024 13:31:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Discovery Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Damian Di Florio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Danielle Beetler]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. DeLisa Fairweather]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Emily Whelan]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=388692</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DeLisa Fairweather, Ph.D., and the students in her lab are identifying biological sex differences to help in the diagnosis and treatment of the deadly heart disease myocarditis.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/teasing-apart-sex-differences-in-heart-disease/">Teasing apart sex differences in heart disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/extracellular-vesicles-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Colorful microscopy image of an extracellular vesicle." class="wp-image-388693" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/extracellular-vesicles-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/extracellular-vesicles-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/extracellular-vesicles-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/extracellular-vesicles-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/extracellular-vesicles-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">A super-resolution microscopy image of an extracellular vesicle (EV), used by the body to communicate molecular messages from cell to cell. The Fairweather lab is studying EVs as a potential treatment approach for myocarditis, a disease that predominantly affects young men. Image created by the Fairweather lab.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Damian Di Florio, Ph.D., remembers the lightning-bolt moment five years ago when he began thinking differently about the questions scientists ask. He was a summer undergraduate student working in the lab of cardiovascular researcher <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/fairweather-delisa-ph-d/bio-20320752" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">DeLisa Fairweather, Ph.D.</a>, when she and another scientist gave a lecture about vitamin D. The lab's studies had found stark differences between how vitamin D affects the heart function of male and female models of disease.</p>



<p>"That was the first alarm bell for me," says Dr. Di Florio, who recently completed his Ph.D. in Clinical and Translational Science at <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a> under Dr. Fairweather's mentorship. "It made sense that sex differences would be an important feature of biology to consider in any type of research, and especially in cardiovascular disorders, which women and men experience differently."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A disease more deadly in men</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="533" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/DeLisaFairweatherPhD.jpg" alt="Image of DeLisa Fairweather, Ph.D." class="wp-image-388696" style="width:205px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/DeLisaFairweatherPhD.jpg 533w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/DeLisaFairweatherPhD-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 533px) 100vw, 533px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">DeLisa Fairweather, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Dr. Fairweather has long studied myocarditis, an inflammation of the heart that's set off by a viral infection and can result in heart failure. The disease is rare, but it predominantly affects men under age 40. It can reduce the heart's ability to pump and can even be instantly fatal. Several viruses, including SARS-CoV2, the virus that causes COVID-19, are known to set off the inflammatory process, but no disease-specific tools exist to detect myocarditis in its early stages.</p>



<p>For Dr. Fairweather, who serves as director for translational research for the Department of Cardiovascular Diseases, a key research goal is using the preclinical model of myocarditis that she developed to depict the disease process and provide new information relevant to human disease. She closely examines data for differences between males and females, including immune signaling which is affected by hormonal differences.</p>



<p>Translational research studies the mechanisms of disease with the goal of finding cures. Dr. Fairweather's lab aims to develop diagnostic tools and treatments that are tailored appropriately to men and women. "The mechanism of what's causing disease differs by sex," she says. "We should be looking for treatments according to that framework."</p>



<p>The perspective helped shape Dr. Di Florio's graduate work and it also yielded important results. "If we had not analyzed a certain data set by sex, we would have missed some of the most important and interesting features of that data," he says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Differences in genes that affect the heart</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="533" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/DamianDiFlorioPhD.jpg" alt="Image of Damian Di Florio, Ph.D." class="wp-image-388697" style="width:198px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/DamianDiFlorioPhD.jpg 533w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/DamianDiFlorioPhD-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 533px) 100vw, 533px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Damian Di Florio, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>During his Ph.D. research, Dr. Di Florio found differences in the male and female responses to viral infection, including genes activated during acute stages of myocarditis. He looked at genes affecting the energy-producing structures in cells — organelles known as mitochondria — that are especially essential in a pumping heart. He found female mice with myocarditis have genes engaged that help mitochondria function; males have the same genes turned off. The lab is characterizing the genes, aiming to identify a target they can manipulate with the goal of making the genes more active in males during the disease process.</p>



<p>Dr. Di Florio also explored whether there might be sex-based variations in how myocarditis affects the pumping of the heart. Using three-dimensional echocardiography, he <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2589004223025701" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">found</a> that both male and female mice showed a reduction in blood squeezed out of the heart, a measurement known as ejection fraction. But when it came to the motion that pushes blood from the heart and to the rest of the body, a force known as global latitudinal strain, males showed worse function than females. Further, that pumping difference correlated with the presence of immune cells in the heart — a sign of inflammation. The findings suggest that measuring global longitudinal strain could be the basis to develop a much-needed clinical test to detect myocarditis at an early stage.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A step toward treatment</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="434" height="533" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/DanielleBeetlerPhD.jpg" alt="Image of Danielle Beetler, Ph.D." class="wp-image-388698" style="width:213px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/DanielleBeetlerPhD.jpg 434w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/DanielleBeetlerPhD-244x300.jpg 244w" sizes="(max-width: 434px) 100vw, 434px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Danielle Beetler, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>During her graduate studies in Clinical and Translational Science, Danielle Beetler, Ph.D., looked at a potential treatment for myocarditis using particles that exist in the body. Her work in Dr. Fairweather's lab also took sex differences into account, focusing on the fact that the symptoms in women with myocarditis tend to be less severe than those in men.</p>



<p>"The idea was that maybe women who are most protected from these cardiovascular conditions have some kind of messaging in their body that can be applied in the context of male-driven disease," says Dr. Beetler, who also graduated this year. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Her experiments looked at extracellular vesicles, or EVs — tiny "envelopes" that are shed by cells and contain molecular messages, including mRNA. The studies <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/smll.202303317" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">found</a> EVs from healthy donors not only shut down the replication of the virus and reduced damage caused by the immune system, but also protected cardiac function. The research also found that the effect of the EVs differed by age and sex of the donor. The researchers speculate that some donors may have had an undetected infection, suggesting that specialized screening would be necessary in the development of a therapy. "The studies overall are a step toward a novel, biocompatible treatment for myocarditis and maybe other cellular messaging-related diseases," says Dr. Beetler.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>An outlook that could change medicine</strong></h2>



<p>The National Institutes of Health granting system has a <a href="https://orwh.od.nih.gov/sites/orwh/files/docs/NOT-OD-15-102_Guidance.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">policy</a> for researchers to include consideration of sex as a biological variable in clinical and preclinical studies. Dr. Fairweather and her mentees are committed to this approach for the benefit of patients. She believes a close examination of sex differences will lead to better biomarkers for diseases that predominantly affect men, such as heart disease, and those that predominantly affect women, such as autoimmune diseases, which she also studies. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Research in her lab looks at sex differences in other cardiovascular conditions, particularly disease pathways that overlap with myocarditis. The lab has recently developed a new model of cardiovascular injury that can occur during cancer treatment. During chest radiation, a patient may incur damage to the heart and later develop cardiomyopathy, a disorder that interferes with the heart's ability to pump. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="533" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/EmilyWhelan.jpg" alt="Image of Emily Whelan" class="wp-image-388699" style="width:199px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/EmilyWhelan.jpg 533w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/EmilyWhelan-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 533px) 100vw, 533px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Emily Whelan</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Emily Whelan, a second-year student in the Clinical and Translational Science graduate track, is looking for genes that may differ by sex and may affect inflammatory and functional responses to injury. The goal is to identify early indicators of cardiomyopathy and possible therapeutic targets, and to improve guidelines for diagnosis and surveillance.</p>



<p>For Dr. Di Florio, who is continuing his research as a postdoctoral fellow at Mayo Clinic, sex differences are now part of his thinking as a researcher and are how he'll evaluate data in future studies. </p>



<p>"The approach has the benefit of more precisely describing mechanisms of disease," he says. "It also has far-reaching sociological implications for how to more justly study and treat disease. It's information we absolutely need to address the biological differences that affect how frequently disease occurs, how severe the damage is and how well the body handles injury."</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/teasing-apart-sex-differences-in-heart-disease/">Teasing apart sex differences in heart disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/extracellular-vesicles-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/extracellular-vesicles-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Damian Di Florio]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Danielle Beetler]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. DeLisa Fairweather]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Emily Whelan]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Benefits of an active workstation</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-benefits-of-an-active-workstation/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 14:19:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=387650</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>For the millions of people who sit at a desk for long hours at a time, day after day, you may want to stand up for this. Mayo Clinic research shows that using an active workstation can help you move more and think better at work — without affecting your job. Sitting too much at work or home [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-benefits-of-an-active-workstation/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Benefits of an active workstation</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>For the millions of people who sit at a desk for long hours at a time, day after day, you may want to stand up for this.<br><br>Mayo Clinic <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-finds-active-workstations-may-improve-cognitive-performance/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">research</a> shows that using an active workstation can help you move more and think better at work — without affecting your job. Sitting too much at work or home can increase your risk of certain diseases, says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/lopez-jimenez-francisco-m-d-m-s/bio-20053705?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Francisco Lopez-Jimenez,</a> a Mayo Clinic cardiologist and senior author of a <a href="https://www.ahajournals.org/doi/10.1161/JAHA.123.031228" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> on the topic. Hear why he says using active workstations boosts brain power and can cut down on sitting time at work. </p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/y5rcORVH1E4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubey5rcORVH1E4"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Benefits of an active workstation" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/y5rcORVH1E4?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:59) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/SCRIPT-MCM-Benefits-of-an-active-workstation.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script.</a></strong></p>



<p>"Sitting for eight hours or more a day is almost as bad as smoking a pack of cigarettes a day in terms of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20353124?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiovasc</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20353124?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">ular health</a> or risk," expresses Dr. Lopez-Jimenez.</p>



<p>He says not everyone can break for exercise. Having an active workstation can be a solution.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/woman-working-from-home-uses-an-under-the-desk-treadmill-at-her-standing-desk_GettyImages-1383390150_16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="A woman working from home uses an under the desk treadmill at her standing desk, active workstation" class="wp-image-385322" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/woman-working-from-home-uses-an-under-the-desk-treadmill-at-her-standing-desk_GettyImages-1383390150_16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/woman-working-from-home-uses-an-under-the-desk-treadmill-at-her-standing-desk_GettyImages-1383390150_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/woman-working-from-home-uses-an-under-the-desk-treadmill-at-her-standing-desk_GettyImages-1383390150_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/woman-working-from-home-uses-an-under-the-desk-treadmill-at-her-standing-desk_GettyImages-1383390150_16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/woman-working-from-home-uses-an-under-the-desk-treadmill-at-her-standing-desk_GettyImages-1383390150_16x9.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<p>"An active workstation could be a desk where you can just stand or stand and move around, or stand and walk, or biking or pedaling, or using a stepper," he says.</p>



<p>You can do this intermittently, alternating with sitting. Whether answering emails, video calls or working on projects, keep moving.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"It allows the user to work to be productive, and, at the same time, burn some calories," Dr. Lopez-Jimenez says.</p>



<p>And you don't have to be active all day to see the benefits.</p>



<p>"As long as you don't sit for more than three or four hours throughout the day, I think that will be a good goal," says Dr. Lopez-Jimenez.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Related posts:</strong></h3>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-tips-for-healthy-heart-from-a-mayo-clinic-cardiologist/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Tips for healthy heart from a Mayo Clinic cardiologist</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-walking-is-a-step-toward-heart-health/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Walking is a step toward heart health</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-the-importance-of-stretching-throughout-your-workday/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: The importance of stretching throughout your workday</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-benefits-of-an-active-workstation/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Benefits of an active workstation</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Active-workstation-man-bike-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Active-workstation-man-desk-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Does intermittent fasting increase heart disease risk?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-does-intermittent-fasting-increase-heart-disease-risk/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Francisco López Jiménez]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[intermittent fasting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=387964</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>For years, people have used intermittent fasting to lose unwanted pounds, while others fast for religious reasons. The popular diet trend is generally safe, but some studies suggest that time-restricted eating could cause heart problems. Dr. Francisco Lopez-Jimenez, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist, says this type of dieting isn't for everyone. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-does-intermittent-fasting-increase-heart-disease-risk/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Does intermittent fasting increase heart disease risk?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>For years, people have used intermittent fasting to lose unwanted pounds, while others fast for religious reasons. The popular diet trend is generally safe, but some <a href="https://newsroom.heart.org/news/8-hour-time-restricted-eating-linked-to-a-91-higher-risk-of-cardiovascular-death" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">studies</a> suggest that time-restricted eating could cause heart problems.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/lopez-jimenez-francisco-m-d-m-s/bio-20053705" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Francisco Lopez-Jimenez</a>, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist, says this type of dieting isn't for everyone.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/X63_bZI7maQ" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeX63bZI7maQ"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Does intermittent fasting increase heart disease risk?" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/X63_bZI7maQ?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:57) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/SCRIPT-jthEDITS_Intermittent-fasting.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>There are several ways to do intermittent fasting. The 16:8 method is popular. This involves eating during an eight-hour window daily. Many dieters do this by skipping breakfast.</p>



<p>"It actually became popular because studies on fruit flies show that when you restrict the calories, the flies will actually live longer. But we are not flies," says Dr. Lopez-Jimenez.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/an-assortment-of-foods-included-in-a-diabetes-diet-fruits-and-vegetables-fish-nuts-legumes-whole-grain-on-a-white-wooden-surface-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="an assortment of foods included in a diabetes diet - fruits and vegetables, fish, nuts, legumes, whole grain - on a white wooden surface" class="wp-image-177358" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/an-assortment-of-foods-included-in-a-diabetes-diet-fruits-and-vegetables-fish-nuts-legumes-whole-grain-on-a-white-wooden-surface-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/an-assortment-of-foods-included-in-a-diabetes-diet-fruits-and-vegetables-fish-nuts-legumes-whole-grain-on-a-white-wooden-surface-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/an-assortment-of-foods-included-in-a-diabetes-diet-fruits-and-vegetables-fish-nuts-legumes-whole-grain-on-a-white-wooden-surface-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Many people use the 16:8 intermittent fasting method.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Time-restrictive dieting can promote weight loss, improve insulin sensitivity, and reduce inflammation. However, some research shows this practice could possibly increase cardiovascular risks.</p>



<p>"This recent study actually showed that those people practicing intermittent fasting are twice as likely of dying from heart disease or dying in general than those who don't practice this," explains Dr. Lopez-Jimenez. The reasons behind the risk factors are unclear. Before trying intermittent fasting, it's a good idea to check with your healthcare team.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The three most popular intermittent fasting methods are:</h3>



<ul>
<li>Alternate day fasting.</li>



<li>5-2 fasting. Eat normal for five days and restrict calories for two days.</li>



<li>Daily time-restricted fasting.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts</h3>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-intermittent-fasting-facts/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Intermittent fasting facts</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/managing-your-health-during-ramadan-fasting/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Managing your health during Ramadan fasting</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-does-intermittent-fasting-increase-heart-disease-risk/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Does intermittent fasting increase heart disease risk?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/04/a-young-couple-out-to-dinner-with-woman-cutting-food-on-her-plate-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/02/a-smiling-young-couple-in-the-kitchen-preparing-food-and-cooking-together-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Francisco López Jiménez]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[intermittent fasting]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Sleep and heart health</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-sleep-and-heart-health/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#socialsensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Juan Cardenas Rosales]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sleep]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386001</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Does how much you sleep affect your heart?&#160;According to the&#160;Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, adults who sleep fewer than seven hours each night are more likely to experience health problems. Dr. Juan Cardenas Rosales, an internal medicine physician at Mayo Clinic, stresses that adequate sleep is crucial for your overall well-being, including your heart [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-sleep-and-heart-health/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Sleep and heart health</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Does how much you sleep affect your heart?&nbsp;According to the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cdc.gov/bloodpressure/sleep.htm#:~:text=Adults%20who%20sleep%20less%20than,attack%2C%20asthma%2C%20and%20depression.&amp;text=Some%20of%20these%20health%20problems,High%20blood%20pressure." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention,</a> adults who sleep fewer than seven hours each night are more likely to experience health problems.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/cardenas-rosales-juan-c-m-d/bio-20526630?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Juan Cardenas Rosales</a>, an internal medicine physician at Mayo Clinic, stresses that adequate sleep is crucial for your overall well-being, including your heart health.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/uZf8Br9jIFI" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeuZf8Br9jIFI"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Sleep and heart health" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/uZf8Br9jIFI?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:59) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/SCRIPT-jthEDITS_MCM-Sleep-and-heart-health.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Getting a good night's sleep can give you the energy to jump-start your day and your health.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Sleeping is very important to try to prevent other chronic conditions in the future, such as diabetes, heart attacks and strokes," says Dr. Cardenas Rosales.</p>



<p>When it comes to how many hours a night adults should&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/adult-health/expert-answers/how-many-hours-of-sleep-are-enough/faq-20057898?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">sleep</a>, keep the number 7 in mind.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/03/man-waking-up-from-sleep-and-turning-off-alarm-clock-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="man waking up from sleep and turning off alarm clock" class="wp-image-85756" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/03/man-waking-up-from-sleep-and-turning-off-alarm-clock-16x9.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/03/man-waking-up-from-sleep-and-turning-off-alarm-clock-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Adults should aim for at least seven hours of sleep each night</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"It's usually recommended for you to sleep at least seven hours per night in order to allow your body to recover to be ready for the following day," he says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Practical steps to help you get better sleep</strong></h2>



<p>"Try to sleep at the same time. Try to get a schedule in which you're going to sleep at the same time and you're waking up also at the same time, that's very important," Dr. Cardenas Rosales says.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Create good sleep habits</strong></h3>



<ul>
<li>Keep the time you go to bed and the time you wake up the same every day, including weekends.</li>



<li>Stay active. Regular activity can lead to a good night's sleep.</li>



<li>Limit naps or do not nap at all.</li>



<li>Limit or do not use caffeine, alcohol and nicotine.</li>



<li>Do not eat large meals or drink a lot of fluids before bed.</li>



<li>Make your bedroom comfortable.</li>



<li>Create a relaxing bedtime ritual, such as taking a warm bath, reading or listening to soft music.</li>
</ul>



<p>"You want to set up the environment to make it easier for your body to fall asleep," he says.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h3>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/when-sleep-disorders-presage-something-more-serious/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Little by little: Small changes can lead to heart health, Mayo Clinic expert says</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/treating-sleep-apnea-made-easier-upper-airway-stimulation-therapy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Treating sleep apnea made easier: Upper airway stimulation therapy</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-are-the-stages-of-sleep/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: What are the stages of sleep?</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-sleep-and-heart-health/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Sleep and heart health</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/04/a-woman-sleeping-in-bed-and-a-man-laying-awake-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/04/a-woman-sleeping-in-bed-and-a-man-laying-awake-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#socialsensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Juan Cardenas Rosales]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Heart Health]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Sleep]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q &#038; A: Heart failure during pregnancy &#8212; what you should know</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-heart-failure-during-pregnancy-what-you-should-know/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Abby Smith]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Demilade Adedinsewo]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart failure and pregnancy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386617</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: I'm in the first trimester of my pregnancy, and I know that heart disease runs in my family. What are the warning signs of heart failure during pregnancy? How can I safely manage or prevent this? ANSWER: First of all, congratulations on being proactive and voicing your concern for yourself and your [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-heart-failure-during-pregnancy-what-you-should-know/">Mayo Clinic Q &amp; A: Heart failure during pregnancy &#8212; what you should know</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/05/shutterstock_751357126_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a pregnant African American woman resting and reading in bed" class="wp-image-192100" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/05/shutterstock_751357126_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/05/shutterstock_751357126_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/05/shutterstock_751357126_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> I'm in the first trimester of my pregnancy, and I know that heart disease runs in my family. What are the warning signs of heart failure during pregnancy? How can I safely manage or prevent this?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER: </strong>First of all, congratulations on being proactive and voicing your concern for yourself and your baby. There are some specific <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiovascular</a> conditions, such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-failure/symptoms-causes/syc-20373142" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart failure</a>, which occur during pregnancy. Symptoms from this can overlap with normal pregnancy symptoms such as swelling of the legs, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/pregnancy-week-by-week/expert-answers/swelling-during-pregnancy/faq-20058467#:~:text=Although%20mild%20foot%20and%20ankle,pressure%20is%20higher%20than%20normal." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ankles</a> and feet, and shortness of breath while lying in bed at night on your back and while walking short distances. Unfortunately, it may be difficult to tell if the symptoms are from normal pregnancy or signs of heart failure. If you are concerned about any of these symptoms, especially if they worsen, please discuss them with your healthcare team early on, and they can determine if any testing might be needed.</p>



<p>During pregnancy, we recommend the same things that we would if a woman were not pregnant, which is following all the guidelines to ensure ideal or optimal cardiovascular health. Don't smoke, eat a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/pregnancy-week-by-week/in-depth/pregnancy-nutrition/art-20045082#:~:text=During%20pregnancy%2C%20the%20basic%20principles,lean%20protein%20and%20healthy%20fats." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">healthy diet</a> and maintain a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/pregnancy-week-by-week/in-depth/pregnancy-weight-gain/art-20044360">healthy weight</a> (which is somewhat different for pregnancy because there is a normal amount of weight gain expected). Getting enough <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/womens-wellness-sleep-tips-during-pregnancy/">sleep</a> is also important. Seven to eight hours of sleep at night is recommended for ideal heart health. You'll want to make sure that you're getting specific things checked by your healthcare team during pregnancy, including your <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/pregnancy-week-by-week/in-depth/pregnancy/art-20046098#:~:text=High%20blood%20pressure%20during%20pregnancy%20poses%20the%20following%20risks%3A,birth%20weight%20or%20premature%20birth." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">blood pressure</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/glucose-tolerance-test/about/pac-20394296#:~:text=Gestational%20diabetes,-If%20you're&amp;text=At%20Mayo%20Clinic%2C%20if%20your,be%20diagnosed%20with%20gestational%20diabetes." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">blood glucose</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/cholesterol-test/about/pac-20384601" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">blood lipids</a>. If treatment is needed, act on it as quickly as possible.</p>



<p>We also get questions about <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/pregnancy-week-by-week/in-depth/pregnancy-exercises/art-20546799#:~:text=Staying%20active%20during%20pregnancy%20can,a%20well%2Drounded%20exercise%20program." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">exercise for pregnant women</a>. If you were exercising before getting pregnant, it is usually safe to continue the same level of activity that you had before pregnancy. If you were not exercising before pregnancy and want to start an exercise program, it's important to check in with your healthcare team first. Start small and slow — don't push yourself too quickly.</p>



<p>Heart failure can be challenging to diagnose during pregnancy. We also know that a delay in the diagnosis of heart failure during this time also contributes significantly to the risk of dying from heart failure. Currently, there is no recommended single test to identify heart failure during pregnancy. The diagnosis often requires your healthcare team to assess your symptoms in addition to other clinical signs and consider testing which may include an <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ekg/about/pac-20384983" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">electrocardiogram (ECG or EKG)</a>, blood test, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/chest-x-rays/about/pac-20393494" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chest X-ray</a> and a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/echocardiogram/about/pac-20393856" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart ultrasound</a>. This is why we are working on a research study that utilizes <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/ai-cardiology/overview/ovc-20486648" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">artificial intelligence</a> to analyze data from an ECG to predict the likelihood of cardiac dysfunction or heart failure. This test is simple, readily available in most clinics, rapid (can be done within 10-30 seconds) and, most importantly, safe for you and your baby. The test provides a prediction that can tell you if a woman is at high risk for heart failure or not.</p>



<p>Based on our preliminary studies, we have evidence showing this test is very effective. If we can demonstrate its usefulness in larger research studies, we believe that this test can lead to a major shift in how we care for pregnant and postpartum women. <em><strong>— </strong></em><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/adedinsewo-demilade-a-m-b-ch-b/bio-20502753" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Demilade Adedinsewo, M.B., Ch.B.</strong></a><strong><em>, Cardiovascular Medicine, </em></strong><em><strong>Mayo Clinic, Jacksonville, Florida</strong></em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-heart-failure-during-pregnancy-what-you-should-know/">Mayo Clinic Q &amp; A: Heart failure during pregnancy &#8212; what you should know</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/05/shutterstock_751357126_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/05/shutterstock_751357126_Fotor-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Demilade Adedinsewo]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Heart failure and pregnancy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&#038;A: Coronary calcium scan evaluates heart disease and stroke risk</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-coronary-calcium-scan-evaluates-heart-disease-and-stroke-risk/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Barber Lindquist]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 10:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[coronary calcium]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Regis Fernandes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386598</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: I recently had a CAT scan of my chest as an evaluation for pneumonia. I didn’t have pneumonia, but I got an unexpected high calcium score in my coronary arteries. Does the calcium I eat affect this? I thought calcium was related to bone health? Now I'm being evaluated for my risk [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-coronary-calcium-scan-evaluates-heart-disease-and-stroke-risk/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Coronary calcium scan evaluates heart disease and stroke risk</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Scan-3-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Male technician prepares woman for a coronary calcium scan, photograph, cardiovascular, heart, photograph, shot by Mike Clayton" class="wp-image-380936" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Scan-3-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Scan-3-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Scan-3-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Scan-3-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Scan-3-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> I recently had a CAT scan of my chest as an evaluation for pneumonia. I didn’t have pneumonia, but I got an unexpected high calcium score in my coronary arteries. Does the calcium I eat affect this? I thought calcium was related to bone health? Now I'm being evaluated for my risk of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart disease</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stroke/symptoms-causes/syc-20350113" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stroke</a>. Should others in my family get their calcium score?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong> A <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/heart-scan/about/pac-20384686" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">coronary calcium scan</a> is a risk assessment tool that helps your healthcare team recommend if measures are needed to lower your risk of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/coronary-artery-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350613" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">coronary artery disease</a>. The scan may show the presence of disease even before someone has symptoms, such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/chest-pain/symptoms-causes/syc-20370838" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chest pain</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/symptoms/shortness-of-breath/basics/definition/sym-20050890" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">shortness of breath</a> and fatigue.</p>



<p>Calcium from the foods we eat or calcium supplements do not have a significant impact on coronary artery calcification.</p>



<p>A coronary calcium scan predicts your amount of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/arteriosclerosis-atherosclerosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20350569" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">atherosclerosis</a>, which is cholesterol and other substances that build up and narrow your arteries and can potentially cause a blood clot. Calcium is present in this buildup, called coronary plaque. The more calcium you have in your coronary arteries, the more plaque you have. The more plaque, the higher your risk for coronary artery disease.</p>



<p>The coronary calcium scan starts with a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ct-scan/about/pac-20393675" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CT scan</a> of your chest that measures calcification in the arteries that feed your heart. It's typically a one-time test that combines a series of X-ray images of your body. If calcification is found, we usually don't repeat the test. If zero calcification is found, we would repeat the scan a few years later to see if the score changes.</p>



<p>Scores must be interpreted in the context of a person's age and other individual risk factors. For the most part, when calcium gets in your arteries, it stays there; it doesn't get removed. But by lowering your cholesterol level through <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-cholesterol/in-depth/cholesterol/art-20045192" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">diet</a> or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-cholesterol/in-depth/statins/art-20045772" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">medications</a>, the cholesterol gets removed and the plaque stabilizes.</p>



<p>Nowadays a calcium score can be derived from any chest CT scan, if no contrast dye is used. In your case, a chest CT scan for pneumonia also showed a high calcium score, even though that was not the initial intent of the test. I commend your healthcare team for using your calcium result to offer you follow-up assessment and possible treatment based on your risk of a heart attack or stroke.</p>



<p>Certain people do not need to get their calcium score. For example, for people who already take a cholesterol medication or who have had a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/coronary-angioplasty/about/pac-20384761" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stent</a> or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/coronary-bypass-surgery/about/pac-20384589" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">coronary artery bypass surgery</a>, a calcium score is not needed. In those situations, they already are taking steps to reduce their risk.</p>



<p>People with a family history of heart disease may want to discuss a coronary calcium scan with their healthcare specialist. For example, if you have first-degree relatives who have had <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-attack/symptoms-causes/syc-20373106" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart attacks</a>, but your cholesterol is not high, a superficial risk assessment may say you're at low risk. A calcium score is going to be able to evaluate risk more precisely and indicate if additional testing should be done. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/fernandes-regis-i-m-d/bio-20305254" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em><strong>Regis Fernandes, M.D.</strong></em></a><em>,<strong> Cardiovascular Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Phoenix</strong></em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-coronary-calcium-scan-evaluates-heart-disease-and-stroke-risk/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Coronary calcium scan evaluates heart disease and stroke risk</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Scan-3-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Scan-1-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[coronary calcium]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Regis Fernandes]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Preventing stroke</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-preventing-stroke/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Osiadacz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blood pressue]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Stephen English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[preventing stroke and heart attack]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stroke]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=385943</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>May is National Stroke Awareness Month, and as part of everyday awareness, Mayo Clinic healthcare professionals suggest reducing stroke risk and knowing the signs. A stroke happens every 40 seconds in the U.S., and the likelihood of stroke increases with age, according to the National Institutes of Health. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute Journalists: Broadcast-quality [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-preventing-stroke/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Preventing stroke</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>May is National <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stroke/symptoms-causes/syc-20350113?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stroke</a> Awareness Month, and as part of everyday awareness, Mayo Clinic healthcare professionals suggest reducing stroke risk and knowing the signs. A stroke happens every <a href="https://www.nih.gov/about-nih/what-we-do/nih-turning-discovery-into-health/our-biggest-health-challenges/heart-disease-stroke" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">40 seconds</a> in the U.S., and the likelihood of stroke increases with age, according to the National Institutes of Health.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wl7U_3jTpAQ" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidwl7U3jTpAQampfeature"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Preventing stroke" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wl7U_3jTpAQ?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:00) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Mayo-Clinic-Minute-Preventing-stroke_script.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Preventing a stroke is a crucial aspect of healthcare, as about 80% of all strokes are preventable. The focus is on managing risk factors to reduce the long-term risk of stroke.</p>



<p>A stroke results from a blocked or torn blood vessel that decreases blood flow to the brain. In the U.S., stroke is a leading cause of death and disability.</p>



<p>“Because about 80% of all strokes are preventable, we really focus on prevention,” says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/english-stephen-w-jr-m-d-m-b-a/bio-20491968?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Stephen English</a>, a Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/neurology/home/orc-20117057?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">neurologist</a>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Preventing stroke risks</h2>



<p>Tips for lowering stroke risk include maintaining blood pressure under 130/80 and keeping cholesterol and blood glucose at appropriate levels.</p>



<p>"(Other modifiable risks include) things like smoking cessation, treatment of sleep apnea with a CPAP device, and some other potential treatments," he says. "We want to make sure that the risk factors are mitigated to help reduce the long-term risk of stroke."</p>



<p>There are risk factors for stroke that cannot be changed. These include age, sex, race and family history. “There are four nonmodifiable risk factors we typically think about. The first is age, so age greater than 55; males; people that have a family history of prior stroke; and then people that are of African American descent,” says Dr. English.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-preventing-stroke/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Preventing stroke</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/stroke2-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/04/stroke2-1200x628.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[blood pressue]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Stephen English]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[preventing stroke and heart attack]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Stroke]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q &#038; A: What is hypertrophic cardiomyopathy?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-what-is-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Barber Lindquist]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 10:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Said Alsidawi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hypertrophic cardiomyopathy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386586</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: I've heard from some of my relatives that heart disease runs in our family, so I've been reading a lot about different conditions. I can barely pronounce it, but what is hypertrophic cardiomyopathy? ANSWER: It is a mouthful. Let's break it down a little. Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM) is a condition where the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-what-is-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy/">Mayo Clinic Q &amp; A: What is hypertrophic cardiomyopathy?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="711" height="400" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/04/medical-illustration-of-heart-with-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy-16x9-2.jpg" alt="medical illustration of heart with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy" class="wp-image-303262" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/04/medical-illustration-of-heart-with-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy-16x9-2.jpg 711w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/04/medical-illustration-of-heart-with-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy-16x9-2-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 711px) 100vw, 711px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> I've heard from some of my relatives that heart disease runs in our family, so I've been reading a lot about different conditions. I can barely pronounce it, but what is hypertrophic cardiomyopathy?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong> It is a mouthful. Let's break it down a little. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy/symptoms-causes/syc-20350198" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</a> (HCM) is a condition where the heart (cardio) muscle (myopathy) becomes thickened (hypertrophied). HCM is the most common type of genetic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cardiomyopathy/symptoms-causes/syc-20370709" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiomyopathy</a>. Patients are born with a gene that makes the heart muscle thicker than it should be.</p>



<p>HCM can be a silent disease, and some people live their whole lives not knowing they have it. We sometimes find it by chance during imaging or an autopsy for a separate reason. However, some patients, at some point in their life, can start experiencing increased heart rhythm issues, which puts these patients at risk of sudden death. In many cases, the first sign of HCM can be <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/sudden-cardiac-arrest/symptoms-causes/syc-20350634" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">sudden cardiac death</a>. Making the right diagnosis at the right time is critical in this condition.</p>



<p>HCM also can create stiffness in the heart muscles and block the outflow of blood from the heart. These patients come to us with a variety of symptoms, including <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/symptoms/shortness-of-breath/basics/causes/sym-20050890" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">shortness of breath</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/chest-pain/symptoms-causes/syc-20370838" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chest pain</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/first-aid/first-aid-fainting/basics/art-20056606" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">fainting</a> or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/dizziness/symptoms-causes/syc-20371787" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dizziness</a>. It is important to seek medical attention when you have any of these symptoms. If a young athlete passes out during exercise, for example, it's important that they get checked by getting an <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ekg/about/pac-20384983" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">electrocardiogram</a> (ECG or EKG) and an <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/echocardiogram/about/pac-20393856" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">echocardiogram</a>.</p>



<p>HCM is not as rare as people think. Data suggests that 1 in 200 to 500 people worldwide have HCM. The problem is that it often goes undiagnosed or missed. Right now, in the U.S., we believe we've only diagnosed 1 out of 7 of the people who have HCM. We are trying to increase awareness in the community about this disease and make sure that healthcare teams are well educated so they don't miss the diagnosis when they look at the imaging of these patients.</p>



<p>It's important to remember that just because you carry the gene doesn't mean you will develop HCM. Some people show signs of HCM at a younger age, in their teens or 20s, while others can show signs of the disease later in life, into their 50s. Knowing your family history and paying close attention to whether anybody in the family was told they have a thick heart muscle or if a family member suddenly died at a young age are the kinds of questions that can lead to clues if you have a genetic factor for HCM.</p>



<p>At Mayo Clinic, we offer a genetic test for those suspected of having HCM and to family members of affected patients. We mail a kit to the patient's home, and they do a swab from inside the mouth and send it back. Within two weeks, we get the results back and can either confirm the diagnosis or find out if they have other diseases that may look like HCM. Genetic testing can be helpful in ruling out these other conditions.</p>



<p>My hope is for people to think about it when they see patients with abnormal heart sounds or have symptoms that might suggest this condition. When treating patients, we should always ask, "Can this be hypertrophic cardiomyopathy?" The eyes won't see what the mind doesn't know, so it's always good to have it at the back of your mind. You really can save people's lives by diagnosing it early and referring them in a timely fashion. We have a lot of new treatments that can help these patients surgically or medically, so making the right diagnosis will improve patient survival and their quality of life. <em><strong>— </strong></em><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/alsidawi-said-m-d/bio-20516525" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Said Alsidawi, M.D.</strong></a><strong><em>, Cardiovascular Medicine, Mayo Clinic</em></strong></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-what-is-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy/">Mayo Clinic Q &amp; A: What is hypertrophic cardiomyopathy?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/04/medical-illustration-of-heart-with-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/04/medical-illustration-of-heart-with-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy-16x9-2.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Said Alsidawi]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[hypertrophic cardiomyopathy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic study finds active workstations may improve cognitive performance</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-finds-active-workstations-may-improve-cognitive-performance/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Terri Malloy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2024 14:21:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Clinical Trials]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Translational Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[active workstations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cardiometabolic diseases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cognitive function]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dan Abraham Healthy Living Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Francisco López-Jiménez]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sedentary behavior]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=384985</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A recent Mayo Clinic study suggests that active workstations incorporating a walking pad, bike, stepper and/or standing desk are successful strategies for reducing sedentary time and improving mental cognition at work without reducing job performance. Extended sedentary behavior, whether at work or home, increases a person's risk of preventable chronic diseases. "Our [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-finds-active-workstations-may-improve-cognitive-performance/">Mayo Clinic study finds active workstations may improve cognitive performance</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="682" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/woman-working-from-home-uses-an-under-the-desk-treadmill-at-her-standing-desk_GettyImages-1383390150-1024x682.jpg" alt="A woman working from home uses an under the desk treadmill at her standing desk" class="wp-image-385321" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/woman-working-from-home-uses-an-under-the-desk-treadmill-at-her-standing-desk_GettyImages-1383390150-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/woman-working-from-home-uses-an-under-the-desk-treadmill-at-her-standing-desk_GettyImages-1383390150-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/woman-working-from-home-uses-an-under-the-desk-treadmill-at-her-standing-desk_GettyImages-1383390150-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/woman-working-from-home-uses-an-under-the-desk-treadmill-at-her-standing-desk_GettyImages-1383390150-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/woman-working-from-home-uses-an-under-the-desk-treadmill-at-her-standing-desk_GettyImages-1383390150.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A recent <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> study suggests that active workstations incorporating a walking pad, bike, stepper and/or standing desk are successful strategies for reducing sedentary time and improving mental cognition at work without reducing job performance. Extended sedentary behavior, whether at work or home, increases a person's risk of preventable <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/metabolic-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20351916?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chronic diseases</a>.</p>



<p>"Our findings suggest that it is feasible to blend movement with office work that previously would have been done during long periods of sitting. Active workstations may offer a way to potentially improve cognitive performance and overall health, simply by moving at work," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/lopez-jimenez-francisco-m-d-m-s/bio-00028001" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Francisco Lopez-Jimenez, M.D.</a>, a preventive cardiologist at Mayo Clinic and senior author of the study.</p>



<p>The research involved 44 participants in a randomized clinical trial where four office settings were evaluated over four consecutive days at Mayo Clinic's Dan Abraham Healthy Living Center. Study findings are published in the <a href="https://www.ahajournals.org/doi/10.1161/JAHA.123.031228" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Journal of the American Heart Association</a>. The settings included a stationary or sitting station on the first day, followed by three active workstations (standing, walking or using a stepper) in a randomized order. Researchers analyzed participants' neurocognitive function based on 11 assessments that evaluated reasoning, short-term memory and concentration. Fine motor skills were assessed through an online typing speed test and other tests. &nbsp;</p>



<p>When participants used the active workstations, their brain function either improved or stayed the same, and their typing speed slowed down only a bit. However, the accuracy of their typing was not affected.&nbsp;The study revealed improved reasoning scores when standing, stepping and walking as compared with sitting.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Being sedentary is the new smoking when it comes to your cardiovascular health, and office workers may spend a large part of their eight-hour workday sitting at a computer screen and keyboard. These findings indicate that there are more ways to do that work while remaining productive and mentally sharp. We would do well to consider an active workstation in the prescription for prevention and treatment of conditions like obesity, cardiovascular disease and diabetes," says Dr. Lopez-Jimenez.</p>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video b-roll of active workstations can be found in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network."</strong></p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> <br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-finds-active-workstations-may-improve-cognitive-performance/">Mayo Clinic study finds active workstations may improve cognitive performance</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/woman-working-from-home-uses-an-under-the-desk-treadmill-at-her-standing-desk_GettyImages-1383390150_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/woman-working-from-home-uses-an-under-the-desk-treadmill-at-her-standing-desk_GettyImages-1383390150_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[active workstations]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cardiometabolic diseases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cognitive function]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dan Abraham Healthy Living Center]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Francisco López-Jiménez]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[sedentary behavior]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: High blood pressure hurts the kidneys</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-high-blood-pressure-hurts-the-kidneys/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 13:58:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chronic kidney disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Ivan Porter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[high blood pressure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hypertension]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kidney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nephrology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=384102</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Hypertension, also known as high blood pressure, is a common problem that affects the body's arteries. If you have high blood pressure, the heart has to work harder to pump blood. In general, hypertension is a blood pressure reading of 130/80 or higher. Dr. Ivan Porter II, a Mayo Clinic nephrologist, says high blood pressure [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-high-blood-pressure-hurts-the-kidneys/">Mayo Clinic Minute: High blood pressure hurts the kidneys</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-pressure/symptoms-causes/syc-20373410?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hypertension</a>, also known as high blood pressure, is a common problem that affects the body's arteries. If you have high blood pressure, the heart has to work harder to pump blood.</p>



<p>In general, hypertension is a blood pressure reading of 130/80 or higher. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/porter-ivan-e-ii-m-d/bio-20113830?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Ivan Porter II</a>, a Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/nephrology-hypertension/sections/overview/ovc-20464571?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">nephrologist</a>, says high blood pressure can lead to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart disease</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stroke/symptoms-causes/syc-20350113?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stroke</a> and other serious health problems, including <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/chronic-kidney-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20354521?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chronic kidney disease</a>.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/WYFCCWk64NQ" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeWYFCCWk64NQ"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: High blood pressure hurts the kidneys" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/WYFCCWk64NQ?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:00) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/MCM_High-blood-pressure-hurts-the-kidneys.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>When you think of high blood pressure, you probably already know that it can cause cardiovascular diseases. But that's not all.</p>



<p>"It also can lead to chronic kidney disease," says Dr. Porter.</p>



<p>He says high blood pressure can cause the kidneys' blood vessels to weaken and damage the kidneys.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="637" height="358" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/12/medicalillustration-of-healthy-and-diseased-kidneys-16-x-9.png" alt="medical illustration of healthy and diseased kidneys" class="wp-image-178582" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/12/medicalillustration-of-healthy-and-diseased-kidneys-16-x-9.png 637w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/12/medicalillustration-of-healthy-and-diseased-kidneys-16-x-9-300x169.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 637px) 100vw, 637px" /></figure></div>


<p>"As chronic kidney disease develops, many people will develop hypertension, they seem to go hand in hand. Conversely, people with hypertension develop chronic kidney disease as well," says Dr. Porter. "Control of high blood pressure is one of the most important things we can do when someone has chronic kidney disease."</p>



<p>And how you control it, mostly involves lifestyle changes.</p>



<p>"The thing about high blood pressure is it responds to many of the things we do in our lifestyle: regular exercise, avoiding processed foods, reduction of our sodium intake, more fruits and vegetables in our regular diet," says Dr. Porter. "Sometimes those lifestyle changes aren't enough. And these are the patients that need medications to help with blood pressure control. But we can make a huge impact with the decisions we make in our lifestyle to control blood pressure."</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h3>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-black-americans-are-at-higher-risk-of-chronic-kidney-disease/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Why Black Americans are at higher risk of chronic kidney disease</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-can-extra-salt-hurt-your-kidneys/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Can extra salt hurt your kidneys?</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-high-blood-pressure-hurts-the-kidneys/">Mayo Clinic Minute: High blood pressure hurts the kidneys</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/nurse-visiting-senior-male-patient-at-home-taking-blood-pressure-diversity-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/nurse-visiting-senior-male-patient-at-home-taking-blood-pressure-diversity-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[chronic kidney disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Ivan Porter]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[high blood pressure]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Hypertension]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Kidney]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[nephrology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>