<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org">

<channel>
	<title>Cardiovascular - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cardiovascular-2/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml">
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cardiovascular-2/
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastbuilddate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 19:59:19 +0000</lastbuilddate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updateperiod>
	hourly	</sy:updateperiod>
	<sy:updatefrequency>
	1	</sy:updatefrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Research study shows the cost-effectiveness of AI-enhanced heart failure screening</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/research-study-shows-the-cost-effectiveness-of-ai-enhanced-heart-failure-screening/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Terri Malloy]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 15:25:11 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[AI and Digital Health]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[AI]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[AI-ECG]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[artificial intelligence]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiology]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Peter Noseworthy]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Xiaoxi Yao]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[ECG]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Electrocardiogram]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Heart Failure]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Kern Center]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Low Ejection Fraction]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=397408</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Clinicians at Mayo Clinic can use artificial intelligence (AI) tools to effectively screen patients for a weak heart pump via a simple electrocardiogram (ECG). A new study addresses the next question: Is it good value for the money spent?&nbsp; ROCHESTER, Minn. &nbsp;— Earlier research showed that primary care clinicians using AI-ECG tools identified more unknown […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/research-study-shows-the-cost-effectiveness-of-ai-enhanced-heart-failure-screening/">Research study shows the cost-effectiveness of AI-enhanced heart failure screening</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"--><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1920" height="1080" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Sully-ECG-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-397425" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Sully-ECG-16x9-1.jpg 1920w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Sully-ECG-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Sully-ECG-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Sully-ECG-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Sully-ECG-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px">



<p><em>Clinicians at Mayo Clinic can use artificial intelligence (AI) tools to effectively screen patients for a weak heart pump via a simple electrocardiogram (ECG). A new study addresses the next question: Is it good value for the money spent?&nbsp;</em></p>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. &nbsp;— <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/trial-demonstrates-early-ai-guided-detection-of-heart-disease-in-routine-practice/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Earlier research</a> showed that primary care clinicians using AI-ECG tools identified more unknown cases of a weak heart pump, also called low ejection fraction, than without AI. New <a href="https://www.mcpdigitalhealth.org/article/S2949-7612(24)00104-4/fulltext#keywords-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study findings</a> published in Mayo Clinic Proceedings: Digital Health suggest that this type of screening is also cost-effective in the long term, especially in outpatient settings.</p>



<p>Incremental <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-failure/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20373148" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">drops in heart function</a> are treatable with medication but can be hard to spot. Patients may or may not have symptoms when their heart is not pumping effectively, and doctors may not order an echocardiogram or other diagnostic test to check <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ekg/expert-answers/ejection-fraction/faq-20058286?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ejection fraction</a> unless there are symptoms. <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/noseworthy-peter-a-m-d-m-b-a/bio-20094212" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Peter Noseworthy, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist and co-author of the study, notes that using AI to catch the hidden signals of heart failure during a routine visit can mean earlier treatment for patients, delaying or stopping disease progression, and fewer related medical costs over time.</p>



<p>According to the study, the cost-effectiveness ratio of using AI-ECG was $27,858 per quality-adjusted life year — a measure of the quality of life and years lived. The program was especially cost-effective in outpatient settings, with a much lower cost-effectiveness ratio of $1,651 per quality-adjusted life year.</p>



<p>The researchers studied the economic impact of using the AI-ECG tool by using real-world information from 22,000 participants in the established <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-021-01335-4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">EAGLE trial</a> and following which patients had weak heart pumps and which did not. They simulated the progression of disease in the longer term, assigning values for the health burden on patients and the resulting effect on economic value.</p>



<p>"We categorized patients as either AI-ECG positive, meaning we would recommend further testing for low ejection fraction, or AI-ECG negative with no further tests needed. Then we followed the normal path of care and looked at what that would cost. Did they have an echocardiogram? Did they stay healthy or develop heart failure later and need hospitalization? We considered different scenarios, costs and patient outcomes," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/yao-xiaoxi-ph-d-m-p-h/bio-20382281" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Xiaoxi Yao, Ph.D.</a>, a professor of Health Services Research at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>Dr. Yao, who is the senior author of the study, notes that cost-effectiveness is an important aspect of the evaluation of AI technologies when considering what to implement in clinical practice.</p>



<p>"We know that earlier diagnosis can lead to better and more cost-effective treatment options. To get there, we have been establishing a framework for AI evaluation and implementation. The next step is finding ways to streamline this process so we can reduce the time and resources required for such rigorous evaluation," says Dr. Yao.</p>



<p>This study was funded by <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/about/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</a>. Mayo Clinic and some of the researchers have a financial interest in the technology referenced in this news release. Mayo Clinic will use any revenue it receives to support its not-for-profit mission in patient care, education and research.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> <br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/research-study-shows-the-cost-effectiveness-of-ai-enhanced-heart-failure-screening/">Research study shows the cost-effectiveness of AI-enhanced heart failure screening</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Sully-ECG-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Sully-ECG-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[AI]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[AI-ECG]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[artificial intelligence]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cardiology]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Peter Noseworthy]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Xiaoxi Yao]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[ECG]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Electrocardiogram]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Heart Failure]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Kern Center]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Low Ejection Fraction]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Cardiac arrest vs. heart attacks: Who is at risk?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-cardiac-arrest-vs-heart-attacks-who-is-at-risk/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Abby Smith]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 15:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Brian Shapiro]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=396850</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;What is the difference between sudden cardiac arrest and a heart attack? Who is at risk for both, and what safety measures can we take? ANSWER:&nbsp;Sudden cardiac arrest may occur in various conditions when someone, while active (playing basketball or walking with friends), collapses and passes out. Their blood pressure drops, and often […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-cardiac-arrest-vs-heart-attacks-who-is-at-risk/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Cardiac arrest vs. heart attacks: Who is at risk?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"--><img decoding="async" width="1000" height="563" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/09/a-Black-middle-aged-man-in-a-white-shirt-holding-his-hand-to-his-chest-and-leaning-against-a-wall-in-pain-short-of-breath-and-perhaps-having-a-heart-attack-16x9-1.jpg" alt="a Black middle aged man in a white shirt holding his hand to his chest and leaning against a wall in pain, short of breath and perhaps having a heart attack or cardiac arrest." class="wp-image-280127" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/09/a-Black-middle-aged-man-in-a-white-shirt-holding-his-hand-to-his-chest-and-leaning-against-a-wall-in-pain-short-of-breath-and-perhaps-having-a-heart-attack-16x9-1.jpg 1000w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/09/a-Black-middle-aged-man-in-a-white-shirt-holding-his-hand-to-his-chest-and-leaning-against-a-wall-in-pain-short-of-breath-and-perhaps-having-a-heart-attack-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/09/a-Black-middle-aged-man-in-a-white-shirt-holding-his-hand-to-his-chest-and-leaning-against-a-wall-in-pain-short-of-breath-and-perhaps-having-a-heart-attack-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px">



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong>&nbsp;What is the difference between sudden <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-what-is-cardiac-arrest/">cardiac arrest</a> and a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-attack/symptoms-causes/syc-20373106?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">heart attack</a>? Who is at risk for both, and what safety measures can we take?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong>&nbsp;Sudden cardiac arrest may occur in various conditions when someone, while active (playing basketball or walking with friends), collapses and passes out. Their blood pressure drops, and often their heart stops. This may be caused by a lethal arrhythmia, which is when the heart beats abnormally and does not efficiently pump anymore. If your heart is not pumping, blood is not getting to the brain, and that's what causes the collapse.&nbsp;</p>



<p>A&nbsp;heart attack occurs when there is a blockage, and your heart muscle is deprived of blood flow. People experience chest pains or difficulty breathing. A heart attack can sometimes cause a sudden cardiac arrest and even induce a lethal arrhythmia due to irritation from lack of oxygen and blood flow. Ventricular fibrillation and ventricular tachycardia occur when the heart is beating too fast, and it becomes dangerous. This also causes a lack of blood flow to your brain and vital organs since your heart is not pumping efficiently.&nbsp;</p>



<p>If someone is in cardiac arrest and you witness it, call 911. When calling for help, ask for an&nbsp;automated external&nbsp;defibrillator (AED) immediately. If the situation is safe to do so, perform CPR or chest compressions. If nearby, use a defibrillator on the person's chest. If an abnormal, dangerous beat is detected, the machine will appropriately shock the patient out of that rhythm. The defibrillator will give you a prompt so that if you've never done it before, you're not a medical professional or you're nervous, you can follow the instructions and it will tell you exactly what to do.</p>



<p>The overall population of those who are going to get sudden cardiac arrest is very small, but it changes based on your age and underlying medical conditions. Under 35, it is much more common to occur from an underlying&nbsp;cardiomyopathy (abnormal heart muscle). The most common type is hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, where the heart muscle is thickened in regions and is more prone to arrhythmia (an irregular heartbeat). The risk of this is 1 in 500. This is what can cause abnormal heartbeat in young athletes in high school and college.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Over 35,&nbsp;the concern switches to coronary artery disease and heart attack risk. Issues can arise&nbsp;with the heart arteries because of hypertension, family history, diabetes, tobacco use and other risk factors that may cause cholesterol-rich plaques in your heart arteries. If that plaque ruptures, there is no blood flow to the muscle, and the muscle goes into abnormal heartbeats.&nbsp;</p>



<p>People who do not exercise often and live a sedentary life can have sudden cardiac arrest. On the flip side, athletes such as triathletes and marathon runners put a large amount of pressure on their hearts. These patients are looked at more carefully. Family history of sudden cardiac arrest is an important consideration during physical examination. Exercise is critically important, not just for your overall mortality but also your mental well-being — the question is how to do it safely and who is at higher risk.</p>



<p>A 65-year-old who has been running marathons their whole life but has had open-heart surgery for coronary artery disease can continue running safely by keeping speed and capacity at a much lower heart rate. We talk to patients about how to do that. During a physical exam, doctors listen for unusual murmurs and conduct an&nbsp;electrocardiogram (EKG or ECG)&nbsp;and chest X-rays in case cardiomyopathy can be detected. Cardiopulmonary stress testing also can be performed, where a special mask is put on the face to measure oxygen and carbon dioxide. This aids healthcare teams in picking up very subtle irregularities that may signal a heart or lung abnormality.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Exercise plans are then tailored accordingly, but be sure to monitor your symptoms. If you have difficulty breathing during minimal exercise or tightness in the chest, dizziness or passing out spells, these things are concerning and warrant further testing. You can get back to exercising and doing the things you enjoy again — whether that's running a 5K or playing softball with your kids — the goal is to always do so safely.&nbsp;<em>—</em>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/shapiro-brian-p-m-d-m-a/bio-20055339"><strong><em>Brian Shapiro, M.D.</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Cardiovascular Medicine,&nbsp;Mayo Clinic, Jacksonville, Florida</em></strong><em></em></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-cardiac-arrest-vs-heart-attacks-who-is-at-risk/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Cardiac arrest vs. heart attacks: Who is at risk?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_1028913613_Fotor-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_1028913613_Fotor-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Brian Shapiro]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: A cardiologist’s tips for a healthy heart</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-tips-for-healthy-heart-from-a-mayo-clinic-cardiologist/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Deb Balzer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 15:30:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Francisco López Jiménez]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[heart heatlh]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=375604</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Today's age of quick access to information, constant updates on medical advancements and health recommendations make it easy to get overwhelmed. But when it comes to maintaining a healthy heart,&nbsp;Dr. Francisco Lopez-Jimenez, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist, has some important and simple tips he'd like to share with everyone. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute Journalists: Broadcast-quality […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-tips-for-healthy-heart-from-a-mayo-clinic-cardiologist/">Mayo Clinic Minute: A cardiologist’s tips for a healthy heart</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<p-->Today's age of quick access to information, constant updates on medical advancements and health recommendations make it easy to get overwhelmed. But when it comes to maintaining a healthy heart,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/lopez-jimenez-francisco-m-d-m-s/bio-20053705?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Francisco Lopez-Jimenez,</a> a Mayo Clinic cardiologist, has some important and simple tips he'd like to share with everyone.<p></p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/hjRWc3a5_is" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls="" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Mayo-Clinic-Minute-Cardiologists-tips-for-a-healthy-life_CLEAN_2.mp4"></video></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:05) is in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/SCRIPT-MCM-Cardiologist-tips-for-healthy-living14.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"An ounce of prevention is worth a pound of cure" is an adage that Mayo Clinic cardiologist Dr. Francisco Lopez-Jimenez says remains true today.</p>



<div class="wp-block-media-text is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/02/Francisco-Lopez-Jimenez_lab-coat-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-360607 size-full" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/02/Francisco-Lopez-Jimenez_lab-coat-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/02/Francisco-Lopez-Jimenez_lab-coat-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/02/Francisco-Lopez-Jimenez_lab-coat-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/02/Francisco-Lopez-Jimenez_lab-coat-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/02/Francisco-Lopez-Jimenez_lab-coat.jpg 1687w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p>"No matter how difficult prevention might look, it is way better than treating heart disease."</p><cite>Francisco Lopez-Jimenez, M.D.</cite></blockquote></figure>



<p></p>
</div></div>



<p>And prevention, he says, can start small by focusing on the simple things, like&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-8-heart-healthy-diet-strategies/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">diet</a>&nbsp;and exercise.</p>



<p>"Trying to eat healthier a little bit at a time, to move around through the day, avoiding sitting for too long," says Dr. Lopez-Jimenez.</p>



<p>A positive outlook also can go far in your physical well-being. Enjoy a walk with a friend, for instance.</p>



<p>"Trying to find purpose every day, and trying to give love every day, because those are some of the emotional things that we don't take care of (that) also affect the heart," he says.</p>



<p>And finally, he says if you are prescribed medication for high&nbsp;blood pressure or high&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-cholesterol/symptoms-causes/syc-20350800?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cholesterol</a>, avoid the risk of a heart attack and follow your doctor's orders.</p>



<p>"Take those medications, check your numbers and be sure that all those factors are well under control," Dr. Lopez-Jimenez says.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Tips and strategies for a heart-healthy diet</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Eat more vegetables and fruits for vitamins, minerals, and heart health.</li>



<li>Select whole grains for fiber and nutrients.</li>



<li>Choose healthy fats, such as monounsaturated and polyunsaturated options.</li>



<li>Opt for low-fat proteins, including lean meat, poultry, fish and legumes.</li>



<li>Reduce salt intake to lower blood pressure.</li>



<li>Control portion sizes to manage calorie intake.</li>



<li>Plan daily menus emphasizing vegetables, fruits, whole grains, lean proteins and good fats.</li>



<li>Enjoy occasional treats in moderation without derailing your healthy eating plan.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-walking-is-a-step-toward-heart-health/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Walking is a step toward heart health</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-who-benefits-from-taking-statins/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Who benefits from taking statins?</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-tips-for-a-heart-healthy-sandwich-2/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Tips for a heart-healthy sandwich</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-tips-for-healthy-heart-from-a-mayo-clinic-cardiologist/">Mayo Clinic Minute: A cardiologist’s tips for a healthy heart</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/02/woman-physician-with-stethoscope-holding-a-red-heart-1x1-square.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/02/woman-physician-with-stethoscope-holding-a-red-heart-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Francisco López Jiménez]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[heart heatlh]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Grateful heart still ticking 65 years after repair</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/grateful-heart-still-ticking-65-years-after-repair/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[amymittlestadt]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 14:30:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Children's Center]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jonathan Johnson]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Joseph Dearani]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Patient Story]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=397164</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Celebrating advancements of cardiac care&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Sixty-five years after her open-heart surgery — a procedure that was pioneered in the U.S. just years before she needed it — Andree Jacob's heart is still ticking strong. She is a living testament to the importance of medical innovation and the lifetime of gratitude that comes with it. When […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/grateful-heart-still-ticking-65-years-after-repair/">Grateful heart still ticking 65 years after repair</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Andree_beach_16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-397167" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Andree_beach_16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Andree_beach_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Andree_beach_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Andree_beach_16x9.jpg 1440w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Andree Jacob at the beach</figcaption>



<p><em><strong>Celebrating advancements of cardiac care&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</em></p>



<p>Sixty-five years after her open-heart surgery — a procedure that was pioneered in the U.S. just years before she needed it — Andree Jacob's heart is still ticking strong. She is a living testament to the importance of medical innovation and the lifetime of gratitude that comes with it.</p>



<p>When Andree, 72, from the Canadian province of Quebec, was a child, her mother noticed she caught colds easily and withdrew to rest often while playing. Her heart would beat rapidly, visible even through her clothes.</p>



<p>Concerned, her mother took her to the doctor multiple times and insisted on testing until a medical team in Montreal discovered Andree had atrial septal defect (ASD). This heart condition, a hole between the upper heart chambers, allows an increased amount of blood through the lungs. This defect may cause shortness of breath; tiredness; swelling of the legs, feet or belly area; and irregular heartbeats, skipped heartbeats, or feelings of a quick, pounding or fluttering heartbeat.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The surgery that saved Andree's life</h2>



<p>In the fall of 1958, Andree was scheduled for heart surgery in Montreal, but the operation was postponed. Her father's cousin, Dr. Camille Dufault, an internist involved in research in Canada, arranged for her to have surgery at the renowned Mayo Clinic.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="565" height="318" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Andree_child_image_16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-397170" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Andree_child_image_16x9.jpg 565w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Andree_child_image_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 565px) 100vw, 565px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Andree Jacob as a child</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>In May 1959, at 7 years old, Andree and her father traveled to Rochester, Minnesota, for surgery.</p>



<p>"I remember the surgery day vividly. My father left me in the care of two nuns before the operation, and I felt abandoned when he didn't follow me into the operating room. I only spoke French at the time," recalls Andree.</p>



<p>Andree's father, a farmer, wrote letters to her mother for the 28 days Andree stayed at Mayo Clinic. He reassured his wife that Andree was doing well, while also reminding her to tend to the dairy cows, pigs and chickens.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A life full of gratitude and resilience</h2>



<p>Returning home in June 1959, Andree resumed life with a new vigor. She grew into an active adult who married her American husband in 1974. Together they built a beautiful life with their two daughters and their families. Other than a more recent medication for heart palpitations, her heart has remained healthy and strong.</p>



<p>"On this year's heart anniversary, the number 65 resonated deeply with me, reminding me of how far I've come and how fortunate I am," she recalls. "The courage my parents showed in pursuing the best possible care for me is something I will always honor. They placed their faith in a medical team across the border."</p>



<p>"I am overwhelmed by gratitude — for the skilled hands of the surgeons at Mayo Clinic, for my parents' unwavering support and for the beautiful life I have lived since. Every year, we reflect on the miracles and the love that have shaped our lives," she continues.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">History of cardiac innovation</h2>



<p>In the 1950s — the time of Andree's surgery — cardiac surgery was still developing. <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/article/S0025-6196(11)63095-4/pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. John W. Kirklin</a>, the Mayo Clinic surgeon who performed Andree's life-changing surgery, was a pioneer in modern-day cardiac care. As a young surgeon supported by a multidisciplinary team of physicians and technicians in Rochester, Dr. Kirklin envisioned using a mechanical pump-oxygenator to support the circulation while working inside the heart.</p>



<p>Dr. Kirklin’s persistence paid off in 1955 with the first successful use of the heart-lung machine at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>"The only way to address structural abnormalities inside the heart, like ASD, was to stop the heart so you could go inside it. We needed a heart-lung machine to support the patient's bodily systems," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/dearani-joseph-a-m-d/bio-20053326" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Joseph Dearani</a>, cardiovascular surgeon at Mayo Clinic. "It was a revolution and paved the way for the whole future of cardiac surgery."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A flutter of innovation</h2>



<p>The first 50 years of cardiac surgery were marked by the introduction of new procedures, especially for congenital heart disease.</p>



<p>The next 50 years have brought many significant advances in cardiology and cardiac surgery:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Heart-lung machines with numerous safeguards and alarms to address issues immediately during surgery.</li>



<li>Cardiac catheterization labs (cath labs) with technology that allows doctors to access the heart through a peripheral vessel or another vein, avoiding open-heart surgery and enabling same-day discharge.</li>



<li>Sophisticated imaging techniques like echocardiography, CT scans and MRI that provide detailed road maps for surgery, allowing surgeons to create 3D models and practice operations on rare anomalies before entering the operating room.</li>



<li>Advanced anesthesia techniques that enable many patients to have their breathing tubes removed immediately after surgery, along with improved pain management protocols aimed at "painless heart surgery."</li>



<li>Robotic heart surgery, minimally invasive surgery and thoracoscopic surgery that use small incisions and cameras, resulting in shorter hospital stays, reduced pain and quicker recovery.</li>



<li>Advanced medications administered around the time of surgery to stabilize patients during the procedure and promote faster recovery.</li>



<li>More aggressive care plans that encourage patients to walk the halls with rehabilitation staff shortly after surgery, enhancing healing and enabling remarkable activity even the day after surgery.</li>



<li>Improved understanding of technologies that help experts enhance patient tolerance to surgery and speed recovery.</li>
</ul>



<p></p>



<p>"So many of the surgeries that we used to perform wouldn't require surgery now because we can treat the patients noninvasively in the cath lab," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/johnson-jonathan-n-m-d/bio-20055043" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Jonathan Johnson</a>, pediatric cardiologist and chair of the Division of Pediatric Cardiology at Mayo Clinic. "Now we routinely replace valves, insert stents — things that once required opening the chest. Many of those patients don't even have to stay overnight in the hospital."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What's next: Transforming cardiac care</h2>



<p>As healthcare continues to evolve at an unprecedented rate, Mayo Clinic continues searching for ways to transform healthcare with artificial intelligence (AI), genetic screening and virtual tools.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Artificial intelligence: In the future, AI will transform how heart defects are detected and diagnosed from birth. AI will be integrated into handheld ultrasound devices and ECGs to help doctors and care teams record the heart's electrical activity more effectively across different healthcare settings and improve their accuracy. This means that signs of heart issues could be spotted much earlier, even when they're not obvious. AI also will support experts by picking up small irregularities on ECG that might suggest more complicated heart conditions, helping doctors better understand and treat heart issues early on.</li>



<li>Genetic screening: New genetic screening technologies will become a vital tool. Healthcare professionals will use genetic information to predict the risk of developing heart defects, providing crucial insights even before any symptoms appear. Collaborations with genetic researchers will refine these screenings, making them more accurate and helpful for predicting and managing heart health from earlier ages.</li>



<li>Advancement in cardiac surgery: Cardiac surgery is increasingly adopting more objective methods to assess and improve performance, focusing on communication and technical skills in the operating room. For example, Mayo Clinic, the University of Michigan, the University of Edinburgh in the U.K., and the United States Tennis Association recently received National Institutes of Health funding to use advanced video assessment techniques to analyze surgical skills in the operating room. This approach will allow surgeons to review their procedures alongside experienced colleagues, providing clearer insights into areas for improvement.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Some things never change</h2>



<p>Despite decades of medical innovation, the heart behind pediatric cardiac care at Mayo Clinic beats as strong as ever.</p>



<p>"Our team of professionals work together to do the best for each child’s situation," reflects Dr. Johnson. "It's a ballet of people working together at the same time to create this amazing performance. It's extremely humbling to be part of a field that saves and improves lives. Every day, this remarkable team has nothing but their patients on their minds — that's an incredible thing."</p>



<p>Andree couldn't agree more. "My story is not just about survival," she says. "It's about the extraordinary strength of family, the advancements in medicine and the kindness of those who care for others. It's a reminder that every day is a gift."</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/grateful-heart-still-ticking-65-years-after-repair/">Grateful heart still ticking 65 years after repair</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Andree_beach_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Andree_beach_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jonathan Johnson]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Joseph Dearani]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Patient Story]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Home blood pressure monitoring benefits Dan Knapp</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/home-blood-pressure-monitoring-benefits-dan-knapp/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Joel Streed]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 11:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Christopher Roberts]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Patient Story]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=396635</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->At 77, Dan Knapp prioritizes his health. "For the past twelve years, I've scheduled annual visits to monitor my conditions," says Knapp, a longtime patient at&nbsp;Mayo Clinic Health System&nbsp;in&nbsp;Eau Claire, Wisconsin. "It gives me peace of mind, knowing I'm doing everything I can to stay ahead of any potential issues." During these visits, Dan meets […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/home-blood-pressure-monitoring-benefits-dan-knapp/">Home blood pressure monitoring benefits Dan Knapp</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Getty-home-bp-monitor-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396638" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Getty-home-bp-monitor-16x9-1.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Getty-home-bp-monitor-16x9-1-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Getty Images</figcaption>



<p></p>



<p>At 77, Dan Knapp prioritizes his health. "For the past twelve years, I've scheduled annual visits to monitor my conditions," says Knapp, a longtime patient at&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System</a>&nbsp;in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/eau-claire" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Eau Claire</a>, Wisconsin. "It gives me peace of mind, knowing I'm doing everything I can to stay ahead of any potential issues."</p>



<p>During these visits, Dan meets with his primary care team to discuss medication and lifestyle changes that may affect his well-being. The team also monitors his chronic conditions, which include diabetes and high blood pressure.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Why your blood pressure matters</h2>



<p>Having high blood pressure increases the risk of heart disease and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/who-is-most-at-risk-for-a-stroke" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stroke</a>, which are the leading causes of death in the U.S.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/know-your-numbers-blood-pressure" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Blood pressure</a>&nbsp;measures how hard blood pushes against arteries as it moves through the body. Over time, elevated or high blood pressure makes the heart work harder and less efficiently. It can also damage the eyes, kidneys and blood vessels.</p>



<p>Blood pressure readings fall into four categories: Normal, elevated, hypertension stage 1 and hypertension stage 2. Knowing your blood pressure numbers is critical for maintaining or improving your health.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Increasing convenience with at-home monitoring</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/6-ways-to-manage-high-blood-pressure" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Controlling high blood pressure</a>&nbsp;requires consistent effort from both patients and healthcare teams. Historically, this has involved in-person visits for regular monitoring.</p>



<p>However, for many people, especially those in rural areas, the inconvenience of these visits can be a barrier to effective care.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A home blood pressure monitoring program offers people more control and convenience when tracking their readings.</strong></h3>



<p>Based on recommendations from the American Medical Association and American Heart Association, people are educated on proper techniques for using their own blood pressure monitors at home.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Monitors that allow upper arm blood pressure and ensure proper cuff size have the most accurate readings.</strong></h3>



<p>Readings can then be manually entered into the patient portal or through Bluetooth-enabled devices.</p>



<p>"Home blood pressure monitoring is a terrific option for our patients," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/christopher-roberts-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Christopher Roberts, M.D.</a>, a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/primary-care" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Primary Care</a>&nbsp;physician in&nbsp;Eau Claire. "Mr. Knapp was motivated to get his blood pressure under control, which made him an excellent candidate for this program. It has saved him the cost and inconvenience of driving 80 miles to our clinic."</p>



<p>"The whole process is incredibly user-friendly — even for a non-tech savvy guy like me," Dan says. "Not all my readings are perfect, but when they're not, I know my care team will be on top of it."</p>



<p>If the blood pressure readings show concerning trends over time, your healthcare team can recommend lifestyle or&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/blood-pressure" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dietary changes</a>&nbsp;and make medication adjustments.</p>



<p>For Dan, this enhanced access has paid off. His most recent blood pressure was 125/69, a dramatic improvement from his starting point.</p>



<p>"Overall, I’m a healthier person because of this process," says Dan. "As I've gotten older, my health has become more important — you can't wait until things go wrong to fix them. I want to live a long time, and this is a way I can do that."</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/patient-stories/home-blood-pressure-monitoring-benefits-dan-knapp" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/home-blood-pressure-monitoring-benefits-dan-knapp/">Home blood pressure monitoring benefits Dan Knapp</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Getty-home-bp-monitor-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Getty-home-bp-monitor-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Christopher Roberts]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Patient Story]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>What makes oatmeal the ideal breakfast for heart health and weight loss?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-makes-oatmeal-the-ideal-breakfast-for-heart-health-and-weight-loss/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Joel Streed]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 11:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Romi Londre]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=396647</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Oatmeal is a nutritious, inexpensive and versatile way to incorporate&nbsp;whole grains&nbsp;into your diet and help you start your morning off right. Oats made history when they became the first food with a Food and Drug Administration health claim label in 1997. This claim was related to&nbsp;heart health&nbsp;and showed that intake of whole oat products decreased […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-makes-oatmeal-the-ideal-breakfast-for-heart-health-and-weight-loss/">What makes oatmeal the ideal breakfast for heart health and weight loss?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/a-close-up-overhead-view-of-a-bowl-of-oatmeal-with-almonds-blueberries-and-cranberries-sprinkled-on-top-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a close-up overhead view of a bowl of oatmeal with almonds, blueberries and cranberries sprinkled on top" class="wp-image-217384" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/a-close-up-overhead-view-of-a-bowl-of-oatmeal-with-almonds-blueberries-and-cranberries-sprinkled-on-top-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/a-close-up-overhead-view-of-a-bowl-of-oatmeal-with-almonds-blueberries-and-cranberries-sprinkled-on-top-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/a-close-up-overhead-view-of-a-bowl-of-oatmeal-with-almonds-blueberries-and-cranberries-sprinkled-on-top-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>Oatmeal is a nutritious, inexpensive and versatile way to incorporate&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/4-key-elements-of-a-heart-healthy-diet" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">whole grains</a>&nbsp;into your diet and help you start your morning off right.</p>



<p>Oats made history when they became the first food with a Food and Drug Administration health claim label in 1997. This claim was related to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/easy-tips-to-improve-your-heart-health" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart health</a>&nbsp;and showed that intake of whole oat products decreased blood cholesterol levels.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">What makes oats so healthy?</h3>



<p>Oats contain a type of soluble fiber called beta-glucan, which lowers blood glucose and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/know-your-numbers-cholesterol" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cholesterol</a>&nbsp;levels and reduces the risk of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/cardiology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart disease</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/diabetes-what-you-need-to-know-and-do" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">diabetes</a>. Beta-glucan also promotes healthy&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/good-bacteria-for-your-gut" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gut bacteria</a>&nbsp;and intestinal health.</p>



<p>Eating oatmeal regularly can have weight management benefits, too. One-half cup of rolled oats cooked in a cup of water has 165 calories, 4 grams of fiber and 6 grams of protein.</p>



<p>Oats' fiber and protein content contribute to feeling full longer and slowing the release of blood glucose. They're also an excellent source of many&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/make-every-calorie-count-with-nutrient-dense-foods" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">vitamins and minerals</a>, including magnesium, copper, thiamine and zinc.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Know the different kinds of oats</h3>



<p>You can find different kinds of oats in the grocery store, including steel-cut, rolled, quick and instant.</p>



<p><strong>Steel-cut oats.</strong><br>Also called Irish oatmeal, whole oat kernels are cut into two or three pieces with steel disks. Because these oats are the least processed, they contain the highest amount of fiber. Steel-cut oats take longer to cook, resulting in a creamy and chewy porridge. They also can be made in a slow cooker.</p>



<p><strong>Rolled oats.</strong><br>These oats are rolled flat to make them easier to cook. Most of the bran is removed, so they have slightly less fiber than steel-cut oats but take less time to cook.</p>



<p><strong>Quick oats.</strong><br>This variation of rolled oats is rolled thinner and cut into small pieces, so they cook even faster.</p>



<p><strong>Instant oats.</strong><br>These are the oats found in single-serve packets. They're typically flavored and can be added to hot water or cooked in the microwave for a few minutes. While instant oats cook the fastest, they usually have more added sugar and less fiber than other types of oats.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Taking oats to the next level</h3>



<p>Oats have a nice flavor on their own, but if you're tired of plain oatmeal, here are a few ideas to try:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Baked oatmeal is almost cake-like and is a great way to make a week's worth of breakfasts in one batch.</li>



<li>To make your morning smoothie more filling, put 1/4 to 1/2 cup rolled oats in a blender and grind until fine. Stir into your smoothie for a breakfast with the staying power of oatmeal.</li>



<li>Overnight oats are made with rolled or quick oats mixed with some type of milk and yogurt, then refrigerated overnight. In the morning, you'll have a cool, creamy oatmeal mixture to eat with fruit or add to a smoothie.</li>
</ul>



<p>You also can play with flavors and add-ins that increase protein and soluble fiber.</p>



<p>Try adding these options to your oatmeal:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Chopped dates, dried cranberries or applesauce</li>



<li>Cocoa powder, a ripe banana and a couple of drops of vanilla extract</li>



<li>Peanut butter and a few drops of vanilla</li>



<li>Pinch of pumpkin pie spice</li>



<li>Roasted pumpkin seeds and a swirl of nut butter or a dollop of Greek yogurt</li>



<li>Sprinkle of chia seeds or ground flax</li>



<li>Unsweetened coconut, chopped cashews or sliced almonds.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Healthy oatmeal recipes</h3>



<p>These baked oatmeal and carrot-cake oatmeal recipes will get your morning off to a great start. Bake the oatmeal in the evening, refrigerate it and warm it up for breakfast. The carrot-cake oatmeal is loaded with calcium, protein, fiber and vitamin A. Chia seeds are high in heart-healthy soluble fiber and omega-3 fatty acids. Both oats and chia seeds provide soluble fiber, which lowers cholesterol levels. The small amount of carrots in this recipe provides 100% of your daily vitamin A and is good for your eyes and immune system.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Baked oatmeal</h4>



<p>Mayo Clinic Staff<br>Servings: 8</p>



<p>1 tablespoon canola oil<br>½ cup unsweetened applesauce<br>⅓ cup brown sugar<br>Egg substitute equivalent to 2 eggs, or 4 egg whites<br>3 cups uncooked rolled oats<br>2 teaspoons baking powder<br>1 teaspoon cinnamon<br>1 cup skim milk<br>1 cup fresh or frozen blueberries</p>



<p>In a large bowl, stir together the oil, applesauce, sugar and eggs. Add the dry ingredients and milk. Mix well. Generously spray a 9-by-13-inch baking pan with cooking spray. Spoon the oatmeal mixture into the pan. Sprinkle blueberries evenly over the oatmeal. Bake uncovered at 350 F for 30 minutes. Serve with toppings of your choice from the ideas above.</p>



<p>Nutritional per 3/4-cup serving (not including toppings): 205 calories, 4 grams total fat, 105 milligrams sodium, 36 grams carbohydrates, 3 grams fiber, 7 grams protein.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Carrot cake overnight oats</h4>



<p>Mayo Clinic Staff<br>Servings: 1</p>



<p>½ cup rolled oats<br>⅔ cup skim milk<br>⅓ cup plain, nonfat Greek yogurt<br>¼ cup finely grated carrot<br>1½ teaspoons chia seeds<br>2 teaspoons maple syrup<br>½ teaspoon cinnamon<br>½ teaspoon vanilla extract<br>1 tablespoon pecans, chopped<br>1 tablespoon shredded coconut, unsweetened</p>



<p>Combine all ingredients, except the pecans and coconut, in a bowl or Mason jar. Top with pecans and coconuts and cover. Refrigerate overnight and serve chilled.</p>



<p>Nutritional per serving: 395 calories, 12 grams total fat, 135 milligrams sodium, 55 grams carbohydrates, 9 grams fiber, 21 grams protein</p>



<p><em><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/romi-londre-rdn" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Romi Londre</a>&nbsp;is a dietitian in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/nutrition" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nutrition</a>&nbsp;in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/eau-claire" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Eau Claire</a>, Wisconsin.</em></p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/start-your-day-with-healthy-oatmeal" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-makes-oatmeal-the-ideal-breakfast-for-heart-health-and-weight-loss/">What makes oatmeal the ideal breakfast for heart health and weight loss?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/a-close-up-overhead-view-of-a-bowl-of-oatmeal-with-almonds-blueberries-and-cranberries-sprinkled-on-top-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/a-close-up-overhead-view-of-a-bowl-of-oatmeal-with-almonds-blueberries-and-cranberries-sprinkled-on-top-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Romi Londre]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: How to make healthy holiday food choices</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-make-healthy-holiday-food-choices/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Deb Balzer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 15:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Health & Wellness]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Cycle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Andrea Delgado]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[dietitian]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[holiday food]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376964</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->During Thanksgiving, food often takes center stage at gatherings of friends and family. The focus is on turkey, pie and all the sides. But it also can challenge healthy eating habits. Andrea Delgado, a Mayo Clinic dietitian, says that by paying attention to how much you eat and how often, you can make healthy food […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-make-healthy-holiday-food-choices/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How to make healthy holiday food choices</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<p-->During Thanksgiving, food often takes center stage at gatherings of friends and family. The focus is on turkey, pie and all the sides. But it also can challenge healthy eating habits.<p></p>



<p>Andrea Delgado, a Mayo Clinic dietitian, says that by paying attention to how much you eat and how often, you can make <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/in-depth/heart-healthy-diet/art-20047702?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">healthy food</a> choices during the holidays.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/nR-biL5MVSw" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls="" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Mayo-Clinic-Minute-How-to-make-healthy-food-choices-during-the-holidays-CLEAN.mp4"></video></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:01) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/SCRIPT-MCM-Making-Healthy-Holiday-Food-Choices.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Sit down. Enjoy your holiday meal, says Delgado.</p>



<p>"There's never an all-or-nothing approach in nutrition, you can still enjoy everything in moderation," she says.</p>



<p>Delgado says overindulging during the holidays can be a tipping point for some.</p>



<p>"Maybe now we have a new diagnosis of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-cholesterol/symptoms-causes/syc-20350800?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">high cholesterol</a> or a new diagnosis of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prediabetes/symptoms-causes/syc-20355278?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">prediabetes</a> or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/diabetes/symptoms-causes/syc-20371444?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">diabetes</a> because, even though we only did it for a short period of time, it was enough that we were close enough to be diagnosed with these new conditions," she says.</p>



<p>One strategy includes weighing your options and making choices.</p>



<p>"Let's say I have a green bean casserole, which is filled with cream of mushroom and a lot of other ingredients, versus just a side of green beans. Your better option would be the green beans," she says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/08/151207-067-PHOTO-144revised_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="roasted green beans for Making Mayo's Recipes. Healthy food choices" class="wp-image-212549" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/08/151207-067-PHOTO-144revised_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/08/151207-067-PHOTO-144revised_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/08/151207-067-PHOTO-144revised_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Make healthy food choices during the holidays - include fresh vegetables when possible.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>But what about that pumpkin pie?</p>



<p>"We can still have a small wedge, but maybe we don't add the whipped topping or the additional toppings that we might add typically. It's not really cutting out entire foods. It's more how can we reduce the portion or what we add to those foods," says Delgado.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h4>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-best-cooking-fats-for-healthy-cholesterol-levels/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Best cooking fats for healthy cholesterol levels</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-cooks-holiday-dish-for-all/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic cooks: Holiday dish for all</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/shame-and-guilt-eating-tackling-binge-eating-disorders/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Shame and guilt eating: Tackling binge-eating disorders</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-make-healthy-holiday-food-choices/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How to make healthy holiday food choices</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/10/a-happy-group-of-family-and-friends-gathering-in-a-kitchen-around-a-turkey-dinner-for-holiday-meal-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/10/a-happy-group-of-family-and-friends-gathering-in-a-kitchen-around-a-turkey-dinner-for-holiday-meal-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Andrea Delgado]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[dietitian]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[holiday food]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Cholesterol — know your numbers</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-cholesterol-know-your-numbers/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Susan Barber Lindquist]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 14:17:58 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cholesterol]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[diverserepresentation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Regis Fernandes]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=396683</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;I am in my 30s and overweight, but I thought I was too young to worry about cholesterol. I just learned my&nbsp;cholesterol is high. I know diet and exercise are important. Do I need medication?&nbsp; ANSWER:&nbsp;Cholesterol is a type of fat in our blood. Our bodies need a small amount of cholesterol to […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-cholesterol-know-your-numbers/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Cholesterol — know your numbers</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<p--><p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Lipid-panel-cholesterol-triglycerides-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Lipid panel cholesterol triglycerides" class="wp-image-380777" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Lipid-panel-cholesterol-triglycerides-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Lipid-panel-cholesterol-triglycerides-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Lipid-panel-cholesterol-triglycerides-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Lipid-panel-cholesterol-triglycerides-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Lipid-panel-cholesterol-triglycerides-16x9-1.jpg 1604w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;</strong>I am in my 30s and overweight, but I thought I was too young to worry about cholesterol. I just learned my&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-cholesterol/symptoms-causes/syc-20350800" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cholesterol is high</a>. I know diet and exercise are important. Do I need medication?&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong>&nbsp;Cholesterol is a type of fat in our blood. Our bodies need a small amount of cholesterol to build the structure of cell membranes, make certain hormones and help with metabolism, such as producing vitamin D. The catch: We don't need too much cholesterol.&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/arteriosclerosis-atherosclerosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20350569" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Atherosclerosis</a>, also known as narrowing of the arteries, happens when cholesterol builds up and blocks blood flow. This buildup is called plaque, which can clog arteries and can burst, leading to a blood clot. Atherosclerosis can cause heart problems such as chest pain (<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/angina/symptoms-causes/syc-20369373" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">angina</a>) or&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-attack/symptoms-causes/syc-20373106" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart attack</a>. It also can lead to problems in the brain, including&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/transient-ischemic-attack/symptoms-causes/syc-20355679" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">transient ischemic attack</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stroke/symptoms-causes/syc-20350113" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stroke</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/peripheral-artery-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350557" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">peripheral artery disease</a>&nbsp;in the legs or arms, and even&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/kidney-failure/symptoms-causes/syc-20369048" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">kidney failure</a>.</p>



<p>Cholesterol and&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-high-triglycerides-mean-and-why-it-matters-to-your-heart/">triglycerides</a>&nbsp;are types of lipids. They travel in our blood by attaching to proteins. Adults 20 and older should ask their healthcare team about their&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-cholesterol/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20350806" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lipid profile and how to interpret the numbers</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol:</strong>&nbsp;We call LDL "bad" cholesterol. Below 100 milligrams per deciliter (mg/dl) is optimal for healthy people in the absence of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/coronary-artery-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350613">coronary artery disease</a>. If you have&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">&nbsp;disease</a>, your LDL should be below 70 mg/dl.&nbsp;Treatment decisions to reach appropriate levels need to be based on personal risk factors.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>High-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol:&nbsp;</strong>We call HDL "good" cholesterol. It absorbs cholesterol in the blood and brings it to the liver, which flushes it from the body. For females, it should be above 50 mg/dl. For males, it should be above 40 mg/dl.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Triglycerides:</strong>&nbsp;Triglycerides are a type of fat we use for energy. If you have too high of a triglycerides level, it can cause heart disease. Less than 150 mg/dl is optimal.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Total cholesterol: This</strong>&nbsp;is the sum of LDL and HDL cholesterol plus 20% of triglyceride levels. A total cholesterol level below 200 mg/dl is desirable.</li>
</ul>



<p>Some people who are overweight may get heart disease not because their LDL is high but, rather, because their HDL is low and their triglycerides are high. That relationship can cause heart disease as much or even more than just high LDL cholesterol. These lipid abnormalities are significant for young people in their 30s or 40s who are overweight. Their triglyceride levels increase, and their HDL lowers. They're becoming&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prediabetes/symptoms-causes/syc-20355278" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">prediabetic</a>. Their LDL is staying the same, but they're still heading to heart disease.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Treating high cholesterol depends on individual risk. The higher the risk — for example, with someone who already had a heart attack — a higher percent of reduction is needed. Medication to lower cholesterol can reduce LDL by about 60% to 65%. Lifestyle changes can reduce LDL by 10% to 15%.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Several medications can help manage lipids. Discuss options with your healthcare team.</p>



<p>The body's ability to handle cholesterol is genetically determined. Genetic disorders that raise cholesterol levels are common.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/familial-hypercholesterolemia/symptoms-causes/syc-20353755" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Familial hypercholesterolemia</a>&nbsp;usually is caused by a genetic mutation preventing the body from clearing cholesterol. People with the condition are more likely to require medication to reduce their cholesterol levels.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For people with genetic disorders that expose them to elevated cholesterol since birth, heart disease can happen at a younger age. So we start treating their high cholesterol with medication at a young age.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Beyond medication, lifestyle modifications help manage lipids:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Limit meat and dairy intake; they have&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/fat/art-20045550" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">saturated fat</a>, which raises LDL cholesterol.</li>



<li>Consume more fish,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/fiber/art-20043983" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">soluble fiber</a>, fruit and vegetables.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Avoid diets high in carbohydrates, particularly refined carbs like sugar and white flour. They raise the blood sugar level quickly, raising triglycerides. Reducing simple refined carbohydrates helps lower triglycerides and weight because you store less fat.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Control your weight. It lowers your triglycerides and improves your HDL levels.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Exercise about 150 minutes of aerobic activity a week at a moderate intensity. Moderate intensity means you must breathe through your mouth. If you're breathing through your nose, that is low intensity. Exercise prevents cholesterol from building up, but it doesn't change LDL concentration levels. You must burn about 2,000 calories a week to lower LDL concentration. However, exercise helps lower triglyceride levels and maintain weight loss.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Do&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/fitness/in-depth/strength-training/art-20046031">strength training</a>&nbsp;at least twice a week. It helps your cardiovascular and muscular systems. Not everything we do to prevent heart disease is about cholesterol.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>The National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute recommends people get their first cholesterol screening between ages 9 and 11, and repeat it every five years. For men 45 to 65 and women 55 to 65, cholesterol screenings should occur every one to two years. Over 65? Test annually. More frequent testing may be needed for people who have or are at risk for&nbsp;coronary artery disease. —&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/fernandes-regis-i-m-d/bio-20305254" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em><strong>Regis Fernandes, M.D.</strong></em></a><em>,<strong>&nbsp;Cardiovascular Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Phoenix</strong></em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-cholesterol-know-your-numbers/">Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A: Cholesterol — know your numbers</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_276129434_Fotor-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_276129434_Fotor-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cholesterol]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[diverserepresentation]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Regis Fernandes]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hourglass-shaped stent could ease severe chest pain from microvascular disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/hourglass-shaped-stent-could-ease-severe-chest-pain-from-microvascular-disease/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Terri Malloy]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Thu, 07 Nov 2024 16:30:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Clinical Trials]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[angina]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[angina treatment]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiology]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[coronary angiogram]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Amir Lerman]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Heart Disease]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[small vessel disease]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=396180</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — A study at Mayo Clinic suggests that an hourglass-shaped stent could improve blood flow and ease severe and reoccurring chest pain in people with microvascular disease. Of 30 participants in a phase 2 clinical trial, 76% saw improvement in their day-to-day life. For example, some participants who reported not being able to […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/hourglass-shaped-stent-could-ease-severe-chest-pain-from-microvascular-disease/">Hourglass-shaped stent could ease severe chest pain from microvascular disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="684" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microvascular-disease_1293229_EC1294075-001-1-1024x684.jpg" alt="View of a heart with coronary artery disease or coronary microvascular disease. An inset highlights the clogging and narrowing of the arteries." class="wp-image-396227" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microvascular-disease_1293229_EC1294075-001-1-1024x684.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microvascular-disease_1293229_EC1294075-001-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microvascular-disease_1293229_EC1294075-001-1-768x513.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microvascular-disease_1293229_EC1294075-001-1.jpg 1464w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A study at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> suggests that an hourglass-shaped stent could improve blood flow and ease severe and reoccurring chest pain in people with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/small-vessel-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20352117" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">microvascular disease</a>. Of 30 participants in a phase 2 clinical trial, 76% saw improvement in their day-to-day life. For example, some participants who reported not being able to walk around the block or up a flight of stairs without chest pain were able to do these ordinary physical activities at the end of a 120-day period. Clinical measures of blood flow related to the microvasculature of the heart significantly improved during follow-up, according to findings published in the <a href="https://authors.elsevier.com/a/1k39I6uPJvuWBq" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Journal of the American College of Cardiology: Cardiovascular Interventions</a>.</p>



<p>Microvascular disease is a condition in which tiny blood vessels in the heart are not working properly, resulting in reduced blood flow to the heart. The resulting chest pains, or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/angina/symptoms-causes/syc-20369373" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">angina</a>, can be debilitating, limiting a person's ability to exercise, do household chores or even walk to the mailbox. About 40% of patients receiving a diagnostic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/coronary-angiogram/about/pac-20384904" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">coronary angiogram</a> for chest pain do not have blocked arteries that also can cause angina. However, up to 66% of these patients do have coronary microvascular disease, which is more common in women overall and found in people with conditions such as diabetes, high blood pressure and obesity.</p>



<p>For decades, there have been few viable treatment options to improve blood flow through the tiny vessels of the heart. At most, doctors have treated symptoms of angina with several medications and cardiovascular disease prevention methods, including healthy eating, weight loss and regular exercise. The use of a stent could target the issue behind the chest pain — the severe reduction in blood flow affecting the heart muscle.</p>



<p>Unlike tube-shaped stents used to open clogged arteries, the hourglass-shaped stent narrows in the middle. The different design is thought to increase back pressure, redistributing blood flow more fully through small vessels in the heart that were not working at capacity.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Amir_Lerman_1539878_3777595_0001-300x200.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396220" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Amir_Lerman_1539878_3777595_0001-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Amir_Lerman_1539878_3777595_0001-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Amir_Lerman_1539878_3777595_0001-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Amir_Lerman_1539878_3777595_0001-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Amir_Lerman_1539878_3777595_0001.jpg 1688w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><sup>Amir Lerman, M.D.</sup></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"The patients with heart-related microvascular dysfunction in this study had little ability to control their chronic angina, which severely limited their day-to-day activities," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/lerman-amir-m-d/bio-00078051" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Amir Lerman, M.D.</a>, a cardiologist at Mayo Clinic and senior author of the study. "Beyond reductions in chest pain and being able to comfortably handle more physical activity, the majority of patients in the study also showed a connection between the changes in their coronary flow reserve, which is a measure of maximum blood flow, and changes in their quality-of-life responses on the survey. This points to the link between the physiological measurement and angina symptoms."</p>



<p>Dr. Lerman notes that more studies are needed to better understand how the reducer stent works and its long-term effects on blood flow. The stent did not improve chest pain symptoms in 20%-30% of the participants, so future research studies will need to better identify which patients respond best to this therapy. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> <br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/hourglass-shaped-stent-could-ease-severe-chest-pain-from-microvascular-disease/">Hourglass-shaped stent could ease severe chest pain from microvascular disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microvascular-disease_510085_EC1294075-001-0_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microvascular-disease_1293229_EC1294075-001_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[angina]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[angina treatment]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cardiology]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[coronary angiogram]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Amir Lerman]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Heart Disease]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[small vessel disease]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Tips for better sleep</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-tips-for-better-sleep-2/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Deb Balzer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 15:18:35 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Cycle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[diverserepresentation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Virend Somers]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Sleep]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=394826</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->No matter if you need five hours of sleep or eight, the key is getting good, refreshing rest. According to&nbsp;Dr. Virend Somers, a cardiologist who specializes in sleep disorders, how much sleep a person needs varies from person to person. However, there are some simple tips that everyone can use to get&nbsp;better sleep. Watch: The […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-tips-for-better-sleep-2/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Tips for better sleep</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<p-->No matter if you need five hours of sleep or eight, the key is getting good, refreshing rest. According to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/somers-virend-m-d-ph-d/bio-20054093?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Virend Somers</a>, a cardiologist who specializes in sleep disorders, how much sleep a person needs varies from person to person. However, there are some simple tips that everyone can use to get&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-5-ways-to-get-better-sleep/">better sleep.</a><p></p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/fjVA_mmFmxU" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubefjVAmmFmxU" title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Tips for better sleep" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fjVA_mmFmxU?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:02) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/SCRIPT.-MCM-Tips-for-better-sleep-VD-edits.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></strong></p>



<p>Different people need different amounts of sleep, and, on average, we can say most people need seven to eight hours," explains Dr. Somers.</p>



<p>He says to consider the quality of sleep, not the quantity. He offers these&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/adult-health/in-depth/sleep/art-20048379">ideas&nbsp;</a>to help you have good sleep hygiene.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Tips for better sleep</h2>



<p>"In the bedroom, you want absolute darkness," says Dr. Somers.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/a-white-woman-sleeping-peacefully-in-bed-in-a-darkened-room-with-a-soft-light-falling-across-her-face-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a white woman sleeping peacefully in bed in a darkened room, with a soft light falling across her face" class="wp-image-364301" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/a-white-woman-sleeping-peacefully-in-bed-in-a-darkened-room-with-a-soft-light-falling-across-her-face-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/a-white-woman-sleeping-peacefully-in-bed-in-a-darkened-room-with-a-soft-light-falling-across-her-face-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/a-white-woman-sleeping-peacefully-in-bed-in-a-darkened-room-with-a-soft-light-falling-across-her-face-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/a-white-woman-sleeping-peacefully-in-bed-in-a-darkened-room-with-a-soft-light-falling-across-her-face-16X9.jpg 1500w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>And that means no screens, no TV, no laptops, no phones, and no ticking clocks or LED displays.</p>



<p>"Avoid bright lights, avoid looking at your phones because light from there can affect your&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements-melatonin/art-20363071">melatonin</a>," Dr. Somers says. That's the hormone that regulates sleep.</p>



<p>He says when it comes to quality sleep, less stimulation is best.</p>



<p>"Minimize alcohol, minimize exercise, minimize lights, minimize external inputs before about two hours or so before bedtime. The bedroom is for sex and sleep. It's not for spreadsheets," says Dr. Somers.</p>



<p>Exercise can help improve sleep, but working out near bedtime can raise arousal levels, making it harder to sleep. And consider a sleep schedule. Going to bed and getting up at the same time each day reinforces your body's sleep-wake cycle.</p>



<p><strong>Related posts:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-happens-to-your-body-when-you-have-obstructive-sleep-apnea/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What happens to your body when you have obstructive sleep apnea?</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-excessive-daytime-sleepiness-can-affect-heart-health/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How excessive daytime sleepiness can affect heart health</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-tips-for-better-sleep-2/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Tips for better sleep</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/01/peaceful-man-sleeping-in-bed-at-home.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2015/12/peaceful-man-sleeping-in-bed-at-home-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[diverserepresentation]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Virend Somers]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Sleep]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</atom:link></channel>
</rss> 