<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org">

<channel>
	<title>Cardiovascular - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cardiovascular-2/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml">
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cardiovascular-2/
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastbuilddate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 15:59:16 +0000</lastbuilddate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updateperiod>
	hourly	</sy:updateperiod>
	<sy:updatefrequency>
	1	</sy:updatefrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>5 things to know about fainting: The heart’s role and when it may signal a serious condition</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/5-things-to-know-about-fainting-the-hearts-role-and-when-it-may-signal-serious-condition/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Sharon Theimer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 14:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Health & Wellness]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[International]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[International News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=399826</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->February is Heart Month in many countries LONDON — You may have heard that people who feel faint should sit with their heads between their knees, but is that true? And how can you tell whether you or someone else who has fainted should go to the emergency department or perhaps even see a cardiologist? […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/5-things-to-know-about-fainting-the-hearts-role-and-when-it-may-signal-serious-condition/">5 things to know about fainting: The heart’s role and when it may signal a serious condition</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/16x9_Featured-image_syncope-post_Behr-fotor-2025021410567-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-399827" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/16x9_Featured-image_syncope-post_Behr-fotor-2025021410567-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/16x9_Featured-image_syncope-post_Behr-fotor-2025021410567-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/16x9_Featured-image_syncope-post_Behr-fotor-2025021410567-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/16x9_Featured-image_syncope-post_Behr-fotor-2025021410567.jpg 1216w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p><em>February is Heart Month in many countries</em></p>



<p>LONDON — You may have heard that people who feel faint should sit with their heads between their knees, but is that true? And how can you tell whether you or someone else who has fainted should go to the emergency department or perhaps even see a cardiologist? <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/doctors/elijah-r-behr-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Elijah Behr, M.D.</a>, a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/patient-care/heart-health" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiologist</a>&nbsp;at&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/patient-care" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Healthcare</a>&nbsp;in London, explains five things it is important to know about fainting.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/first-aid/first-aid-fainting/basics/art-20056606" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Fainting</a> or blacking out, also known as syncope, is a temporary loss of consciousness due to insufficient blood flow to the brain. &nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">There are different types of syncope</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/vasovagal-syncope/symptoms-causes/syc-20350527" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Vasovagal syncope</a> is the medical term for the most benign kind of fainting, simple fainting without a serious underlying cause, Dr. Behr explains. This type of fainting is common.</p>



<p>"In some people, if they have a drop in blood pressure from emotional distress, pain, illness or dehydration, for example, or just generally have a low blood pressure, any provocation causes a reflex in the heart," Dr. Behr says. "Rather than the heart speeding up and pumping more forcefully to maintain the blood pressure, it starts to slow down. The blood pressure drops, the heart rate slows further, and the heart can pause for many seconds; sometimes close to a minute for some people who have more severe fainting episodes."</p>



<p>Usually with this type of fainting, the person falls to the floor, blood pressure returns to the brain and the person starts to recover. However, if someone faints in a vulnerable location or vulnerable position, it can be dangerous to that person and others, Dr. Behr notes.</p>



<p>The syncope that most concerns healthcare professionals is cardiac syncope, blacking out due to an underlying heart disease such as a heart rhythm abnormality, or <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/patient-care/cardiology/cardiology-specialty-areas/arrhythmia-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">arrhythmia</a>, he explains.</p>



<p>"This is usually a more abrupt loss and return of consciousness than in simple fainting. If you're older, you're more likely to have underlying <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/patient-care/cardiology/cardiology-specialty-areas" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart disease</a> that you may or may not be aware of. That's one of the reasons to be more concerned about loss of consciousness in older individuals," Dr. Behr says. "Young people can also have heart diseases that can cause cardiac syncope that may be a warning sign of something more serious to come, so it is important to investigate it."</p>



<p>Others for whom a blackout can be a warning sign of a serious heart problem include people with a family history of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">inherited heart problems</a>, unexplained deaths or premature sudden deaths; people whose fainting is related to exercise; and people whose fainting is associated with heart palpitations or the heart feeling like it's racing away, he adds.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Before a simple faint, you might experience one or more signs that you should sit or lie down</h2>



<p>"There will be a sensation of lightheadedness. There may be a sensation of nausea or buzzing or ringing in the ears," Dr. Behr says. "Some people describe tunnel vision — their vision closing in on them before they actually pass out — and some may actually lose vision but still be aware, not lose consciousness completely, and then recover. Other typical signs include feeling sweaty and clammy."</p>



<p>Some people get about a half-hour of warnings before fainting; some people may get 30 seconds, he adds.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What to do if you faint or someone else does:</h2>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Check that the person is breathing and has a pulse. If not, call for emergency help, and if you know how to provide <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/first-aid/first-aid-cpr/basics/art-20056600" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiopulmonary resuscitation</a>, initiate it.</li>



<li>If the person is still breathing and has a pulse, ensure they are lying flat, and their airway is open using the recovery position and call for help.</li>



<li>If you feel like a faint may be coming on, position your head lower than your heart: for example, between the knees.</li>



<li>Rest after coming out of the faint.</li>



<li>Drink water after the faint, adding electrolytes if you have them.</li>
</ul>



<p>"If your blood pressure is getting low and you're getting those symptoms, it means the blood doesn't get into your brain, and if your heart is trying to push the blood to your brain against gravity, then it's struggling. You really need to get your head level or below your heart so the blood pressure gets back to the brain, and that will avert all the symptoms and the vicious cycle that ensues," Dr. Behr advises. "Get your head between your knees or lie down and put your head down and your feet up in the air, depending on where you are and what is feasible to do."</p>



<p>Getting up and walking around straight away is probably the worst thing to do, he warns.</p>



<p>"Your blood pressure will drop further, and you’ll feel worse, and collapse and fall and injure yourself," Dr. Behr says. "The best thing is to stay where you are and get flat, and when you're feeling better, drink some water, maybe with some electrolytes if you're dehydrated. For general preventive measures, we advise most people who have fainted to drink more water and to sometimes add a bit of salt to their food, because generally they're running a low blood pressure."</p>



<p>Sometimes, getting hydrated and adding salt to the diet may not be enough. Occasionally people need to take medications to improve blood pressure control and increase blood pressure to prevent fainting episodes, Dr. Behr says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">When to seek medical help</h2>



<p>"If somebody has had simple fainting with the clear precipitants that I described, it is best to have a chat with your GP (your primary care physician) to talk about it. Particularly if it's a first onset of symptoms, it's best not to ignore it," Dr. Behr says. "Often people go to the emergency department after a first faint, which I think is very fair to do and I would encourage."</p>



<p>If someone has had simple faints before, the circumstances that bring them on are typical for them and they have been evaluated by their primary care physician or a cardiologist before, they may not need to go to the emergency department every time, he adds.</p>



<p>The more concerning situations are older people having faints where other conditions may also be having an effect, people who are having recurrent faints despite keeping well hydrated, if there has been an injury due to a faint, and if the blackout comes on abruptly and with other signs that there may be an underlying cardiac condition.</p>



<p>"We need to make sure that they are treated and that something else isn't being missed," Dr. Behr says. "Also, sometimes faints can look like seizures. They can cause fitting activity, and differentiating a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/epilepsy/symptoms-causes/syc-20350093" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">seizure and epilepsy</a> from fainting requires involvement of a cardiologist and neurologist."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">If you faint at the sight of blood, you may be able to condition yourself not to</h2>



<p>"It's very common, but it can be surmounted by various means," Dr. Behr says.</p>



<p>For example, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/cognitive-behavioral-therapy/about/pac-20384610" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cognitive behavioural therapy</a> (CBT) may help, he suggests. In CBT, you work with a mental health counselor such as a psychotherapist or therapist to become aware of inaccurate or negative thinking, so you can view challenging situations more clearly and respond to them more effectively.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Healthcare</strong><br>Mayo Clinic Healthcare, located in London, is a wholly owned subsidiary of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>, a not-for-profit academic medical center. Mayo Clinic is top ranked by U.S. News &amp; World Report in more specialties than any other hospital for a reason: quality of care. Mayo Clinic Healthcare is the U.K.'s front door to that unparalleled experience. Visit <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Healthcare</a> for more information.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Sharon Theimer, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/5-things-to-know-about-fainting-the-hearts-role-and-when-it-may-signal-serious-condition/">5 things to know about fainting: The heart’s role and when it may signal a serious condition</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/1x1_Featured-image_syncope-post_Behr-fotor-20250214105725.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/16x9_Featured-image_syncope-post_Behr-fotor-2025021410567.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[International News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: What high&nbsp;triglycerides mean and why it matters to your heart&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-high-triglycerides-mean-and-why-it-matters-to-your-heart/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Deb Balzer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 15:30:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Arizona]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Video]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#dailynews]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cholesterol]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Regis Fernandes]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[heart heatlh]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[triglcerides]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=380736</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->You may be familiar with&nbsp;high-density, or good cholesterol; low-density lipoproteins (LDL), or bad cholesterol; and their connections to heart health. But what about&nbsp;triglycerides? Often that word gets skimmed over when talking about cholesterol levels. Dr. Regis Fernandes, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist, says triglycerides provide the body with energy from food. High levels can indicate signs […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-high-triglycerides-mean-and-why-it-matters-to-your-heart/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What high&nbsp;triglycerides mean and why it matters to your heart&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<p-->You may be familiar with&nbsp;high-density, or good cholesterol; low-density lipoproteins (LDL), or bad cholesterol; and their connections to heart health. But what about&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-what-are-triglycerides-and-why-do-they-matter/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">triglycerides</a>? Often that word gets skimmed over when talking about cholesterol levels.<p></p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/fernandes-regis-i-m-d/bio-20305254" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Regis Fernandes</a>, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist, says triglycerides provide the body with energy from food. High levels can indicate signs of other conditions, like diabetes or prediabetes, that can increase the risk of heart disease and stroke.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/99Hf2oHy1pQ" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls="" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mayo-Clinic-Minute-What-high-triglycerides-mean-and-why-it-matters-to-your-heart_CLEAN.mp4"></video></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:10) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/SCRIPT-MCM-High-TriglyceridesJSEDIT7283.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Triglycerides, the main kind of fat in your body, store extra energy from the food you eat.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"It's an energy source. It's like a little battery used for energy. But too many triglycerides can also cause heart disease," says Dr. Fernandes.</p>



<p>People who are overweight, in general, have high triglyceride levels and good cholesterol levels that are low.</p>



<p>"They may get heart disease not because their LDL is high, they get heart disease because the HDL is low and the triglycerides is high," he says.</p>



<p>And this is significant for people in their 30s and 40s.</p>



<p>So what can you do?&nbsp;Reducing simple carbohydrates, such as refined sugars and flours, can help lower your weight and improve your cholesterol and triglyceride levels. And you can back that up with exercise.</p>



<p>"One of the best ways to lower triglyceride levels is to exercise. Also, exercise helps to lose weight. And when you lose weight, your triglycerides improve a lot," says Dr. Fernandes.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Tips to lower triglcyerides&nbsp;</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Aim for 30 minutes of exercise most days.</li>



<li>Cut sugar and refined carbs.</li>



<li>Lose weight and focus on reducing calories.</li>



<li>Choose healthier fats like olive oil and fish that are rich in omega-3.</li>



<li>Limit alcohol, which can be high in calories and sugar.</li>
</ul>



<p></p>



<p>Medications, including&nbsp;statins,&nbsp;may be prescribed if lifestyle modifications don't help.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-high-triglycerides-mean-and-why-it-matters-to-your-heart/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What high&nbsp;triglycerides mean and why it matters to your heart&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Lipid-panel-cholesterol-triglycerides-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Lipid-panel-cholesterol-triglycerides-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#dailynews]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cholesterol]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Regis Fernandes]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[heart heatlh]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[triglcerides]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tomorrow’s Cure: AI Powered Stethoscopes Improve Access to Heart Care</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-ai-powered-stethoscopes-improve-access-to-heart-care/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Joel Streed]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 13:02:09 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[AI Stethoscope]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Demilade Adedinsewo]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Tomorrow's Cure]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=399690</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->The stethoscope, one of the most iconic symbols of medicine, was invented over 200 years ago. Today, artificial intelligence is revolutionizing this essential tool, empowering doctors to detect cardiac disease at its earliest stages with greater precision. Discover these groundbreaking advancements on a new episode of Tomorrow's Cure. The podcast episode features Dr. Demilade Adedinsewo, […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-ai-powered-stethoscopes-improve-access-to-heart-care/">Tomorrow’s Cure: AI Powered Stethoscopes Improve Access to Heart Care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/MCP-17536_TC_S02E04_DS_YT-Thumbnail__1280x720_-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-399740" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/MCP-17536_TC_S02E04_DS_YT-Thumbnail__1280x720_-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/MCP-17536_TC_S02E04_DS_YT-Thumbnail__1280x720_-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/MCP-17536_TC_S02E04_DS_YT-Thumbnail__1280x720_-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/MCP-17536_TC_S02E04_DS_YT-Thumbnail__1280x720_.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>The stethoscope, one of the most iconic symbols of medicine, was invented over 200 years ago. Today, artificial intelligence is revolutionizing this essential tool, empowering doctors to detect cardiac disease at its earliest stages with greater precision. Discover these groundbreaking advancements on a new episode of <a href="https://careinfo.mayoclinic.org/tomorrows-cure-podcast?mc_id=global&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=tcseasontwoepisodefour&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=global&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=190203" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tomorrow's Cure</a>.</p>



<p>The podcast episode features <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/adedinsewo-demilade-a-m-b-ch-b/bio-20502753" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Demilade Adedinsewo, </a>cardiologist, and Jason Bellet, co-founder of Eko Health. Together, they discuss innovative and lifesaving technology that is transforming heart health.</p>



<p>The AI-powered digital stethoscope, developed by Eko Health, captures electrocardiogram (ECG) data and heart sounds. This advanced tool enhances the detection of peripartum cardiomyopathy, a serious yet treatable condition that weakens the heart muscle during pregnancy or postpartum.</p>



<p>"There is a diagnostic gap when it comes to how do we identify a high index of suspicion and how we make it to that diagnosis," explains Dr. Adedinsewo. "Also, we do not have a simple, noninvasive screening test that is safe for mother and the baby."</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe id="videoidhttpsyoutubejbAN6gKp3tw" title="AI Powered Stethoscopes Improve Access to Heart Care | Tomorrow's Cure Season 2 Episode 4" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jbAN6gKp3tw?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>Recognizing a weak heart pump caused by pregnancy is crucial because its symptoms — shortness of breath when lying down, swelling in the hands and feet, weight gain, and rapid heartbeat — can easily be mistaken for normal pregnancy-related conditions.</p>



<p>"We really believe that this technology has the ability to improve access to early detection, which then can inform the patient to go to a cardiologist on a more expedited timeline and get the advanced care they need," Bellet says. "If we can just detect heart murmurs that much better or AFib that much better in the physical exam, we can then get those patients referred into cardiology faster, get the echocardiogram and, hopefully, get the treatment they need earlier."</p>



<p>This technology holds immense potential to revolutionize the healthcare field.</p>



<p>"Our vision is to create a pipeline of algorithms such that when you put the stethoscope on the chest in a future physical exam, we'll be able to take those 15 to 30 seconds of heart sounds — and eventually lung sounds — and analyze them for a host of conditions, really turning that wellness visit that we all know with our provider that can be 15, 30 or 45 minutes into a really powerful early detection opportunity," Bellet says. </p>



<p>To learn more, check out the latest episode of <a href="https://careinfo.mayoclinic.org/tomorrows-cure-podcast?mc_id=global&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=tcseasontwoepisodefour&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=global&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=190203" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tomorrow's Cure</a> wherever you get your podcasts. To see a complete list of episodes and featured experts, visit <a href="https://careinfo.mayoclinic.org/tomorrows-cure-podcast?mc_id=global&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=tcseasontwoepisodefour&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=global&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=190203" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">tomorrowscure.com</a>.</p>



<p>Related Articles:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/clinical-research-shows-ai-enabled-digital-stethoscope-can-detect-pregnancy-related-heart-disease/">Clinical research shows AI-enabled digital stethoscope can detect pregnancy-related heart disease </a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/pregnancy-related-heart-failure-is-under-detected-ai-enabled-stethoscope-helped-doctors-diagnose-twice-as-many-cases/">Pregnancy-related heart failure is under-detected; AI-enabled stethoscope helped doctors diagnose twice as many cases</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/spotlight-on-early-detection-of-3-heart-diseases-using-ecg-ai/">Spotlight on early detection of 3 heart diseases using ECG-AI</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-ai-powered-stethoscopes-improve-access-to-heart-care/">Tomorrow’s Cure: AI Powered Stethoscopes Improve Access to Heart Care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/MCP-17536_TC_S02E04_DS_NewsNetwork__1080x1080__RLSD-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/MCP-17536_TC_S02E04_DS_YT-Thumbnail__1280x720_.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[AI Stethoscope]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Demilade Adedinsewo]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Tomorrow's Cure]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers and surgeons test virtual reality to calm presurgery jitters&nbsp;&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-and-surgeons-test-virtual-reality-to-calm-presurgery-jitters/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Terri Malloy]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 17:02:15 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[AI and Digital Health]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Research]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Anxiety]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiology]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. John Stulak]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jordan Miller]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Joseph Dearani]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[immersive VR]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[open heart surgery]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Rochester news releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[virtual reality]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[VR]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=399702</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — Heart surgery is a serious and invasive medical procedure, and that can be intimidating for a patient. A new study published in Mayo Clinic Proceedings suggests that virtual reality (VR) can be an effective tool to reduce preoperative anxiety in older patients undergoing their first open-heart surgery. While much of the research […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-and-surgeons-test-virtual-reality-to-calm-presurgery-jitters/">Mayo Clinic researchers and surgeons test virtual reality to calm presurgery jitters&nbsp;&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/patient_using_virtual_reality-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-399778" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/patient_using_virtual_reality-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/patient_using_virtual_reality-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/patient_using_virtual_reality-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/patient_using_virtual_reality-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/patient_using_virtual_reality-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Heart surgery is a serious and invasive medical procedure, and that can be intimidating for a patient. A new study <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/article/S0025-6196(24)00474-9/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">published in Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a> suggests that <a href="https://tryhealium.com/how-it-works" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">virtual reality (VR)</a> can be an effective tool to reduce preoperative anxiety in older patients undergoing their first <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/cardiovascular-surgery/sections/overview/ovc-20123422" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">open-heart surgery</a>. While much of the research to date using VR involved younger patient populations, these research findings suggest that immersive VR was effective and well tolerated in older patients. These reductions in anxiety are particularly significant given the known link between preoperative anxiety and negative postoperative outcomes, including increased pain, reduced activity and higher medication use.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"This research represents a step forward in improving the patient experience and potentially using this approach to optimize postoperative recovery," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/miller-jordan-d-ph-d/bio-00027578" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jordan Miller, Ph.D.</a>, a cardiovascular disease researcher at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> and senior author of the study.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/dearani-joseph-a-m-d/bio-00083538" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Joseph Dearani, M.D.</a>, and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/stulak-john-m-m-d/bio-20133266" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">John Stulak, M.D.</a>, both cardiac surgeons at Mayo Clinic involved with the study, emphasize the importance of emotional state before and after cardiac surgery. "We currently offer music and massage therapy after cardiac surgery because we know what a negative impact high anxiety has on recovery from surgery. Our team is now exploring broader implementation of VR — which can be used at any time and place, inside or outside the hospital — throughout the surgical episode to further evaluate its impact on clinical outcomes."&nbsp;</p>



<p>Unlike traditional anti-anxiety medications, which can have drawbacks such as increased difficulty placing the tube that helps a patient breathe during surgery and a longer time to remove the tube after surgery, VR offers a nonpharmacological alternative. The study also highlights the potential of VR as a flexible tool, with the tablet-based option providing a viable alternative for patients susceptible to VR-induced motion sickness.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The research included 100 participants who were scheduled for open-heart surgery. Each patient wore a monitor to record vital signs and completed a standardized, clinically validated anxiety test before and after the VR intervention on the day of surgery. The test asked them to rate their current state with 20 questions related to feelings ranging from calm to upset. Participants rated each feeling on a scale of 1 to 4, with 1 being "not at all" and 4 being "very much."&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="168" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Seasons_Change_High_Res-300x168.png" alt="" class="wp-image-399788" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Seasons_Change_High_Res-300x168.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Seasons_Change_High_Res-1024x575.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Seasons_Change_High_Res-768x431.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Seasons_Change_High_Res-1536x863.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Seasons_Change_High_Res-2048x1150.png 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"></figure></div>


<p>Half of the participants were assigned to a VR tablet and the other half to immersive VR goggles while they waited in the holding area prior to surgery. The VR provided a 10-minute nature experience with guided breathing as they viewed trees and a waterfront that changed through four seasons. The tablet played a video of the content seen by patients in VR, while people who used the immersive VR headset were able to look all around and identify environmental features, which helped them advance through the scene. Both interventions reduced the pulse rate of participants, but they did not affect respiration rate or oxygen levels.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Overall anxiety scores decreased an average of 2 points with the tablet treatment and 2.9 points with the VR goggles. Additionally, the researchers note that the scores improved considerably in up to seven of the anxiety-focused questions with the tablet and VR goggles. Several of those responses specifically represent a more positive outlook change from their previously negative feelings — a finding that has the researchers feeling optimistic about the abilities of VR to make surgery less stressful for patients.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>###&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-and-surgeons-test-virtual-reality-to-calm-presurgery-jitters/">Mayo Clinic researchers and surgeons test virtual reality to calm presurgery jitters&nbsp;&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/patient_using_virtual_reality_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/patient_using_virtual_reality_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Anxiety]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Cardiology]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. John Stulak]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jordan Miller]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Joseph Dearani]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[immersive VR]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[open heart surgery]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Rochester news releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[virtual reality]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[VR]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Expert explains how to improve heart health, even if your family has history of heart conditions</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/expert-explains-how-to-improve-heart-health-even-if-your-family-has-history-of-heart-conditions/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Sharon Theimer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=399669</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — It’s not unusual to have one or more family members with some form of heart disease. Nonetheless, some people may not even know they have heart disease until they experience a heart attack or stroke or are diagnosed with heart failure. Despite the prevalence of heart disease, many people are still unclear […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/expert-explains-how-to-improve-heart-health-even-if-your-family-has-history-of-heart-conditions/">Expert explains how to improve heart health, even if your family has history of heart conditions</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="682" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Child-man-grocery-produce-1024x682.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-384699" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Child-man-grocery-produce-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Child-man-grocery-produce-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Child-man-grocery-produce-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Child-man-grocery-produce-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Child-man-grocery-produce.jpg 1688w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — It’s not unusual to have one or more family members with some form of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/search-results?q=Heart%20disease" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart disease</a>. Nonetheless, some people may not even know they have heart disease until they experience a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-attack/symptoms-causes/syc-20373106" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart attack</a> or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stroke/symptoms-causes/syc-20350113" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stroke</a> or are diagnosed with heart failure. Despite the prevalence of heart disease, many people are still unclear about how genetics can impact heart disease and, most importantly, what they can do to lower their risk. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/kopecky-stephen-l-m-d/bio-20054286" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stephen Kopecky, M.D.</a>, a cardiologist at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>, explains how you can improve your heart health, even if your family has a history of cardiovascular problems.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Kopecky-Stephen-L.-MD_10023313_201905210207-250x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-399668" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Kopecky-Stephen-L.-MD_10023313_201905210207-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/02/Kopecky-Stephen-L.-MD_10023313_201905210207.jpg 667w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><sup>Stephen Kopecky, M.D.</sup></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Heart disease is a broad term that describes several conditions impacting the heart's structure and function. The most common type of heart disease is <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/coronary-artery-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350613" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">coronary heart disease</a> typically caused by plaque buildup in and around the artery walls on the heart. But you may also have heard of heart valve disease, heart muscle disease (<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cardiomyopathy/symptoms-causes/syc-20370709" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiomyopathy</a>), conditions involving the heart's electrical system, or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/adult-congenital-heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20355456" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">congenital heart disease</a>. The exact symptoms depends on the type and severity of the disease.</p>



<p>Lifestyle factors — encompassing how much you move, what you eat, how well you sleep and more — play the biggest role in your heart health, Dr. Kopecky says. But circumstances you can’t control — namely, your <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/cardiovascular-genomics-program/overview/ovc-20442075" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">genetics and family history</a> — also impact your risk of heart disease.</p>



<p>Congenital heart disease, for example, is thought to run in families — meaning the condition may be passed down, also called inherited, from parent to child. Other research indicates that some genetic conditions, such as Down syndrome and certain types of muscular dystrophy, may be linked to cardiovascular conditions.</p>



<p>Family history may have a hand in heart disease that develops later in life as well. Though the exact numbers range, research consistently indicates that people with a family history of coronary artery disease, for example, have a significantly higher risk of developing the condition themselves. Similarly, people from families with two or more premature heart-related deaths have a three times higher risk of developing cardiovascular disease themselves before age 50.</p>



<p>Understanding your family history is an important piece of the puzzle, according to Dr. Kopecky. But it’s equally important not to blow genetic risk out of proportion. Genetics account for 20% to 30% of your risk, Dr. Kopecky says. But positive habits such as regular exercise and a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/in-depth/heart-healthy-diet/art-20047702" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">healthy diet</a> can impact your genes much more drastically.</p>



<p>“Certain good lifestyles can ‘turn off’ the bad genes and ‘turn on’ the good genes,” Dr. Kopecky explains. “We see patients in our prevention clinic with very high cholesterol, genetically determined. We know that if they have a good lifestyle, starting early in life, it lowers their heart attack and stroke risk.” In other words, Dr. Kopecky says the day-to-day, year-over-year habits you make to protect your heart health are oftentimes much more impactful than the genetic lottery.</p>



<p>There’s no magic or any one routine that will prevent heart disease and its more serious complications such as heart attack and stroke. By now, most people know it’s the small, consistent choices in all parts of life that add up in big ways.</p>



<p>“If you have genetic risk factors, it’s more important to have a healthy lifestyle,” Dr. Kopecky says. “I tell patients frequently: You have a new part-time job called ‘your health’.”</p>



<p>To get started, consider the following strategies:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Incorporate a variety of nutritious foods.</strong>&nbsp;When making choices for meals and snacks, emphasize fresh fruits, vegetables, legumes and whole grains. Limit overly sugary, salty and processed foods that can raise blood pressure and cholesterol.</li>



<li><strong>Move as much as you can.</strong>&nbsp;For adults, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) recommends a minimum of 150 minutes of moderate activity every week. Exercise can help lower blood pressure, decrease cholesterol levels and maintain a heart-healthy weight. To get started, Dr. Kopecky recommends incorporating as much movement into your day as possible — and making time for light strength training and interval workouts as often as you can. Gardening, walking and taking the stairs all count!</li>



<li><strong>Prioritize sleep.</strong>&nbsp;Dr. Kopecky says getting enough quality sleep is critical for your heart health and overall quality of life. To ensure you’re well rested, Dr. Kopecky recommends consistently going to bed and waking up at the same time. “Don’t set an alarm to wake up. Set an alarm to go to sleep or get ready to go to bed,” he adds. “You shouldn’t need an alarm to wake up unless you’re traveling. Just wake up on your own.”</li>



<li><strong>Quit smoking and avoid alcohol.</strong>&nbsp;Heart attacks are more common in people who smoke. If you use any tobacco products, quitting as soon as possible helps lower your risk of heart disease. Similarly, it’s a good idea to limit your alcohol intake or avoid alcohol altogether.</li>



<li><strong>Lean on your healthcare team.</strong>&nbsp;If you have a family history of heart attack or heart disease — especially in first-degree relatives such as parents or siblings — or are unsure of your risk, talk with your healthcare team. Your care team also can help you determine the best plan for protecting your heart health.</li>
</ul>



<p>Though it can seem overwhelming to make so many changes, just remember: Dr. Kopecky says nothing you do is ever too little or too late. When it comes to your heart health, you may find that positive reinforcement is a much more powerful motivator than shame or fear. Even small changes can compound and help protect your heart health, so do what you can as often as you can and celebrate the successes along the way.</p>



<p>For more information about heart health, please visit <a href="https://mcpress.mayoclinic.org/healthy-heart/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Press</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">MayoClinic.org</a>.</p>



<p>###&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Sharon Theimer, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/expert-explains-how-to-improve-heart-health-even-if-your-family-has-history-of-heart-conditions/">Expert explains how to improve heart health, even if your family has history of heart conditions</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Child-man-grocery-produce-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Child-man-grocery-produce-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Cholesterol — know your numbers</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-cholesterol-know-your-numbers/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Abby Smith]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 16:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Arizona]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[diverse representation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Regis Fernandes]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=397690</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;I am in my 30s and overweight, but I thought I was too young to worry about cholesterol. I just learned my&nbsp;cholesterol is high. I know diet and exercise are important. Do I need medication?&nbsp; ANSWER:&nbsp;Cholesterol is a type of fat in our blood. Our bodies need a small amount of cholesterol to […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-cholesterol-know-your-numbers/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Cholesterol — know your numbers</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-young-Latino-man-with-a-serious-look-on-his-face-standing-with-his-arms-crossed-in-a-loft-apartment-or-office-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a young Latino man with a serious look on his face, standing with his arms crossed in a loft apartment or office" class="wp-image-371417" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-young-Latino-man-with-a-serious-look-on-his-face-standing-with-his-arms-crossed-in-a-loft-apartment-or-office-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-young-Latino-man-with-a-serious-look-on-his-face-standing-with-his-arms-crossed-in-a-loft-apartment-or-office-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-young-Latino-man-with-a-serious-look-on-his-face-standing-with-his-arms-crossed-in-a-loft-apartment-or-office-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-young-Latino-man-with-a-serious-look-on-his-face-standing-with-his-arms-crossed-in-a-loft-apartment-or-office-16X9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-young-Latino-man-with-a-serious-look-on-his-face-standing-with-his-arms-crossed-in-a-loft-apartment-or-office-16X9.jpg 1688w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>


<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;</strong>I am in my 30s and overweight, but I thought I was too young to worry about cholesterol. I just learned my&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-cholesterol/symptoms-causes/syc-20350800" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cholesterol is high</a>. I know diet and exercise are important. Do I need medication?&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong>&nbsp;Cholesterol is a type of fat in our blood. Our bodies need a small amount of cholesterol to build the structure of cell membranes, make certain hormones and help with metabolism, such as producing vitamin D. The catch: We don't need too much cholesterol.&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/arteriosclerosis-atherosclerosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20350569" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Atherosclerosis</a>, also known as narrowing of the arteries, happens when cholesterol builds up and blocks blood flow. This buildup is called plaque, which can clog arteries and can burst, leading to a blood clot. Atherosclerosis can cause heart problems such as chest pain (<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/angina/symptoms-causes/syc-20369373" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">angina</a>) or&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-attack/symptoms-causes/syc-20373106" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart attack</a>. It also can lead to problems in the brain, including&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/transient-ischemic-attack/symptoms-causes/syc-20355679" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">transient ischemic attack</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stroke/symptoms-causes/syc-20350113" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stroke</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/peripheral-artery-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350557" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">peripheral artery disease</a>&nbsp;in the legs or arms, and even&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/kidney-failure/symptoms-causes/syc-20369048" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">kidney failure</a>.</p>



<p>Cholesterol and&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-high-triglycerides-mean-and-why-it-matters-to-your-heart/">triglycerides</a>&nbsp;are types of lipids. They travel in our blood by attaching to proteins. Adults 20 and older should ask their healthcare team about their&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-cholesterol/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20350806" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lipid profile and how to interpret the numbers</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol:</strong>&nbsp;We call LDL "bad" cholesterol. Below 100 milligrams per deciliter (mg/dl) is optimal for healthy people in the absence of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/coronary-artery-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350613">coronary artery disease</a>. If you have&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">&nbsp;disease</a>, your LDL should be below 70 mg/dl.&nbsp;Treatment decisions to reach appropriate levels need to be based on personal risk factors.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>High-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol:&nbsp;</strong>We call HDL "good" cholesterol. It absorbs cholesterol in the blood and brings it to the liver, which flushes it from the body. For females, it should be above 50 mg/dl. For males, it should be above 40 mg/dl.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Triglycerides:</strong>&nbsp;Triglycerides are a type of fat we use for energy. If you have too high of a triglycerides level, it can cause heart disease. Less than 150 mg/dl is optimal.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Total cholesterol: This</strong>&nbsp;is the sum of LDL and HDL cholesterol plus 20% of triglyceride levels. A total cholesterol level below 200 mg/dl is desirable.</li>
</ul>



<p>Some people who are overweight may get heart disease not because their LDL is high but, rather, because their HDL is low and their triglycerides are high. That relationship can cause heart disease as much or even more than just high LDL cholesterol. These lipid abnormalities are significant for young people in their 30s or 40s who are overweight. Their triglyceride levels increase, and their HDL lowers. They're becoming&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prediabetes/symptoms-causes/syc-20355278" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">prediabetic</a>. Their LDL is staying the same, but they're still heading to heart disease.&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1604" height="902" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Lipid-panel-cholesterol-triglycerides-16x9-1.jpg" alt="Lipid panel cholesterol triglycerides" class="wp-image-380777" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Lipid-panel-cholesterol-triglycerides-16x9-1.jpg 1604w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Lipid-panel-cholesterol-triglycerides-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Lipid-panel-cholesterol-triglycerides-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Lipid-panel-cholesterol-triglycerides-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Lipid-panel-cholesterol-triglycerides-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1604px) 100vw, 1604px"></figure>



<p>Treating high cholesterol depends on individual risk. The higher the risk — for example, with someone who already had a heart attack — a higher percent of reduction is needed. Medication to lower cholesterol can reduce LDL by about 60% to 65%. Lifestyle changes can reduce LDL by 10% to 15%.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Several medications can help manage lipids. Discuss options with your healthcare team.</p>



<p>The body's ability to handle cholesterol is genetically determined. Genetic disorders that raise cholesterol levels are common.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/familial-hypercholesterolemia/symptoms-causes/syc-20353755" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Familial hypercholesterolemia</a>&nbsp;usually is caused by a genetic mutation preventing the body from clearing cholesterol. People with the condition are more likely to require medication to reduce their cholesterol levels.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For people with genetic disorders that expose them to elevated cholesterol since birth, heart disease can happen at a younger age. So we start treating their high cholesterol with medication at a young age.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Beyond medication, lifestyle modifications help manage lipids:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Limit meat and dairy intake; they have&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/fat/art-20045550" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">saturated fat</a>, which raises LDL cholesterol.</li>



<li>Consume more fish,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/fiber/art-20043983" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">soluble fiber</a>, fruit and vegetables.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Avoid diets high in carbohydrates, particularly refined carbs like sugar and white flour. They raise the blood sugar level quickly, raising triglycerides. Reducing simple refined carbohydrates helps lower triglycerides and weight because you store less fat.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Control your weight. It lowers your triglycerides and improves your HDL levels.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Exercise about 150 minutes of aerobic activity a week at a moderate intensity. Moderate intensity means you must breathe through your mouth. If you're breathing through your nose, that is low intensity. Exercise prevents cholesterol from building up, but it doesn't change LDL concentration levels. You must burn about 2,000 calories a week to lower LDL concentration. However, exercise helps lower triglyceride levels and maintain weight loss.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Do&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/fitness/in-depth/strength-training/art-20046031">strength training</a>&nbsp;at least twice a week. It helps your cardiovascular and muscular systems. Not everything we do to prevent heart disease is about cholesterol.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>The National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute recommends people get their first cholesterol screening between ages 9 and 11, and repeat it every five years. For men 45 to 65 and women 55 to 65, cholesterol screenings should occur every one to two years. Over 65? Test annually. More frequent testing may be needed for people who have or are at risk for&nbsp;coronary artery disease. —&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/fernandes-regis-i-m-d/bio-20305254" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em><strong>Regis Fernandes, M.D.</strong></em></a><em>,<strong>&nbsp;Cardiovascular Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Phoenix</strong></em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-cholesterol-know-your-numbers/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Cholesterol — know your numbers</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-young-Latino-man-with-a-serious-look-on-his-face-standing-with-his-arms-crossed-in-a-loft-apartment-or-office-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-young-Latino-man-with-a-serious-look-on-his-face-standing-with-his-arms-crossed-in-a-loft-apartment-or-office-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[diverse representation]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Regis Fernandes]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Suffering from cold feet?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-suffering-from-cold-feet/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Deb Balzer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 16:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Arizona]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Cycle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jesse Bracamonte]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=399249</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Do your feet always feel cold, even when it's not chilly outside? While cold weather can be a common cause, persistent cold feet might point to something more — like circulatory issues, immune problems or nerve disorders. Dr. Jesse Bracamonte, a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician, says it's important to seek medical advice if the […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-suffering-from-cold-feet/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Suffering from cold feet?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<p-->Do your feet always feel <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/cold-feet-that-arent-cold-to-the-touch-may-indicate-neurologic-problem/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cold</a>, even when it's not chilly outside? While cold weather can be a common cause, persistent cold feet might point to something more — like <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/treatment-options-for-poor-circulation-in-feet/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">circulatory issues</a>, immune problems or <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-may-be-causing-your-hands-and-feet-to-tingle/">nerve disorders</a>.<p></p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/bracamonte-jesse-d-d-o/bio-20432246" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Jesse Bracamonte</a>, a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician, says it's important to seek medical advice if the condition persists. Getting evaluated can help identify and treat any underlying health conditions.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/mfjly7ZhaU0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubemfjly7ZhaU0" title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Suffering from cold feet" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mfjly7ZhaU0?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p></p>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (0:55) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/SCRIPT-MCM-Suffering-from-cold-feet_.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">&nbsp;script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Sometimes, cold feet simply mean you need warmer socks. But if your feet are always cold, no matter the weather, it might be something more.</p>



<p>"Anything from circulatory problems, not having adequate blood flow, heart condition problems, immune or autoimmune conditions such as like having thyroid disease, and sometimes nerve or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/peripheral-neuropathy/symptoms-causes/syc-20352061?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;cauid=100721">neuropathic </a>problems. Having nerve disorders can cause cold feet," says Dr. Bracamonte.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/peripheral-neuropathy/symptoms-causes/syc-20352061" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="522" height="294" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Peripheral-neuropathy-feet-16-x-9.jpg" alt="a medical illustration of peripheral neuropathy" class="wp-image-399431" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Peripheral-neuropathy-feet-16-x-9.jpg 522w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Peripheral-neuropathy-feet-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 522px) 100vw, 522px"></a></figure></div>


<p>Where to start? He offers a few immediate steps.</p>



<p>"Warm socks, lifting your feet, staying hydrated, diet, nutrition is really important. Exercise is important. And, obviously, if you smoke, don't smoke," he says.</p>



<p>If your feet remain to feel cold but are not cold to the touch, it might be time to see your healthcare team.</p>



<p>"There are certain tests that it can easily be done to ensure that you have no circulatory issues, and a few blood tests may be warranted just to make sure you have no autoimmune issues or even signs of anemia," Dr. Bracamonte says.</p>



<p><strong>Related posts:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tapping-regenerative-sciences-to-unlock-mysteries-of-peripheral-neuropathy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tapping regenerative sciences to unlock mysteries of peripheral neuropathy</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-may-be-causing-your-hands-and-feet-to-tingle/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: What may be causing your hands and feet to tingle</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-suffering-from-cold-feet/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Suffering from cold feet?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Cold-Feet-1-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Cold-Feet-1-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Jesse Bracamonte]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: What to do for a healthier heart</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-to-do-for-a-healthier-heart/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Alex Osiadacz]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 15:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Florida]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Diet]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Demilade Adedinsewo]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Exercise]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Heart Health Month]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Sleep]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=380638</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Heart disease&nbsp;is the leading cause of death in the U.S., according to the American Heart Association. Heart disease refers to a range of conditions, of which many can be prevented or treated by making healthy lifestyle choices. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:07) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-to-do-for-a-healthier-heart/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What to do for a healthier heart</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<p--><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Heart disease</a>&nbsp;is the leading cause of death in the U.S., according to the <a href="https://www.heart.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Heart Association</a>. Heart disease refers to a range of conditions, of which many can be prevented or treated by making healthy lifestyle choices.<p></p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/wXk1Nj28Hm4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubewXk1Nj28Hm4" title="Mayo Clinic Minute - What to do for a healthier heart" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wXk1Nj28Hm4?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:07) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network."</strong> Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Mayo-Clinic-Minute-What-to-do-for-a-healthier-heart_SCRIPT.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>The average heart beats 100,000 times per day, circulating blood and oxygen throughout the body.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/adedinsewo-demilade-a-m-b-ch-b/bio-20502753?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Demilade Adedinsewo</a> (DEM-eee-LAH-day Ah-day-deen-SHAY-wo), a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/cardiovascular-medicine/home/orc-20121930?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiologist</a>, says that to keep the heart healthy, there are eight behaviors and numbers to keep in check.</p>



<p>Let's start with sleep.</p>



<p>"Seven to eight hours of sleep at night is recommended for ideal cardiovascular health," says Dr. Adedinsewo. "Fewer hours or poor-quality sleep can lead to physical symptoms that impact the rest of your body, including your heart."</p>



<p>In addition to sleep, it's important to:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Maintain an appropriate weight.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Keep blood glucose, blood cholesterol and blood pressure within range.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Avoid smoking and secondhand smoke exposure.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Follow an eating plan rich in nutrients, such as the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/mediterranean-diet/art-20047801?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mediterranean</a> or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/dash-diet/art-20048456?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">DASH</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/dash-diet/art-20048456?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"> </a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/dash-diet/art-20048456?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">diets</a>.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Exercise.</li>
</ul>



<p>"Get at least <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-stacking-your-exercise-over-the-weekend/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">150 minutes</a> of moderate-intensity physical activity every week," says Dr. Adedinsewo. "This does not necessarily have to be split up 30 minutes, five days a week, even though that's an easy way that we think about it. Really, every little thing that you do adds up."</p>



<p>Related posts:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-do-you-practice-good-sleep-hygiene/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">Mayo Clinic Minute: Do you practice good sleep hygiene?</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-heart-disease-in-african-american-women/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">Mayo Clinic Minute: Heart disease in African American women</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-jump-start-your-workout/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">Mayo Clinic Minute: How to jump-start your workout</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-to-do-for-a-healthier-heart/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What to do for a healthier heart</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/03/a-health-care-provider-in-a-white-lab-coat-and-stethoscope-holding-a-red-plastic-heart-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/03/a-health-care-provider-in-a-white-lab-coat-and-stethoscope-holding-a-red-plastic-heart-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Diet]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Demilade Adedinsewo]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Exercise]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Heart Health Month]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Sleep]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: What to eat for a healthy heart</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-what-to-eat-for-a-healthy-heart/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Abby Smith]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 16:47:59 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[diverse representation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Juan Cardenas Rosales]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=396857</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;We hear a lot about "heart-healthy" diets, but the guidance seems to always change. It's confusing to me. What foods are important, and what should we avoid?&nbsp; ANSWER:&nbsp;One of the most important factors for a healthy heart is to try to follow a healthy diet. We usually recommend a&nbsp;Mediterranean diet, which is mostly […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-what-to-eat-for-a-healthy-heart/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: What to eat for a healthy heart</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/business-people-eating-healthy-lunch-packed-in-home-containers-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="business people eating healthy lunch packed in home containers" class="wp-image-177898" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/business-people-eating-healthy-lunch-packed-in-home-containers-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/business-people-eating-healthy-lunch-packed-in-home-containers-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/business-people-eating-healthy-lunch-packed-in-home-containers-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong>&nbsp;We hear a lot about "<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-navigating-nutrition-for-heart-health/">heart-healthy</a>" diets, but the guidance seems to always change. It's confusing to me. What foods are important, and what should we avoid?&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong>&nbsp;One of the most important factors for a healthy heart is to try to follow a healthy diet. We usually recommend a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/mediterranean-diet/art-20047801">Mediterranean diet</a>, which is mostly based on trying to eat more white meat, such as fish and chicken, instead of red meat, such as beef or pork. This type of diet also focuses on eating more vegetables, fruits, nuts, seeds, legumes, beans, whole grains and olive oil.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Studies have shown that people living in Mediterranean countries, such as Italy and Greece, are less likely to die of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118">heart disease</a>.&nbsp;The World Health Organization recognizes the Mediterranean diet as a healthy eating pattern. Many nutrition experts in the U.S. recommend it and it is important to follow the diet long term in order to see heart benefits.</p>



<p>Cutting out&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-cholesterol/in-depth/trans-fat/art-20046114">trans fats</a>&nbsp;in fried food, frozen pizza and microwave popcorn, and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/the-not-so-sweet-truth-of-added-sugars">added sugar</a>&nbsp;in soda, sweets and pastries is also important for your heart health. Switching your snacks, especially before or after exercising, from cookies or chocolates to carrots or broccoli, can help you continue to snack but with beneficial ingredients. Staying hydrated helps your heart pump blood more effectively and benefits your blood vessels and muscles. Drink at least 2 liters of water each day.</p>



<p>Avoiding tobacco and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/alcohol/art-20044551">alcohol consumption</a>&nbsp;are important factors to prevent future cardiovascular conditions. It has been shown that after just one year of quitting tobacco use, your risk of having a cardiovascular event drops in half in comparison with patients who smoke tobacco. That's how big the impact of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/nicotine-dependence/symptoms-causes/syc-20351584">quitting tobacco</a>&nbsp;use is on your heart, and it's never too late to stop. Alcohol use can trigger difficulty for you to fall asleep, and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/sleep-disorders/symptoms-causes/syc-20354018">sleep disorders</a>&nbsp;have been linked to heart disease. Incorporating these healthy habits will make you more likely to have refreshed sleep.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Following diet trends such as making the switch to strictly plant-based or vegan or going gluten- or lactose-free is individual to each person because patients may have an intolerance to this type of food or its components. In general, low-sugar, low-salt and low-carb diets are usually helpful for all our patients to stay out of cardiovascular risk.&nbsp;</p>



<p>By maintaining a healthy lifestyle, you can avoid some medical conditions in the future such as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-pressure/symptoms-causes/syc-20373410">hypertension</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/diabetes/symptoms-causes/syc-20371444">diabetes</a> and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-cholesterol/symptoms-causes/syc-20350800">high cholesterol</a>. These conditions increase your risk of having a cardiovascular event such as a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-attack/symptoms-causes/syc-20373106">heart attack</a>&nbsp;or a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stroke/symptoms-causes/syc-20350113">stroke</a>. One of my best tips is to start adjusting your lifestyle little by little but consistently, taking baby steps&nbsp;— even if you adjust just one factor per day or per week, whether that's trying to cut down on the amount of high sugar, high fat or high salt in your diet. Little by little and with time, those changes will remain and will help you prevent any type of long-term medical condition in the future.&nbsp;<em>—&nbsp;</em><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/cardenas-rosales-juan-c-m-d/bio-20526630"><strong><em>Juan Cardenas Rosales, M.D.</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Internal Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Jacksonville, Florida</em></strong></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-what-to-eat-for-a-healthy-heart/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: What to eat for a healthy heart</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/01/woman-shopping-in-grocery-store-for-healthy-food-vegetables-1x1-square.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/01/woman-shopping-in-grocery-store-for-healthy-food-vegetables-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[diverse representation]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Juan Cardenas Rosales]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: &nbsp;Leg pain? It may be your arteries</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-leg-pain-it-may-be-your-arteries/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Susan Barber Lindquist]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 15:30:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cardiovascular]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Health & Wellness]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Fahad Shuja]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=397510</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;I'm 52 years old and enjoy long walks with my husband and our dog. I recently started to experience pain in my left calf during our walks. The leg pain goes away when I rest. Because I have a history of high blood pressure, I went to see my primary care physician and […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-leg-pain-it-may-be-your-arteries/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: &nbsp;Leg pain? It may be your arteries</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/12/a-woman-man-and-dog-walking-down-a-snowy-path-in-the-woods-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a woman, man and dog walking down a snowy path in the woods" class="wp-image-109367" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/12/a-woman-man-and-dog-walking-down-a-snowy-path-in-the-woods-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/12/a-woman-man-and-dog-walking-down-a-snowy-path-in-the-woods-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/12/a-woman-man-and-dog-walking-down-a-snowy-path-in-the-woods-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong>&nbsp;I'm 52 years old and enjoy long walks with my husband and our dog. I recently started to experience pain in my left calf during our walks. The leg pain goes away when I rest. Because I have a history of high blood pressure, I went to see my primary care physician and was diagnosed with peripheral artery disease. What is this condition, and what treatments are available? Will I need surgery?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:&nbsp;</strong><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-is-peripheral-artery-disease-diagnosed/">Peripheral artery disease</a>&nbsp;is a common, chronic medical condition that affects circulation in the body due to narrowed arteries. The narrowing of arteries is caused by a buildup of fatty deposits, called plaque, which reduces blood flow from the heart to different regions of the body. This can affect the arms, but most commonly, it is an issue found in the legs.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/peripheral-artery-disease-16-x-9.jpg" alt="Medical illustration of peripheral artery disease" class="wp-image-348220" style="width:690px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/peripheral-artery-disease-16-x-9.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/peripheral-artery-disease-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px"></figure></div>


<p>The risk of developing peripheral artery disease increases with age, particularly for those over 65 or after 50 if you have certain risk factors. Factors that can contribute to your risk include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>A family history of peripheral artery disease, heart disease or stroke</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-pressure/symptoms-causes/syc-20373410">High blood pressure</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-cholesterol/symptoms-causes/syc-20350800">High cholesterol</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/diabetes/symptoms-causes/syc-20371444">Diabetes</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/chronic-kidney-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20354521">Chronic kidney disease</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/obesity/symptoms-causes/syc-20375742">Obesity</a>&nbsp;(a body mass index over 30)</li>



<li>Smoking tobacco/using tobacco products</li>
</ul>



<p>Many people with peripheral artery disease have mild or no symptoms, while others experience leg pain when walking or even at rest. The severity of your symptoms and the extent of the blockage are used to categorize the stage of your peripheral artery disease and inform specific treatment options.</p>



<p>There are two stages of peripheral artery disease. The early stage is called&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/claudication/symptoms-causes/syc-20370952">claudication</a>, when people experience pain when walking or engaging in activity. In this stage, the pain begins during exercise and ends with rest. It is usually felt in the calves, thighs and buttocks.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The advanced, severe stage of peripheral artery disease is called critical limb threatening ischemia. During this stage, pain is often felt in the feet, even without walking, and is worse during rest or when lying down. You also may experience open sores or wounds on your limbs or feet that won't heal. Critical limb threatening ischemia may cause tissue death or gangrene on your feet. If this goes untreated, it can lead to leg amputation.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/peripheral-artery-disease/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20350563">Treatment</a>&nbsp;for peripheral artery disease varies depending on its severity. When it's diagnosed early, lifestyle changes and treatment of underlying medical conditions are often enough to manage symptoms. This may mean taking appropriate medications to control high blood pressure and high cholesterol, controlling blood sugar levels if you have diabetes, quitting smoking, eating a healthier diet with fewer fatty and highly processed foods, and regular exercise or engaging in a walking program.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For more advanced disease, restoration of blood flow is necessary in addition to lifestyle changes. Therefore, the goal of surgery is to restore blood flow and prevent leg amputation.&nbsp;</p>



<p>One treatment option is percutaneous endovascular surgery, a minimally invasive approach. In this operation, the surgeon guides a thin, flexible tube called a catheter through the groin, foot or wrist to the narrowed part of the artery. A tiny balloon is inflated to widen the blocked artery and improve blood flow. A stent, a small wire mesh tube, may also be placed in the artery to keep it open.</p>



<p>The more invasive surgical option is bypass surgery. The surgeon creates a path around the blocked artery using either a healthy blood vessel from another part of the body or a synthetic one. One end of the healthy vein is connected to the artery above the blockage, and the other is attached below the blockage so that the blood will detour into the bypass.&nbsp;</p>



<p>When diagnosed with peripheral artery disease, it’s important to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/vascular-and-endovascular-surgery/overview/ovc-20458819">consult a vascular surgeon</a>&nbsp;to determine the best treatment for you. Vascular surgeons can perform both minimally invasive procedures and complex bypass surgery.&nbsp;</p>



<p>By incorporating lifestyle changes and treating any underlying medical conditions early, you can significantly improve your quality of life and prevent progression to more severe stages of disease. Peripheral artery disease is a marker for your overall cardiovascular health, and managing it correctly can lead to a longer, healthier life. —&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/shuja-fahad-m-b-b-s/bio-20323775"><strong><em>Fahad Shuja, M.B.B.S.,</em></strong></a><strong><em>&nbsp;Vascular Surgery, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota</em></strong><strong></strong></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-leg-pain-it-may-be-your-arteries/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: &nbsp;Leg pain? It may be your arteries</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/04/Senior-leg-pain_1x1-e1678115582794.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/04/Senior-leg-pain_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Fahad Shuja]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</atom:link></channel>
</rss> 