<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Cardiovascular - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cardiovascular-2/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/cardiovascular-2/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 14:06:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Peripheral artery system at risk of disease due to family history, lifestyle</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/peripheral-artery-system-at-risk-of-disease-due-to-family-history-lifestyle/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[amandadyslin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 15:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cardioloy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cardiovascular disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Michel Barsoum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News app]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[peripheral artery disease]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=382536</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Eau Claire, Wis. — Most people have heard of heart attacks occurring because of a blocked coronary artery. But the body has two types of artery systems: the coronary artery system, which relates to the heart, and peripheral artery system, which involves the arteries carrying oxygenated blood to the arms, legs, brain and the rest [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/peripheral-artery-system-at-risk-of-disease-due-to-family-history-lifestyle/">Peripheral artery system at risk of disease due to family history, lifestyle</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/a-medical-illustration-of-a-healthy-artery-and-one-with-peripheral-artery-disease-16X9.jpg" alt="a medical illustration of a healthy artery and one with peripheral artery disease" class="wp-image-112263" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/a-medical-illustration-of-a-healthy-artery-and-one-with-peripheral-artery-disease-16X9.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/a-medical-illustration-of-a-healthy-artery-and-one-with-peripheral-artery-disease-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></figure></div>


<p>Eau Claire, Wis. — Most people have heard of heart attacks occurring because of a blocked coronary artery. But the body has two types of artery systems: the coronary artery system, which relates to the heart, and <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/peripheral-artery-disease-can-signal-cardiovascular-trouble-for-heart-brain-and-legs/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">peripheral artery system</a>, which involves the arteries carrying oxygenated blood to the arms, legs, brain and the rest of the body.</p>



<p>"Just like coronary arteries, peripheral arteries can become diseased," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/michel-barsoum-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Michel Barsoum, M.B., Ch.B.</a>, a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/cardiology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiologist</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/vascular-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">vascular medicine</a> specialist at Mayo Clinic Health System in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/chippewa-falls" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Chippewa Falls</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/eau-claire" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Eau Claire</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/rice-lake" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Rice Lake</a>, Wisconsin. "This condition, called <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-is-peripheral-artery-disease-diagnosed/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">peripheral artery disease,</a> or PAD, narrows arteries and reduces blood flow due to a buildup of fatty and calcium deposits on the artery walls."</p>



<p>This can cause claudication, which is muscle pain and cramping when a person is active but usually disappears after a few minutes of rest.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Risk factors for peripheral artery disease</h3>



<p>"So who is at risk of peripheral artery disease? People who smoke or have diabetes at any age are at the greatest risk," says Dr. Barsoum.</p>



<p><strong>Other risk factors include:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Body mass index&nbsp;over 30.</li>



<li>Family history&nbsp;of PAD, heart disease or stroke.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-pressure/symptoms-causes/syc-20373410" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">High blood pressure</a>.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-cholesterol/symptoms-causes/syc-20350800" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">High cholesterol</a>.</li>



<li>Increasing age, especially if you are 65 or older.<br></li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Symptoms include:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Aching or cramping in the arms when knitting, writing or performing other manual tasks.</li>



<li>Change in the color of your leg or arm.</li>



<li>Coldness of the lower leg or foot even after walking in a warm weather.</li>



<li>Sores on the toes, feet or leg that don't heal.</li>



<li>Weakening pulse in the foot.</li>



<li>Erectile dysfunction in men.</li>



<li>Hair loss on the legs.<br></li>
</ul>



<p>"If neck arteries to your brain are affected, symptoms may include difficulty talking, weakness in the arms and legs, or loss of vision," says Dr. Barsoum. "If you experience any of these symptoms, make an appointment with a vascular medicine specialist, who will conduct a physical exam and record your health history."</p>



<p>The exam will include finding a pulse in the affected neck artery and comparing it with the pulse in the unaffected neck artery. Vascular medicine specialists have a wide range of tools available, depending on the degree of your symptoms, to help you return to the activities you love.</p>



<p>For example, if you can walk a few blocks with only mild pain, they may prescribe medications such as aspirin, statins or blood thinners. They also may discuss ways you can modify your risk factors, including quitting smoking; controlling blood pressure, cholesterol and diabetes; and increasing your activity level.</p>



<p>If you have more significant symptoms, such as not being able to tolerate the pain when walking, a vascular medicine specialist typically will order an ultrasound or a CT scan with contrast, or even an angiogram to determine the location and degree of the blockage. Your care team will discuss a variety of surgical options to deal with the blockage.</p>



<p>"Prevention of peripheral artery disease is always the best treatment," says Dr. Barsoum. "Quit smoking, eat a heart-healthy diet, exercise regularly, keep your blood sugar in check if you have diabetes, maintain a healthy weight, and manage your blood pressure and cholesterol levels."</p>



<p>In addition, if you have one or more risk factors, avoid certain over-the-counter cold remedies that contain&nbsp;pseudoephedrine. These medications constrict your blood vessels and might worsen your symptoms.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><a><strong>About Mayo Clinic Health System</strong></a></p>



<p><a href="https://mayoclinichealthsystem.org">Mayo Clinic Health System</a> has a physical presence in 44 communities and consists of 53 clinics, 16 hospitals and other facilities that serve the healthcare needs of people in Iowa, Minnesota and Wisconsin. The community-based healthcare professionals, paired with the resources and expertise of Mayo Clinic, enable patients in the region to receive the highest-quality physical and virtual healthcare close to home.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong> Amanda Dyslin, Mayo Clinic Health System Communications Department, <a href="mailto:dyslin.amanda@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/symptoms-that-may-require-a-consultation-with-a-cardiologist/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Symptoms that may require a consultation with a cardiologist</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-month-mayo-clinic-says-heart-attack-symptoms-in-women-are-often-different-than-men/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Heart attack symptoms in women are often different than men</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/take-heart-murmurs-seriously/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Take heart murmurs seriously</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/peripheral-artery-system-at-risk-of-disease-due-to-family-history-lifestyle/">Peripheral artery system at risk of disease due to family history, lifestyle</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/a-medical-illustration-of-peripheral-artery-disease-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/peripheral-artery-disease-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cardioloy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cardiovascular disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Michel Barsoum]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News app]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[peripheral artery disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>A promise delivered: A new heart for a new mom</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-promise-delivered-a-new-heart-for-a-new-mom/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tia R. Ford]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 13:29:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Rohan Goswami]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Promise Garell]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=382509</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A challenge from the beginning Promise Garell grew up with a congenital heart defect. She was born with transposition of the great arteries, where her heart vessels and her heart were not correctly transfigured, preventing her heart from providing adequate blood flow to the rest of her body. Her first surgery to address this was [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-promise-delivered-a-new-heart-for-a-new-mom/">A promise delivered: A new heart for a new mom</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-and-Paxton-Garell16x9-1024x577.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-382515" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-and-Paxton-Garell16x9-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-and-Paxton-Garell16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-and-Paxton-Garell16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-and-Paxton-Garell16x9-1536x865.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-and-Paxton-Garell16x9-2048x1153.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A challenge from the beginning</h2>



<p>Promise Garell grew up with a congenital heart defect. She was born with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/transposition-of-the-great-arteries/symptoms-causes/syc-20350589" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">transposition of the great arteries</a>, where her heart vessels and her heart were not correctly transfigured, preventing her heart from providing adequate blood flow to the rest of her body. Her first surgery to address this was at 3 days old. Throughout her formative years, she says her childhood was normal. She was active and even played sports.</p>



<p>"I was fine until I was probably 8 years old, when the symptoms started," says Promise. "At the time, I was having signs of a heart attack, but it was because my troponin levels were elevated. This would happen sporadically when I was working out or playing softball."</p>



<p>It would be another seven years before Promise would receive open-heart surgery to address these issues. "I think I was 15, and finally, after about seven years of having these issues and being in and out of the emergency room undergoing constant testing, I received an invasive procedure that lasted about 5 ½ hours," says Promise. "Luckily, after that surgery, I was pretty healthy."</p>



<p>In 2020, she married her husband, Andrew, who serves in the Navy. By early 2022 at age 24, Promise received the exciting news that their family was growing. She was expecting their first child. About six months into her pregnancy, she began to struggle. The toll of carrying a growing baby led to complications during her pregnancy, including congestive heart failure.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Watch Promise's Story</h3>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/WF3186101_Promise-Garell_Heart-Transplant_Feb19_ExternalV2_MAM-2.mp4"></video><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Promise Garell tells her story</figcaption></figure>



<p>"I was fine for the first couple of months, and then the third trimester came, and my body could not handle the fluid shifts," says Promise. "Due to that, I ended up in cardiogenic shock, which is pretty much where your whole body is just shutting down because your heart is no longer perfusing like it's supposed to."</p>



<p>Promise's son, Paxton, was born 11 weeks early in June. He spent two months in a neonatal intensive care unit. Throughout this time, Promise's health continued to decline due to heart failure. She would spend time in and out of several hospitals as teams tried to determine the best course for her care. Ultimately, Promise and her family made the decision to transfer to Mayo Clinic.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Mayo Clinic provides new heart, new lease on life</h2>



<p>In early September 2022, Promise arrived at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a>. Throughout her life, she says she always kept Mayo Clinic in the back of her mind as one of the top healthcare institutions she would use in the event of an emergency.</p>



<p>"As a congenital heart defect patient or someone with lifelong heart issues, you always keep in mind the right places to go just in case something happens," says Promise. "And luckily, it worked in my favor."</p>



<p>Thanks to a timely military transfer, stationing her husband at Naval Air Station Jacksonville, Promise was now close enough to the healthcare institution she often thought about throughout her health journey. "The Navy definitely got us where we needed to be at the right time," says Promise.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img decoding="async" width="225" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-garell2-225x300.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-382528" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-garell2-225x300.jpeg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-garell2-768x1024.jpeg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-garell2-1152x1536.jpeg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-garell2-1536x2048.jpeg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /></figure></div>


<p>Doctors immediately knew Promise needed to be transferred to the ICU, where temporary pumps and medication helped keep her alive until her care team could figure out if she was a candidate for a transplant and if she would survive one.</p>



<p>"When we met Promise for the first time, we realized she was probably one of the sickest patients that we would encounter," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/goswami-rohan-m-m-d/bio-20432467" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Rohan Goswami</a>, a Mayo Clinic transplant cardiologist. "It was clear within minutes of seeing her she was going to need to be transferred to the ICU. We had a new mother really working to survive to take care of her family."</p>



<p>Two days after arriving, she was added to the heart transplant waitlist.</p>



<p>"I knew the doctors were going to do what they needed to get me on the list, to get me a heart," says Promise. "I think them knowing that I had a 3-month-old son was just as much a motivation for them as it was for me."</p>



<p>Seeking a plan on how to transplant Promise's heart, the team needed more information about the vessels in her heart. "We needed to have a game plan for how we were going to take the heart out, what type of heart we were going to accept, and how we were going to implant it," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/patel-parag-c-m-d/bio-20055567" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Parag Patel</a>, a Mayo Clinic transplant cardiologist.</p>



<p>3D technology emerged as the solution. Given the complexity of her situation, surgery would not have been possible without a 3D rendering for planning. The 3D team received the request from Promise's transplant team, and within 24 hours, they were able to research, design and deliver.</p>



<p>"Through a multidisciplinary fashion with our heart transplant team, critical care team, cardiothoracic team and cardiac anesthesia, we were able to work together to find out what things would prevent us from being successful with her care," says Dr. Patel. "It became very evident that in order to optimize her care, we needed to know what we were getting into, how her heart position was actually related to her chest wall, and how her vessels were within her chest. So we reached out to our 3D printing team and our 3D reconstruction team and asked them to reconstruct Promise's heart."</p>



<p>The 3D renderings helped the team to quickly establish a game plan. The surgeons were able to reference the model in the operating room even as they performed her procedure.</p>



<p>When listed for her transplant, Promise's team decided to employ a strategy for a donation after cardiac death heart using ex vivo perfusion, also known as "heart-in a box." This allowed the heart to beat while being transported from the donor center, and, thereby, allowed physicians to monitor the donor heart closely to ensure it was stable before the transplant. Her doctors say both hearts — her "original" heart and the donor's heart — were beating simultaneously in the same room prior to the start of the procedure. Organ perfusion systems, such as "heart in a box," have allowed for increased use of donation after cardiac death, where the heart stops beating. Once the heart is reanimated, the function of the organ is assessed for transplant. The system allows the organ to stay warm and metabolically active, extending the time between retrieval and transplant by several hours.</p>



<p>Promise's new heart came from a hepatitis C-positive donor. In an effort to expand donor pools, organs that previously would have been discarded are now saving more lives thanks to a new generation of highly effective antiviral medications that allow for safe transplantation. After the transplant, patients begin antiviral treatment that will eliminate the virus.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-Garell1-768x1024.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-382529" style="aspect-ratio:1.7777777777777777;object-fit:cover;width:848px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-Garell1-768x1024.jpeg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-Garell1-225x300.jpeg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-Garell1-1152x1536.jpeg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-Garell1-1536x2048.jpeg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /></figure>



<p>"Because of the collaborative approach and high level of communication with each of the members of our multidisciplinary team, we were able to take separate pieces of technology and cater our therapies and tailor it for Promise," says Dr. Patel. "The biggest thing to understand is when we have technology, it provides us more knowledge than what we had a year ago. And taking that technology and taking that knowledge is imperative for us to identify, No. 1: How can we do better for our patients? And No. 2: How can we prevent problems for our patients? And most importantly, how can we do things now that we could not do a year or two ago?"</p>



<p>Promise received her new heart on Sept. 15, 2022. She has since celebrated many milestones, including her son's first birthday, her 25<sup>th</sup> birthday and her first transplant anniversary.</p>



<p>"When you come to Mayo Clinic, they care," says Promise. "They want to make you better. They will do whatever it takes to make you healthy, and I am forever grateful for that. Being on that table as a new mom, as a wife, a daughter, I think the biggest thought was I had to pull through this surgery for my son — if not for myself, my husband, my mom and my brother — for my son. My son needed me."</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-promise-delivered-a-new-heart-for-a-new-mom/">A promise delivered: A new heart for a new mom</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-and-Garell1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Promise-and-Paxton-Garell16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Rohan Goswami]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Promise Garell]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Study shows daylight saving time has minimal effect on heart health</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/study-shows-daylight-saving-time-has-minimal-effect-on-heart-health/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Vincent Jacobbi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 15:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Bernard Gersh]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Health Month]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381780</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A recent Mayo Clinic study examining the effects of daylight saving time (DST) on heart health suggests that the impact is likely minimal. In the nationwide study, researchers applied an advanced statistical model to look for any connections between DST and serious cardiovascular problems, including heart attacks and strokes. The study looked [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/study-shows-daylight-saving-time-has-minimal-effect-on-heart-health/">Study shows daylight saving time has minimal effect on heart health</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="582" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Red-alarm-clock-and-heart-shape-on-white-bed-sheet-against-the-pillow_shutterstock_473451853.jpg" alt="Red alarm clock and heart shape on white bed sheet against the pillow, sleep well concept" class="wp-image-382723" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Red-alarm-clock-and-heart-shape-on-white-bed-sheet-against-the-pillow_shutterstock_473451853.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Red-alarm-clock-and-heart-shape-on-white-bed-sheet-against-the-pillow_shutterstock_473451853-300x218.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Red-alarm-clock-and-heart-shape-on-white-bed-sheet-against-the-pillow_shutterstock_473451853-768x559.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A recent Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2542454823000814#appsec1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> examining the effects of daylight saving time (DST) on heart health suggests that the impact is likely minimal.</p>



<p>In the nationwide study, researchers applied an advanced statistical model to look for any connections between DST and serious cardiovascular problems, including heart attacks and strokes. The study looked at 36,116,951 adults aged 18 and up across most U.S. states. (Arizona and Hawaii were excluded since these states do not observe DST.)</p>



<p>Researchers focused on the week directly after the spring and fall DST transition, when clocks are set either an hour forward or backward.</p>



<p>"We looked at five years across the U.S., and what we found is that it’s unlikely that there is a clinically meaningful difference in cardiovascular health due to daylight saving time," says Benjamin Satterfield, M.D., Ph.D., a cardiovascular diseases fellow and lead author of the study.</p>



<p>Researchers found 74,722 adverse cardiovascular events occurred throughout the study during the spring and fall DST transition. An adverse cardiovascular event was documented when a person was hospitalized with a primary diagnosis of a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-attack/symptoms-causes/syc-20373106?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart attack</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stroke/symptoms-causes/syc-20350113" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stroke</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cardiogenic-shock/symptoms-causes/syc-20366739" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiogenic shock</a> or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/sudden-cardiac-arrest/symptoms-causes/syc-20350634?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiac arrest</a>.</p>



<p>"These cardiovascular events are common health conditions, so this led to the question of whether this is more than would be expected if this had not followed the daylight saving time transition," says Dr. Satterfield.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The observance of daylight saving time <a href="https://www.nist.gov/image/world-time-zone-map" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">varies around the world</a>. Countries that move clocks forward or back one hour may do so on different dates, and some do not observe daylight saving time at all.</p>



<p>In the Mayo Clinic study, the Monday and Friday following the spring DST transition showed a statistically slight increase in the rates of cardiovascular events — but when looking at all the data, researchers did not see the rise as clinically significant, he said.</p>



<p>Researchers note that the time change practice was intended to align social and work activities with daylight hours and to conserve energy using less artificial lighting. They underscore that making changes to the DST system out of concern for heart health is unnecessary.</p>



<p>"When decisions are made about whether to abolish daylight saving time, there is no need to take concerns regarding heart health into account," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/gersh-bernard-j-m-b-ch-b-d-phil/bio-20053461?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bernard J. Gersh, M.B., Ch.B., D.Phil.</a>, cardiologist and senior author of the study.</p>



<p>Dr. Gersh and Dr. Satterfield note that the debate over DST includes other aspects of health. For example, Dr. Satterfield said researchers are exploring DST's effect on mental health and its effect on the rates of motor vehicle accidents.</p>



<p>The <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/education-training" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</a> supported this research. Review the <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2542454823000814#appsec1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</strong><br>The Mayo Clinic Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery collaborates with clinical areas across Mayo to create and evaluate data-driven solutions to transform the experience of health and healthcare for patients, staff, and communities. It drives continuous improvement of Mayo Clinic as a learning health system, enabling always safe, evidence-based, high-quality care.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Vincent Jacobbi, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/study-shows-daylight-saving-time-has-minimal-effect-on-heart-health/">Study shows daylight saving time has minimal effect on heart health</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Red-alarm-clock-and-heart-shape-on-white-bed-sheet-against-the-pillow_shutterstock_473451853_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Red-alarm-clock-and-heart-shape-on-white-bed-sheet-against-the-pillow_shutterstock_473451853_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Bernard Gersh]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Heart Health Month]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Understanding your heart test: What to expect, how to prepare</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/understanding-your-heart-test-what-to-expect-how-to-prepare/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2024 14:58:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Michael Meyers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=382532</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Heart health is an essential part of your overall health and well-being. Your primary care provider will monitor your blood pressure and lab work during an annual physical exam or more frequently. If you have symptoms that indicate your heart may not be functioning properly, such as blood pressure higher than the recommended level, chest [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/understanding-your-heart-test-what-to-expect-how-to-prepare/">Understanding your heart test: What to expect, how to prepare</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Cardiac-stress-test-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-373783" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Cardiac-stress-test-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Cardiac-stress-test-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Cardiac-stress-test-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Cardiac-stress-test-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Cardiac-stress-test-16x9-1.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Heart health is an essential part of your overall health and well-being. Your primary care provider will monitor your blood pressure and lab work during an annual physical exam or more frequently. If you have symptoms that indicate your heart may not be functioning properly, such as blood pressure higher than the recommended level, chest pain or swelling in your feet or legs, you may be <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/when-to-see-a-cardiologist" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">referred to a cardiologist</a>.</p>



<p>A cardiologist uses diagnostic testing to evaluate the heart's ability to pump and move blood and oxygen throughout your body. Hearing you need a test on your heart may be confusing or scary, so understanding the purpose of the tests can help put you at ease.</p>



<p>Learn about various tests to help diagnose heart diseases and conditions.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What's a cardiac stress test?</h2>



<p>A cardiac stress test shows how your heart works during physical activity. Also known as an exercise stress test, it can detect problems with blood flow when the heart is pumping faster and harder than usual. The test can be done while walking on a treadmill or riding a stationary bike. Or you may be given a drug to mimic the effects of exercise while in a seated, resting position.</p>



<p>You may have a stress test to:</p>



<ul>
<li>Diagnose if coronary artery disease, which is the buildup of cholesterol deposits or plaques, is causing damage or disease in your coronary arteries.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/racing-heart-beat-heart-arrhythmia-101" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Identify arrhythmias</a> that cause your heart to beat too fast, slow, or irregularly.</li>



<li>Determine when to proceed with cardiac surgery or valve replacement treatments.</li>
</ul>



<p>A nuclear stress test may be recommended if an exercise stress test doesn't reveal the cause of your symptoms. During a nuclear stress test, short-lived radioactive medications are injected into the body and taken up by the heart to create an image of the heart's function at rest and with stress. This medication rapidly leaves the body after the test and is safe and painless.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What's a coronary CT angiogram?</h2>



<p>During a coronary CT angiogram, advanced CT technology and injected dye are used to take high-resolution 3D images of your heart. The 3D pictures of the beating heart and major blood vessels are used to identify coronary artery blockages. From the 3D images, your healthcare team can see if there are plaque or calcium deposits in the arteries.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What's an echocardiogram?</h2>



<p>Sound waves produce images of your heart during an echocardiogram. This is a common test to see your heart beating and pumping blood. The images from an echocardiogram can help identify heart disease, detect congenital heart defects before birth and check for problems with the valves or chambers of your heart.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">You may have one of several types of echocardiograms:</h3>



<ul>
<li><strong>Transthoracic<br></strong>The standard type of echocardiogram that converts sound wave echoes into moving images.</li>



<li><strong>Transesophageal</strong><br>Provides more detailed images than the standard echocardiogram.</li>



<li><strong>Doppler</strong><br>Can be used with transthoracic or transesophageal echocardiogram to measure the speed and direction of blood flow in your heart.</li>



<li><strong>Stress</strong><br>Ultrasound images of your heart before and after physical activity can be used to check for coronary artery problems.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What's an electrocardiogram?</h2>



<p>An electrocardiogram (EKG or ECG) is a noninvasive and painless way to quickly detect heart problems and monitor the heart health of people of all ages. You may have an ECG if you have symptoms such as chest pain, dizziness, confusion, heart palpitations or shortness of breath.</p>



<p>Small, adhesive electrodes are attached to your chest, arms and legs during an ECG. The electrodes record the electrical activity of your heart, and the ECG machine prints out a chart of your heart's electrical signals.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">An ECG can be used to diagnose many common heart problems and may detect:</h3>



<ul>
<li>Arrhythmias or&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/is-it-love-or-atrial-fibrillation">abnormal heart rhythm</a></li>



<li>Blocked or narrowed arteries in your heart or coronary artery disease</li>



<li>If you have had a previous heart attack</li>
</ul>



<p>Continuous ECG monitoring may be recommended if your symptoms come and go, which causes difficulty with a standard ECG test.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The two types of remote or continuous monitors are:</h3>



<ul>
<li><strong>Holter<br></strong>A small device you can wear records 24 to 48 hours of continuous ECG monitoring.</li>



<li><strong>Event</strong><br>A portable device that records heart electrical signals for a few minutes at a time, typically over the course of 30 days.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What you can do to prepare for a heart test</h2>



<p>Preparing for diagnostic heart tests helps ensure the results are accurate. Talk with your healthcare team about your questions when preparing for the test recommended specifically for your symptoms.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Here are a few general steps you can take before a heart test:</h3>



<ul>
<li>Notify your care team of prescription medications, over-the-counter drugs, <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/do-supplements-help-or-hurt-gut-health" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">supplements or herbal products</a> you are taking. Your heart can be affected by some medicines. Your healthcare team will tell you if adjustments are needed to your medications for the test.</li>



<li>You may need to fast before specific tests. This means you may have to avoid food or beverages before the test. Your healthcare team will give you detailed fasting instructions if necessary.</li>



<li>Wear loose, comfortable clothing that allows access to your chest, arms and legs. You may need to wear a hospital gown during the test. Avoid applying lotion, oil or powder to your skin before specific tests, like an ECG.</li>



<li>Limit strenuous activity that may elevate your heart rate for a few hours before the test. <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/what-are-hidden-sources-of-caffeine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Consuming caffeine</a> or nicotine before some tests can affect your heart rate and interfere with the results.</li>



<li>Some tests require sedation or other medicine to help you relax. This can affect your ability to drive after the test, so you need to arrange a ride to and from the healthcare facility.</li>



<li>Follow specific instructions from your healthcare team.</li>
</ul>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/michael-meyers-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Michael Meyers, M.D.</em></a><em>, is a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/cardiology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiologist</a> in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/la-crosse" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">La Crosse</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/sparta" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sparta</a>, Wisconsin.</em></p>



<p>This article originally posted to the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/understanding-your-heart-test">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/understanding-your-heart-test-what-to-expect-how-to-prepare/">Understanding your heart test: What to expect, how to prepare</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Cardiac-stress-test-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Cardiac-stress-test-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Michael Meyers]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Heart transplant patient finding motivation through competition, music and the Mayo Clinic community</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-patient-finding-motivation-through-competition-music-and-the-mayo-clinic-community/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tia R. Ford]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiology Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Melissa Lyle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Rohan Goswami]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mark Forbess]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=382327</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The fall It was Good Friday 2023. Mark Forbess was just leaving Mayo Clinic in Florida after his first appointment as a new patient at the heart failure program, when everything went black. "I found myself on the pavement in front of Mayo Clinic," says Mark. "I was emerging from unconsciousness. Everything was dark. I [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-patient-finding-motivation-through-competition-music-and-the-mayo-clinic-community/">Heart transplant patient finding motivation through competition, music and the Mayo Clinic community</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="575" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano16x9-1024x575.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-382337" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano16x9-1024x575.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano16x9-300x168.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano16x9-768x431.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano16x9.jpg 1512w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mark Forbess playing the piano in the Mayo atrium</figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The fall</strong></h2>



<p>It was Good Friday 2023. Mark Forbess was just leaving <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a> after his first appointment as a new patient at the heart failure program, when everything went black.</p>



<p>"I found myself on the pavement in front of Mayo Clinic," says Mark. "I was emerging from unconsciousness. Everything was dark. I opened my eyes to see that my face was pressed onto the hot, black pavement."</p>



<p>People nearby ran to his aid as he experienced excruciating pain in his head, back and neck. From there, he was rushed to the emergency department in the building he was just leaving.</p>



<p>Mark had experienced a devastating heart electrical event.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Where it all began</strong></h2>



<p>At around 33 years old, Mark was diagnosed with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy/symptoms-causes/syc-20350198?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM)</a>, a disease in which the heart muscle becomes thickened. The thickened heart muscle makes it harder for the heart to pump blood.</p>



<p>"Over time, my heart health began to decline," says Mark. "The heart failure turned into devastating episodes of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/atrial-fibrillation/symptoms-causes/syc-20350624?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">atrial fibrillation (AFib)</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/ventricular-tachycardia/symptoms-causes/syc-20355138?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ventricular tachycardia (V-tach)</a>. During this time, I experienced four V-tach episodes which required my <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/implantable-cardioverter-defibrillators/about/pac-20384692?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">implantable cardioverter defibrillator (ICD)</a> to bring me back to life, in addition to eight cardiac ablations."</p>



<p>In the fall of 2022, he was referred to Mayo Clinic for a PET scan to look for other heart diseases. At the time, nothing was found that met Mayo Clinic's heart failure treatment criteria, so he was not approved as a cardiology patient. However, in March of 2023, after experiencing congestive heart failure while being treated at another medical institution, he was referred to Mayo Clinic again as a candidate for the heart failure program.</p>



<p>The following month, he was approved for the program under the care of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/lyle-melissa-a-m-d/bio-20491562?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Melissa Lyle, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist</a>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A candidate for transplant</strong></h2>



<p>After the emergency department triage, Mark recalls his cardiologist saying, "Congratulations, Mr. Forbess. You just won a ticket to be evaluated for the heart transplant program." From there, he went through a battery of evaluation tests, which he passed, officially allowing him access to Mayo Clinic's heart transplant program.</p>



<p>"I knew that when Dr. Lyle told me I was entered into the Mayo Clinic heart transplant program that God was in total control of my life," says Mark. "He was guiding her and providing the confidence, from years of training, that I could live a happy life again by having a new heart."</p>



<p>Within a month, Mark was admitted to Mayo Clinic and waitlisted for his new heart. Transplant patients are ranked by necessity, and due to his condition, he was at the top of the list.</p>



<p>Mark had a rare heart deformation in which his left ventricle was very enlarged. This is considered unusual in HCM patients because their heart walls are usually very thick and the ventricles are small. As a result, Mark became eligible for a cardiac device — a small heart pump that helped improve his oxygen blood levels while he waited for his heart transplant.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF_Logo-768x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-382340" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF_Logo-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF_Logo-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF_Logo-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF_Logo.jpg 1512w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The Daytona 500 meets the ICU</strong></h2>



<p>In an effort to lift the spirits of their patients and encourage some much-needed exercise, the nurses on Mark's floor came up with some competitive fun.</p>



<p>"These patients are not your typical ICU patients," says Sara Vilela, registered nurse. "They are often walking and talking, something we are not used to in the ICU. This means we have to make sure we are catering to this special patient population and ensuring that not only their medical needs are being taken care of, but also their social needs."</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="523" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Transplant_Games-1024x523.png" alt="" class="wp-image-382339" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Transplant_Games-1024x523.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Transplant_Games-300x153.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Transplant_Games-768x392.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Transplant_Games-1536x784.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Transplant_Games.png 1788w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mark and fellow cardiac ICU playing dominoes</figcaption></figure>



<p>The nursing staff set up a series of games from dominoes to a "Cardiac Device 500" footrace between patients around the hospital unit, measured by the distance they walked each day.</p>



<p>"It was a bit of a leap to think playing games at a time like this was appropriate," says Mark. "After all, we were in the ICU. When you showed up and participated, you were hooked. It was that much fun and necessary. No medical tests, no medicine and no bad news. Nothing but fun, and that’s always good for the soul. I participated in afternoon game sessions with other heart transplant patients, their families, my brother Jeff and the outstanding Mayo nursing staff. We looked forward to the opportunity to meet each other and focus our minds on something we had in common and away from our current health status."</p>



<p>The games were a big hit among the patients, inspiring much creativity, especially the races. They created names for their cardiac devices, team logos and even fake sponsors. Mark named his heart pump "Archie," after his father.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="225" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF11-225x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-382341" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF11-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF11-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF11-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF11.jpg 1512w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /></figure></div>


<p>Mark recalls being barely able to walk a small lap at the beginning of this journey. However, walking more and more each day, motivated by a new heart and some friendly competition, he began walking about five to seven miles a day, even hitting a heart pump record of 10.8 miles.</p>



<p>"By hosting game times, these patients were able to talk to one another about the struggles of waiting for a heart transplant, but also the triumphs, such as beating their previous day's record of laps," says Vilela. "They connected over this unique experience and bond with one another, which resulted in a patient population encouraging each other, remembering they are not alone on this journey."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Inspired by memories</strong></h2>



<p>Mark lost his wife of nearly 40 years, Michele, in June 2022, approximately 10 months before entering Mayo Clinic on the heart transplant waitlist.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano_1x1-300x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-382338" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano_1x1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano_1x1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano_1x1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano_1x1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano_1x1.jpg 1512w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure></div>


<p>"I had spent many days grieving in the Mayo atrium over my wife," he says. "I wanted to change that to positive, fun memories instead by providing a little entertainment playing the beautiful grand piano and maybe brighten someone else's day." He pursued the opportunity to play with the encouragement of one of his nurses, Frances Ausley, and Rose Grace from the Humanities in Medicine Department. Grace is a concert level pianist herself who occasionally visited Mark in his hospital room to play the keyboard.</p>



<p>"Frances Ausley has incredible capabilities and a very hard work ethic while providing care to all those around her," Mark says. "Rose Grace encouraged me and gave me the confidence that I could play the piano under these circumstances."</p>



<p>While playing the piano helped, he still found himself battling anxiety and sadness around the anniversary of losing his wife.</p>



<p>"Managing anxiety on the one-year anniversary of my wife's passing was going to be very difficult," Mark says. "Wanting to celebrate her life outside, I was stuck in the ICU waiting for a heart, knowing that any high anxiety could trigger severe heart arrhythmia. Carolina Robles de Brady, a wonderful and thoughtful nurse from El Salvador, secretly arranged to reenact the dinner my wife and I had made on our first date — chicken cordon bleu with blueberry fluff as dessert. She asked me the day before about memories of a favorite dinner with my wife. I was pleasantly surprised as Carolina kept me calm while we celebrated my wife's life."</p>



<p>Later on, Mark would nominate Carolina for a DAISY Award, honoring nurses who go above and beyond to provide compassionate care to patients and families. She was selected and recognized with the award in December 2023.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A new heart, a new day, a new future</strong></h2>



<p>On July 14, 2023, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/goswami-rohan-m-m-d/bio-20432467?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Rohan Goswami</a> entered Mark's room. Expecting another donor update, the news was different this time. "I found you the perfect heart," Mark recalls Dr. Goswami saying.</p>



<p>"I never had children, but I’m guessing this is one of the most exciting pieces of medical news you could ever receive," says Mark. "After several months of waiting, Dr. Goswami is telling me I have a heart coming. It was an unbelievable experience. The sacrifice a donor family makes to give organs to another human being is one of the greatest acts of unselfishness and kindness a person can do on this earth. It's real, and it's effective. My donor family will be forever in my soul as I wake up every day thanking them in my prayers."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="225" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF5-225x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-382343" style="width:266px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF5-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF5-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF5-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF5.jpg 1512w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mark Forbess</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Mark received his new heart on July 17, 2023.</p>



<p>After more than 30 years as an investment banker, Mark started thinking about a long-term career goal he'd always wanted to pursue. Since childhood, he wanted to be a screenwriter and filmmaker.</p>



<p>"Before I entered the hospital for my transplant, I purchased screenwriters professional software used to write film scripts and loaded it onto my computer," says Mark. "I always wanted to produce films that would help people find true, long-term happiness in life. If I could write one particular story while waiting for my heart transplant, I would be a happy person myself."</p>



<p>Since leaving the hospital, he has achieved this goal by completing his first screenplay and has begun the process of marketing it to the film industry. As for his health journey, he continues to excel at cardiac rehabilitation, lowering medications every month as his recovery progresses.</p>



<p>Paying regular visits to Mayo Clinic staff since his transplant, Mark acknowledges that everyone he met while waiting for his transplant helped make his experience a good one.</p>



<p>"During this time, I would meet many incredible nurses, doctors, physician assistants, housekeeping team members, Food Services team members and a host of other personnel who took great pride in their roles," says Mark.</p>



<p>His interactions with all staff, even beyond his hospital room, became an expansion of his care team. Many share that Mark had just as much of an impact on them.</p>



<p>"The power of food and how it changes the patient experience by broadening the scope of meal service providing comfort, connection and nutrition is a component of their care," says Casey Wingerter, patient ambassador for Mayo Clinic Food Services. "During Mark's stay at Mayo, meals became a medium for connection, and connection was&nbsp;critical for his transplant journey. He healed while at Mayo, and it was the people that made the difference. That human connection is what he held on to and is why he became a bright spot in our staff's days as well."</p>



<p>Mark recalls how much Wingerter and her team truly made a difference. Before he left the hospital, he says the Food Services team gifted him a small suitcase full of his favorite gum as a way of saying thank you from Wingerter and the Food Services team.</p>



<p>"I firmly believe God answers our prayers," says Mark. "My hope is that my testimony can serve as a powerful tool for you to convey the profound significance of God in our lives. His presence can guide us through seemingly impossible challenges, which will lead to a truly long-term, happy life."</p>



<p><strong>Additional resources:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-know-the-warning-signs-of-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Know the warning signs of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/sharing-mayo-clinic-a-heart-patients-fall-picks-up-something-big/">Sharing Mayo Clinic: A heart patient’s fall picks up something big</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What is hypertrophic cardiomyopathy?</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-patient-finding-motivation-through-competition-music-and-the-mayo-clinic-community/">Heart transplant patient finding motivation through competition, music and the Mayo Clinic community</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF6_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF6_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Melissa Lyle]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Rohan Goswami]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mark Forbess]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Take heart murmurs seriously</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/take-heart-murmurs-seriously/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[amandadyslin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 15:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Michel Barsoum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Murmur]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=382269</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Eau Claire, Wis. — Detecting a heart murmur on your own can be tricky. A&#160;murmur&#160;is an extra heart sound that can be heard by a stethoscope. Sometimes, a murmur sounds like a humming sound, which can be faint or loud. It might be temporary or persistent. Heart murmurs may be present at birth or develop [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/take-heart-murmurs-seriously/">Take heart murmurs seriously</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-young-man-with-his-shirt-open-so-a-medical-person-perhaps-a-doctor-or-nurse-practitioner-can-listen-to-his-heart-wth-a-stethoscope-on-the-patients-chest-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-310765" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-young-man-with-his-shirt-open-so-a-medical-person-perhaps-a-doctor-or-nurse-practitioner-can-listen-to-his-heart-wth-a-stethoscope-on-the-patients-chest-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-young-man-with-his-shirt-open-so-a-medical-person-perhaps-a-doctor-or-nurse-practitioner-can-listen-to-his-heart-wth-a-stethoscope-on-the-patients-chest-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-young-man-with-his-shirt-open-so-a-medical-person-perhaps-a-doctor-or-nurse-practitioner-can-listen-to-his-heart-wth-a-stethoscope-on-the-patients-chest-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-young-man-with-his-shirt-open-so-a-medical-person-perhaps-a-doctor-or-nurse-practitioner-can-listen-to-his-heart-wth-a-stethoscope-on-the-patients-chest-16x9-1.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Eau Claire, Wis. — Detecting a heart murmur on your own can be tricky. A&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-murmurs/basics/definition/con-20028706" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">murmur</a>&nbsp;is an extra heart sound that can be heard by a stethoscope.</p>



<p>Sometimes, a murmur sounds like a humming sound, which can be faint or loud. It might be temporary or persistent. Heart murmurs may be present at birth or develop later in life during pregnancy, phases of rapid growth like adolescence, or from a fever or anemia.</p>



<p>"The murmur may disappear as quickly as it comes if it has a temporary cause," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/michel-barsoum-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Michel Barsoum, M.B., Ch.B.</a>, a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/cardiology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiologist</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/vascular-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">vascular medicine</a> specialist at Mayo Clinic Health System in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/chippewa-falls" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Chippewa Falls</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/eau-claire" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Eau Claire</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/rice-lake" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Rice Lake</a>, Wisconsin. "However, a murmur also could be persistent and loud, easily heard, and sound like a churning mill wheel or cooing seagull. This might indicate a serious heart problem."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What causes a heart murmur?</strong><strong></strong></h2>



<p>Several factors can cause a murmur. It could be a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-valve-disease/basics/definition/con-20036065" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart valve problem</a>&nbsp;or a hole in the heart.</p>



<p>The valves in your heart act as doors between the chambers, or rooms, of the heart. In the case of a murmur, a valve may be tight or leaky. When heart valves are narrow, this is called stenosis. A murmur also could be from a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/treating-mitral-valve-regurgitation" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">leaky valve</a>, called regurgitation.</p>



<p>A murmur also may occur from high blood flow in people with a fever or with low red blood cells, called anemia.</p>



<p>Some people have a family history of heart murmur and heart disease. Some are born with a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/genetic-testing-and-cardiac-conditions" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">congenital condition</a> causing a murmur. Others have had a recent severe infection or illness that could damage a heart valve and need immediate medical attention.</p>



<p>Innocent or harmless heart murmurs don't typically cause symptoms, and most heart murmurs aren't serious.</p>



<p>Symptoms of a serious or worrisome heart murmur depend on the cause and require evaluation by a healthcare professional.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>These heart murmur symptoms may include:</strong><strong></strong></h2>



<ul>
<li>Blue or gray lips or fingernails</li>



<li>Chest pain</li>



<li>Fainting</li>



<li>Fever</li>



<li>Leg swelling</li>



<li>Lingering cough</li>



<li>Shortness of breath</li>



<li>Sudden weight gain</li>



<li>Swollen liver or neck veins</li>



<li>Worsening fatigue</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>How is a heart murmur diagnosed?</strong><strong></strong></h2>



<p>It's common for a heart murmur to be detected during a physical exam being given for another reason. If a healthcare professional hears a murmur, you'll be asked questions about your personal and family history that could indicate a reason for the murmur.</p>



<p>Several criteria are used to determine if a murmur is innocent or worrisome, including:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Volume<br></strong>The loudness of the heart murmur is evaluated on a scale from 1 to 6. The loudest heart murmur is a 6.</li>



<li><strong>Location<br></strong>The location of the murmur in the heart will be identified, along with determining if the sound spreads to the neck or back.</li>



<li><strong>Pitch<br></strong>The heart murmur may have a high, medium or low pitch.</li>



<li><strong>Timing<br></strong>A heart murmur that occurs when blood leaves the heart is a systolic murmur. A murmur that occurs when the heart fills with blood is called a diastolic murmur. A murmur also may be heard throughout the heartbeat. When the murmur is heard as blood passes through the heart, it may be a sign of a larger heart problem.<br></li>
</ul>



<p>You will need to undergo testing to determine the cause of the heart murmur. Your healthcare professional likely will order an ultrasound picture of your heart, called an&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/echocardiogram/basics/definition/prc-20013918" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">echocardiogram</a>,&nbsp;or echo, to show detailed images of your heart's valves, chambers, structure and function.</p>



<p>"Once the cause of a heart murmur has been found, some people will need repeated evaluation over the years," says Dr. Barsoum. "It's important to find the cause so the right treatment can be determined."</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Health System</strong></p>



<p><a href="https://mayoclinichealthsystem.org" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System</a> has a physical presence in 44 communities and consists of 53 clinics, 16 hospitals and other facilities that serve the healthcare needs of people in Iowa, Minnesota and Wisconsin. The community-based healthcare professionals, paired with the resources and expertise of Mayo Clinic, enable patients in the region to receive the highest-quality physical and virtual healthcare close to home.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<p>Amanda Dyslin, Mayo Clinic Health System Communications Department, <a href="mailto:dyslin.amanda@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/take-heart-murmurs-seriously/">Take heart murmurs seriously</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-young-man-with-his-shirt-open-so-a-medical-person-perhaps-a-doctor-or-nurse-practitioner-can-listen-to-his-heart-wth-a-stethoscope-on-the-patients-chest-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-young-man-with-his-shirt-open-so-a-medical-person-perhaps-a-doctor-or-nurse-practitioner-can-listen-to-his-heart-wth-a-stethoscope-on-the-patients-chest-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Michel Barsoum]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Heart Murmur]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Spotlight on early detection of 3 heart diseases using ECG-AI </title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/spotlight-on-early-detection-of-3-heart-diseases-using-ecg-ai/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Terri Malloy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[American Heart Month]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[artificial intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiac Amyloidosis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiomyopathy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Demilade Adedinsewo]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Konstantinos Sionitis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Martha Grogan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ECG]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ECG-AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HCM]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hypertrophic cardiomyopathy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[peripartum cardiomyopathy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=382201</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Too often, the first sign of cardiovascular disease may be a major event like a heart attack, stroke or cardiac arrest. Now, researchers and clinicians at Mayo Clinic are using artificial intelligence (AI) technology to flag heart problems earlier, boosting the abilities of a diagnostic test that has been around for over [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/spotlight-on-early-detection-of-3-heart-diseases-using-ecg-ai/">Spotlight on early detection of 3 heart diseases using ECG-AI </a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1000" height="546" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/Medicine-person-holding-red-heart-model-and-futuristic-icon-medical-network-connection-with-virtual-screen-shutterstock_686402860.jpg" alt="Medical person holding red heart model and futuristic icon medical network connection with virtual screen" class="wp-image-319754" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/Medicine-person-holding-red-heart-model-and-futuristic-icon-medical-network-connection-with-virtual-screen-shutterstock_686402860.jpg 1000w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/Medicine-person-holding-red-heart-model-and-futuristic-icon-medical-network-connection-with-virtual-screen-shutterstock_686402860-300x164.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/Medicine-person-holding-red-heart-model-and-futuristic-icon-medical-network-connection-with-virtual-screen-shutterstock_686402860-768x419.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Too often, the first sign of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiovascular disease</a> may be a major event like a heart attack, stroke or cardiac arrest. Now, researchers and clinicians at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> are using artificial intelligence (AI) technology to flag heart problems earlier, boosting the abilities of a diagnostic test that has been around for over a century — the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ekg/about/pac-20384983?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">electrocardiogram (ECG)</a>.   </p>



<p>Early detection of heart disease can make a significant difference in a patient's quality of life and longevity, but a lack of defining symptoms adds complexity. The <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/ai-cardiology/overview/ovc-20486648?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">AI-enabled ECG</a> provides a way to potentially detect heart disease earlier and track disease progression using a test that is relatively inexpensive, readily available and often already part of a patient's electronic health record.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic has developed ECG-AI algorithms that are currently used in research to predict a patient's likelihood of having heart conditions like <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/atrial-fibrillation/symptoms-causes/syc-20350624?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">atrial fibrillation</a>, amyloidosis, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/aortic-stenosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20353139?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">aortic stenosis</a>, low ejection fraction, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM) and more. The AI can also predict a patient's biological age using traditional 12-lead and single-lead ECGs from smartwatches and portable devices.</p>



<p>One standout application is the use of ECG-AI to detect low ejection fraction, commonly called a weak heart pump. The 12-lead algorithm for detecting this condition is cleared for clinical use by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and licensed to <a href="https://anumana.ai/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Anumana</a>. A single-lead algorithm for handheld devices externally applied to the chest is licensed to <a href="https://www.ekohealth.com/pages/about-us" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Eko Health</a> for commercial development.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Diagnosing a weak heart pump</h2>



<p>Approximately 3% of Americans have a treatable condition called <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ekg/expert-answers/ejection-fraction/faq-20058286?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">low ejection fraction</a>, where the heart is weakened and pumps less blood out to the body. The underlying causes and symptoms are often treatable, but people may not be aware of their condition until symptoms such as shortness of breath, fatigue and swelling in their legs start to get worse. Left untreated, low ejection fraction can progress to worsening <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-failure/symptoms-causes/syc-20373142?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart failure</a>, affecting quality of life and potentially become severe enough to require a heart transplant or lead to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/sudden-cardiac-arrest/symptoms-causes/syc-20350634?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiac arrest</a>.</p>



<p>Unfortunately, the symptoms of a weak heart pump can be confused with those seen with normal pregnancy. At Mayo Clinic in Florida, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/adedinsewo-demilade-a-m-b-ch-b/bio-20507418" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Demilade Adedinsewo, M.B., Ch.B.</a>, a cardiologist, uses AI as a tool to detect a condition in women called peripartum <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cardiomyopathy/symptoms-causes/syc-20370709?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiomyopathy</a>, a weak heart pump that can develop during pregnancy or shortly after giving birth. Heart muscle weakness can be predicted with AI from a traditional 12-lead ECG and from an AI-enabled digital stethoscope that captures single-lead ECG and heart sound recordings.</p>



<p>"Our research with obstetric patients in Nigeria suggests that portable technology like the AI-enabled digital stethoscope has the potential to flag twice as many cases of peripartum cardiomyopathy as compared to routine care," says Dr. Adedinsewo. "It may be a powerful tool to bring portable cardiomyopathy diagnostics to more women in underserved urban and rural populations around the world. Access is an important consideration in addressing health disparities in the U.S., because Black women have up to a sixteenfold greater risk of developing peripartum cardiomyopathy, compared to white women."</p>



<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PsJJKSjOf1U" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Watch: Dr. Demilade Adedinsewo explains peripartum cardiomyopathy in this Mayo Clinic Minute</strong></a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidPsJJKSjOf1U"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Red flags for heart failure during pregnancy" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PsJJKSjOf1U?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Amyloid buildup in the heart</h2>



<p>Amyloidosis is a rare disease of misfolded proteins that go astray to form deposits of amyloid in organs, nerves and tissues. There are several different types, but when enough <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/cardiac-amyloidosis-clinic/overview/ovc-20508423?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">amyloid builds up in the heart</a>, it causes heart failure and symptoms such as shortness of breath, fluid buildup and fainting. Patients also can have heart rhythm problems and might need a pacemaker. Early diagnosis is critical because, while amyloidosis is not curable, it is treatable with new medical therapies that can dramatically reduce the amount of amyloid produced and stop disease progression.</p>



<p>Using ECG-AI, clinicians at Mayo Clinic can potentially flag patients who are in the early stages of cardiac amyloidosis. The technology is used in research and has FDA breakthrough device designation.</p>



<p>"We've done some research indicating that, if we apply artificial intelligence just to the electrocardiogram, we can suggest if the patient has the diagnosis, often before a clinician has even suspected it. So we believe that this is a way to make an early diagnosis," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/grogan-martha-m-d/bio-20053492?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Martha Grogan, M.D.</a>, a cardiologist at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota. "Now, it has to be put in clinical context. It's not just that one AI ECG, but it can really help us suspect amyloidosis."</p>



<p>"It's a very powerful tool because it's inexpensive. It's available almost everywhere. Our research showed that even a single lead, which is something that you could do on a watch or a simple mobile device, can give us this prediction of amyloidosis," says Dr. Grogan. "So, one could imagine that, in underserved populations throughout the world, a simple ECG might help determine if a patient has amyloidosis, especially in those high-risk groups."</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/zuwjqqAwov0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Martha Grogan discusses detecting cardiac amyloidosis using AI and the ECG</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubezuwjqqAwov0"  title="Detecting cardiac amyloidosis using AI and the ECG" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zuwjqqAwov0?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites with Dr. Grogan are available in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Name super/CG: Martha Grogan, M.D./Cardiovascular Medicine/Mayo Clinic.</strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy/symptoms-causes/syc-20350198?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</a> is one of the most common genetic heart diseases, affecting 1 in 200 to 500 people. HCM happens when the heart's walls become thicker over time, which can disrupt the heart's electrical signals, increasing the risk of sudden cardiac death. Unfortunately, people often don't notice any symptoms until the disease progresses. It's like having a silent intruder in your heart.</p>



<p>Early detection is crucial but challenging. HCM does not always show up on basic tests, such as a 12-lead ECG. Most patients would not be referred to more resource-intensive tests, like an echocardiogram or MRI, unless a problem was suspected. But ECG-AI can spot HCM by recognizing subtle patterns that even expert clinicians might miss.</p>



<p>"Applying this AI algorithm to routine ECGs shows promise as a means to make early detection of HCM more practical, accurate and accessible as part of a heart health checkup," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/siontis-konstantinos-m-d/bio-20503925?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Konstantinos Siontis, M.D.</a>, a cardiac electrophysiologist at Mayo Clinic in Rochester. "Athletes with yet undiagnosed HCM, who may be more at risk of dangerous arrhythmias during exercise, could benefit from early detection. And because HCM often runs in families, detecting it early in one person can lead to identifying other family members at risk."</p>



<p>###&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<ul>
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/spotlight-on-early-detection-of-3-heart-diseases-using-ecg-ai/">Spotlight on early detection of 3 heart diseases using ECG-AI </a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/Medicine-person-holding-red-heart-model-and-futuristic-icon-medical-network-connection-with-virtual-screen-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/Medicine-person-holding-red-heart-model-and-futuristic-icon-medical-network-connection-with-virtual-screen-shutterstock_686402860.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[AI]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[American Heart Month]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[artificial intelligence]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cardiac Amyloidosis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cardiology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cardiomyopathy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Demilade Adedinsewo]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Konstantinos Sionitis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Martha Grogan]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[ECG]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[ECG-AI]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[HCM]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Heart Disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[hypertrophic cardiomyopathy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[peripartum cardiomyopathy]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cardiac amyloidosis 101: Why early diagnosis and targeted treatment matter</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/cardiac-amyloidosis-101-why-early-diagnosis-and-targeted-treatment-matter/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[DeeDee Stiepan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiac Amyloidosis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Martha Grogan]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=382188</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Amyloidosis occurs when the body produces abnormal proteins that bind together to form a substance called amyloid. Amyloids can deposit in any tissue or organ, including the heart, kidneys, liver and nerves. When it occurs in the heart, it's called cardiac amyloidosis. Dr. Martha Grogan, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist and director of the Cardiac Amyloid [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/cardiac-amyloidosis-101-why-early-diagnosis-and-targeted-treatment-matter/">Cardiac amyloidosis 101: Why early diagnosis and targeted treatment matter</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/02/166064-001-0-16x9-1.jpg" alt="medical illustration of healthy heart muscle and a second heart with cardiac amyloidosis" class="wp-image-297669" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/02/166064-001-0-16x9-1.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/02/166064-001-0-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/amyloidosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20353178?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Amyloidosis</a> occurs when the body produces abnormal proteins that bind together to form a substance called amyloid. Amyloids can deposit in any tissue or organ, including the heart, kidneys, liver and nerves. When it occurs in the heart, it's called cardiac amyloidosis.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/grogan-martha-m-d/bio-20053492" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Martha Grogan</a>, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist and director of the Cardiac Amyloid Clinic at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota, explains what cardiac amyloidosis is, why knowing the type of amyloid is key to treatment, and what's on the horizon to help patients with this rare condition.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/LxExaG8PFRA" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Martha Grogan discusses cardiac amyloidosis</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeLxExaG8PFRA"  title="Cardiac amyloidosis 101: Why early diagnosis and targeted treatment matter" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/LxExaG8PFRA?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites with Dr. Grogan are available in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Name super/CG: Martha Grogan, M.D./Cardiovascular Medicine/Mayo Clinic.</strong></p>



<p>When amyloid collects in the heart muscle, it causes thickening of the heart wall and disrupts heart function. It reduces the heart's ability to fill with blood between heartbeats, resulting in less blood being pumped with each beat and higher pressures in the heart chambers.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"The heart is the most important abnormality in amyloidosis because if the heart is affected, that is the complete driver of how the patient will do and what their prognosis is," says Dr. Grogan. "That's why cardiac amyloidosis is so important to recognize and treat as early as possible."</p>



<p>Three types of amyloids can affect the heart:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Light chain amyloid</strong> is produced in the bone marrow, progresses quickly and has the worst prognosis.</li>



<li><strong>Wild-type transthyretin amyloid (TTR)</strong> is produced in the liver and is the most common. This type typically shows up in men over 60, however women may also develop this condition.</li>



<li><strong>Hereditary type transthyretin amyloid </strong>is caused by a gene mutation and is considered rare, except in Black Americans. Not everyone with the gene variation will get the condition.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">"The key thing, once a clinician suspects amyloid, is that it's a medical emergency."</h2>



<p>Dr. Grogan says amyloidosis is tricky to diagnose. At first, there are no symptoms. Later, the symptoms often imitate other conditions.</p>



<p>"We need to get to the bottom of: Does the patient really have amyloidosis or not? And then after, we do a series of tests. We need to figure out for sure what type of amyloid it is. We can't be guessing at what type because the treatment completely depends on the type," says Dr. Grogan.</p>



<p>For light chain amyloidosis, treatment is directed at the bone marrow and may include chemotherapy or stem cell transplant with a patient's own cells. Treatment for transthyretin amyloidosis aims to stabilize or reduce the amount of amyloid being produced from the liver.</p>



<p>There are current clinical trials of medication that will try to actively take the amyloid out of the heart, but they're not yet approved. However, Dr. Grogan says the future looks bright.</p>



<p>"These new medications are very exciting. In fact, that area of amyloidosis research is truly an explosion, there is so much going on. We went from very few options to so many options. We need to keep testing these and studying these," says Dr. Grogan.</p>



<p><strong>Additional resources:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/expert-alert-cardiac-amyloidosis-masquerades-as-other-conditions-1-type-affects-more-black-americans/">Expert Alert: Cardiac amyloidosis masquerades as other conditions; 1 type affects more black Americans</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/discoverys-edge-cell-research-on-amyloidosis/">Discovery’s Edge: Cell research on amyloidosis</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/cardiac-amyloidosis-101-why-early-diagnosis-and-targeted-treatment-matter/">Cardiac amyloidosis 101: Why early diagnosis and targeted treatment matter</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/02/166064-001-0-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/02/166064-001-0-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cardiac Amyloidosis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Martha Grogan]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Know your numbers: What is your heart rate?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/know-your-numbers-what-is-your-heart-rate/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Xiaoke Liu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[heart rate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=382248</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Know your numbers: What is your heart rate? Your heart rate, or pulse, is the number of times your heart beats per minute. Your resting heart rate is when the heart is pumping the lowest amount of blood you need because you're not exercising. If you're sitting or lying down ― and you're calm, relaxed [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/know-your-numbers-what-is-your-heart-rate/">Know your numbers: What is your heart rate?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/adult-checking-heart-rate-on-wrist-watch16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-382262" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/adult-checking-heart-rate-on-wrist-watch16x9.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/adult-checking-heart-rate-on-wrist-watch16x9-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Know your numbers: What is your heart rate?</h2>



<p>Your heart rate, or pulse, is the number of times your heart beats per minute. Your resting heart rate is when the heart is pumping the lowest amount of blood you need because you're not exercising. If you're sitting or lying down ― and you're calm, relaxed and aren't sick ― your heart rate is typically between 60 and 100 beats per minute.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Other factors that can affect your heart rate include:</h3>



<ul>
<li><strong>Air temperature.</strong> When <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/effects-of-high-temperatures-on-blood-pressure-heart" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">temperatures or humidity increases</a>, the heart pumps more blood, so your pulse or heart rate may increase.</li>



<li><strong>Body position.</strong>&nbsp;Sometimes, when going from sitting to standing, your pulse may go up a little. After a few minutes, it should return to a typical rate.</li>



<li><strong>Emotions.</strong>&nbsp;If you're stressed, anxious or incredibly happy, your emotions can raise your heart rate.</li>



<li><strong>Body size.</strong>&nbsp;Body size usually does not increase your heart rate. However, if you're obese, you may have a higher resting heart rate.</li>



<li><strong>Medication use.</strong>&nbsp;Medications that block adrenaline tend to slow your heart rate. Thyroid medication may raise it.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Why your heart rate matters</h3>



<p>Cardiovascular exercise, also called cardio or aerobic exercise, keeps you and your heart healthy. This specific type of exercise gets your heart rate up and your heart beating faster for several minutes. Cardiovascular exercise helps strengthen your heart, allowing it to pump blood more efficiently and improving blood flow to all parts of your body. It also boosts your high-density lipoprotein (or HDL), or "good" <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/know-your-numbers-cholesterol" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cholesterol</a>, and lowers your low-density lipoprotein (or LDL), or "bad" cholesterol. This may result in less buildup of plaque in your arteries.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What's your target heart rate?</h2>



<p>Your target heart rate is the minimum heart rate you need to maintain in a given amount of time to reach the energy level necessary to give your heart a good workout. To find your target heart rate to maximize your cardiovascular exercise, the first step is determining your maximum heart rate.</p>



<p>Your maximum heart rate is 220 minus your age. Your target heart rate for moderate to vigorous exercise is about 50%–85% of your maximum heart rate.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Averages by age as a general guide are:</h3>



<ul>
<li>20: 100–170 beats per minute</li>



<li>30: 95–162 beats per minute</li>



<li>35: 93–157 beats per minute</li>



<li>40: 90–153 beats per minute</li>



<li>45: 88–149 beats per minute</li>



<li>50: 85–145 beats per minute</li>



<li>55: 83–140 beats per minute</li>



<li>60: 80–136 beats per minute</li>



<li>65: 78–132 beats per minute</li>



<li>70: 75–128 beats per minute</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">What you can do</h3>



<ul>
<li><strong>Start slow.</strong>&nbsp;If you are beginning an exercise program, aim for the lower end of your target heart rate zone and then gradually build up intensity.</li>



<li><strong>Try interval training.</strong> <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/interval-training-for-heart-health/">Interval training</a>, which includes short bursts ― 15–60 seconds ― of higher-intensity exercise, alternated with longer, less strenuous exercise, effectively increases cardiovascular fitness. Talk with your healthcare team before trying interval training, but it is typically safe for those with existing heart disease and Type 2 diabetes.</li>



<li><strong>Take the "talk test."</strong>&nbsp;If you can carry on a conversation in brief sentences while exercising, you're probably in the moderate intensity range. You'll be breathing faster, developing a light sweat and feeling some muscle strain. If you're working at a vigorous intensity, you won't be able to say more than a few words without catching your breath. If you can sing while working out, you're probably in the low-intensity range, so step it up.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Know your numbers</h2>



<p>Many wearable activity trackers can&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/how-to-take-pulse/art-20482581" target="_blank">monitor your heart rate</a>&nbsp;when you exercise and periodically throughout the day. If you don't have an activity tracker, you can use the radial artery in your wrist or the carotid artery in your neck. If you have heart disease or long-standing diabetes, it's best to use the artery on your wrist.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">To find your heart rate manually:</h3>



<ul>
<li>Locate the artery you will use to find your heart rate.</li>



<li>Using the tips of your first two fingers, press lightly over the artery.</li>



<li>Count your heartbeats for 30 seconds and multiply by two to find your total beats per minute.</li>
</ul>



<p>If your heart rate is too high, take it easier. If it's too low, add some intensity and push yourself to get your heart rate closer to your target.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Abnormal heart rate</h3>



<p>If you experience irregular heartbeats, including a racing heartbeat, slow heartbeat or a feeling of fluttering in your chest, you may be experiencing a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/racing-heart-beat-heart-arrhythmia-101" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart arrhythmia</a>. Heart rhythm or heartbeat problems can occur when the electrical impulses that coordinate your heartbeats don't work properly, causing your heart to beat too fast, slow or irregularly. Talk with your healthcare team if you have heart rhythm concerns.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Next steps</h2>



<ul>
<li>Watch Dr. Liu explain the&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://youtu.be/1OnQHdN4m_Q?si=1URr89jYgsS7EleH" target="_blank">best exercise and wearable fitness trackers</a>.</li>



<li>Learn when <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/young-athletes-and-heart-health" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">athletes need evaluation for heart health</a>.</li>



<li>Hear the&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fyqFfeC2FE4" target="_blank">difference between heart rate and heart rhythm</a>.</li>



<li>Find a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/cardiology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart care expert</a> near you.</li>
</ul>



<p><em><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/xiaoke-ken-liu-md-phd" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Xiaoke (Ken) Liu, M.D.</a>, is a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/cardiology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiologist</a> in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/la-crosse" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">La Crosse</a>, Wisconsin.</em></p>



<p>This article first appeared on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/know-your-numbers-heart-rate" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog.</a></p>



<p><strong>Additional resources:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-hit-your-target-heart-rate/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How to hit your target heart rate</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/know-your-numbers-what-is-your-heart-rate/">Know your numbers: What is your heart rate?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/adult-checking-heart-rate-on-wrist-watch1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/adult-checking-heart-rate-on-wrist-watch16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Xiaoke Liu]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[heart rate]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Know the warning signs of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-know-the-warning-signs-of-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 16:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Said Alsidawi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hypertrophic cardiomyopathy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381650</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>It's often silent but can be a deadly killer. Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy is a genetic condition that occurs in 1 in 500 people. Dr. Said Alsidawi, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist, says the problem is that many people don't even know they have it because they have no symptoms. And in 20% of cases, the first presentation [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-know-the-warning-signs-of-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Know the warning signs of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>It's often silent but can be a deadly killer. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy/symptoms-causes/syc-20350198?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</a> is a genetic condition that occurs in 1 in 500 people.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/alsidawi-said-m-d/bio-20516525?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Said Alsidawi</a>, a Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/cardiovascular-medicine/home/orc-20121930?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiologist</a>, says the problem is that many people don't even know they have it because they have no symptoms. And in 20% of cases, the first presentation is sudden cardiac death.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/M6RrnuAc_1M" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeM6RrnuAc1M"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Know the warning signs of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/M6RrnuAc_1M?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:07) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MCM_Hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy is a genetic condition that causes the heart muscle to thicken, making it harder to pump blood and sometimes causing an irregular heart rhythm.</p>



<p>"So right now, what we think in the United States, we've only diagnosed 1/7 of the people who have hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. So we're trying to increase the awareness in the community about this disease," says Dr. Alsidawi.</p>



<p>He says patients are born with a genetic mutation. The disease can start at a young age or later in life — many times with no symptoms.&nbsp; </p>



<p>"We know the patients that we lose to this condition, the majority of them are young, active and athletes. So high-level athletic exercise can put you at higher risk of sudden cardiac death," says Dr. Alsidawi.</p>



<p>He says it's important to seek medical attention if you have any symptoms, especially with exertion, "including shortness of breath, chest pain, lightheaded, dizzy or passing out."</p>



<p>If diagnosed, the good news is hypertrophic cardiomyopathy can be treated with medications, surgery, implanting a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/implantable-cardioverter-defibrillators/about/pac-20384692?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">defibrillator</a> that monitors the heart or, in severe cases, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/heart-transplant/about/pac-20384750?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart transplantation</a>.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Additional resources:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/sex-and-race-disparities-found-in-management-of-patients-with-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy-in-the-hospital/">Sex and race disparities found in management of patients with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy in the hospital</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-researchers-create-test-ai-to-improve-ekg-testing-for-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy/">Mayo researchers create, test AI to improve EKG testing for hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-know-the-warning-signs-of-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Know the warning signs of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/04/medical-illustration-of-heart-with-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/04/medical-illustration-of-heart-with-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy-16x9-2.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cardiology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Said Alsidawi]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Heart]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[hypertrophic cardiomyopathy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>