<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Gastroenterology - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/gastrointestinal-90/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/gastrointestinal-90/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 11:32:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Consumer Health: Do you need more dietary fiber or less?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-do-you-need-more-dietary-fiber-or-less/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laurel Kelly]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dietary fiber]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[high-fiber diet]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Low-Fiber Diet]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=372175</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Dietary fiber, also known as roughage or bulk, includes the parts of plant foods your body can't digest or absorb. Unlike other food components, such as fats, proteins or carbohydrates — which your body breaks down and absorbs — fiber isn't digested by your body. Instead, it passes relatively intact through your stomach, small intestine [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-do-you-need-more-dietary-fiber-or-less/">Consumer Health: Do you need more dietary fiber or less?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" width="1024" height="735" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/GettyImages-1394468472-1024x735.jpg" alt="an empty wooden plate alongside a linen napkin, wooden serving utensils tied together with twine and small bowls of pink salt and whole peppercorns, all on a dark tabletop,  dietary
" class="wp-image-372202" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/GettyImages-1394468472-1024x735.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/GettyImages-1394468472-300x215.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/GettyImages-1394468472-768x551.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/GettyImages-1394468472-1536x1103.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/GettyImages-1394468472.jpg 1567w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Dietary fiber, also known as roughage or bulk, includes the parts of plant foods your body can't digest or absorb. Unlike other food components, such as fats, proteins or carbohydrates — which your body breaks down and absorbs — fiber isn't digested by your body. Instead, it passes relatively intact through your stomach, small intestine and colon and out of your body. Fiber is commonly classified as soluble, which dissolves in water, or insoluble, which doesn't dissolve.</p>



<p>The recommended amount of dietary fiber is 14 grams for every 1,000 calories per day, or about 25 grams for women and 38 grams for men each day, according to the <a href="https://www.eatright.org/health/essential-nutrients/carbohydrates/fiber" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics</a>.</p>



<p>The amount of fiber your body needs may vary depending on your energy needs. It also can depend on certain health conditions you may have.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px">Why you might need more fiber in your diet</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/constipation/symptoms-causes/syc-20354253?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Constipation</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hemorrhoids/symptoms-causes/syc-20360268?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hemorrhoids</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-cholesterol/symptoms-causes/syc-20350800?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">high cholesterol</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/diabetes/symptoms-causes/syc-20371444?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">diabetes</a> are some of the health conditions for which your healthcare team might advise you to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/fiber/art-20043983?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">increase your fiber intake</a>:</p>



<p>In particular, a high-fiber diet:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Normalizes bowel movements.</strong><br>Dietary fiber increases the weight and size of your stool and softens it. A bulky stool is easier to pass, decreasing your chance of constipation. If you have loose, watery stools, fiber may help to solidify the stool because it absorbs water and adds bulk to the stool.</li>



<li><strong>Helps maintain bowel health.</strong><br>A high-fiber diet may lower your risk of developing hemorrhoids and small pouches in your colon (diverticular disease). Studies have also found that a high-fiber diet likely lowers the risk of colorectal cancer. Some fiber is fermented in the colon. Researchers are looking at how this may play a role in preventing colon diseases.</li>



<li><strong>Lowers cholesterol levels.</strong><br>Soluble fiber found in beans, oats, flaxseed and oat bran may help lower total blood cholesterol levels by lowering low-density lipoprotein, or "bad," cholesterol levels. Studies also have shown that high-fiber foods may have other heart-health benefits, such as reducing blood pressure and inflammation.</li>



<li><strong>Helps control blood sugar levels.</strong><br>In people with diabetes, fiber — particularly soluble fiber — can slow the absorption of sugar and help improve blood sugar levels. A healthy diet that includes insoluble fiber also may reduce the risk of developing type 2 diabetes.</li>



<li><strong>Aids in achieving healthy weight.</strong><br>High-fiber foods tend to be more filling than low-fiber foods, so you're likely to eat less and stay satisfied longer eating high-fiber foods. And high-fiber foods tend to take longer to eat and are less "energy dense," which means they have fewer calories for the same volume of food.</li>



<li><strong>Helps you live longer.</strong><br>Studies suggest that increasing your dietary fiber intake — especially cereal fiber — is associated with a reduced risk of dying from cardiovascular disease and all cancers.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px">Why you might need less fiber in your diet</h2>



<p>Some of the reasons your healthcare team might recommend a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/low-fiber-diet/art-20048511?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">low-fiber diet</a> include:</p>



<ul>
<li>You have narrowing of the bowel. This may be due to a tumor or an inflammatory disease, such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/crohns-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353304?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Crohn's disease</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/ulcerative-colitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20353326?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ulcerative colitis</a>.</li>



<li>You have had bowel surgery.</li>



<li>You are having treatment that damages or irritates your digestive system. For example, radiation can cause irritation.</li>
</ul>



<p>Eating a low-fiber diet will limit your bowel movements. It may help reduce diarrhea or other symptoms, such as stomach pain. After a short time, you may be able to slowly introduce fiber into your diet again.</p>



<p>Because a low-fiber diet limits what you can eat, it can be difficult to meet your nutritional needs. You should follow a low-fiber diet only as long as directed by your healthcare team.</p>



<p>If you must continue eating this diet for a longer time, consult a registered dietitian. A dietitian can help make sure you are meeting all your nutritional needs.</p>



<p>Connect with others talking about high-fiber and low-fiber diet strategies in the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/digestive-gastrointestinal-problems/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Digestive Health Support Group</a> on&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Connect</a>, an online patient community moderated by Mayo Clinic.<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/wp-admin/post.php?post=330707&amp;action=edit"></a></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-do-you-need-more-dietary-fiber-or-less/">Consumer Health: Do you need more dietary fiber or less?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/an-empty-wooden-plate-alongside-a-linen-napkin-wooden-serving-utensils-tied-together-with-twine-and-small-bowls-of-pink-salt-and-whole-peppercorns-all-on-a-dark-tabletop-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/an-empty-wooden-plate-alongside-a-linen-napkin-wooden-serving-utensils-tied-together-with-twine-and-small-bowls-of-pink-salt-and-whole-peppercorns-all-on-a-dark-tabletop-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[dietary fiber]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[high-fiber diet]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Low-Fiber Diet]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic&#8217;s AI innovation inspires hope in early detection of pancreatic cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-innovation-inspires-hope-in-early-detection-of-pancreatic-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ethan Grove]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 14:25:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pancreatic Cancer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=375016</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Algorithm seeks to address 'last-mile' barrier by identifying disease when cure still possible ROCHESTER, Minn. —&#160;Estimated to become the second leading cause of cancer deaths in the U.S. by 2030, pancreatic cancer has a grim prognosis with nearly 70% of patients facing mortality within the first year of diagnosis. Unfortunately, 40% of small pancreatic cancers [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-innovation-inspires-hope-in-early-detection-of-pancreatic-cancer/">Mayo Clinic&#8217;s AI innovation inspires hope in early detection of pancreatic cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Algorithm seeks to address 'last-mile' barrier by identifying disease when cure still possible</em></p>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. —&nbsp;Estimated to become the second leading cause of cancer deaths in the U.S. by 2030, pancreatic cancer has a grim prognosis with nearly 70% of patients facing mortality within the first year of diagnosis. Unfortunately, 40% of small pancreatic cancers elude detection on CT scans until they've advanced to an incurable stage.</p>



<p>This creates a critical "last-mile" barrier for early detection efforts where, in most patients — including those high-risk subjects undergoing active screening — imaging detects the cancer at a stage when a cure is unlikely. This makes imaging the final frontier in the quest for early cancer detection.</p>



<p>In a <a href="https://www.gastrojournal.org/article/S0016-5085(23)04958-2/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">recent breakthrough</a>, Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center researchers used the world's most extensive imaging dataset to build a versatile artificial intelligence (AI) model that has shown the potential for autonomous detection of pancreatic cancer on standard CTs when surgical intervention can still promise a cure.</p>



<p>"This is where the study emerges as a beacon of hope," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/goenka-ajit-h-m-d/bio-20152402?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ajit H. Goenka, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic radiologist and principal investigator and corresponding author. "It addresses the last-mile challenge — detecting the cancer at a stage when the cancer is even beyond the scope of experts."</p>



<p>The group developed a highly accurate AI model, trained on the largest — more than 3,000 patients — and most diverse CT dataset, for fully automated cancer detection, including small and otherwise difficult-to-detect tumors. Published in <a href="https://www.gastrojournal.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gastroenterology</a>, the journal of the American Gastroenterological Association, the study not only builds on the group's recent work on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ai-applied-to-prediagnostic-cts-may-help-diagnose-pancreatic-cancer-at-earlier-more-treatable-stage/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">radiomics-based early detection models</a> but also underscores Mayo Clinic's standing as a beacon of innovation in AI healthcare solutions.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="410" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Graphical-Abstract-1024x410.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375061" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Graphical-Abstract-1024x410.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Graphical-Abstract-300x120.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Graphical-Abstract-768x307.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Graphical-Abstract-1536x615.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Graphical-Abstract-2048x820.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p>Most important, the model could detect visually imperceptible cancer from normal-appearing pancreases on prediagnostic CT images (i.e., those acquired at three to 36 months prior to clinical diagnosis) substantially early — a median of 438 days — before clinical diagnosis.</p>



<p>"These findings suggest that AI has the potential to detect hidden cancers in asymptomatic individuals, allowing for surgical treatment at a stage when a cure is still achievable," Dr. Goenka says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Finally, the model remained reliable and accurate across diverse patient groups and variations in scanning equipment and imaging techniques. This resilience is crucial for the model's utility in a wide array of real-world medical scenarios.</p>



<p>Addressing a major concern in the AI healthcare landscape, the team also deconstructed the AI's decision-making process to ensure transparency, acknowledging that trust and quality control are essential for AI's broader clinical acceptance.</p>



<p>"We owe the progress to the ingenious efforts of the Framework for AI Software Technology, or FAST, team led by Panagiotis Korfiatis, Ph.D., complemented by our team of exceptionally bright research fellows and data science analysts," says Dr. Goenka. "They dedicated months to meticulous preparation for our initial submission and invested significant effort to astutely address the incisive queries of the panel of international reviewers."</p>



<p>"We're only at the beginning but stand ready to address the challenges of early cancer detection, leveraging the capabilities of AI and next-generation molecular imaging in conjunction with complementary biomarkers," he adds.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic has already initiated the steps for clinical validation and the models are undergoing regulatory processes. With backing from the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>, the team is set to undertake benefactor-funded prospective screening trials. The insights from these trials will refine and bolster the practical effectiveness of their innovative approach.</p>



<p>Their cross-disciplinary endeavor involves co-author experts from Radiology (Garima Suman, M.D., Nandakumar Patnam Gopal Chetty, M.B.B.S., M.D., Kamaxi H. Trivedi, M.B.B.S., M.D., Aashna M. Karbhari, M.B.B.S., M.D., Sovanlal Mukherjee, Ph.D., Cole J. Cook, Ph.D., M.S., Jason R. Klug, Ph.D., Naveen Rajamohan, M.D.,&nbsp; Hala A. Khasawneh, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/fletcher-joel-g-m-d/bio-20053419?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Joel G. Fletcher, M.D.</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/bolan-candice-w-m-d/bio-20055590?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Candice W. Bolan, M.D.</a>, and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/sandrasegaran-kumar-m-b-ch-b/bio-20433978?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kumar Sandrasegaran, M.B., Ch.B.</a>), Surgery (<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/truty-mark-j-m-d-m-s/bio-20055639?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mark J. Truty, M.D., M.S.</a>), and Gastroenterology (<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/majumder-shounak-m-d/bio-20343690?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Shounak Majumder, M.D.</a>, Suresh T. Chari, M.D.).</p>



<p>Research reported in this news release was supported by the National Cancer Institute&nbsp;of the National Institutes of Health under award numbers: R01CA272628 and R01CA256969, as well as from the Centene Charitable Foundation, and the Champions for Hope Pancreatic Cancer Research Program of the Funk Zitiello Foundation. The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institutes of Health.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<ul>
<li>Ethan Grove, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-ai-innovation-inspires-hope-in-early-detection-of-pancreatic-cancer/">Mayo Clinic&#8217;s AI innovation inspires hope in early detection of pancreatic cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/12/pancreas-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/12/pancreas-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[AI]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Pancreatic Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Coeliac disease vs gluten intolerance: Mayo Clinic Healthcare expert explains the difference</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/coeliac-disease-vs-gluten-intolerance-mayo-clinic-healthcare-expert-explains-the-difference/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sharon Theimer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374932</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>LONDON — As gluten-free food options increase, it can be difficult to decide whether to include gluten in your diet or not. For most people, there is no need to completely eliminate foods containing gluten and no proven benefit from doing so, says Sarmed Sami, MBChB, a gastroenterologist at Mayo Clinic Healthcare in London. In [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/coeliac-disease-vs-gluten-intolerance-mayo-clinic-healthcare-expert-explains-the-difference/">Coeliac disease vs gluten intolerance: Mayo Clinic Healthcare expert explains the difference</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="800" height="533" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/loaf-of-sliced-wheat-bread_shutterstock_559840864.jpg" alt="loaf of sliced wheat bread" class="wp-image-374934" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/loaf-of-sliced-wheat-bread_shutterstock_559840864.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/loaf-of-sliced-wheat-bread_shutterstock_559840864-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/loaf-of-sliced-wheat-bread_shutterstock_559840864-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p>LONDON — As <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/gluten-free-diet/art-20048530?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gluten-free</a> food options increase, it can be difficult to decide whether to include gluten in your diet or not. For most people, there is no need to completely eliminate foods containing gluten and no proven benefit from doing so, says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/celiac-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20352220?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sarmed Sami, MBChB</a>, a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/patient-care/gastroenterology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gastroenterologist</a> at <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/why-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Healthcare</a> in London. In this expert alert, Dr. Sami explains why, and the difference between two gluten-related medical conditions: <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/celiac-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20352220" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">coeliac disease</a> and gluten intolerance. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Gluten is a protein found in grains such as wheat, barley and rye. In coeliac disease, eating gluten triggers an autoimmune reaction that causes cell damage to the small intestine. This in turn can cause <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/diarrhea/symptoms-causes/syc-20352241?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">diarrhoea</a>,&nbsp; fatigue, weight loss, bloating, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/anemia/symptoms-causes/syc-20351360?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">anaemia</a> and other problems and lead to serious complications.</p>



<p>Gluten intolerance is more common, Dr. Sami says. It is comparable to an intolerance to dairy, onions or garlic, he adds.</p>



<p>"In gluten intolerance, there is no cell damage or inflammation. It's more of a sensitivity: 'Gluten doesn't agree with me,'" Dr. Sami says. "If you eat gluten and have an immediate reaction, such as diarrhoea, that's more likely to be gluten intolerance than coeliac disease, which is a slow process that you don't tend to feel immediately."</p>



<p>One sign that someone has gluten intolerance or coeliac disease is the presence of one or more gastrointestinal symptoms such as diarrhoea, bloating or heartburn that diminish or go away if gluten is removed from the diet and come back if the person resumes eating foods with gluten, Dr. Sami says. If this happens, it is important to be tested in case it is the more serious coeliac disease, he adds.</p>



<p>Addressing gluten intolerance may be as simple as cutting back on foods containing gluten rather than eliminating them completely, Dr. Sami says.</p>



<p>"It depends on the intolerance level. Some people may be fine by halving the gluten intake, while others may need to cut down more," Dr. Sami says. "It's different from coeliac disease, where you have to be strictly, completely, gluten-free."</p>



<p>Diagnosing coeliac disease typically starts with a blood test to determine whether the body views gluten as an invader and is generating high levels of antibodies to protect itself. If a blood test is positive, an imaging test called endoscopy is used to take biopsies to check for damage in the small intestine.</p>



<p>"We typically recommend that people should not be on a gluten-free diet if they are being tested for coeliac disease, because that can create false negative results on the blood test," Dr. Sami says.</p>



<p>For the majority of patients diagnosed with coeliac disease, eliminating gluten keeps it under control, Dr. Sami says. But without a coeliac diagnosis, there is no reason to eliminate gluten.</p>



<p>"There's no evidence that a gluten-free diet by itself is healthier," Dr. Sami says. "It's not about the gluten. Take a biscuit, for example: It's more about the fat and the sugar in the biscuit, rather than the gluten." &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Healthcare</strong><br>Mayo Clinic Healthcare, located in London, is a wholly owned subsidiary of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>, a not-for-profit academic medical center. Mayo Clinic is ranked the No. 1 hospital by U.S. News &amp; World Report for a reason: quality of care. Mayo Clinic Healthcare is the U.K.'s front door to that unparalleled experience. Visit <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Healthcare</a> for more information.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact: </strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Sharon Theimer, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/coeliac-disease-vs-gluten-intolerance-mayo-clinic-healthcare-expert-explains-the-difference/">Coeliac disease vs gluten intolerance: Mayo Clinic Healthcare expert explains the difference</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/loaf-of-sliced-wheat-bread_shutterstock_559840864_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/loaf-of-sliced-wheat-bread_shutterstock_559840864_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[International News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New gene markers detect Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer, Mayo Clinic study</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-gene-markers-detect-lynch-syndrome-associated-colorectal-cancer-mayo-clinic-study/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelley Luckstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 16:22:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[colorectal cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jewel Samadder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[genetic markers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genetic Testing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lynch Syndrome]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374770</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Researchers from Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center and Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine have discovered new genetic markers to identify Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer with high accuracy. Studies are underway to determine if these genetic markers are in stool samples and, if so, how this could lead to a non-invasive screening [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-gene-markers-detect-lynch-syndrome-associated-colorectal-cancer-mayo-clinic-study/">New gene markers detect Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer, Mayo Clinic study</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="689" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610-1024x689.jpg" alt="a close-up view of a deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) sequencing test illuminated in green, blue, and purple" class="wp-image-362241" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610-1024x689.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610-300x202.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610-768x517.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610-1536x1034.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610.jpg 1671w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Researchers from <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine/education/gerstner-family-career-development-awards" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine</a> have discovered new genetic markers to identify Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer with high accuracy. Studies are underway to determine if these genetic markers are in stool samples and, if so, how this could lead to a non-invasive screening option for patients with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lynch-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20374714?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lynch syndrome.</a> Their research was published in <a href="https://aacrjournals.org/cancerpreventionresearch/article/doi/10.1158/1940-6207.CAPR-23-0107/729134/Methylated-DNA-Markers-for-Sporadic-Colorectal-and" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cancer Prevention Research</a>, a journal of the American Association for Cancer Research.</p>



<p>"This is an exciting finding that brings us closer to the reality that clinicians may soon be able to offer a non-invasive cancer screening option to patients with the highest risk of getting cancer," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/samadder-niloy-jewel-jewel-j-m-d/bio-20415667?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jewel Samadder, M.D.</a>, co-lead author of the paper and gastroenterologist at Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center. "I look forward to the day when I no longer have to remind patients with Lynch Syndrome to schedule their annual colonoscopy and complete the prep, when they will instead be able to provide a stool sample to screen for cancer."</p>



<p>Lynch syndrome is an inherited genetic condition that significantly increases the risk of multiple cancers, most notably colorectal and uterine cancers. Approximately 1 in 300 people have Lynch syndrome, many of whom are unaware of it. Patients with Lynch syndrome undergo <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/colonoscopy/about/pac-20393569?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colonoscopies</a> annually to detect and remove pre-cancerous lesions that can form colorectal cancer, in addition to undergoing invasive tests or prophylactic surgery to prevent uterine cancer.</p>



<p>For this study, the researchers evaluated a panel of methylated DNA markers (MDM) for sporadic colorectal and endometrial cancers in people with Lynch syndrome (LS). Sporadic cancer is cancer that occurs randomly in people with no family history or known predisposing risk factors. The researchers also included control groups with no cancer. For colorectal cancer, there were 23 LS cases, 48 sporadic cases, 32 LS controls, and 48 sporadic controls. For endometrial cancer, there were 30 LS cases, 48 sporadic cases, 29 LS controls and 37 sporadic controls.</p>



<p>"We found that a marker panel composed of three biomarkers (LASS4, LRRC4, PPP2R5C) could effectively differentiate Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer from Lynch syndrome controls, with 92% accuracy. This three-marker panel also performed similarly in distinguishing sporadic colorectal cancer cases from controls," says Dr. Samadder. This three-marker panel is being tested in a multi-site clinical trial in patients with Lynch syndrome as a non-invasive screening option.</p>



<p>"Our findings support the feasibility of cancer detection in stool and lower gynecologic genital tract samples in the setting of Lynch syndrome and warrant further testing," says Dr. Samadder.</p>



<p>The research was funded by the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine</a> and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine/education/gerstner-family-career-development-awards#:~:text=The%20Gerstner%20Family%20Career%20Development,research%20using%20individualized%20medicine%20approaches." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gerstner Family Career Development Award</a>. For a full list of funding, authors and conflicts of interest, see the <a href="https://aacrjournals.org/cancerpreventionresearch/article/doi/10.1158/1940-6207.CAPR-23-0107/729134/Methylated-DNA-Markers-for-Sporadic-Colorectal-and" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">paper</a>.  </p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive&nbsp;Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;is defining new boundaries in possibility, focusing on patient-centered care, developing novel treatments, training future generations of cancer experts, and bringing cancer research to communities. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs that are changing approaches to cancer prevention, screening, and treatment and improving the lives of cancer survivors.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-gene-markers-detect-lynch-syndrome-associated-colorectal-cancer-mayo-clinic-study/">New gene markers detect Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer, Mayo Clinic study</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/a-close-up-view-of-a-deoxyribonucleic-acid-DNA-sequencing-test-illuminated-in-green-blue-and-purple-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/a-close-up-view-of-a-deoxyribonucleic-acid-DNA-sequencing-test-illuminated-in-green-blue-and-purple-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[colorectal cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jewel Samadder]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[genetic markers]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Genetic Testing]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Lynch Syndrome]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Consumer Health: What is familial adenomatous polyposis?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-what-is-familial-adenomatous-polyposis/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laurel Kelly]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2023 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[colon polyps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[colorectal cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[familial adenomatous polyposis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[genetic mutations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genetic Testing]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=360794</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Cancer in the colon&#160;and&#160;cancer in the rectum, often referred to together as colorectal cancer, is the third most common cancer diagnosed in both men and women in the U.S. excluding skin cancers, according to the&#160;American Cancer Society. Among the risk factors that can increase your risk of colorectal cancer are certain genetic syndromes, including&#160;familial adenomatous [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-what-is-familial-adenomatous-polyposis/">Consumer Health: What is familial adenomatous polyposis?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="717" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/12/genetic-testing-original.jpg" alt="a colorful illustration or graphic depicting genetic testing" class="wp-image-290055" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/12/genetic-testing-original.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/12/genetic-testing-original-300x210.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/12/genetic-testing-original-768x538.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353669?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cancer in the colon</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/rectal-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352884?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer in the rectum</a>, often referred to together as colorectal cancer, is the third most common cancer diagnosed in both men and women in the U.S. excluding skin cancers, according to the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/colon-rectal-cancer/about/key-statistics.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Cancer Society</a>.</p>



<p>Among the risk factors that can increase your risk of colorectal cancer are certain genetic syndromes, including&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/familial-adenomatous-polyposis/symptoms-causes/syc-20372443?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">familial adenomatous polyposis</a>. This is a rare condition caused by a defect in the <em>adenomatous polyposis coli</em> gene. Most people inherit the gene from a parent, but for 25% to 30% of people, the genetic mutation occurs spontaneously.</p>



<p>With this condition, extra tissue, called <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-polyps/symptoms-causes/syc-20352875?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">polyps</a>, forms in your colon and rectum. Polyps also can occur in the upper gastrointestinal tract, especially the upper part of your small intestine. If untreated, the polyps in the colon and rectum are likely to become cancerous when you are in your 40s.</p>



<p>Most people with familial adenomatous polyposis eventually need surgery to remove the large intestine to prevent cancer. The polyps in the upper part of the small intestine also can develop cancer, but they usually can be managed by careful monitoring and regularly removing the polyps.</p>



<p>Some people have a milder form of the condition, called attenuated familial adenomatous polyposis. People with this milder form usually have fewer colon polyps and develop cancer later in life.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Symptoms</strong></h2>



<p>The main sign of familial adenomatous polyposis is hundreds or even thousands of polyps growing in your colon and rectum, usually starting by your mid-teens. The polyps are nearly 100% certain to develop into colon cancer or rectal cancer by the time you're in your 40s.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Risk factors</strong></h2>



<p>Familial adenomatous polyposis is caused by a defect in a gene that's usually inherited from a parent. But some people develop the abnormal gene that causes the condition. Your risk is higher if you have a parent, child, brother or sister with the condition.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Prevention</strong></h2>



<p>Preventing familial adenomatous polyposis is not possible, since it is predominantly an inherited genetic condition. However, if you or your child are at risk because of a family member with the condition, you will need genetic testing and counseling. </p>



<p>A blood test can determine if you carry the abnormal gene that causes familial adenomatous polyposis. Ruling it out spares at-risk children years of screening and emotional distress. For children who carry the gene, appropriate screening and treatment greatly reduces the risk of cancer.</p>



<p>For people at risk, it's important to be screened frequently, starting in childhood. Annual exams can detect the growth of polyps before they become cancerous.</p>



<p>If you have been diagnosed with familial adenomatous polyposis, you will need regular screening, followed by surgery if needed. Surgery can help prevent the development of colorectal cancer or other complications.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Treatment</strong></h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/familial-adenomatous-polyposis/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20372446?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Treatment</a> for familial adenomatous polyposis begins with your health care professional removing any small polyps found during your colonoscopy exam. Eventually, though, the polyps will become too numerous to remove individually, usually by your late teens or early 20s. Then you will need surgery to prevent cancer developing. You also will need surgery if a polyp is cancerous. If you have attenuated familial adenomatous polyposis — the milder form of the condition, you may not need surgery.</p>



<p>Surgery doesn't cure familial adenomatous polyposis. Polyps can continue to form in the remaining or reconstructed parts of your colon, stomach and small intestine. Depending on the number and size of the polyps, having them removed endoscopically may not be enough to reduce your risk of cancer. You may need additional surgery. You also will need regular screening — and treatment if needed — for the complications of familial adenomatous polyposis that can develop after colorectal surgery.</p>



<p>Connect with others talking about familial adenomatous polyposis and colorectal cancer&nbsp;in the <a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/colorectal-cancer/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Colorectal Cancer</a> support group on <a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Connect</a>, an online patient community moderated by Mayo Clinic.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-what-is-familial-adenomatous-polyposis/">Consumer Health: What is familial adenomatous polyposis?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/12/genetic-testing-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/12/genetic-testing-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[colon polyps]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[colorectal cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[familial adenomatous polyposis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[genetic mutations]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Genetic Testing]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers publish key findings about cell proteins to determine effectiveness of immunotherapy for colon cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-publish-key-findings-about-cell-proteins-to-determine-effectiveness-of-immunotherapy-for-colon-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelley Luckstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2023 13:53:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[colorectal cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Frank Sinicrope]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immunotherapy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tumor]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=373671</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center researchers have identified key findings that can assist clinicians in predicting whether a patient with advanced colorectal cancer will benefit from immunotherapy. The study was published in the journal Clinical Cancer Research and highlights the potential of using spatial analysis of specific proteins as a predictive tool [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-publish-key-findings-about-cell-proteins-to-determine-effectiveness-of-immunotherapy-for-colon-cancer/">Mayo Clinic researchers publish key findings about cell proteins to determine effectiveness of immunotherapy for colon cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="800" height="625" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/Micrograph-of-colon-cancer-cells_GettyImages-99310985.jpg" alt="Micrograph of colon cancer cells" class="wp-image-373687" style="aspect-ratio:16/9;object-fit:cover" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/Micrograph-of-colon-cancer-cells_GettyImages-99310985.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/Micrograph-of-colon-cancer-cells_GettyImages-99310985-300x234.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/Micrograph-of-colon-cancer-cells_GettyImages-99310985-768x600.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> researchers have identified key findings that can assist clinicians in predicting whether a patient with advanced <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353669?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colorectal cancer</a> will benefit from <a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/blog/hematology/newsfeed-post/immunotherapy-to-fight-cancer-what-is-it-and-how-does-it-work/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">immunotherapy</a>. The study was published in the journal <a href="https://aacrjournals.org/clincancerres/article/doi/10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-23-1109/728423" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Clinical Cancer Research</a> and highlights the potential of using spatial analysis of specific proteins as a predictive tool for selecting appropriate candidates for PD-1 blockade immunotherapy in colorectal cancer, ultimately improving treatment outcomes and minimizing unnecessary treatments.</p>



<p>The study authors found that the distance between cells that express programmed cell death protein 1 (PD-1) and programmed cell death ligand 1 (PD-L1) within the tumor can predict the outcome of immunotherapy in colorectal cancers with a defective DNA repair system, known as mismatch repair.&nbsp;PD-1 and PD-L1 are immune checkpoint proteins, primarily located on the surface of immune cells, whose binding is blocked by drugs known as checkpoint inhibitors.</p>



<p>"The finding suggests that this spatial analysis within tumors may be useful to select patients who are more likely to benefit from immunotherapy," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/sinicrope-frank-a-m-d/bio-20054019?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Frank Sinicrope, M.D.</a>, medical oncologist and gastroenterologist at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>. "If cells expressing these proteins were at or within 10 microns of each other within the tumor, then immunotherapy treatment was able to significantly improve patient survival. This finding suggests a critical threshold for effective blockade of the PD-1/PD-L1 axis."</p>



<p>While immunotherapy continues to advance cancer treatment, not all patients with metastatic colorectal cancer who have a defective DNA repair system benefit from this treatment. Accordingly, there is a need for predictive biomarkers of response and survival, adds Dr. Sinicrope, lead author of the study.</p>



<p>According to the researchers, among the patient tumors that were examined, 60% had an increased number of cells with PD-1 and PD-L1 in close proximity, meaning that 60% of these patients are likely to benefit from immunotherapy. Furthermore, such data has the potential to assist clinicians in selecting patients for treatment while the other 40% who are less likely to benefit from immunotherapy could be treated with combination therapy or another type of treatment.</p>



<p>The researchers share that they are in the process of validating their findings, and if the results can be validated, the finding would allow patient selection of those most likely to benefit from PD-1 blockade, and spare patients not likely to benefit from it the potential toxicity and cost of the drug. </p>



<p>"To our knowledge, this is the first report of this finding in colorectal cancer; however, reports showing the importance of PD-1 and PD-L1 proximity have been reported in melanoma and non-small cell lung cancer," says Dr. Sinicrope. "While our results are promising, the study data await validation in an independent cohort so are not yet ready to be used in clinical practice."</p>



<p>This study was supported, in part, by NCI R01 CA210509 (to Dr. Sinicrope) and by Roche Diagnostics.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive&nbsp;Cancer Center</strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;is defining new boundaries in possibility, focusing on patient-centered care, developing novel treatments, training future generations of cancer experts, and bringing cancer research to communities. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs that are changing approaches to cancer prevention, screening, and treatment and improving the lives of cancer survivors.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-publish-key-findings-about-cell-proteins-to-determine-effectiveness-of-immunotherapy-for-colon-cancer/">Mayo Clinic researchers publish key findings about cell proteins to determine effectiveness of immunotherapy for colon cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/Micrograph-of-colon-cancer-cells_GettyImages-99310985_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/Micrograph-of-colon-cancer-cells_GettyImages-99310985_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[colorectal cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Frank Sinicrope]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[immunotherapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[tumor]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Burning mouth syndrome: Why doctors sometimes fight its fire with fire</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/burning-mouth-syndrome-why-doctors-sometimes-fight-its-fire-with-fire/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sharon Theimer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[burning mouth syndrome]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sarmed Sami]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=370053</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Menopause is a risk factor for painful condition, Mayo Clinic Healthcare expert explains LONDON — Hot flashes, mood swings and sleep problems are common as a woman approaches and passes menopause. Much less common but as disruptive is another condition that can afflict perimenopausal and postmenopausal women: burning mouth syndrome. Sarmed Sami, MBChB, a gastroenterologist [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/burning-mouth-syndrome-why-doctors-sometimes-fight-its-fire-with-fire/">Burning mouth syndrome: Why doctors sometimes fight its fire with fire</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/16x9_Featured-image-for-burning-mouth-syndrome-posts_GettyImages-13066693821-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-370055" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/16x9_Featured-image-for-burning-mouth-syndrome-posts_GettyImages-13066693821-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/16x9_Featured-image-for-burning-mouth-syndrome-posts_GettyImages-13066693821-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/16x9_Featured-image-for-burning-mouth-syndrome-posts_GettyImages-13066693821-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/16x9_Featured-image-for-burning-mouth-syndrome-posts_GettyImages-13066693821-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/16x9_Featured-image-for-burning-mouth-syndrome-posts_GettyImages-13066693821-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><em>Menopause is a risk factor for painful condition, Mayo Clinic Healthcare expert explains</em></p>



<p>LONDON — Hot flashes, mood swings and sleep problems are common as a woman approaches and passes menopause. Much less common but as disruptive is another condition that can afflict <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/perimenopause/symptoms-causes/syc-20354666?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">perimenopausal</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/menopause/symptoms-causes/syc-20353397?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">postmenopausal</a> women: <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/burning-mouth-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20350911?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">burning mouth syndrome</a>. <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/doctors/sarmed-s-sami-mbchb#details" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sarmed Sami, MBChB</a>, a gastroenterologist at <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/why-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Healthcare</a> in London, describes the painful condition, how it is diagnosed and why doctors sometimes fight its fire with fire.</p>



<p>"Burning mouth syndrome can affect swallowing, eating, speech and sleep," Dr. Sami says. "There's a lot more to it than your mouth feeling uncomfortable. In addition to affecting your quality of life, it can affect various aspects of your health."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/Sarmed-Sami_1-200x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-370061" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/Sarmed-Sami_1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/Sarmed-Sami_1-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/Sarmed-Sami_1-768x1151.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/Sarmed-Sami_1-1025x1536.jpg 1025w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/Sarmed-Sami_1-1366x2048.jpg 1366w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><sup><strong>Sarmed Sami, MBChB</strong></sup></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Burning mouth syndrome can include a burning feeling in the tongue, lips, gums, throat, or roof of the mouth. Other symptoms may be thirst, a dry mouth, a bitter or metallic taste in the mouth, loss of taste and mouth tingling, stinging or numbness. The frequency of symptoms can vary widely, from all day every day to sporadic.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Treatment involves addressing symptoms and the cause, Dr. Sami says. For example, if the burning mouth syndrome is likely related to menopause, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/menopause/in-depth/hormone-therapy/art-20046372?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hormone replacement therapy</a> may help. Other potential underlying conditions include <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/patient-care/gastroenterology/gastrointestinal-specialty-areas/esophageal-conditions-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gastro-oesophageal reflux</a>, thyroid problems, vitamin deficiencies, and irritation from toothpaste, mouthwash or acidic foods and beverages. The cause cannot always be identified.</p>



<p>"We use medications to essentially calm down the nerves and sensors in the mouth, because we think there is hypersensitivity," Dr. Sami says. "Stress can also cause it, so we may use complementary therapies such as acupuncture."</p>



<p>Other therapies may include hot sauce, also known as pepper sauce: "There are certain chemicals that help reduce sensitivity. Hot sauce may seem counterintuitive, but it has <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements/capsaicin-topical-route/description/drg-20062561?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">capsaicin</a>, which can help relieve burning pain in nerves," Dr. Sami says.</p>



<p>Factors that put people at the highest risk for burning mouth include being female, perimenopausal or postmenopausal, over 50 and smoking. Secondary factors that can raise risk include recent illness; medical conditions such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/fibromyalgia/symptoms-causes/syc-20354780?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">fibromyalgia</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/parkinsons-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20376055?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Parkinson's disease</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/rheumatology/sections/conditions-treated/orc-20477148?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">autoimmune diseases</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/peripheral-neuropathy/symptoms-causes/syc-20352061?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">neuropathy</a>; dental work; food allergies; some medicines; and stress, anxiety, depression and traumatic life events.</p>



<p>In addition to medical treatment, burning mouth symptoms may be eased by lifestyle changes and other self-help measures. Those include drinking plenty of liquids; sucking on ice chips; avoiding acidic foods and liquids such as tomatoes, orange juice, carbonated beverages, and coffee; avoiding alcohol; avoiding spicy foods; refraining from tobacco use; avoiding products with cinnamon or mint; and using mild or flavor-free toothpastes. Working to reduce stress and relax can also help.&nbsp;</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Healthcare</strong><br>Mayo Clinic Healthcare, located in London, is a wholly owned subsidiary of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>, a not-for-profit academic medical center. Mayo Clinic is ranked the No. 1 hospital by U.S. News &amp; World Report for a reason: quality of care. Mayo Clinic Healthcare is the U.K.’s front door to that unparalleled experience. Visit <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Healthcare</a> for more information.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact: </strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Sharon Theimer, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/burning-mouth-syndrome-why-doctors-sometimes-fight-its-fire-with-fire/">Burning mouth syndrome: Why doctors sometimes fight its fire with fire</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/1x1_Featured-image-for-burning-mouth-syndrome-posts_GettyImages-13066693821.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/16x9_Featured-image-for-burning-mouth-syndrome-posts_GettyImages-13066693821.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[burning mouth syndrome]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Sarmed Sami]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[International News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mcthumb >https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/16x9_Featured-image-for-burning-mouth-syndrome-posts_GettyImages-13066693821-150x150.jpg</mayoclinic:mcthumb >	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Healthcare in London adds doctors in several medical specialties</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-healthcare-in-london-adds-doctors-in-several-medical-specialties-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sharon Theimer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=369999</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>LONDON —&#160;Mayo Clinic Healthcare is adding several doctors, including cardiologists, a gastroenterologist, experts in women's and men's health, and radiologists who specialize in a range of conditions and imaging techniques. Several of the doctors are multilingual. Mayo Clinic Healthcare, located at 15 Portland Place in the Harley Street Medical Area, provides personalised healthcare including specialized [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-healthcare-in-london-adds-doctors-in-several-medical-specialties-2/">Mayo Clinic Healthcare in London adds doctors in several medical specialties</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="800" height="450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/16x9_Mayo-Clinic_Portland-Place_0051.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-369864" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/16x9_Mayo-Clinic_Portland-Place_0051.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/16x9_Mayo-Clinic_Portland-Place_0051-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/16x9_Mayo-Clinic_Portland-Place_0051-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p>LONDON —&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Healthcare</a> is adding several doctors, including cardiologists, a gastroenterologist, experts in women's and men's health, and radiologists who specialize in a range of conditions and imaging techniques. Several of the doctors are multilingual.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic Healthcare, located at 15 Portland Place in the Harley Street Medical Area, provides personalised healthcare including specialized care, second opinions, advanced medical imaging and tailored wellness plans. The clinic also serves as a gateway to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/international?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic’s</a> roughly 4,000 physicians in the United States.</p>



<p>Joining Mayo Clinic Healthcare are:</p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/doctors/stephen-brecker-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stephen Brecker, M.D.</a>, a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/patient-care/cardiology/cardiology-specialty-areas" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiologist</a> who specializes in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/patient-care/cardiology/cardiology-specialty-areas/heart-valve-disease-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart valve disease</a> and the connection between heart disease and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/cerebrovascular-diseases-critical-care-group/overview/ovc-20443614" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cerebrovascular</a>, or brain and blood vessel, conditions such as stroke. Dr. Brecker treats a wide range of heart conditions, including <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/angina/symptoms-causes/syc-20369373" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">angina</a>, chest pain caused by reduced blood flow to the heart; <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/vasovagal-syncope/symptoms-causes/syc-20350527" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">neurocardiogenic syncope</a>, fainting due to a sudden drop in heart rate and blood pressure; heart rhythm disorders; congestive heart failure; and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/atrial-septal-defect/symptoms-causes/syc-20369715?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">atrial septal defects</a>, holes in the heart that increase the flow of blood through the lungs.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/doctors/tito-kabir-mbbs#details" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tito Kabir, M.B.B.S.</a>, an interventional cardiologist whose areas of focus include <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/coronary-angioplasty/about/pac-20384761?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">angioplasty</a>, a procedure used to open clogged heart arteries; <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/acute-coronary-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20352136?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">acute coronary syndrome</a>, sudden reduced blood flow to the heart; heart rhythm disorders; congestive heart failure; and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/arteriosclerosis-atherosclerosis/multimedia/development-of-atherosclerosis/img-20005848?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">atherosclerosis</a>, plaque buildup on artery walls; syncope; and high blood pressure.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/doctors/ricardo-petraco-md#details" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ricardo Petraco, M.D.</a>, a cardiologist who specializes in angina, breathlessness, chest pain, coronary artery disease and heart failure. Dr. Petraco is fluent in English and Portuguese.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/doctors/pradeep-bhandari-mbbs" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pradeep Bhandari, M.D.</a>, a gastroenterologist who treats conditions including abnormal liver function; acid reflux; Barrett's oesophagus; changes in bowel habits; Crohn's disease; <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/peptic-ulcer/symptoms-causes/syc-20354223?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">peptic ulcers</a>; <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/indigestion/symptoms-causes/syc-20352211?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dyspepsia</a>, or indigestion; inflammatory bowel disease; irritable bowel syndrome; obesity; rectal bleeding; and weight loss. Dr. Bhandari is fluent in English and Hindi.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/doctors/may-al-araji-mrcgp" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">May Al-Araji, MBChB</a>, a general medicine doctor whose areas of focus include family medicine and women's health including menopause. Dr. Al-Araji is fluent in English and Arabic.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/doctors/vikas-mehta-mrcgp" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Vikas Mehta, MBChB</a>, a general medicine doctor whose focus areas include men's health, women's health, and lifestyle medicine. Dr. Mehta treats conditions including asthma and other chronic respiratory conditions; diabetes; ear, nose and throat conditions; family health; sexual health; gastric conditions; musculoskeletal conditions; and urologic conditions. He is fluent in English, Hindi, Punjabi, Swahili, and Urdu.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/doctors/ashok-adams-mbbs-mrcr" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ashok Adams, M.B.B.S.</a>, a radiologist who specializes in ear, nose and throat conditions, salivary gland conditions and thyroid diseases. Dr. Adams is fluent in English and Spanish.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/doctors/muaaze-ahmad-mb" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Muaaze Ahmad, MBChB</a>, a radiologist whose areas of focus include musculoskeletal imaging, arthritis, tendonitis and soft tissue tumors.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/doctors/david-rohan-evans-mbbs" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">David Rohan Evans, M.B.B.S.</a>, a radiologist who specializes in breast radiology including breast cancer screening.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/doctors/hatef-mansoubi-mbbs" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hatef Mansoubi, M.B.B.S.</a>, a cardiothoracic radiologist. Dr. Mansoubi is fluent in English, Farsi and Greek.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/doctors/graham-munneke-mbbs" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Graham Munneke, M.B.B.S.</a>, a radiologist specializing in chest, abdominal and cancer imaging.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/doctors/niall-power-mrcpi" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Niall Power, MRCPI</a>, a radiologist whose areas of focus include abdominal imaging and gastroenterologic and hepatobiliary imaging. Dr. Power is fluent in English and Irish.</li>
</ul>



<p>Mayo Clinic Healthcare offers a range of <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/patient-care" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">diagnostics</a> including advanced cardiac imaging, colonoscopies and other cancer screenings, abdominal ultrasounds, bone density tests, CT coronary angiograms, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), X-rays, electrocardiograms and echocardiograms.</p>



<p>###<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Healthcare</strong><br>Mayo Clinic Healthcare, located in London, is a wholly owned subsidiary of&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-ranked-no-1-hospital-in-nation-by-u-s-news-world-report/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>, a not-for-profit academic medical center. Mayo Clinic in the U.S. is ranked No. 1 in the world by <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-again-recognized-as-worlds-best-hospital-in-newsweek-rankings-2/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Newsweek</a> and No. 1 in the nation by <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-ranked-no-1-hospital-in-nation-by-u-s-news-world-report/">U.S. News &amp; World Report</a> for a reason: quality of care. Mayo Clinic Healthcare is the U.K.’s front door to that unparalleled experience. Visit&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthcare.co.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Healthcare</a>&nbsp;for more information.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/international?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong> </p>



<ul>
<li>Sharon Theimer, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-healthcare-in-london-adds-doctors-in-several-medical-specialties-2/">Mayo Clinic Healthcare in London adds doctors in several medical specialties</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/1x1_Mayo-Clinic_Portland-Place_0051.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/16x9_Mayo-Clinic_Portland-Place_0051.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[International News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Consumer Health: What&#8217;s the difference between heartburn and GERD?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-whats-the-difference-between-heartburn-and-gerd/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laurel Kelly]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barrett's Esophagus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gastroesophageal reflux disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GERD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[heartburn]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=360777</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Heartburn — that burning pain in your chest after eating certain foods or when you lie down in the evening — is a common complaint and usually no cause for alarm. Heartburn occurs when stomach acid backs up into the esophagus, which is the tube that carries food from your mouth to your stomach. Most [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-whats-the-difference-between-heartburn-and-gerd/">Consumer Health: What&#8217;s the difference between heartburn and GERD?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="680" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/10/shutterstock_104000960-1024x680.jpg" alt="a Caucasian man with his hand on his chest as if he's suffering with pain, heart attack, heartburn, acid reflux, GERD" class="wp-image-252039" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/10/shutterstock_104000960-1024x680.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/10/shutterstock_104000960-300x199.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/10/shutterstock_104000960-768x510.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heartburn/symptoms-causes/syc-20373223?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Heartburn</a> — that burning pain in your chest after eating certain foods or when you lie down in the evening — is a common complaint and usually no cause for alarm. Heartburn occurs when stomach acid backs up into the esophagus, which is the tube that carries food from your mouth to your stomach.</p>



<p>Most people can manage the discomfort of heartburn on their own with lifestyle changes, including maintaining a healthy weight and avoiding smoking, alcohol and foods that trigger your symptoms; and nonprescription medications, such as antacids.</p>



<p>When heartburn occurs repeatedly over time and interferes with your routine, it's considered <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/gerd/symptoms-causes/syc-20361940?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gastroesophageal reflux disease, or GERD</a>. Approximately 20% of the people in the U.S. have GERD, according to the <a href="https://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/digestive-diseases/acid-reflux-ger-gerd-adults/definition-facts#:~:text=see%20your%20doctor.-,How%20common%20is%20GERD%3F,the%20United%20States%20have%20GERD." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</a>.</p>



<p>The constant backwash of acid with GERD can irritate the lining of your esophagus, often causing it to become inflamed. Over time, chronic inflammation in your esophagus can cause serious damage, including narrowing of the esophagus, called esophageal stricture, or the precancerous changes of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/barretts-esophagus/symptoms-causes/syc-20352841?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Barrett's esophagus</a>.</p>



<p>In addition to heartburn, symptoms of GERD can include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Upper abdominal or chest pain</li>



<li>Trouble swallowing</li>



<li>Sensation of a lump in your throat</li>



<li>A chronic cough</li>



<li>Inflammation of the vocal cords</li>



<li>New or worsening asthma</li>
</ul>



<p>With GERD, your health care professional is likely to recommend that you first try lifestyle changes and nonprescription medications — similar to the treatment recommendations for heartburn. And with both conditions, if these measures aren't effective, there are prescription medications that may be recommended.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" style="font-size:18px"><strong>Surgery and other procedures for GERD</strong></h2>



<p>If medications don't help with GERD, or you wish to avoid long-term medication use, your health care team may recommend:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Fundoplication.</strong><br>With this procedure, the surgeon wraps the top of your stomach around the lower esophageal sphincter, to tighten the muscle and prevent reflux. Fundoplication is usually done with a minimally invasive laparoscopic procedure.</li>



<li><strong>LINX device.</strong><br>With this procedure, a ring of tiny magnetic beads is wrapped around the junction of the stomach and esophagus. The magnetic attraction between the beads is strong enough to keep the junction closed to refluxing acid but weak enough to allow food to pass through. The LINX device can be implanted using minimally invasive surgery. The magnetic beads do not have an effect on airport security or MRI.</li>



<li><strong>Transoral incisionless fundoplication.</strong><br>This new procedure involves tightening the lower esophageal sphincter by creating a partial wrap around the lower esophagus using polypropylene fasteners. Transoral incisionless fundoplication is performed through the mouth by using an endoscope and requires no surgical incision. Its advantages include quick recovery time and high tolerance.</li>
</ul>



<p>Connect with others talking about GERD and heartburn in the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/digestive-gastrointestinal-problems/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Digestive Health</a> support group on <a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Connect</a>, an online patient community moderated by Mayo Clinic.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-whats-the-difference-between-heartburn-and-gerd/">Consumer Health: What&#8217;s the difference between heartburn and GERD?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/10/shutterstock_104000960_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/10/shutterstock_104000960_Fotor-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Barrett's Esophagus]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Consumer Health Tips]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[gastroesophageal reflux disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[GERD]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[heartburn]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers link environmental exposures to liver disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-link-environmental-exposures-to-liver-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Colette Gallagher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2023 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Konstantinos Lazaridis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Liver Disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Primary Sclerosing Cholangitis]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=367439</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have identified a diverse range of environmental chemicals in human bile in patients with primary sclerosing cholangitis, a rare, chronic liver disease of the bile ducts. The study, published in Exposome, represents a new frontier of research at Mayo Clinic's Center for Individualized Medicine that explores the exposome, the measure of environmental [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-link-environmental-exposures-to-liver-disease/">Mayo Clinic researchers link environmental exposures to liver disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/liver-disease-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-367437" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/liver-disease-16x9-1.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/liver-disease-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/liver-disease-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have identified a diverse range of environmental chemicals in human bile in patients with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/primary-sclerosing-cholangitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20355797?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">primary sclerosing cholangitis</a>, a rare, chronic liver disease of the bile ducts. The <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36687160/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>, published in Exposome<em>,</em> represents a new frontier of research at <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic's Center for Individualized Medicine</a> that explores the exposome, the measure of environmental contributors to disease and health.</p>



<p>Most people with primary sclerosing cholangitis also have some type of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/inflammatory-bowel-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353315?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">inflammatory bowel disease</a>, such as ulcerative colitis or Crohn's disease, often leading to end-stage liver disease and cancer. Liver transplantation is the only evidence-based treatment for this advanced disease and no drug therapy exists to improve survival without a transplant.</p>



<p>"We know patients with this complex bile duct disorder have an altered metabolome (the complete set of small-molecule chemicals found within a biological sample), which environmental chemicals may influence," says Mayo Clinic researcher <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/lazaridis-konstantinos-n-m-d/bio-20054459?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Konstantinos N. Lazaridis, M.D.</a>, the <em>Carlson and Nelson Endowed Executive Director for Mayo Clinic's Center for Individualized Medicine. "Now we have a comprehensive exposome characterization of bile, which is critical, as bile directly </em>comes into contact with diseased bile ducts."</p>



<p>Dr. Lazaridis notes that this could contribute to higher absorption of environmental chemicals for patients with primary sclerosing cholangitis who also have inflammatory bowel disease.</p>



<p>This liver disease likely develops from genetic and environmental factors. Understanding the contribution of environmental exposures to this disease could lead to discoveries about its causes and risk factors.</p>



<p>For the study, researchers investigated bile samples from patients with the disease using high-resolution mass spectrometry and found various environmental chemicals. This new technology allowed researchers to measure and analyze external chemical exposures and their biological responses, with enough coverage to study the relationships between potential disease drivers and their effects.</p>



<p>The researchers assessed these similarities and differences in the bile of patients in the U.S. versus Norway.</p>



<ul>
<li>They detected 83 environmental chemicals in patients in the U.S. and Norway at statistically similar concentrations.</li>



<li>U.S. patients showed higher environmental chemical bile content and increased links between chemicals and metabolic pathways within their bile than in Norway.</li>



<li>Researchers identified polychlorinated biphenyl (PCB)-118 and PCB-101 chemicals of interest for additional study, given those chemicals' broad connections with metabolic pathways in the U.S. and Norwegian patients. These are highly stable organic chemicals that were widely used in plasticizers, paints and electrical equipment until they were banned by the Stockholm Convention on persistent organic pollutants.</li>



<li>Glycan degradation pathways were associated with one or multiple environmental chemicals in both samples of patients. Glycans are crucial in gut regulation and may be linked to the disease's cause.</li>
</ul>



<p>"The findings of the derived chemical-metabolomic links in the bile serve as a starting point," says Dr. Lazaridis. "They are essential in understanding the biochemical changes that happen with environmental chemical exposure, as they may reflect the cause and progression of primary sclerosing cholangitis and may lead to new medical therapies."</p>



<p>This article originally appeared on the Mayo Clinic <a href="https://individualizedmedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/05/22/mayo-clinic-researchers-link-environmental-exposures-to-liver-disease/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Individualized Medicine blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-link-environmental-exposures-to-liver-disease/">Mayo Clinic researchers link environmental exposures to liver disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/liver-disease-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/liver-disease-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Konstantinos Lazaridis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Liver Disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Primary Sclerosing Cholangitis]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss><!-- Static page delivered by HubScale -->