<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Gastroenterology - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/gastrointestinal-90/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/gastrointestinal-90/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 18:52:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Hepatic artery infusion pump therapy for colorectal liver metastases</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/hepatic-artery-infusion-pump-therapy-for-colorectal-liver-metastases/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[colorectal cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Katherine Poruk]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395246</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>When facing colorectal liver metastases or colorectal cancer that has spread to the liver, finding effective treatment options can be challenging. Dr. Katherine Poruk, a surgical oncologist at Mayo Clinic, says a specialized therapy known as hepatic artery infusion pump (HAIP) chemotherapy is an option for some. Watch: Dr. Katherine Poruk explains hepatic artery infusion [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/hepatic-artery-infusion-pump-therapy-for-colorectal-liver-metastases/">Hepatic artery infusion pump therapy for colorectal liver metastases</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>When facing colorectal liver metastases or colorectal cancer that has <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-when-colon-cancer-spreads-to-the-liver/">spread to the liver</a>, finding effective treatment options can be challenging. Dr. Katherine Poruk, a surgical oncologist at Mayo Clinic, says a specialized therapy known as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/cancer/news/hepatic-artery-infusion-pump-chemotherapy-spares-livers-and-saves-lives/mac-20539443">hepatic artery infusion pump (HAIP)</a> chemotherapy is an option for some.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WWYe1mON_-w">Watch: Dr. Katherine Poruk explains hepatic artery infusion pump therapy</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe id="videoidWWYe1mONw"  title="Dr. Katherine Poruk - Hepatic artery infusion pump for colorectal liver metastases" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/WWYe1mON_-w?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites with Dr. Poruk are available in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Name super/CG: Katherine Poruk, M.D./Surgical Oncology/Mayo Clinic</strong>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What is HAIP therapy?</h2>



<p>HAIP therapy targets tumors specifically in the liver, whether they are primary liver cancers or cancers that have spread from other parts of the body, most commonly the colon. The process begins with the surgical implantation of a small pump under the skin, typically in the abdomen.</p>



<p>This pump acts as a reservoir for chemotherapy, which is delivered directly to the liver through a catheter placed in the hepatic artery — the main artery supplying blood to the liver.&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-style-center-align-caption"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="960" height="540" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Hepatic-artery-infusion-pump-HAIP-16-x-9.jpg" alt="Hepatic artery infusion pump therapy - HAIP medical illustration" class="wp-image-395715" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Hepatic-artery-infusion-pump-HAIP-16-x-9.jpg 960w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Hepatic-artery-infusion-pump-HAIP-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Hepatic-artery-infusion-pump-HAIP-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Medical illustration showing placement of hepatic artery infusion pump </figcaption></figure>



<p>"The benefit of HAIP therapy is that it provides a very high dose directly to the liver, allows the chemotherapy to stay there, and can prevent some of the systemic therapy side effects that patients often experience," explains Dr. Poruk.</p>



<p>This method allows for much higher doses of chemotherapy than standard treatments. The liver receives the full force of the medication, while the rest of the body avoids common&nbsp;</p>



<p>chemotherapy side effects such as nausea, vomiting and fatigue.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Who benefits from HAIP therapy?</h2>



<p>"Patients who have liver metastases from a colorectal tumor that are not amenable to surgery or other local therapies, we find that these patients would benefit from pump therapy, as it can help to downstage the tumors and potentially treat them. And this is true whether or not they're responding to systemic chemotherapy," says Dr. Poruk.</p>



<p></p>



<p>Patients who have already undergone surgery to remove liver tumors also may benefit from HAIP. In these cases, HAIP is used after surgery to deliver chemotherapy directly to the liver, reducing the risk of cancer coming back. It also can help patients who haven't responded well to traditional chemotherapy.</p>



<p>"HAIP therapy does not close any doors, but can potentially open new avenues of treatment," she says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What to expect during the procedure</h2>



<p>HAIP is a surgical procedure that many patients find manageable, says Dr. Poruk. During surgery, a small pump, roughly the size of a hockey puck, is implanted under the skin, usually on the right side of the abdomen. The surgeon makes an incision, locates the hepatic artery, and inserts a catheter that connects the pump to the artery. This operation can be done either open or minimally invasive, depending on the patient.&nbsp;&nbsp;Once in place, the pump continuously delivers chemotherapy directly to the liver, where it can attack cancer cells more aggressively.</p>



<p>The pump remains in the body as long as chemotherapy is needed, typically for at least six months. After treatment is completed, the pump can be removed, although many patients continue with it if there is evidence of disease.</p>



<p>"The pump is very discreet under clothing, and most patients can wear clothes normally without anyone knowing they have it," explains Dr. Poruk.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Improving quality of life</h2>



<p>One of the most significant advantages of HAIP is its improvement in quality of life for patients compared to traditional chemotherapy. While chemotherapy affects the entire body, HAIP localizes treatment to the liver.</p>



<p>"Patients who undergo HAIP therapy are often very happy with their results and are surprised at the ease of surgery and how well they feel despite undergoing high doses of chemotherapy," she says.</p>



<p>Less side effects means patients can often maintain their daily routines with fewer interruptions.</p>



<p>The goal of HAIP, says Dr. Poruk, is not just to manage cancer but to potentially lead to a cure. Patients who were previously not candidates for surgery may find their tumors shrinking enough to be surgically removed, giving them a chance at long-term remission or even cure.</p>



<p>"This can help shrink the tumors and allow patients to undergo either curative surgery or potentially even a liver transplant," she says.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/hepatic-artery-infusion-pump-therapy-for-colorectal-liver-metastases/">Hepatic artery infusion pump therapy for colorectal liver metastases</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/HAIP-location-Mayo-Clinic-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Hepatic-artery-infusion-pump-HAIP-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[colorectal cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Katherine Poruk]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Magnifying U.S. gastrointestinal disease mortality reveals health disparities</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/magnifying-u-s-gastrointestinal-disease-mortality-reveals-health-disparities/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alison Satake]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Translational Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Wafa Aldhaleei]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=394913</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Diseases affecting the digestive system, including the upper gastrointestinal (GI) tract, chronic liver disease, cirrhosis, inflammatory bowel disease and others, are significant causes of death worldwide. Mayo Clinic and North Dakota State University researchers recently delved into demographic data at the national, state and county level in the U.S. to see which populations are most [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/magnifying-u-s-gastrointestinal-disease-mortality-reveals-health-disparities/">Magnifying U.S. gastrointestinal disease mortality reveals health disparities</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/AIAN-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="U.S. map with color-coded county data depicting digestive disease mortality rate per 100,000 American Indian and Alaska Natives in 2019." class="wp-image-394914" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/AIAN-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/AIAN-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/AIAN-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/AIAN-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/AIAN-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">U.S. map depicting digestive disease mortality rate per 100,000 American Indian and Alaska Natives in 2019.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Diseases affecting the digestive system, including the upper gastrointestinal (GI) tract, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/liver-problems/symptoms-causes/syc-20374502" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chronic liver disease</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cirrhosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20351487" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cirrhosis</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/inflammatory-bowel-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353315" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">inflammatory bowel disease</a> and others, are significant causes of death worldwide. Mayo Clinic and North Dakota State University researchers recently delved into demographic data at the national, state and county level in the U.S. to see which populations are most affected by digestive diseases mortality. They found a significant upward trend in these deaths among Native populations whose race and ethnicity are designated as "American Indian and Alaska Native" in research, in several regions.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="819" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Aldhaleei-Wafa_30293053_20240701-819x1024.jpg" alt="Image of Wafa Aldhaleei, M.D., M.P.H." class="wp-image-394916" style="width:200px" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Aldhaleei-Wafa_30293053_20240701-819x1024.jpg 819w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Aldhaleei-Wafa_30293053_20240701-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Aldhaleei-Wafa_30293053_20240701-768x960.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Aldhaleei-Wafa_30293053_20240701.jpg 900w" sizes="(max-width: 819px) 100vw, 819px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Wafa Aldhaleei, M.D., M.P.H.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Our findings revealed that Native people experienced the highest mortality rates from diseases affecting the digestive system, particularly among females, which highlights a critical health disparity. This suggests that we need to address regional health inequalities through healthcare access and disease prevention programs," says Mayo Clinic Advanced Motility Fellow Wafa Aldhaleei, M.D., M.P.H., first author of the study, which was published in the journal <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1542356524007687?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Clinical Gastroenterology and Hepatology</a>.</p>



<p>Her research team examined health data from 3,110 U.S. counties and identified 10 counties with the highest prevalence of digestive disease mortality. The 10 counties were Minnehaha County, South Dakota; Cascade County, Montana; Bannock County, Idaho; Gila County, Arizona; Fremont County, Wyoming; La Paz County/Yuma County, Arizona; Oglala Lakota County, South Dakota; Rio Arriba County, New Mexico; Hennepin County, Minnesota; and Woodbury County, Iowa.</p>



<p>They also specifically investigated the digestive diseases mortality rate by race and ethnicity — white, Black, Latino, American Indian and Alaska Native and Asian and Pacific Islander populations — as well as by sex.</p>



<p>Within the 10 counties with the highest digestive disease mortality rate, American Indian and Alaska Native people were affected the most.</p>



<p>Native populations can face barriers such as access to gastrointestinal specialty care and preventive vaccine programs, write the researchers.</p>



<p>"Deep-rooted, systemic racism can affect the design of health policies for certain areas and populations, and that affects health," Dr. Aldhaleei says. "Throughout the world, poverty, food insecurity, lack of access to clean water, environmental exposures, vaccine hesitancy, lack of insurance and healthcare access, as well as personal risk factors such as excess body weight, alcohol and substance use disorders can influence the gut microbiome."</p>



<p>The researchers conducted statistical analyses on data spanning 2000-2019 from the <a href="https://www.healthdata.org/research-analysis/gbd" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Global Burden of Disease study</a>. This study encompassed 10 non-cancerous digestive disease categories: cirrhosis and other chronic liver diseases; gallbladder and biliary diseases; pancreatitis; upper digestive system diseases; paralytic ileus and intestinal obstruction; inguinal, femoral and abdominal hernia; inflammatory bowel disease; vascular intestinal disorders; appendicitis and other digestive diseases. The results from this first detailed examination of digestive diseases mortality across race, ethnicity, geography and sex were striking.</p>



<p>"Although the overall national digestive diseases mortality rate has declined, when we look closer, we can see that Native people, as well as white women, had an increased risk of mortality from digestive diseases," Dr. Aldhaleei says. All other races and ethnicities saw fewer deaths from these diseases across the study period.</p>



<p>Additionally, among the states, West Virginia had the highest mortality rate from GI disease in 2019 in the nation.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="640" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Bhagavathula-Akshaya_30365630_20240603.jpg" alt="Image of Akshaya Bhagavathula, Ph.D." class="wp-image-394917" style="width:200px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Bhagavathula-Akshaya_30365630_20240603.jpg 640w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Bhagavathula-Akshaya_30365630_20240603-240x300.jpg 240w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Akshaya Bhagavathula, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"This research has the potential to inform public health strategies and policy development to reduce these disparities, particularly among Native populations, and to promote health equity across the U.S.," says lead and corresponding author Akshaya Bhagavathula, Ph.D., who is a research collaborator at Mayo Clinic in Florida.</p>



<p>The researchers advocate for targeted interventions to reduce the health disparities revealed by their analyses. They support future research to explore the complex interplay of factors contributing to these disparities, including socioeconomic status, cultural barriers and healthcare access. According to the researchers, developing sustainable solutions will require collaboration between researchers, healthcare providers, policymakers and community organizations that promote equitable digestive health outcomes and gastrointestinal health equity for all populations.</p>



<p>Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1542356524007687?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/magnifying-u-s-gastrointestinal-disease-mortality-reveals-health-disparities/">Magnifying U.S. gastrointestinal disease mortality reveals health disparities</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/AIAN-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/AIAN-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Wafa Aldhaleei]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why exercise is essential after bariatric surgery</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/why-exercise-is-essential-after-bariatric-surgery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Melinda Hahm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=392958</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Bariatric surgery is more than just surgery. It's a lifestyle change that includes a lifelong commitment to eating healthy with your dietitian's guidance and incorporating regular exercise into your routine. After bariatric surgery, patients who regularly exercise for 60 minutes six days a week lose weight more quickly and dramatically improve their capacity for exercise. Take advantage of peak weight-loss [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/why-exercise-is-essential-after-bariatric-surgery/">Why exercise is essential after bariatric surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/person-in-gym-in-plank-position16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-392961" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/person-in-gym-in-plank-position16x9.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/person-in-gym-in-plank-position16x9-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/thinking-about-weight-loss-surgery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bariatric surgery</a> is more than just surgery. It's a lifestyle change that includes a lifelong <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/establishing-healthy-behaviors-that-stick" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">commitment to eating healthy</a> with your dietitian's guidance and incorporating <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/the-5-elements-of-fitness" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">regular exercise</a> into your routine.</p>



<p>After bariatric surgery, patients who regularly exercise for 60 minutes six days a week lose weight more quickly and dramatically improve their capacity for exercise.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Take advantage of peak weight-loss period</h2>



<p>The time to <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/doctors-orders/need-to-exercise-start-slowly" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">establish your exercise habits</a> is before you have the surgery. Then solidify that routine during the first year after surgery, which is when people typically find it easiest to lose weight.</p>



<p>After bariatric surgery, your body may try to hold onto its fat stores until its other energy sources are depleted. This can lead to the loss of muscle mass after surgery. To minimize or prevent the body from using muscle mass for energy, it's crucial to work your muscles regularly.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Some of the benefits of cardio, strength and endurance training are:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Improved heart condition, balance, stability and mood</li>



<li>Increased energy, lean muscle mass and bone density</li>



<li>Reduced body fat, risk of injury and stress</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Amp up, change your exercise routine</h2>



<p>When people lose weight, their energy expenditure — the number of calories the body burns — is reduced both at rest and during exercise. This means that when you lose weight, but continue the same exercise routine, you burn fewer calories than before you lost weight.</p>



<p>In addition, regular exercise increases your capacity and ability to work harder. As you become better conditioned, your workout will feel easier than when you first began. This is an indication that it's time to increase the exercise intensity.</p>



<p>You want to aim for a level of cardiorespiratory exercise that's somewhat difficult for you. One test of intensity is if you can talk in breathy sentences as you exercise. If you can't speak, scale back until you can.</p>



<p>Consider changing your exercise routine by <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/prevent-boredom-and-injury-during-physical-activity" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">trying something new</a>. If you feel comfortable with your treadmill workout, try switching to another piece of equipment, such as an elliptical or cycle. Or take a class such as low-impact aerobics, spinning, <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/aquatic-exercise-healthy-easy-on-the-body" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">water fitness</a> or aerobic dance.</p>



<p>These tweaks to your routine can challenge your body in new ways and help maintain your interest in exercising. Workout variety also plays a significant role five to six months after bariatric surgery, when many patients experience a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/why-has-my-weight-plateaued-when-i-have-50-more-pounds-to-lose" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">weight-loss plateau</a>. Changing your exercise routine can minimize or even eliminate a plateau.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Increase exercise intensity, time, frequency</h2>



<p>As your fitness improves, you'll be able to increase the intensity, time or frequency of your exercise routine. One way to do that is through <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/interval-training-for-heart-health" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">high-intensity interval training (HIIT)</a>. As with any new form of exercise, check with your healthcare team to make sure HIIT is a good fit for you.</p>



<p>A HIIT workout alternates between short intense bursts of exercise and active recovery, which is like a "breather" with less intense exercise. Research shows that HIIT workouts are more effective for heart health, fat loss and strength gain than traditional cardio and strength training. HIIT can be incorporated into nearly any exercise from running to water fitness.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Pay attention to strength training</h2>



<p>As you plan your routine, focus on <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/no-matter-your-age-or-skill-level-its-never-too-late-to-start-weight-training" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">muscle-strengthening exercises</a> at least three days a week, which will also improve your bone density and metabolism. Muscle burns calories even at rest, so if you increase your muscle mass, you will burn more calories throughout the day.</p>



<p>You can build muscle strength using weight machines, resistance bands, free weights and <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/isometric-exercise-and-blood-pressure" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">your own body weight</a>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A new lifestyle, not a chore</h2>



<p>You've undergone bariatric surgery not only to lose weight but also to improve your health. Reaching your goals requires changing your lifestyle, and exercise is essential to that success. Becoming a regular exerciser can be empowering, fun and open doors to meeting new people and broadening your interests.</p>



<p>To keep exercise from becoming a chore, find what you like to do, but switch it up to add variety and challenge your body in different ways. Cardio and strength training are both key to a successful exercise and weight-loss routine.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Next steps:</h2>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Find <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/bariatric-surgery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bariatric surgery</a> resources.</li>



<li>Explore the option of a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/athletic-or-personal-trainer-best-fit" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">personal or athletic trainer</a>.</li>
</ul>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/melinda-hahm" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Melinda Hahm</em></a><em> is a clinical exercise physiologist in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/bariatric-surgery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bariatric Surgery</a> and a cardiac rehab tech in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/cardiology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cardiology</a> in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/eau-claire" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Eau Claire</a>, Wisconsin.</em></p>



<p>This article first appeared on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/exercise-and-bariatric-surgery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/why-exercise-is-essential-after-bariatric-surgery/">Why exercise is essential after bariatric surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/person-in-gym-in-plank-position1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/person-in-gym-in-plank-position16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Melinda Hahm]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Expert alert: Keep your gut healthy and avoid inflammatory disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/expert-alert-keep-your-gut-healthy-and-avoid-inflammatory-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rhoda Madson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 13:30:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=392250</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A healthy gut helps lower your risk of developing inflammatory diseases such as inflammatory bowel disease (IBD), a chronic condition that causes inflammation in the digestive tract. Victor Chedid, M.D., a gastroenterologist and IBD expert at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, offers tips people can take to keep their gut healthy and inflammatory [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/expert-alert-keep-your-gut-healthy-and-avoid-inflammatory-disease/">Expert alert: Keep your gut healthy and avoid inflammatory disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/08/a-young-sad-looking-woman-lying-on-a-couch-holding-her-stomach-as-if-she-has-a-tummy-ache-maybe-cramps-from-her-monthly-period-menstrual-cycle-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a young, sad looking woman lying on a couch holding her stomach as if she has a tummy ache, maybe cramps from her monthly period, menstrual cycle" class="wp-image-169176" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/08/a-young-sad-looking-woman-lying-on-a-couch-holding-her-stomach-as-if-she-has-a-tummy-ache-maybe-cramps-from-her-monthly-period-menstrual-cycle-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/08/a-young-sad-looking-woman-lying-on-a-couch-holding-her-stomach-as-if-she-has-a-tummy-ache-maybe-cramps-from-her-monthly-period-menstrual-cycle-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/08/a-young-sad-looking-woman-lying-on-a-couch-holding-her-stomach-as-if-she-has-a-tummy-ache-maybe-cramps-from-her-monthly-period-menstrual-cycle-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A healthy gut helps lower your risk of developing inflammatory diseases such as inflammatory bowel disease (IBD), a chronic condition that causes inflammation in the digestive tract. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/chedid-victor-g-m-d-m-s/bio-20478657" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Victor Chedid, M.D.</a>, a gastroenterologist and IBD expert at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, offers tips people can take to keep their gut healthy and inflammatory diseases at bay.</p>



<p>Dr. Chedid recommends a four-pronged approach to gut health:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Nutrition: Try to eat a well-balanced <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/mediterranean-diet/art-20047801" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mediterranean-style</a> diet that includes plenty of vegetables, fruits, whole grains, beans, nuts and seeds, and olive oil. Dr. Chedid recommends eating 30 to 40 grams of fiber daily. Dr. Chedid says this type of diet has a lot of antioxidants and fewer foods that cause inflammation.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Exercise/healthy lifestyle: Aim to incorporate regular exercise into your routine. The type of exercise can vary by person.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Mental health: It's important to maintain your mental health and well-being, given the many interactions between the gut and the brain. For example, people who have been through childhood trauma or who have many other stressors in their lives may experience gastrointestinal symptoms or conditions, including irritable bowel syndrome, functional dyspepsia, pelvic floor dysfunction or constipation.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Water intake: Aim to drink 64 ounces of water daily. This helps prevent constipation and ensures your organs are well nourished. It is particularly important in hot climates, where dehydration can be an issue.</li>
</ul>



<p>"Paying attention to all these factors is essential for maintaining gut health," Dr. Chedid says.</p>



<p>Maintaining gut health is important, especially when a person is dealing with inflammatory bowel disease. There are two main types of IBD:&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/crohns-disease/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20353309?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Crohn's disease</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/ulcerative-colitis/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20353331?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ulcerative colitis</a>.</p>



<p>IBD is a <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/jgh.14872#:~:text=Traditionally%2C%20IBD%20has%20been%20regarded%20as%20a%20disease,which%20have%20more%20than%20one%20billion%20inhabitants%202." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">global</a> disease with about 6-8 million cases <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/langas/article/PIIS2468-1253(19)30333-4/fulltext#:~:text=In%202017%2C%20there%20were%206%C2%B78%20million,%2895%25%20UI%206%C2%B74%E2%80%937%C2%B73%29%20cases%20of%20IBD%20globally." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">worldwide</a>. The prevalence of Crohn's disease and ulcerative colitis is on the <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7684461/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">rise</a> in African countries, the Middle East and the Asia Pacific region.</p>



<p>"That's why we have to increase awareness and make sure that people seek care when they have symptoms so that they can get the diagnosis and care that is appropriate for them," Dr. Chedid says.</p>



<p>There is no cure for IBD, but a variety of treatments exist to help patients achieve remission. These include anti-inflammatory drugs, immune system suppressors, biologics, antibiotics and surgery.</p>



<p>Diarrhea and rectal bleeding are common symptoms, but these symptoms can make people with IBD feel ashamed and hesitant to seek support. Dr. Chedid says families can play a crucial role in helping their loved ones manage IBD.</p>



<p>"It's about being there for them, recognizing that they're not always going to be themselves at all times," Dr. Chedid says. "There will be times when they feel down, are in pain or don't want to eat what you cook. Don't be offended. You just need to be there for them."</p>



<p>###<strong></strong></p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Rhoda Madson, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/expert-alert-keep-your-gut-healthy-and-avoid-inflammatory-disease/">Expert alert: Keep your gut healthy and avoid inflammatory disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/08/a-young-sad-looking-woman-lying-on-a-couch-holding-her-stomach-as-if-she-has-a-tummy-ache-maybe-cramps-from-her-monthly-period-menstrual-cycle-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/08/a-young-sad-looking-woman-lying-on-a-couch-holding-her-stomach-as-if-she-has-a-tummy-ache-maybe-cramps-from-her-monthly-period-menstrual-cycle-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Thriving, not just surviving, after bariatric surgery</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/thriving-not-just-surviving-after-bariatric-surgery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Kathriena Greenwell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=389781</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A trip to Disney World in 2023 was an eye-opener for Katie Crow. It wasn't the rides, parades or immersive activities that caught her attention but that she struggled to have the energy to go to the amusement park every day. "It wasn't the experience I wanted it to be. That's when I knew I [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/thriving-not-just-surviving-after-bariatric-surgery/">Thriving, not just surviving, after bariatric surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/katie-crow16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-389784" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/katie-crow16x9.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/katie-crow16x9-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></figure>



<p>A trip to Disney World in 2023 was an eye-opener for Katie Crow. It wasn't the rides, parades or immersive activities that caught her attention but that she struggled to have the energy to go to the amusement park every day.</p>



<p>"It wasn't the experience I wanted it to be. That's when I knew I finally needed to do something about my weight," says Katie, an endoscopy nurse with Mayo Clinic Health System in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/la-crosse" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">La Crosse</a>, Wisconsin.</p>



<p>That summer, the 36-year-old saw her weight reach 296 pounds. Katie suffered from leg and back pain, had been diagnosed with severe <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/do-i-have-sleep-apnea" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">sleep apnea</a>, and her energy was at an all-time low. She also worried about developing diabetes and heart disease, which run in her family. Since 2019, she also had been coping with anxiety and depression.</p>



<p>"The worst part was I couldn't keep up with my kids," says Katie, the mother of three children, now ages 15, 13 and 3. "I was just surviving."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Exploring the options</h2>



<p>No stranger to battling her weight, Katie had tried a slew of diets, but none were successful. In the spring of 2023, her primary care provider referred her to the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/la-crosse/services-and-treatments/bariatric-surgery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bariatric Surgery Department</a> at Mayo Clinic Health System in La Crosse. There she learned about her options, which included <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/whats-the-skinny-on-weight-loss-drugs" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">weight-loss drugs</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/thinking-about-weight-loss-surgery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bariatric surgery</a>.</p>



<p>"I considered the weight-loss drugs, but at the time, some hadn't been approved yet, and given the side effects, they didn't seem like an option for me," says Katie. "But the statistics showing the success of bariatric surgery sounded promising."</p>



<p>Katie hadn't decided on her next steps, and then came the Disney World trip. The trip turned out to be the push she needed to finalize her decision to proceed with surgery, even though she was nervous about the permanent nature of the procedure.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Choosing weight-loss surgery</h2>



<p>With the decision made, Katie started her bariatric surgery journey, which included various consultations, a psychological examination and a two-week pre-op diet to prepare her body for the surgery. She also met with <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/kathriena-greenwell-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kathriena Greenwell, M.D.</a>, who would perform the surgery.</p>



<p>"Dr. Greenwell took the time to answer all my questions and thoroughly explain the risks and benefits," says Katie.</p>



<p>"Katie was an excellent candidate for surgery. Since the surgery, she's been very motivated in her weight-loss goals, dedicated to the weight-management program and is taking her lifestyle changes seriously," says Dr. Greenwell.</p>



<p>In December 2023, Katie underwent surgery. While her body healed, she was on a restricted diet for six weeks.</p>



<p>"I thought I'd never eat real food again," says Katie. "But I'd made the commitment and was determined to make it work."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="325" height="400" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/katie-crow-before-and-after.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-389786" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/katie-crow-before-and-after.jpg 325w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/katie-crow-before-and-after-244x300.jpg 244w" sizes="(max-width: 325px) 100vw, 325px" /></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Making lifestyle changes</h2>



<p>When she made her choice, Katie knew that this was a lifelong commitment. She decided to track her experience on social media, posting about the ups and downs of her weight loss and the changes she was making. The most noticeable was the pounds she was shedding. In five months, Katie lost 109 pounds and 84 inches off her body. She'd dropped from size 3X to large.</p>



<p>There were other changes, as well. Dr. Greenwell says Katie's&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/obesity/symptoms-causes/syc-20375742" target="_blank">body mass index, or BMI</a>, has decreased from 49.26 to 31, and she no longer is considered morbidly obese. Dr. Greenwell also noted that Katie has stopped experiencing gastric reflux and anticipates that as she loses more weight, she won't require a continuous positive airway pressure, or CPAP, machine to treat her sleep apnea.</p>



<p>"Hopefully, by losing weight now while she's young, it will prevent her from developing the complications of obesity, including diabetes, heart disease and hypertension," says Dr. Greenwell.</p>



<p>Katie also has seen other personal victories beyond the numbers on the scale. Her leg and back pain are gone, she doesn't worry if a chair will hold her when she sits down, and she delights in shopping for clothes wherever she wants. Her anxiety and depression also have subsided.</p>



<p>"I have more energy than before," says Katie. "My goal is to get down to 150 pounds, but based on the way I feel now, I'd be happy staying at this weight. Bariatric surgery is a tool, but you still have to do the work every day. It requires mental toughness and dedication; I didn't realize how challenging it would be mentally."</p>



<p>For those considering weight-loss surgery, Katie advises researching the process and understanding the commitment you'll be making.</p>



<p>"Going in, you know that you're going to be on vitamins and supplements forever, you won't be able to tolerate certain foods, you need to monitor your protein and hydration, and you have to become a regular exerciser," says Katie. "But ultimately, you have to look at the bigger picture.</p>



<p>"I'm no longer just surviving; I'm thriving. I've become the mom I always dreamt of being," she says. "My only regret is that I didn't do this sooner."</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/patient-stories/thriving-thanks-to-weight-loss" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/thriving-not-just-surviving-after-bariatric-surgery/">Thriving, not just surviving, after bariatric surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/katie-crow1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/katie-crow16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Kathriena Greenwell]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>IBD Pride Clinic: Belonging while battling bowel disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ibd-pride-clinic-belonging-while-battling-bowel-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=389677</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Dealing with chronic conditions like Crohn's disease and ulcerative colitis can be challenging and sometimes embarrassing. Inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) can cause diarrhea, stomach pain, weight loss and other symptoms. Also, the intersectionality of LGBTQ+ identity and having a chronic illness like IBD can sometimes make it difficult for patients to discuss their symptoms with [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ibd-pride-clinic-belonging-while-battling-bowel-disease/">IBD Pride Clinic: Belonging while battling bowel disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Dealing with chronic conditions like Crohn's disease and ulcerative colitis can be challenging and sometimes embarrassing. <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-inflammatory-bowel-disease/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Inflammatory bowel disease (IBD)</a> can cause diarrhea, stomach pain, weight loss and other symptoms. Also, the intersectionality of LGBTQ+ identity and having a chronic illness like IBD can sometimes make it difficult for patients to discuss their symptoms with healthcare professionals.</p>



<p>In July 2022, Mayo Clinic in Rochester was one of the first in the nation to open an <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/vid-20555152" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">IBD Pride Clinic</a>. The clinic aims to create an affirming space for LGBTQ+ patients to talk about their specific healthcare concerns.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/w_OdhIiiB40" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: IBD Pride Clinic: Belonging while battling bowel disease</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubewOdhIiiB40"  title="IBD Pride Clinic: Belonging while battling bowel disease" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/w_OdhIiiB40?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (2:58) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/SCRIPT-IBD-Pride-Clinic.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/ani-2-768x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-389743" style="width:717px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/ani-2-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/ani-2-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/ani-2-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/ani-2-1536x2048.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> IBD patient Ani Roy in the early years of his diagnosis</figcaption></figure>



<p>Twenty-seven-year-old Ani Roy, a patient, Mayo Clinic staff member and transmasculine nonbinary person, says the IBD Pride Clinic is a place of comfort.</p>



<p>Ani doesn't take eating for granted. They were diagnosed with Crohn's disease in 2017 after experiencing painful stomach aches and, at times, being unable to eat.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>It was difficult to digest foods</strong></h3>



<p>"The only thing that I was really able to eat was chicken strips and raspberry iced tea. For some reason, those were the only things that didn't make me want to vomit," explains Ani.</p>



<p>Inflammatory bowel disease took a toll on Ani's body, causing frequent trips to the toilet with bloody diarrhea and other symptoms.</p>



<p>"It got to the point where I was starting to pass out," they say. "I was shaking and just, like, sweating, feeling very faint and wasn't really able to function as a human being."</p>



<p>After several hospitalizations and failed medications, Ani had their colon and rectum removed, leaving them with an <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/in-depth/ostomy/art-20045825">ileostomy</a>. The surgical procedure creates an opening in the stomach to divert stool. Waste is collected in an ostomy bag that's attached to the abdomen," says Ani.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Crohn's disease is mentally and physically challenging</strong></h3>



<p>"It is a very big mental adjustment," they say.</p>



<p>With the stigma surrounding the ileostomy and their gender identity and sexual orientation, Ani reached out to the Mayo Clinic IBD Pride Clinic for support.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Ani-and-chedid-2-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-389699" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Ani-and-chedid-2-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Ani-and-chedid-2-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Ani-and-chedid-2-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Ani-and-chedid-2-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Ani-and-chedid-2.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Patient Ani Roy talks with Dr. Victor Chedid.</figcaption></figure>



<p>"Many LGBTQ+ patients suffer in silence," says Dr. Victor Chedid, director of the Mayo Clinic IBD Pride Clinic.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"They might be struggling with their identity internally. And add to it the fact that you're struggling with your diagnosis of inflammatory bowel disease, that has a double or additional psychological impact on you," says Dr. Chedid.</p>



<p>"It's so nice to go to a provider that is informed about the LGBTQ+ community so that I don't feel like I have to educate them on that part of me. I can just be that part of me," says Ani.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Healing and Hope</strong></h3>



<p>The IBD Pride Clinic is staffed by healthcare professionals who are trained to be sensitive in the care of LGBTQ+ patients.</p>



<p>"This is a safe space for you to talk to us about your inflammatory bowel disease and anything that might be impacting your life," says Dr. Chedid.</p>



<p>Meanwhile, Ani is turning their pain into purpose, sewing ostomy bag covers for themselves and others. Living life one day — and one stitch — at a time.</p>



<p>"Overall, I'm doing pretty well, living life as best as I can," says Ani.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ibd-pride-clinic-belonging-while-battling-bowel-disease/">IBD Pride Clinic: Belonging while battling bowel disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/Two-men-sitting-in-grass-LGBTQ-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/Men-holding-hands-LGBTQ-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>&#8216;I&#8217;m so happy we&#8217;re here:&#8217; An unexpected diagnosis saves Rich Bugay&#8217;s life</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/im-so-happy-were-here-an-unexpected-diagnosis-saves-rich-bugays-life/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[meganlakatos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 13:55:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiology Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Charles Jain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Gabor Bagameri]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Houssam Halawi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rich Bugay]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=388591</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Rich Bugay had an appointment with the Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota, on a Monday, where he had hoped to get answers and relief for what he thought was refractory acid reflux — until his doctor discovered a heart murmur. The next morning, Rich was told he had congenital [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/im-so-happy-were-here-an-unexpected-diagnosis-saves-rich-bugays-life/">&#8216;I&#8217;m so happy we&#8217;re here:&#8217; An unexpected diagnosis saves Rich Bugay&#8217;s life</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill3-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-388597" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill3-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill3-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill3-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill3-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill3-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Rich Bugay had an appointment with the </strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/gastroenterology-hepatology-digestive-care/home/orc-20348202" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</strong></a><strong> at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota, on a Monday, where he had hoped to get answers and relief for what he thought was refractory <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-healthcare-expert-explains-why-reflux-disease-isnt-just-heartburn/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">acid reflux </a>— until his doctor discovered a heart murmur. The next morning, Rich was told he had congenital heart disease and a severely dilated aorta that could rupture. Just two days later, Rich underwent lifesaving heart surgery. After a whirlwind four days, Rich was on the road to recovery.<br>___________________________________________________________________________________</strong></p>



<p>Rich Bugay, an HVAC business owner, husband, and father to two children, hadn't been feeling well for over a year. What started out as sinus issues gradually turned into severe acid reflux and exhaustion, making it hard for Rich to get through the workday.</p>



<p>"I wasn't feeling well — I had a lot of acid reflux and stomach discomfort. I had been going to a lot of different doctor visits, like my family practitioner, and I wasn't getting any answers," says Rich. "And so, at some point, I decided I wanted to go to the best place I could go."</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/sjFvuv-NnHo" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Rich's story</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubesjFvuvNnHo"  title="‘I’m so happy we’re here:’ An unexpected diagnosis saves Rich Bugay’s life" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/sjFvuv-NnHo?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>Rich and his wife, Lori, left their house in Escanaba, Michigan, and drove more than six hours to Mayo Clinic in Rochester for an appointment with Dr. Houssam Halawi, a Mayo Clinic gastroenterologist.</p>



<p>During the appointment, Dr. Halawi listened to Rich's history, concerns and symptoms.</p>



<p>"And what caught my attention was, he had a lot of different symptoms that didn't really belong in the GI (gastrointestinal) world," says Dr. Halawi. "And at that point, in my mind, I was thinking this is not an acid reflux problem."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill1-1x1-1-300x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-388595" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill1-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill1-1x1-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill1-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill1-1x1-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill1-1x1-1.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Halawi listening to Rich's heart</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>When Dr. Halawi listened to Rich's heart, he heard a suspicious murmur. He knew something — potentially big — was going on, and he recommended that Rich receive an urgent <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/echocardiogram/about/pac-20393856#:~:text=An%20echocardiogram%20uses%20sound%20waves%20to%20create%20pictures%20of%20the,disease%20and%20other%20heart%20conditions." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">echocardiogram</a>. An echocardiogram is a common test that uses sound waves to create pictures of the heart to find heart disease and other heart conditions. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Rich was hesitant to have the echocardiogram since he just wanted some relief from his presumed acid reflux and didn't think he had a life-threatening issue.</p>



<p>Knowing that Rich would most likely go home if the echocardiogram couldn't be scheduled quickly, Dr. Halawi asked the scheduling team if there was any way they could arrange the echocardiogram for the next day. When the scheduler asked, "Would tomorrow morning work for you?" Dr. Halawi didn't expect it to be that quick.</p>



<p>Rich and Lori decided to stay at Mayo Clinic for the echocardiogram the next morning.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill2-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-388596" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill2-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill2-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill2-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill2-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill2-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Jain meeting with Rich</figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Confirming suspicions</h2>



<p>Kylie Marvin, the sonographer who performed the echocardiogram, immediately noticed something was seriously wrong. She walked out into the hallway and informed <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/jain-c-charles-m-d/bio-20543120" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Charles Jain</a>, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist, about her findings.</p>



<p>"His aorta was severely dilated, well over what we would traditionally consider as the surgical cutoff for elective intervention," says Dr. Jain.</p>



<p>A severely enlarged aorta — the pipe that delivers blood out of the heart — could have acute complications, such as a rupture, which can be life-threatening.</p>



<p>The echocardiogram also showed that Rich had a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/bicuspid-aortic-valve/cdc-20385577" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bicuspid aortic valve</a>.</p>



<p>The aortic valve usually has three cusps. A bicuspid valve has only two cusps. Rich's bicuspid valve wasn't closing tightly, which was causing blood to flow backward.</p>



<p>Dr. Jain called a radiologist and arranged an urgent <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ct-scan/about/pac-20393675" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CT scan</a> for Rich that same day. The results of the CT scan confirmed the findings, and Dr. Jain called <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/bagameri-gabor-m-d/bio-20384030" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Gabor Bagameri,</a> a Mayo Clinic cardiovascular surgeon, who was willing to make room in his schedule to quickly see Rich and arrange for surgery.</p>



<p>"At Mayo Clinic, the needs of the patient always come first, and even in the middle of the night, 24/7, you can always reach for help," says Dr. Bagameri.</p>



<p>He encouraged Rich that his heart problems were fixable and advised him not to wait to undergo surgery.</p>



<p>"He let me think about it and came back into the room about five minutes later and he says, 'OK, so we're going to do this Thursday, right?' I say, 'You know it.' And he says, 'I knew you were going to say that!' So, we were ready," says Rich.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">"Like a well-oiled machine<strong>"</strong></h2>



<p>On the day of the surgery, Rich said everything was very structured and organized. The surgery itself was a success, as was his hospital stay.</p>



<p>"Like a well-oiled machine, everything just went so well, so smoothly," says Lori. "I've never experienced anything like that before, and that's how healthcare should be everywhere. Everyone deserves to be treated like they do here."</p>



<p>Now, nearly six months after his procedure, Rich feels almost 100% better.</p>



<p>"They saved my life," says Rich. "I'm a completely different person — I feel like a million bucks. I can do what I want to do, and my energy levels are much better."</p>



<p>Looking back on the experience, Dr. Halawi recognizes that Rich wouldn't have had such a positive outcome without every single person involved at Mayo Clinic. Dr. Jain echoes that sentiment, "When there are patients who are having a significant abnormality, particularly with urgency, such as Rich's, everything is already set up for teamwork to be natural, and fortunately, this makes it all relatively seamless."</p>



<p>Reflecting on his healthcare journey, Rich says that you need to advocate for yourself.</p>



<p>"If you haven’t been feeling right for a long time and feel like you're not getting answers, come to Mayo Clinic because they'll get to the bottom of it," says Rich.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/im-so-happy-were-here-an-unexpected-diagnosis-saves-rich-bugays-life/">&#8216;I&#8217;m so happy we&#8217;re here:&#8217; An unexpected diagnosis saves Rich Bugay&#8217;s life</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill3-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Bugaystill3-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Charles Jain]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Gabor Bagameri]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Houssam Halawi]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Rich Bugay]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: What is inflammatory bowel disease?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-inflammatory-bowel-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[colitis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Crohn's Disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Victor Chedid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IBD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Inflammatory Bowel Disease]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386624</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) affects an estimated 1.6 million Americans. In fact, there are more than 70,000 new cases of IBD in the United States each year, according to the Crohn's &#38; Colitis Foundation. IBD is a chronic condition that causes inflammation in the digestive tract, but it can also affect other areas of the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-inflammatory-bowel-disease/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What is inflammatory bowel disease?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) affects an estimated 1.6 million Americans. In fact, there are more than 70,000 new cases of IBD in the United States each year, according to the <a href="https://www.crohnscolitisfoundation.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Crohn's &amp; Colitis Foundation.</a></p>



<p>IBD is a chronic condition that causes inflammation in the digestive tract, but it can also affect other areas of the body. Crohn’s and Colitis (both classified as IBD) Awareness Week is observed each year from Dec. 1-7.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/chedid-victor-g-m-d-m-s/bio-20478657?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Victor Chedid</a>, a Mayo Clinic gastroenterologist, explains what IBD is and how symptoms can be managed.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/r8WnDavgSXo" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutuber8WnDavgSXo"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: What is inflammatory bowel disease?" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/r8WnDavgSXo?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:02) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/SCRIPT-jthEDITS_MCM-What-is-IBD.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>People often associate IBD with the bathroom because of its symptoms, but it's a serious and chronic condition. There are two main types of IBD: <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/crohns-disease/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20353309?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Crohn's disease</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/ulcerative-colitis/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20353331?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ulcerative colitis</a>.</p>



<p>"Ulcerative colitis only impacts the colon and causes inflammation in the entire colon, while Crohn's disease can impact anywhere from the mouth to the anus," says Dr. Chedid.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/11/a-young-child-perhaps-a-girl-holding-her-stomach-because-it-aches-and-hurts-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="a young child, perhaps a girl, holding her stomach because it aches and hurts" class="wp-image-324332" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/11/a-young-child-perhaps-a-girl-holding-her-stomach-because-it-aches-and-hurts-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/11/a-young-child-perhaps-a-girl-holding-her-stomach-because-it-aches-and-hurts-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/11/a-young-child-perhaps-a-girl-holding-her-stomach-because-it-aches-and-hurts-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/11/a-young-child-perhaps-a-girl-holding-her-stomach-because-it-aches-and-hurts-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/11/a-young-child-perhaps-a-girl-holding-her-stomach-because-it-aches-and-hurts-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Young girl experiencing stomach pain.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Patients often experience diarrhea, rectal bleeding, fatigue, weight loss, and stomach and joint pain.</p>



<p>"Some patients might develop what we call extraintestinal manifestations of their inflammatory bowel disease. And these can impact other organs. That means organs that are beyond the intestines," explains Dr. Chedid.</p>



<p>There is no cure and no exact cause for IBD, but there are medications to reduce inflammation. Also, watching what you eat can help alleviate some symptoms.</p>



<p>"We have to have a focus on diets that are high in anti-inflammatory foods and antioxidants, and low in foods that are processed that can be proinflammatory," says Dr. Chedid.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Treatments to manage inflammatory bowel disease</h2>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Anti-inflammatory drugs</li>



<li>Immune system suppressors</li>



<li>Biologics</li>



<li>Antibiotics</li>



<li>Nutrition therapy</li>



<li>Surgery</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-do-you-know-the-signs-of-inflammatory-bowel-disease/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Do you know the signs of IBD?</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-treating-crohns-disease-and-ulcerative-colitis/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Treating Crohn's disease and ulcerative colitis.</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-living-with-crohns-disease-and-colitis/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Living with Crohn's disease and colitis.</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-can-diet-help-with-inflammatory-bowel-disease/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Can diet help with inflammatory bowel disease?</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-inflammatory-bowel-disease/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What is inflammatory bowel disease?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/shutterstock_488527312_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/04/a-young-Black-man-sitting-on-a-couch-near-a-pizza-box-looking-in-pain-with-a-stomach-ache-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[colitis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Crohn's Disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Victor Chedid]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[gastroenterology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[IBD]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Inflammatory Bowel Disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: What are gallstones?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-are-gallstones/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 13:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#socialsensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Irving Jorge]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gallbladder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gallbladder surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gallstones]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386042</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Gallstones are hardened deposits of digestive fluid, called bile, in your gallbladder. They range in size from as small as a grain of sand to as large as a golf ball. Dr. Irving Jorge, a Mayo Clinic general surgeon, says people who experience pain and other symptoms from gallstones usually require gallbladder removal surgery. Watch: [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-are-gallstones/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What are gallstones?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/gallstones/symptoms-causes/syc-20354214?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gallstones</a> are hardened deposits of digestive fluid, called bile, in your <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cholecystitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20364867?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gallbladder</a>. They range in size from as small as a grain of sand to as large as a golf ball.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/jorge-irving-a-m-d/bio-20514261?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Irving Jorge</a>, a Mayo Clinic general surgeon, says people who experience pain and other symptoms from gallstones usually require <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/cholecystectomy/about/pac-20384818?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gallbladder removal surgery</a>.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/o5Snl52wSps" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeo5Snl52wSps"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - What are gallstones?" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/o5Snl52wSps?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:08) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/MCM_Gallstones.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>You experience sudden, intense pain in your abdomen or back pain between your shoulder blades — maybe even nausea or vomiting. You could have gallstones.</p>



<p>"Typically, symptoms of gallbladder-related pain is pain associated with meals. Usually after you eat meals with fatty foods," says Dr. Jorge.</p>



<p>He says there are several reasons why your gallbladder can form gallstones. The most common cause is what you eat. A diet high in fiber and low in cholesterol and fat will reduce your risk.</p>



<p>"Native Americans and Hispanic populations have a higher risk of developing gallstones and so do women. And as we get older, we're at higher risk of developing gallstones," says Dr. Jorge.</p>



<p>He says, once you have gallstones, they won't go away on their own. Recommended treatment is surgery to remove your gallbladder.</p>



<p>"It's an organ that people can live without and not have any long-term consequences from," says Dr. Jorge. "We take out the gallbladder not just because it has stones, but it's because it's where most stones are formed. But there is a small percentage of patients that can develop stones within the bile ducts themselves."</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-are-gallstones/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What are gallstones?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Gallstone-Pain-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Gallstone-Pain-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#socialsensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Irving Jorge]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[gallbladder]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[gallbladder surgery]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[gallstones]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[General Surgery]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: How to cope with irritable bowel syndrome</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/4-27-ready-mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-cope-with-irritable-bowel-syndrome/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#socialsensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Brian Lacy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IBS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[irritable bowel syndrome]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=365304</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Irritable bowel syndrome (IBS) can significantly disrupt a person's daily life. Some people suffer in silence because of painful stomach cramps, diarrhea and constipation. These symptoms can significantly affect a person's quality of life. April 19 is World IBS Day, intended to raise awareness about IBS, which affects the stomach and intestines, also called the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/4-27-ready-mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-cope-with-irritable-bowel-syndrome/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How to cope with irritable bowel syndrome</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/irritable-bowel-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20360016?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Irritable bowel syndrome (IBS)</a> can significantly disrupt a person's daily life. Some people suffer in silence because of painful stomach cramps, diarrhea and constipation. These symptoms can significantly affect a person's quality of life.</p>



<p>April 19 is World IBS Day, intended to raise awareness about IBS, which affects the stomach and intestines, also called the gastrointestinal tract.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/7a_bHYW-di0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutube7abHYWdi0"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: How to cope with irritable bowel syndrome" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/7a_bHYW-di0?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:59) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/SCRIPT-MCM-How-to-cope-with-irritable-bowel-syndrome.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"Irritable bowel syndrome is a common disorder in the United States, affecting approximately 10% of U.S. adults," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/lacy-brian-e-m-d-ph-d/bio-20392407?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Brian Lacy</a>, a Mayo Clinic gastroenterologist.</p>



<p>The symptoms of IBS are sometimes embarrassing and can affect a person's physical and emotional well-being.</p>



<p>"Patients have symptoms of disordered defecation. And that, in some patients, means constipation, skipping days without a bowel movement, straining of a bowel movement, or diarrhea, loose, watery urgent bowel movements," says Dr. Lacy.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/a-medical-illustration-of-irritable-bowel-syndrome-16X9.jpg" alt="a medical illustration of irritable bowel syndrome" class="wp-image-241979" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/a-medical-illustration-of-irritable-bowel-syndrome-16X9.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/a-medical-illustration-of-irritable-bowel-syndrome-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></figure></div>


<p>The exact cause of IBS is still unclear, but it's believed to be a combination of factors, including changes in the gut microbiome and food intolerances.</p>



<p>IBS is now categorized as a disorder of gut-brain interaction, which means there is a problem with how the gut and the brain communicate with each other.</p>



<p>"That stress, which can affect the brain, then sends signals to the gut, changing gut function and worsening your IBS symptoms," says Dr. Lacy.</p>



<p>There is no cure for IBS, but symptoms can be managed. Try eating smaller, more frequent meals, and exercising regularly. Deep breathing and yoga are also helpful to reduce stress.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">When to see a doctor for irritable bowel syndrome</h3>



<p>See your healthcare professional if you have significant changes in bowel habits. Some severe symptoms include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Bloody stools.</li>



<li>Unintended weight loss.</li>



<li>Unexplained vomiting.</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/4-27-ready-mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-cope-with-irritable-bowel-syndrome/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How to cope with irritable bowel syndrome</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/11/a-young-child-perhaps-a-girl-holding-her-stomach-because-it-aches-and-hurts-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/03/IBS-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#socialsensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Brian Lacy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[IBS]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[irritable bowel syndrome]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>