<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Health &amp; Wellness - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/health-and-wellness/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/health-and-wellness/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 14:18:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Building a back-to-school routine</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-building-a-back-to-school-routine/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[DeeDee Stiepan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 15:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[back to school]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Back-to-school routine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Stephen Whiteside]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=371538</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>For many kids,&#160;summer is a time to stay up late, sleep in and hang out with friends. Waking up for that first day of a new school year can be a shock if young children, teenagers, parents or caregivers have not come up with a routine. In this Mayo Clinic Minute, Dr. Stephen Whiteside, a [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-building-a-back-to-school-routine/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Building a back-to-school routine</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>For many kids,&nbsp;summer is a time to stay up late, sleep in and hang out with friends. Waking up for that first day of a new school year can be a shock if young children, teenagers, parents or caregivers have not come up with a routine.</p>



<p>In this Mayo Clinic Minute, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/whiteside-stephen-p-ph-d-l-p/bio-20054748?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Stephen Whiteside</a>, a Mayo Clinic child psychologist, offers some tips for getting into a back-to-school routine.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/NcCbjDivMCY" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe id="videoidhttpsyoutubeNcCbjDivMCY"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Building a back-to-school routine" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/NcCbjDivMCY?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:59) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/SCRIPT-MCM-B2S-Routines.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Transitioning from a laid-back summer schedule to the structure of a new school year doesn't have to be a rude awakening. Dr. Whiteside says developing routines for morning,&nbsp;bedtime&nbsp;and any other recurring event can make things run more smoothly at home and at school.</p>



<p>"Routines are a natural part of life and just very straightforward, provide structure, help kids predict and expect what's going to happen," says Dr. Whiteside.</p>



<p>One way to help make the transition a little smoother is to give your family time to ease into the new routine.</p>



<p>"Taking a week or so before school starts to help kids start adjusting to waking up earlier, getting ready and having breakfast as soon as they get up," says Dr. Whiteside.</p>



<p>Dr. Whiteside says parents shouldn't stress if things don't go exactly as planned.</p>



<p>"Kids need to learn that they can handle change. And having a routine is good. Learning that you can handle life not following that routine is equally good," says Dr. Whiteside.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-building-a-back-to-school-routine/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Building a back-to-school routine</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/08/a-group-of-young-elementary-school-children-with-backpacks-getting-on-a-school-bus-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/08/a-group-of-young-elementary-school-children-with-backpacks-getting-on-a-school-bus-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[back to school]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Back-to-school routine]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Stephen Whiteside]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Checkups, screenings are key for men&#8217;s health</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/checkups-screenings-are-key-for-mens-health/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 14:08:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Mohammed Solaiman]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=392674</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Historically, men have been hesitant to seek medical attention when something seems wrong with their health. Also, men aren't as likely as women to have preventive screenings and checkups with their healthcare team. This is a problem because early detection of a medical issue is the best way to treat and manage it effectively. Why [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/checkups-screenings-are-key-for-mens-health/">Checkups, screenings are key for men&#8217;s health</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/MiddleAgedMan16x9-1024x576.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-348257" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/MiddleAgedMan16x9-1024x576.jpeg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/MiddleAgedMan16x9-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/MiddleAgedMan16x9-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/MiddleAgedMan16x9-1536x864.jpeg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/MiddleAgedMan16x9.jpeg 1604w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Historically, men have been hesitant to seek medical attention when something seems wrong with their health. Also, men aren't as likely as women to have preventive screenings and checkups with their healthcare team. This is a problem because early detection of a medical issue is the best way to treat and manage it effectively.</p>



<p>Why should you reconsider your reservations about seeing a healthcare professional? Delaying or avoiding a checkup or screening could lead to a treatable situation turning deadly.</p>



<p>While you should get some screenings, such as HIV and hepatitis C, you should have other screenings for certain conditions and cancers regularly.</p>



<p>Vaccines also are essential to prevent infectious diseases. Vaccinations for men are administered at different intervals throughout adulthood.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Regular physical exams</h2>



<p>Males older than 50 should have a yearly physical exam, and those younger than 50 should have a physical exam every three to five years. Even if you're feeling healthy, a regular checkup with your healthcare team is an excellent way to validate your health or identify a problem in its early stages.</p>



<p>Another thing to think about: Health isn't only physical. <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/trust-primary-care-provider" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Talk to your healthcare team</a> about your mental and emotional health. If you're struggling in those areas, effective help is available.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Screening can identify specific conditions and cancers, including:</h3>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Abdominal aortic aneurysm</h4>



<p>For men between 65 and 75 who have smoked more than 100 cigarettes in their lifetime, the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force recommends a one-time abdominal aortic aneurysm screening ultrasound. An abdominal aortic aneurysm is an enlarged area in the lower part of the aorta, the major blood vessel that supplies blood to the body. Because the aorta is the body's main supplier of blood, a ruptured abdominal aortic aneurysm can cause life-threatening bleeding. Men over 60 with a family history of abdominal aortic aneurysm should consider repeat screening at regular intervals.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Colon cancer</h4>



<p>Colon cancer screening should begin at age 45 or 10 years prior to an age at which an immediate relative was diagnosed with colon cancer. For example, get screened at age 36 if your mother was diagnosed at age 46. A colonoscopy is a traditional, effective procedure to identify colon cancer or precancerous polyps. A more recent noninvasive option available is a&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/stool-dna-test/about/pac-20385153" target="_blank">take-home test to screen for colon cancer</a>.</p>



<p>Talk to your healthcare professional about which option is best for you.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Diabetes</h4>



<p>If you're older than 45 or have a body mass index above 25, no matter your age, the American Diabetes Association recommends that you be screened for diabetes. <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/how-to-live-well-with-diabetes" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Type 2 diabetes</a> and prediabetes symptoms can happen slowly and may not be noticeable, so staying aware of your blood sugar levels and risk of developing diabetes is essential.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">High blood pressure</h4>



<p>A blood pressure reading is a good indication to many aspects of your health. High blood pressure can lead to many physical problems, especially those associated with the heart.</p>



<p>You should have your blood pressure checked at least every two years. However, talk to your healthcare professional about having it checked more frequently if you have <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/know-your-heart-health-numbers" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">high blood pressure</a> or are at risk of developing high blood pressure.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">High cholesterol</h4>



<p>Like high blood pressure, high cholesterol may pose serious risks to your health and well-being. Starting at age 18, men at average risk for heart disease should have a cholesterol screening every five years. If you have a family history of high cholesterol or heart attacks, smoke, eat a poor diet, are overweight, have diabetes, are physically inactive or older than 45, you may need more frequent testing.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Lung cancer</h4>



<p>The U.S. Preventative Services Task Force recommends annual screening for lung cancer with a low-dose CT for adults ages 50 to 80 who have a 20-pack-per-year smoking history, currently smoke or have quit within the past 15 years. Screening can be stopped when a person has not smoked for 15 years or develops a health problem that substantially limits life expectancy.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Prostate cancer</h4>



<p>Many organizations advise men to be screened for prostate cancer starting at age 50. However, the subject is somewhat controversial, so the best course of action is to discuss what's best for you with your healthcare team.</p>



<p>Do yourself and your family a favor by protecting your health with regular checkups and screenings.</p>



<p><em><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/mohammed-solaiman-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mohammed Solaiman, M.D.</a>, is a physician in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/family-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Family Medicine</a> in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/st-peter" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">St. Peter</a>, Minnesota.</em></p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/mens-health-checkups-and-screenings-are-key" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/checkups-screenings-are-key-for-mens-health/">Checkups, screenings are key for men&#8217;s health</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/MiddleAgedMan1x1.jpeg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/MiddleAgedMan16x9.jpeg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Mohammed Solaiman]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Back-to-school essentials: Parent&#8217;s guide for a healthy start to the school year</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/back-to-school-essentials-parents-guide-for-a-healthy-start-to-the-school-year/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[back-to-school]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Christina Andrist]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=392593</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>As the back-to-school season approaches, parents and guardians have much to consider for their children to have a healthy and successful start to the new academic year. From scheduling well-child examinations to planning for proper nutrition and adequate sleep, the list of tasks may feel daunting. Here are back-to-school tips to help you and your [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/back-to-school-essentials-parents-guide-for-a-healthy-start-to-the-school-year/">Back-to-school essentials: Parent&#8217;s guide for a healthy start to the school year</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/two-kids-by-school-lockers16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-392596" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/two-kids-by-school-lockers16x9.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/two-kids-by-school-lockers16x9-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></figure>



<p>As the back-to-school season approaches, parents and guardians have much to consider for their children to have a healthy and successful start to the new academic year. From scheduling well-child examinations to planning for proper nutrition and adequate sleep, the list of tasks may feel daunting.</p>



<p>Here are back-to-school tips to help you and your children prepare.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Well-child examinations</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/schedule-your-childs-back-to-school-physical" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Well-child examinations</a> are a cornerstone of healthcare for children of all ages. These check-ups are essential for monitoring your child's growth and development, catching potential health issues early and ensuring they are physically and mentally prepared for school.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">During a well-child examination, the healthcare team will:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Create a comprehensive medical history, which is crucial for future healthcare needs.</li>



<li>Identify and manage potential health problems before they become more serious.</li>



<li>Monitor and track your child's growth patterns and development.</li>



<li>Update your child's medical history and verify that vaccinations are current.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Vaccinations</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/the-facts-about-vaccinations" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Vaccinations play a critical role</a> in protecting children from various infectious diseases. Illnesses can quickly spread, so ensuring your child is current on vaccinations is vital.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and healthcare professionals recommend these vaccinations:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Diptheria/tetanus/pertussis</li>



<li>Haemophilus influenza B</li>



<li>Hepatitis A</li>



<li>Hepatitis B</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/hpv-immunization-who-can-benefit" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Human papilloma virus</a></li>



<li>Influenza</li>



<li>Meningococcal</li>



<li>MMR</li>



<li>Pneumococcal</li>



<li>Polio</li>



<li>Rotavirus</li>



<li>Varicella (chickenpox)</li>
</ul>



<p>Talk with your healthcare team about vaccines your state requires to attend school.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Nutrition</h2>



<p>A balanced diet is fundamental to a child's physical and cognitive development. Proper nutrition helps children maintain energy levels, concentrate better in school and support overall growth and development. Children require different amounts of nutrients based on their age.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Follow these nutrition tips for your family:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Encourage your child to drink plenty of water to stay hydrated, especially during the warmer months.</li>



<li>Minimize sugary snacks and <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/the-buzz-on-energy-drinks" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">sweetened beverages</a> to help prevent obesity and dental problems.</li>



<li>Offer meals made from fresh foods, including dairy, fruits, protein, vegetables and whole grains.</li>



<li>Provide nutritious snacks like fruits, nuts and yogurt to energize your child throughout the day.</li>



<li>Start every day with breakfast.</li>



<li>Visit <a href="https://www.healthychildren.org/English/healthy-living/nutrition/Pages/Healthy-Active-Living-for-Families.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Healthy Active Living for Families</a> to learn about the 5-2-1-0 rule.</li>
</ul>



<p>Talk with your child's healthcare team if you have questions about your child's nutritional needs.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Sleep</h2>



<p>Adequate sleep is crucial for a child's overall well-being, affecting everything from their mood to their ability to learn and retain information. Children who do not get enough sleep are more likely to experience attention problems, behavioral issues and poor academic performance.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Tips for ensuring adequate sleep include:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Create a consistent bedtime routine to help your child wind down and prepare for sleep.</li>



<li>Encourage your child to get the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/sleep-an-essential-element-of-success-for-children" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">recommended amount of sleep</a> each night, typically eight to 10 hours for school-aged children.</li>



<li>Ensure your child's bedroom is quiet, dark and cool to facilitate restful sleep.</li>



<li>Reduce exposure to screens at least an hour before bedtime to promote better sleep quality and remove screens from the room at bedtime.</li>



<li>Try a red light in the bedroom, which may help release melatonin naturally. Avoid using a blue light.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Bullying</h2>



<p>Bullying is a serious issue that can significantly affect a child's mental and emotional health. It occurs far too often nationwide in elementary, junior high and high schools. Parents and guardians must <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/cyberbullying-tips-to-protect-kids" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">take bullying seriously</a> and teach your children a few tactics to address bullies productively.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Steps to take if bullying occurs:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Ask a teacher or other school officials for help.</li>



<li>Don't fight back and maintain composure.</li>



<li>Say "stop" confidently.</li>



<li>Walk away.</li>
</ul>



<p>It's crucial to offer emotional support and reassurance to your child. If needed, consider professional counseling to help them cope with the effects of bullying.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Creating a positive start to the school year</h2>



<p>Preparing for the new school year involves more than buying school supplies and updating the calendar with activities. It's also about prioritizing your child's health and well-being to ensure their success and happiness.</p>



<p>By scheduling well-child examinations, keeping vaccinations up to date, providing balanced nutrition, ensuring adequate sleep, addressing bullying and modeling these healthy habits yourself, you can help your child have a healthy, productive and successful school year.</p>



<p><em>Christina Andrist, D.O., is a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/pediatrics-and-adolescent-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pediatrician</a> in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/albert-lea" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Albert Lea</a>, Minnesota.</em></p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/back-to-school-essentials-for-parents" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/back-to-school-essentials-parents-guide-for-a-healthy-start-to-the-school-year/">Back-to-school essentials: Parent&#8217;s guide for a healthy start to the school year</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/two-kids-by-school-lockers1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/two-kids-by-school-lockers16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[back-to-school]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Christina Andrist]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Stacking your exercise over the weekend</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-stacking-your-exercise-over-the-weekend/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Osiadacz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 13:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Wesley Troyer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sports injuries]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[weekend warrior]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=351715</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>While the Summer Olympics in Paris are winding down, some weekend warriors might have the itch to get their athletic juices flowing again. Researchers have found that condensing exercise into a few days is as effective as spreading activity out across a week. Dr. Wes Troyer, a Mayo Clinic physical medicine and rehabilitation physician, explains [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-stacking-your-exercise-over-the-weekend/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Stacking your exercise over the weekend</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>While the Summer Olympics in Paris are winding down, some weekend warriors might have the itch to get their athletic juices flowing again.</p>



<p>Researchers have found that condensing <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/troyer-wesley-wes-d-d-o/bio-20509040?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">exercise</a> into a few days is as effective as spreading activity out across a week. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/troyer-wesley-wes-d-d-o/bio-20509040">Dr. Wes Troyer</a>, a Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/physical-medicine-rehabilitation-mayo-clinic/sections/overview/ovc-20467039?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">physical medicine and rehabilitation</a> physician, explains how people who stack their workouts can avoid common injuries and reap the benefits of their activity.</p>



<p><a href="https://youtu.be/MVa2mkwL7dw" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</strong></a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeMVa2mkwL7dw"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Stacking your exercise over the weekend" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/MVa2mkwL7dw?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:57) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post.&nbsp;Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network."&nbsp;Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Script-MCM-Weekend-Warrior-Exercising.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Exercise is key to a healthy lifestyle.</p>



<p>For those on a time crunch, stacking weekly exercise into a couple of days comes with the title "weekend warrior."</p>



<p>“Things like running, jogging, high-intensity workouts, ideally, the more that you can do, the better. People that did this, lowered mortality, lowered cardiovascular events," says Dr. Troyer.</p>



<p>At least <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/fitness/expert-answers/exercise/faq-20057916?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">150 minutes</a> of moderate-intensity exercise or 75 minutes of vigorous activity is recommended for adults each week.</p>



<p>"We don't expect people that have gone from a sedentary activity of not doing anything to jumping into 150 minutes a week. So taking days of break in between, assessing how your body responds to that activity," says Dr. Troyer.</p>



<p>Repeating the same motions or ramping up too quickly could lead to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/fitness/in-depth/overuse-injury/art-20045875?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">overuse injuries</a>, inflammation and pain.</p>



<p>“If you take a couple days off and it's still persistent pain with daily activity — pain that keeps you up at night or keeps you from sleeping — these are all things that we typically recommend people coming in to be evaluated," he says.</p>



<p><strong>Related articles:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-tips-to-avoid-weekend-warrior-athlete-sports-injuries/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Tips to avoid 'weekend warrior athlete' sports injuries</a>"</li>



<li>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-weekend-warrior-exercise-tips/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Weekend warrior exercise tips</a>"</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-stacking-your-exercise-over-the-weekend/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Stacking your exercise over the weekend</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/10/healthy-woman-running-on-street-for-exercise-and-wellness-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/10/healthy-woman-running-on-street-for-exercise-and-wellness-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Wesley Troyer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Exercise]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[sports injuries]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[weekend warrior]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-23/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jaynelle Ramon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 12:25:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=392615</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week. Mayo Clinic Minute: Boost your health and productivity with 'activity snacks' Sitting at a desk for hours at a time may make some feel exhausted and unmotivated. If that's ever happened to you, it may be time [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-23/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C-ajQwAuJXr/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="103023" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/a-woman-celebrating-health-and-weight-loss-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a woman celebrating health and weight loss" class="wp-image-103023" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/a-woman-celebrating-health-and-weight-loss-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/a-woman-celebrating-health-and-weight-loss-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/a-woman-celebrating-health-and-weight-loss-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=511759521523537" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="101712" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/Legionella-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Bacterium Legionella pneumophila on surrealistic space background" class="wp-image-101712" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/Legionella-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/Legionella-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/Legionella-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C-IhxBlA3C4/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="373216" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/Young-girl-back-to-school-vaccination-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Young girl back to school vaccination" class="wp-image-373216" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/Young-girl-back-to-school-vaccination-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/Young-girl-back-to-school-vaccination-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/Young-girl-back-to-school-vaccination-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/Young-girl-back-to-school-vaccination-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/Young-girl-back-to-school-vaccination-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C-S7x50CQNY/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="392431" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Activity-Snack2-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-392431" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Activity-Snack2-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Activity-Snack2-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Activity-Snack2-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Activity-Snack2-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Activity-Snack2-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C-JEDCgyGMg/?img_index=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="169194" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/08/a-man-in-a-kitchen-cutting-tomatoes-and-other-healthy-vegetables-for-a-salad-dish-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a man in a kitchen cutting tomatoes and other healthy vegetables for a salad dish" class="wp-image-169194" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/08/a-man-in-a-kitchen-cutting-tomatoes-and-other-healthy-vegetables-for-a-salad-dish-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/08/a-man-in-a-kitchen-cutting-tomatoes-and-other-healthy-vegetables-for-a-salad-dish-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/08/a-man-in-a-kitchen-cutting-tomatoes-and-other-healthy-vegetables-for-a-salad-dish-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>
</figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week.</h3>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-boost-your-health-and-productivity-with-activity-snacks/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Boost your health and productivity with 'activity snacks'</a></h2>



<p>Sitting at a desk for hours at a time may make some feel exhausted and unmotivated. If that's ever happened to you, it may be time for a snack … an activity snack.⁠<br>⁠<br>Dr. Francisco Lopez-Jimenez, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist, explains the concept of activity snacks and how they can be incorporated into just about anyone's daily routine.⁠</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/expert-alert-keep-your-gut-healthy-and-avoid-inflammatory-disease/">Expert Alert: Keep your gut healthy and avoid inflammatory disease</a></h2>



<p>A healthy gut helps lower your risk of developing inflammatory diseases such as inflammatory bowel disease (IBD), a chronic condition that causes inflammation in the digestive tract. Dr. Victor Chedid, a gastroenterologist and IBD expert at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota, offers tips people can take to keep their gut healthy and inflammatory diseases at bay.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-weaning-off-popular-weight-loss-medications/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Weaning off popular weight-loss medications</a></h2>



<p>Many people have lost unwanted pounds by using popular injectable weight-loss medications such as Ozempic, Wegovy and Zepbound. Some studies show that you can lose up to 15% of your body weight.&nbsp;But what if you want to wean off weight-loss medications?</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-to-know-about-legionnaires-disease/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What to know about Legionnaires' disease</a></h2>



<p>Legionnaires' disease is a serious lung infection caused by Legionella bacteria. While most people exposed to the bacteria don't get sick, some people are at higher risk of infection and potentially serious illness. Dr. Nipunie Rajapakse,&nbsp;a Mayo Clinic infectious disease expert, explains how this disease is spread and what you should know about Legionnaires' disease.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-back-to-school-vaccination-checkup/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Back-to-school vaccination checkup</a></h2>



<p>As schools are getting ready for students to return, it's important for parents to think about their children's back-to-school vaccination checklist.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Nipunie Rajapakse, who specializes in pediatric infectious disease at&nbsp;Mayo Clinic's Children's Center,&nbsp;says that parents should check with their primary healthcare team to make sure their children's regular&nbsp;vaccinations&nbsp;are up to date before school starts.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-23/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Activity-Snack2-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/web-top-5_08092024.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Weaning off popular weight-loss medications</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-weaning-off-popular-weight-loss-medications/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 13:10:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Meera Shah]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=391911</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Many people have lost unwanted pounds by using popular injectable weight-loss medications such as Ozempic, Wegovy and Zepbound. These drugs contain semaglutide, liraglutide or tirzepatide, which curb appetite and increase insulin sensitivity. Some studies show that you can lose up to 15% of your body weight. But what if you want to wean off weight-loss [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-weaning-off-popular-weight-loss-medications/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Weaning off popular weight-loss medications</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Many people have lost unwanted pounds by using popular injectable weight-loss medications such as Ozempic, Wegovy and Zepbound. These drugs contain semaglutide, liraglutide or tirzepatide, which curb appetite and increase insulin sensitivity. Some studies show that you can lose up to 15% of your body weight. But what if you want to wean off weight-loss medications?</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/shah-meera-m-b-ch-b/bio-20114165" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Meera Shah</a>, a Mayo Clinic endocrinologist, says that if you want to lose weight permanently, you need to stay consistently active and eat a nutritious diet.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/BMrA37hEXrM" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeBMrA37hEXrM"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Weaning off popular weight loss medications" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BMrA37hEXrM?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:00) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/weight-loss-drugs-script.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script.</a></strong></p>



<p>You step on the scale and the numbers are moving in the right direction after taking one of the popular injectable weight-loss drugs. But now you want to stop the medication, so what do you do? How long can you stay on these drugs?</p>



<p>"We just haven't had people on this class of medicines for long enough to know what happens in five years, even three years, and when might be the right time to withdraw people off these medicines," says Dr. Shah.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/Wegovy-semaglutide-weight-loss-drug-injection-pen-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="A closeup shot of a Wegovy semaglutide weight-loss drug injection demonstration pen." class="wp-image-367519" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/Wegovy-semaglutide-weight-loss-drug-injection-pen-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/Wegovy-semaglutide-weight-loss-drug-injection-pen-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/Wegovy-semaglutide-weight-loss-drug-injection-pen-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/Wegovy-semaglutide-weight-loss-drug-injection-pen-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/Wegovy-semaglutide-weight-loss-drug-injection-pen-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Some <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9542252/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">studies</a> show people regain weight after ditching diet drugs.</p>



<p>"If you stopped medication, say within six months of being on it, there's a very high chance for weight regain," explains Dr Shah.</p>



<p>This could have something to do with an increase in appetite once you stop taking weight-loss medications.</p>



<p>"What the medicine is doing is it's actually changing those appetite signals, but when you don't have that medicine on board, then your body goes back to its default state," says Dr. Shah.</p>



<p>Talk with your healthcare team before stopping these types of weight-loss drugs.&nbsp; It's also a good idea to eat a balanced diet and stay active.</p>



<p>Related Posts:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/5-23-mayo-clinic-minute-whats-the-skinny-on-weight-loss-drugs/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What's the skinny on weight-loss drugs?</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-weight-loss-medications-alone-are-not-a-quick-fix/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Weight-loss medications alone are not a quick fix</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-weaning-off-popular-weight-loss-medications/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Weaning off popular weight-loss medications</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/01/a-blue-measuring-tape-on-the-floor-and-closeup-of-a-white-persons-feet-standing-on-a-scale-to-check-their-weight-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/a-woman-celebrating-health-and-weight-loss-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Meera Shah]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: What to know about Legionnaires&#8217; disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-to-know-about-legionnaires-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Infectious Diseases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nipunie Rajapakse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=392418</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Legionnaires' disease&#160;is a serious lung infection caused by Legionella bacteria. While most people exposed to the bacteria don't get sick, some people are at higher risk of infection and potentially serious illness.&#160; Dr. Nipunie Rajapakse,&#160;a Mayo Clinic infectious disease expert, explains how this disease is spread and what you should know about Legionnaires' disease. Watch: [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-to-know-about-legionnaires-disease/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What to know about Legionnaires&#8217; disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/the-summer-risk-of-legionnaires-disease/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Legionnaires' disease</a>&nbsp;is a serious lung infection caused by Legionella bacteria. While most people exposed to the bacteria don't get sick, some people are at higher risk of infection and potentially serious illness.&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/rajapakse-nipunie-s-m-d-m-p-h/bio-20308514?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Nipunie Rajapakse,</a>&nbsp;a Mayo Clinic infectious disease expert, explains how this disease is spread and what you should know about Legionnaires' disease.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/N0_LtcERqe8" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeN0LtcERqe8"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: What to know about Legionnaires&#039; disease" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/N0_LtcERqe8?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:10) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/SCRIPT-MCM-Legionnaires-disease_NRedit2843.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Legionnaires' disease is a type of serious pneumonia that people can get typically from exposure to mist or water. It's not spread person-to-person.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="935" height="631" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/CDC-legionnaires.jpg" alt="microscopic slide of legionella-- Legionnaires' disease" class="wp-image-101662" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/CDC-legionnaires.jpg 935w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/CDC-legionnaires-300x202.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/CDC-legionnaires-768x518.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 935px) 100vw, 935px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Courtesy CDC - microscopic image of legionella </figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Legionnaires' disease is spread through inhaling mist that has the Legionella bacteria in it," says Dr. Rajapakse.</p>



<p>"That mist can come from many different sources that use water. The more common places that we see outbreaks associated are whirlpools, air conditioning units or fountains," she says.</p>



<p>Home and car air conditioning units aren't a risk for Legionella growth because they don't use water to cool the air.</p>



<p>Not everyone exposed gets sick, but some people are more susceptible to illness than others.</p>



<p>"Certain people might be at more risk of getting Legionnaires' disease; we definitely see it more commonly in older individuals or people who have weakened immune systems," says Dr. Rajapakse.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Symptoms</h2>



<p>It can take 2 to 4 days after exposure to feel symptoms.</p>



<p>"Symptoms of Legionnaires' disease can start as a flu-like illness with fever, body aches, cough, malaise, kind of feeling really tired; then [it] can present like pneumonia," she says.</p>



<p>It can progress to severe illness requiring hospitalization.</p>



<p>Although the infection primarily affects the lungs, occasionally, it can cause infections in wounds and in other parts of the body, including the heart.</p>



<p>"When identified and treated early, it is treatable with antibiotics," says Dr. Rajapakse.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-to-know-about-legionnaires-disease/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What to know about Legionnaires&#8217; disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/Legionella-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/09/Legionella-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nipunie Rajapakse]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Press launches new consumer health and wellness podcast portfolio</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-press-launches-new-consumer-health-and-wellness-podcast-portfolio/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=392278</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic Press, the trade and consumer publishing division of the nation's leading hospital, announces the launch of a new portfolio of consumer-focused health and wellness podcasts, offering Mayo Clinic's expert insight, guidance and practical tips on a broad spectrum of health topics. The new podcasts aim to provide listeners worldwide with the knowledge to [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-press-launches-new-consumer-health-and-wellness-podcast-portfolio/">Mayo Clinic Press launches new consumer health and wellness podcast portfolio</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Young-African-American-woman-with-headphones-on-holds-a-coffee-cup-GETTY_16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-392290" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Young-African-American-woman-with-headphones-on-holds-a-coffee-cup-GETTY_16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Young-African-American-woman-with-headphones-on-holds-a-coffee-cup-GETTY_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Young-African-American-woman-with-headphones-on-holds-a-coffee-cup-GETTY_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Young-African-American-woman-with-headphones-on-holds-a-coffee-cup-GETTY_16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Young-African-American-woman-with-headphones-on-holds-a-coffee-cup-GETTY_16x9-2048x1153.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><a href="https://mcpress.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Press</a>, the trade and consumer publishing division of the nation's leading hospital, announces the launch of a new portfolio of consumer-focused health and wellness podcasts, offering Mayo Clinic's expert insight, guidance and practical tips on a broad spectrum of health topics. The new podcasts aim to provide listeners worldwide with the knowledge to navigate medical diagnoses and make healthy, educated choices.</p>



<p>Whether listeners are interested in a specific condition or just aiming to stay informed, each podcast gives access to Mayo Clinic's experts' wisdom, the very latest in medical science and practical tips, providing health and wellness knowledge from the leading voices in healthcare.</p>



<p>The new podcast lineup includes:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong><em>Health Matters, hosted by Kristen Meinzer</em></strong><strong>&nbsp;</strong><br>In each episode of <em>Health Matters,</em> Kristen talks with leading medical experts from Mayo Clinic who share their insights and opinions on the latest health and wellness subjects and information.&nbsp; Kristen’s informed yet informal point of view results in a series that gives listeners a front row seat to an informative yet entertaining discussion about the most important of topics:&nbsp; your health.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong><em>Mayo Clinic On Nutrition, hosted by Tara Schmidt</em></strong><strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong><br><em>On Nutrition</em> helps listeners unravel the complexities of modern diets, offers evidence-based nutritional advice and debunks common myths about what we eat. Explore weight management, innovative nutritional therapies, and how to make the best, most informed choices about your diet.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong><em>Mayo Clinic Kids, hosted by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mattke-angela-c-m-d/bio-20055584" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Angela Mattke, M.D.</a>         </em></strong><br><em>Kids Health Matters</em> helps listeners make sense of children's health and wellness, drawing on the most up-to-date expert medical advice so that they can help the children in their lives grow to be healthy, happy adults.<br></li>



<li><strong><em>Aging Forward, hosted by Christina Chen, M.D. </em></strong><strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong><br><em>Aging Forward</em> offers enlightening conversations and expert advice on healthy aging and geriatric medicine, enabling listeners to embrace older age with vitality and joy. Learn about the science of aging and discover strategies for healthy habits, preventive care, caregiving and living your best life.</li>
</ul>



<p>The podcasts each function as a gateway to Mayo Clinic's unparalleled expertise, translating complex medical information into understandable and actionable insights for everyday life.</p>



<p>"We are thrilled to share these new podcasts with the public, bringing Mayo Clinic's world-renowned expertise directly to listeners, wherever they are," says Dan Harke, publisher of Mayo Clinic Press. "With these podcasts, we have real experts sharing insight and guidance, in a way that's both accessible and engaging."</p>



<p>For more information about the Mayo Clinic Press podcasts or to listen to the latest episodes, visit mcpress.mayoclinic.org/podcasts or wherever you listen to podcasts.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Press:</strong></p>



<p>Mayo Clinic Press is the exclusive trade and consumer publishing division of Mayo Clinic. Guided by Mayo Clinic's multispecialty model of care, the Press publishes a diverse range of authors and experts, covering the entire scope of human health and medicine. Its mission is to empower individuals with the knowledge to build healthier, happier lives.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-press-launches-new-consumer-health-and-wellness-podcast-portfolio/">Mayo Clinic Press launches new consumer health and wellness podcast portfolio</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Young-African-American-woman-with-headphones-on-holds-a-coffee-cup-GETTY_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Young-African-American-woman-with-headphones-on-holds-a-coffee-cup-GETTY_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-22/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jaynelle Ramon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=392330</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week. What you should know about processed, ultra-processed foods Processed, and especially ultra-processed, foods have been blamed for the national rise in obesity, high blood pressure and diabetes. But what exactly are these foods, and are they really [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-22/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-2 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:ugcPost:7224489422082166784/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="392138" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-David-T.-Jones-Showing-Computer-Scans-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-392138" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-David-T.-Jones-Showing-Computer-Scans-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-David-T.-Jones-Showing-Computer-Scans-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-David-T.-Jones-Showing-Computer-Scans-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-David-T.-Jones-Showing-Computer-Scans-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Dr.-David-T.-Jones-Showing-Computer-Scans-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C95Ocr6s9Bo/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="316817" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/a-young-or-middle-aged-Asian-man-in-a-workout-gym-lifting-weights-and-exercising-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="a young or middle aged Asian man in a workout gym lifting weights and exercising" class="wp-image-316817" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/a-young-or-middle-aged-Asian-man-in-a-workout-gym-lifting-weights-and-exercising-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/a-young-or-middle-aged-Asian-man-in-a-workout-gym-lifting-weights-and-exercising-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/a-young-or-middle-aged-Asian-man-in-a-workout-gym-lifting-weights-and-exercising-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/a-young-or-middle-aged-Asian-man-in-a-workout-gym-lifting-weights-and-exercising-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/a-young-or-middle-aged-Asian-man-in-a-workout-gym-lifting-weights-and-exercising-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C-DRS1Wxl2v/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="760" height="428" data-id="392192" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/16x9_ht-rate-variability-post_Feature-image_shutterstock_141652744-fotor-20240729141143.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-392192" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/16x9_ht-rate-variability-post_Feature-image_shutterstock_141652744-fotor-20240729141143.jpg 760w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/16x9_ht-rate-variability-post_Feature-image_shutterstock_141652744-fotor-20240729141143-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 760px) 100vw, 760px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/706347941527986/posts/893920279437417" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="660" height="370" data-id="392154" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/instant-soup-with-noodles-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-392154" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/instant-soup-with-noodles-16x9-1.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/instant-soup-with-noodles-16x9-1-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C-BH7ScvnF_/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="230021" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/02/shutterstock_1046485810_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a senior woman with gray hair and a hearing aid in her ear" class="wp-image-230021" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/02/shutterstock_1046485810_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/02/shutterstock_1046485810_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/02/shutterstock_1046485810_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>
</figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week.</h3>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-you-should-know-about-processed-ultra-processed-foods/">What you should know about processed, ultra-processed foods</a></h2>



<p>Processed, and especially ultra-processed, foods have been blamed for the national rise in obesity, high blood pressure and diabetes. But what exactly are these foods, and are they really all that bad for you?</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-untreated-hearing-loss-can-result-in-a-negative-health-spiral/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How untreated hearing loss can result in a negative health spiral</a></h2>



<p>Hearing loss often is thought of as a normal part of aging, but recent studies have shown untreated hearing loss can significantly affect overall health. Dr. Nicholas Deep, a Mayo Clinic otolaryngologist, explains how untreated hearing loss can affect cognitive, social and physical health.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-using-ai-and-brain-waves-for-early-diagnosis-of-neurodegenerative-diseases/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Using AI and brain waves for early diagnosis of neurodegenerative diseases</a></h2>



<p>In a recent study, a research team led by Mayo Clinic is investigating use of artificial intelligence (AI) with routine electroencephalogram (EEG) tests to help diagnose Alzheimer's disease and other brain disorders. Dr. David T. Jones, a Mayo Clinic neurologist and senior author of the study, explains what this means.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-jump-start-your-workout/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How to jump-start your workout</a></h2>



<p>The Summer Olympics have started, which might inspire you to be more physically active. But jump-starting your workout routine can be challenging if you've been sitting on the couch for a while. It can seem like a daunting task.</p>



<p>Dr. Nathan LeBrasseur, director of the Robert and Arlene Kogod Center on Aging at Mayo Clinic, says it's never too late to get moving, even if you're an older adult.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/your-wearable-says-your-heart-rate-variability-has-changed-now-what/">Your wearable says your heart rate variability has changed. Now what?</a></h2>



<p>Wearables measure several aspects of health, and heart rate variability might be one of those. It may be surprising when your device informs you that your heart rate variability is high or low, but what does it mean? Dr. Elijah Behr, a cardiologist at Mayo Clinic Healthcare in London, explains heart rate variability and how it factors into health.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-22/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/a-young-or-middle-aged-Asian-man-in-a-workout-gym-lifting-weights-and-exercising-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/web-top-5_08022024.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic hospitals again earn star ratings for quality</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-hospitals-again-earn-star-ratings-for-quality/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ann Schauer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 11:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=392299</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic hospitals received high ratings from the Centers for Medicare &#38; Medicaid Services for overall hospital quality. Mayo leaders thank staff for their commitment to delivering high-quality care, attention to detail and empathy. Mayo Clinic hospitals across the organization received star ratings from the Centers for Medicare &#38; Medicaid Services on July 31. The [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-hospitals-again-earn-star-ratings-for-quality/">Mayo Clinic hospitals again earn star ratings for quality</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Nurse-Helping-patient-GettyImages-1473157220-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-392312" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Nurse-Helping-patient-GettyImages-1473157220-16x9-1.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Nurse-Helping-patient-GettyImages-1473157220-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Nurse-Helping-patient-GettyImages-1473157220-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Mayo Clinic hospitals received high ratings from the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services for overall hospital quality. Mayo leaders thank staff for their commitment to delivering high-quality care, attention to detail and empathy.</strong></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p>Mayo Clinic hospitals across the organization received star ratings from the <a href="https://www.cms.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services</a> on July 31.</p>



<p>The ratings for overall hospital quality provide patients with information on several aspects of quality. The star ratings measure five broad categories: mortality, safety of care, readmission, patient experience, and timely and effective care.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Overall hospital quality star ratings</strong></h2>



<p>Across Mayo Clinic, nine hospitals received four- and five-star ratings for overall hospital quality. Eight of the nine hospitals achieved five stars — the best score possible — and one hospital received four stars. The national average is three stars.</p>



<p>"This honor truly belongs to Mayo Clinic staff," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/dowdy-sean-c-m-d/bio-20054619" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sean Dowdy, M.D.</a>, Mayo Clinic's chief value officer. "They embody the true spirit of service, continually going above and beyond to deliver exceptional, empathic and high-quality care."</p>



<p>Hospitals earning four and five stars are:</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Five stars</strong></h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Mayo Clinic Hospital in Arizona.</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Hospital in Florida.</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Hospital in Rochester.</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in Albert Lea and Austin, Minnesota.</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in Eau Claire, Wisconsin.</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in La Crosse, Wisconsin.</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in Mankato, Minnesota.</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System — Red Cedar in Menomonie, Wisconsin.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Four stars</strong></h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in Red Wing, Minnesota.</li>
</ul>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-hospitals-again-earn-star-ratings-for-quality/">Mayo Clinic hospitals again earn star ratings for quality</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Nurse-Helping-patient-GettyImages-1473157220_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Nurse-Helping-patient-GettyImages-1473157220-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>