<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Health &amp; Wellness - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/health-and-wellness/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/health-and-wellness/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 13:56:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>What you should know about processed, ultra-processed foods</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-you-should-know-about-processed-ultra-processed-foods/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Anne Harguth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=392153</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Processed, and especially ultra-processed, foods have been blamed for the national rise in obesity, high blood pressure and diabetes. But what exactly are these foods, and are they really all that bad for you? Defining processed foods According to the&#160;Department of Agriculture, processed foods are any raw agricultural commodities altered from their original state. This [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-you-should-know-about-processed-ultra-processed-foods/">What you should know about processed, ultra-processed foods</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/instant-soup-with-noodles-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-392154" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/instant-soup-with-noodles-16x9-1.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/instant-soup-with-noodles-16x9-1-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></figure>



<p>Processed, and especially ultra-processed, foods have been blamed for the national rise in obesity, high blood pressure and diabetes. But what exactly are these foods, and are they really all that bad for you?</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Defining processed foods</h2>



<p>According to the&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.usda.gov/wps/portal/usda/usdahome" target="_blank">Department of Agriculture</a>, processed foods are any raw agricultural commodities altered from their original state. This includes washing, cleaning, milling, cutting, chopping, heating, pasteurizing, blanching, cooking, canning, freezing, drying, dehydrating, mixing or packaging.</p>



<p>While processing includes basic steps like washing, foods cross into ultra-processed territory when they contain preservatives, flavorings and other food additives, or substances approved for use in food products, such as salt, <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/are-you-consuming-too-much-sugar" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">sugars</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/fast-facts-on-fats-and-heart-health" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">fats</a> used to enhance flavor and increase shelf life.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Ranking foods from minimally to ultra-processed</h2>



<p>Here's how the&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.eatright.org/" target="_blank">Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics</a>&nbsp;ranks processed foods from minimally to mostly or ultra-processed:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Minimally processed foods, such as fresh blueberries, cut vegetables and roasted nuts, prepped for convenience.</li>



<li>Foods processed at their peak to lock in nutritional quality and freshness including canned tomatoes, tuna, frozen fruit or vegetables.</li>



<li>Foods with ingredients added for flavor and texture, such as sweeteners, spices, oils, colors and preservatives, include jarred pasta sauce, salad dressing, yogurt and cake mixes.</li>



<li>Ready-to-eat foods like crackers, chips and deli meat, which are more heavily processed.</li>



<li>The most heavily or ultra-processed foods include sweetened breakfast cereals, soda, energy drinks, artificially flavored crackers and potato chips, chicken nuggets and hot dogs.</li>
</ul>



<p>Minimally processed foods have a place in healthy diets. For example, low-fat milk, whole-grain or wheat bread, precut vegetables and fresh-cut greens are considered processed foods. Dairy- and plant-based milks and juices may be fortified with vitamin D and calcium, while breakfast cereals may have added fiber. Canned fruits packed in water or natural fruit juice can be part of a healthy diet when fresh fruit isn't readily available.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Reading the labels</h2>



<p>When choosing foods, do some investigative work by examining ingredient lists and analyzing the nutrition facts labels:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Avoid foods that contain additives and preservatives, such as high fructose corn syrup, hydrogenated oils, food dyes, monosodium glutamate, sodium nitrates, sodium nitrites and sulfites such as sulfur dioxide, sodium bisulfite or sodium sulfite.</li>



<li>Cut back on ultra-processed foods and purchase more unprocessed or minimally processed foods.</li>



<li>Look for more natural ingredients.</li>
</ul>



<p>When reading the nutrition facts labels, watch for hidden sugars, fats and salt, especially those added during processing.</p>



<p>Most labels now include <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/the-not-so-sweet-truth-of-added-sugars" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">added sugars</a>. The <a href="https://www.dietaryguidelines.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dietary Guidelines for Americans</a> recommends that people older than 2 get less than 10% of total calories from added sugars, or about 200 calories in a 2,000-calorie diet. Children younger than 2 shouldn't have any added sugars in their diets. Learn to spot words like maltose, brown sugar, corn syrup, honey and fruit juice concentrate.</p>



<p>When it comes to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/kids-and-sodium-serious-risks-and-alarming-realities">sodium</a>, people often comment that they salt their food. As it turns out, you don't need to because manufacturers have already added salt for you, and it's often too much. The Dietary Guidelines also recommends adults consume less than 2,300 milligrams of sodium per day. Look for low- or reduced-sodium foods. Also try rinsing canned vegetables with water to remove some of the salt.</p>



<p>When checking fat content on labels, scan for saturated fats and&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-cholesterol/in-depth/trans-fat/art-20046114" target="_blank">trans fats</a>. Choose foods lower in saturated fats. Trans fats are considered one of the worst types of fat because they can raise your low-density lipoprotein (LDL or "bad") cholesterol and lower your high-density lipoprotein (HDL or "good") cholesterol.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Taking baby steps toward healthier eating</h2>



<p>Take baby steps by making one dietary change at a time. Consider healthy swaps, such as whole-grain cereal with no added sugar instead of highly processed, sugary cereals. Choose whole-grain, high-fiber breads over white bread products. When looking for a healthy snack, reach for fresh fruit or vegetables instead of crackers, potato chips or processed cookies.</p>



<p>The key to healthy eating starts with you. Educate yourself on what to look for and talk with your healthcare professional or nutrition expert to discuss a food plan that works best for you.</p>



<p><em>Anne Harguth is a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/nutrition" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">registered dietitian</a> in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/waseca" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Waseca</a>, Minnesota.</em></p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/processed-foods-what-you-should-know" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-you-should-know-about-processed-ultra-processed-foods/">What you should know about processed, ultra-processed foods</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/instant-soup-with-noodles-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/instant-soup-with-noodles-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Anne Harguth]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Once a bariatric surgery patient, nurse now inspires others</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/once-a-bariatric-surgery-patient-nurse-now-inspires-others/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tia R. Ford]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Steven Bowers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Julie Pulmano]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=392048</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Eastern Caribbean or Western Caribbean, lounging on the ship or island hopping, Julie Pulmano's love language is "any vacation on a boat." The 60-year-old nurse has been on more than two dozen cruises in her life — including the one where she met her husband, Sherman. Of all the cruises she's taken, though, one stands [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/once-a-bariatric-surgery-patient-nurse-now-inspires-others/">Once a bariatric surgery patient, nurse now inspires others</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Before-After-with-Text-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-392057" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Before-After-with-Text-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Before-After-with-Text-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Before-After-with-Text-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Before-After-with-Text-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Before-After-with-Text.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Eastern Caribbean or Western Caribbean, lounging on the ship or island hopping, Julie Pulmano's love language is "any vacation on a boat." The 60-year-old nurse has been on more than two dozen cruises in her life — including the one where she met her husband, Sherman.</p>



<p>Of all the cruises she's taken, though, one stands out in Julie's mind.</p>



<p>"I was going up the stairs on a ship, and I was having chest pain and was short of breath," she says. "My husband said to me, 'You really need to go to the doctor. You promised me 90 years together.' That was a promise we made to each other, that we'd be married for 90-plus years. I didn't want to let him or our kids down. I went and had my heart checked out. It wasn't my heart, though. It was my weight."</p>



<p>Julie wasn't surprised by the news. She'd always battled her weight.</p>



<p>"I was that person who would be getting ready to go somewhere and I'd be in the closet, trying to find something that would fit," she says. "But nothing looked good on me, so I wouldn’t go. I'd tell my husband that I wasn't going and would just cry in the closet instead.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="204" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Before-204x300.png" alt="Julie Pulmano sitting on a scooter before her bariatric surgery" class="wp-image-392049" style="width:188px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Before-204x300.png 204w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Before.png 585w" sizes="(max-width: 204px) 100vw, 204px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Julie Pulmano before her bariatric surgery</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"I'd plan amazing cruises for six months out and buy cute outfits and start trying to lose weight, but I'd never lose it, and I'd be so sad. I'd go buy big-girl clothes instead and still go on the cruise, but the whole time I'd be so jealous of all the thin people around me. So, I'd promise myself that, next time, I was going to be one of those thin people. But then I'd book another cruise, and the same pattern would just repeat every year."</p>



<p>It took learning her weight was harming her health — and could potentially shorten her life — to encourage Julie to take additional action.</p>



<p>"That was what made me realize I needed to do something," she says. "I've never looked back."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Turning to Mayo Clinic</h2>



<p>At the time, Julie was working as a nurse on the surgical floor of Mayo Clinic. Mayo had opened its <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/bariatric-center-florida/sections/overview/ovc-20523458" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bariatric Center in Florida</a> in 2007, and ever since, Julie had been struck by the success stories she heard from patients who'd gone through the program.</p>



<p>In 2012, Julie entered the program as a candidate for weight-loss surgery. While Sherman and her kids supported her, Julie felt judged by other family members and friends, and she left the program.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/bowers-steven-m-d/bio-20055099" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Steven Bowers</a>, a surgeon in the Bariatric Center, says the response Julie received isn't uncommon. "Some people may view surgery as extreme," he says. "But they're often not thinking about the long-term toll obesity has on health. They also may not recognize that if you have a lot of weight to lose, you're unlikely to get there through diet alone."</p>



<p>In 2014, Julie realized she needed help if she was going to meet her weight-loss goals. She reentered the program, determined to complete it successfully this time.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Second time's the charm</h2>



<p>The Bariatric Center at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a> offers surgical and non surgical options for patients. To be cleared for bariatric surgery, patients must undergo certain evaluations, including blood and imaging tests, as well as behavioral, heart and lung assessments to reduce the risk of complications.</p>



<p>"I went through the evaluations," Julie says. "I met with the dietitians and nurses. I met with the bariatrician, who determined I was a great candidate for surgery. And I went to the classes to learn how to eat properly and exercise. Everyone in the program was wonderful."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="227" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/After-227x300.png" alt="Julie Pulmano standing on a staircase following bariatric surgery" class="wp-image-392050" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/After-227x300.png 227w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/After.png 585w" sizes="(max-width: 227px) 100vw, 227px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Julie Pulmano following bariatric surgery</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Julie credits the lifestyle changes she learned before her gastric bypass surgery with the outcome she achieved afterward — losing 125 pounds and keeping it off for 10 years and counting. The behavior modifications she maintains, like focusing on portion size, not plate size, and learning how to meal prep, have been the most important factor, she says.</p>



<p>"Buying into the behavior aspects of the program is what leads to success with bariatric surgery," says Dr. Bowers, who was Julie's surgeon. "Julie is a great example of someone who took to heart the importance of changing your diet and changing your lifestyle, and she's done extremely well."</p>



<p>Although Julie acknowledges she's biased because she works for Mayo Clinic, she says she'll never go anywhere else for her health.</p>



<p>"Mayo Clinic has the highest standards," Julie says. "They're so comprehensive. They truly walk alongside you, from start to finish."</p>



<p>In addition to the help and encouragement Julie received from the bariatric program team, she also drew inspiration and motivation from her peers through the program's support groups.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A (role) model nurse</h2>



<p>In May 2023, Julie switched roles, moving from the surgical floor to work as a nurse in the Bariatric Center. She now serves as a "standard bearer" for bariatric patients coming behind her, Dr. Bowers says. She shares her story with patients, as well as before-and-after photos, and tells them how much the program has helped her.</p>



<p>"This is the perfect job for me," Julie says. "I feel like I'm able to inspire patients. I tell them it's not easy, but it's worth it. And it will bring them longevity and happiness."</p>



<p>Julie stresses to patients that deciding to go through the bariatric program and have weight-loss surgery is something they must choose for themselves.</p>



<p>"It took me two tries," Julie says. "The second time was the right time for me, and it has to be the right time for them. But helping to overcome the judgment patients may feel from others is one of the reasons I want to share my own experiences now."</p>



<p>Julie says she also explains to patients that weight-loss surgery is about much more than appearance.</p>



<p>"Obviously, it gives your confidence a boost, but it also benefits your health and gives you a better quality of life," she says. "You just feel better. Your whole attitude toward life is better."</p>



<p>With her next cruise coming up in September, Julie says she no longer wonders if she'll be able to fit into her clothes by the time she boards.</p>



<p>"Now, I go into the closet and pull out an outfit and know it's going to fit," she says. "It's such an amazing feeling to hold my head high and not hide in a corner. Going through the bariatric program is the best decision I've ever made. My one regret is that I didn't do it sooner."</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/once-a-bariatric-surgery-patient-nurse-now-inspires-others/">Once a bariatric surgery patient, nurse now inspires others</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/After-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Before-After-without-Text.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Steven Bowers]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Julie Pulmano]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: How to jump-start your workout</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-jump-start-your-workout/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 15:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nathan LeBrasseur]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workout]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=379614</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Summer Olympics have started, which might inspire you to be more physically active. But jump-starting your workout routine can be challenging if you've been sitting on the couch for a while. It can seem like a daunting task. Dr. Nathan LeBrasseur, director of the Robert and Arlene Kogod Center on Aging at Mayo Clinic, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-jump-start-your-workout/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How to jump-start your workout</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Summer Olympics have started, which might inspire you to be more physically active. But jump-starting your workout routine can be challenging if you've been sitting on the couch for a while. It can seem like a daunting task.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/lebrasseur-nathan-k-ph-d-m-s/bio-00055041" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Nathan LeBrasseur</a>, director of the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-arlene-kogod-center-aging" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Robert and Arlene Kogod Center on Aging</a> at Mayo Clinic, says it's never too late to get moving, even if you're an older adult.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/mEkRo550oKg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubemEkRo550oKg"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: How to jump-start your workout" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mEkRo550oKg?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (0:55) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/SCRIPT-MCM-Jump-start-your-workout.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Starting a workout program or being physically active takes motivation and commitment. The key is to start slowly and do something you take pleasure in.</p>



<p>"If you hate swimming, don't try to start to become a swimmer. But (if) you enjoy dancing or other activities (such as) gardening, those are forms of activity that once you engage in, you increase your consistency and compliance that will have the most health benefits," says Dr. LeBrasseur.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/12/a-smiling-older-woman-seated-on-a-yoga-mat-doing-stretches-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a smiling older woman seated on a yoga mat, doing stretches" class="wp-image-256796" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/12/a-smiling-older-woman-seated-on-a-yoga-mat-doing-stretches-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/12/a-smiling-older-woman-seated-on-a-yoga-mat-doing-stretches-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/12/a-smiling-older-woman-seated-on-a-yoga-mat-doing-stretches-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/12/a-smiling-older-woman-seated-on-a-yoga-mat-doing-stretches-16X9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/12/a-smiling-older-woman-seated-on-a-yoga-mat-doing-stretches-16X9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Being active can build muscle strength and improve cognitive and cardiovascular health.</p>



<p>"Three percent, or 30 minutes a day, of our waking hours, if we commit that to physical activity, will have huge benefits," explains Dr. LeBrasseur.</p>



<p>And for those young at heart, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention recommends 150 minutes of moderate exercise a week.</p>



<p>"As we get older, dedicating time, purposeful time, to getting some form of aerobic exercise or endurance exercise, like walking or cycling or swimming, and also getting some form of strength training is critically important," says Dr. LeBrasseur.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Tips to get started and stick with a workout plan:</strong></h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Research workout routines.</li>



<li>Schedule your workouts.</li>



<li>Find an exercise buddy.</li>



<li>Be consistent.</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-jump-start-your-workout/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How to jump-start your workout</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/a-young-or-middle-aged-Asian-man-in-a-workout-gym-lifting-weights-and-exercising-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/08/a-smiling-older-woman-in-the-pool-in-a-swimming-or-water-fitness-class-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nathan LeBrasseur]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Workout]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Preventing measles outbreaks in the US through vaccination</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/preventing-measles-outbreaks-in-the-us-through-vaccination/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 14:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Children's Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Infectious Diseases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nipunie Rajapakse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Measles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=372997</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention&#160;reports&#160;more than a dozen outbreaks of measles in the U.S., with more than 165 confirmed cases of the highly contagious viral disease. Most of the cases are among children under age&#160;5,&#160;and more than half of all cases have resulted in hospitalization. "Measles is a viral infection that is highly [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/preventing-measles-outbreaks-in-the-us-through-vaccination/">Preventing measles outbreaks in the US through vaccination</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/measles-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="medical illustration of child with measles" class="wp-image-113742" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/measles-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/measles-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/measles-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention&nbsp;<a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.cdc.gov%2Fmeasles%2Fdata-research%2Findex.html&amp;data=05%7C02%7CBalzer.Deborah%40mayo.edu%7C8f5eb7b309754bd5c29208dcad78c854%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C638575981467696430%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=gaYUdQUKH8tzQL%2FkAlCCfY1%2FoC9PWjKgV9O0hHKmda4%3D&amp;reserved=0">reports</a>&nbsp;more than a dozen outbreaks of measles in the U.S., with more than 165 confirmed cases of the highly contagious viral disease. Most of the cases are among children under age&nbsp;5,&nbsp;and more than half of all cases have resulted in hospitalization.</p>



<p>"Measles is a viral infection that is highly contagious if you're not immune to it,"&nbsp;says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/rajapakse-nipunie-s-m-d-m-p-h/bio-20308514?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Nipunie Rajapakse,</a>&nbsp;a&nbsp;pediatric infectious diseases physician with the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/childrens-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Children's Center.</a>&nbsp;"It’s generally characterized by fever, cough, runny nose and a pretty characteristic rash that can involve much of the skin surface."</p>



<p>Measles was declared eliminated in the U.S. in 2000 through a successful vaccine program, yet it persists globally. People can bring it to the U.S. if they're not vaccinated and get infected when they travel. The CDC says travelers should seek medical care if they develop symptoms of measles, including a rash, high fever, cough, runny nose or red, watery eyes.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Measles is one of the most contagious infectious diseases out there. If you're in the same airspace as someone with measles, if they were there two hours ago and you're not immune to it, you can still contract measles, even without ever coming in face-to-face contact with that person. That's why the vaccination is so important. It gives you baseline immunity," says Dr. Rajapakse.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/824KBG3ERNs" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Nipunie Rajapakse talks about measles</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutube824KBG3ERNs"  title="Preventing measles outbreaks in the US through vaccination" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/824KBG3ERNs?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites with Dr. Rajapakse are available in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Name super/CG: Nipunie Rajapakse, M.D./Pediatric Infectious Diseases/Mayo Clinic.</strong></p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Complications from measles&nbsp;</h3>



<p>"Measles used to be a relatively common childhood illness. Since we've introduced very effective immunization, measles is quite rare to see here in the U.S.," says Dr. Rajapakse. "It can infect the brain, for example, resulting in something called encephalitis. It can cause severe pneumonia. We're trying to avoid these complications by vaccinating children before they get sick with it."</p>



<p>Children under the age of 5, adults over 20, pregnant women and those with compromised immune systems are more likely to have complications from infection.</p>



<p>Complications from measles include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Diarrhea and vomiting.</li>



<li>Ear infection.</li>



<li>Bronchitis, laryngitis or croup.</li>



<li>Pneumonia.</li>



<li>Encephalitis.</li>



<li>Pregnancy problems, including premature or low-birth-weight babies.</li>
</ul>



<p>The CDC says that out of every 1,000 children with measles, about 1 to 3 die due to breathing and brain problems.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="720" height="405" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/red-splotches-measles-on-a-little-childs-face-16x9-1.jpg" alt="close up of child's face with measles" class="wp-image-113745" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/red-splotches-measles-on-a-little-childs-face-16x9-1.jpg 720w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/red-splotches-measles-on-a-little-childs-face-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 720px) 100vw, 720px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Measles causes a red, blotchy rash that usually appears first on the face and behind the ears, then spreads downward to the chest and back and finally to the feet.</figcaption></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Reducing measles outbreaks </h3>



<p>"Measles vaccination is a component of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements/measles-and-rubella-virus-vaccine-live-intramuscular-route-injection-route/proper-use/drg-20062133" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">measles, mumps, rubella (MMR) vaccine</a>&nbsp;that is routinely given between 12 to 18 months of age, and then again in the preschool vaccines between 4 to 6 years of age," Dr. Rajapakse says.</p>



<p>Two MMR vaccine doses are 97% effective against measles, while one is about 93% effective.</p>



<p>Before the 1963 measles vaccination program, around 3 to 4 million people got measles every year in the U.S., according to the CDC.</p>



<p>Learn more about the history of the measles vaccine development on the Mayo Clinic&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/history-disease-outbreaks-vaccine-timeline/measles">website.</a></p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Related posts:</strong></h4>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-childhood-vaccines-moving-the-needle-up/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Childhood vaccines – moving the needle up</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/do-you-know-who-to-talk-to-about-your-childs-routine-vaccinations/">Do you know who to talk to about your child’s routine vaccinations?</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/9-common-questions-about-vaccines-and-travel/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">9 common questions about vaccines and travel</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/preventing-measles-outbreaks-in-the-us-through-vaccination/">Preventing measles outbreaks in the US through vaccination</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/01/a-medical-illustration-of-a-young-boy-with-measles-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/01/a-medical-illustration-of-a-young-boy-with-measles-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nipunie Rajapakse]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Infectious Diseases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Measles]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-21/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jaynelle Ramon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 13:29:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=392077</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week. Mayo Clinic Minute: Why skipping breakfast can be bad for your heart Some say that breakfast is the most important meal of the day. Is it really? That's up for debate. However, skipping the first meal is [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-21/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=361639170106553" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="302659" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/04/close-up-of-a-middle-aged-white-womans-hands-as-she-rubs-her-fingers-and-joints-that-look-painful-with-arthritis-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="close up of a middle aged white woman's hands as she rubs her fingers and joints that look painful with arthritis" class="wp-image-302659" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/04/close-up-of-a-middle-aged-white-womans-hands-as-she-rubs-her-fingers-and-joints-that-look-painful-with-arthritis-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/04/close-up-of-a-middle-aged-white-womans-hands-as-she-rubs-her-fingers-and-joints-that-look-painful-with-arthritis-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/04/close-up-of-a-middle-aged-white-womans-hands-as-she-rubs-her-fingers-and-joints-that-look-painful-with-arthritis-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/04/close-up-of-a-middle-aged-white-womans-hands-as-she-rubs-her-fingers-and-joints-that-look-painful-with-arthritis-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/04/close-up-of-a-middle-aged-white-womans-hands-as-she-rubs-her-fingers-and-joints-that-look-painful-with-arthritis-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C9klhKXI8sK/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="390364" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx2-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390364" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx2-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx2-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx2-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx2-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx2-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:share:7219823417993121792" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="213528" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/08/MayoClinicEntranceFlag-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Entrance to Mayo Clinic Gonda building with flags flying outside" class="wp-image-213528" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/08/MayoClinicEntranceFlag-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/08/MayoClinicEntranceFlag-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/08/MayoClinicEntranceFlag-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/08/MayoClinicEntranceFlag-1.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C9xdgmBt3mx/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="228388" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/02/shutterstock_790420780_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a healthy vegetarian breakfast of oatmeal porridge with banana, blueberries and nuts and cup of green tea" class="wp-image-228388" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/02/shutterstock_790420780_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/02/shutterstock_790420780_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/02/shutterstock_790420780_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C90yQsAMItw/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="392015" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Body-composition-change-16x9-3-1024x576.jpg" alt="Abdominal CT scans in the same individual prior to diagnosis of pancreatic cancer shows profound changes in body composition from 14 months and nine months prior to cancer diagnosis." class="wp-image-392015" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Body-composition-change-16x9-3-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Body-composition-change-16x9-3-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Body-composition-change-16x9-3-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Body-composition-change-16x9-3-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Body-composition-change-16x9-3.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>
</figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week.</h3>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-skipping-breakfast-can-be-bad-for-your-heart/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Why skipping breakfast can be bad for your heart</a></h2>



<p>Some say that breakfast is the most important meal of the day. Is it really? That's up for debate. However, skipping the first meal is not the healthiest choice and can even put someone at risk for health issues. In this Mayo Clinic Minute,&nbsp;Dr. Francisco Lopez-Jimenez, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist, explains why.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/detecting-pancreatic-cancer-through-changes-in-body-composition-and-metabolism/">Detecting pancreatic cancer through changes in body composition and metabolism</a></h2>



<p>New research from Mayo Clinic&nbsp;represents a promising step toward identifying biological signals or biomarkers that may aid in early detection of pancreatic cancer. By tracking changes in body composition and metabolism, researchers are working to identify high-risk patients who could benefit from selective screening for the disease, which kills more than 50,000 Americans a year.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-reducing-thumb-arthritis-pain/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Reducing thumb arthritis pain</a></h2>



<p>Thousands of Americans suffer from thumb arthritis. This disorder can greatly affect daily life and can make it a struggle to do simple things like opening doors or holding objects.</p>



<p>Dr. Sanj Kakar, a Mayo Clinic orthopedic surgeon who specializes in wrist and hand disorders, explains the condition and available treatments.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-role-of-the-larynx-and-how-to-protect-it/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Role of the larynx and how to protect it</a></h2>



<p>When you talk, many parts of your body work together to make a sound. The larynx, also called the voice box, plays an important part in the process. </p>



<p>Dr. David Lott, a Mayo Clinic otolaryngologist who led the first known clinical trial on laryngeal transplantation in the U.S., says that, along with speech production, the larynx has many other vital roles.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-recognized-for-disability-inclusion/">Mayo Clinic recognized for disability inclusion</a></h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic recently received the highest possible score on the Disability Equality Index and was named a "Best Place To Work For Disability Inclusion" by the&nbsp;American Association of People with Disabilities&nbsp;and&nbsp;Disability:IN.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-21/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx2-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/web-top-5_07262024.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>NIH award supports new center at Mayo Clinic for health disparities in uterine fibroid treatment</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/nih-award-supports-new-center-at-mayo-clinic-for-health-disparities-in-uterine-fibroid-treatment/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Gerri Kelly]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Ebbie Stewart]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uterine Fibroids]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=391997</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Uterine fibroids, noncancerous tumors of the uterus, affect about 70% of white women and up to 90% of Black women according to the National Institutes of Health (NIH). Fibroid symptoms may include heavy menstrual bleeding, pelvic pain, bowel and bladder problems, and sometimes infertility and miscarriage. For women of African descent, fibroids may develop at [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/nih-award-supports-new-center-at-mayo-clinic-for-health-disparities-in-uterine-fibroid-treatment/">NIH award supports new center at Mayo Clinic for health disparities in uterine fibroid treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/a-medical-illustration-of-uterine-fibroids-16X9.jpg" alt="a medical illustration of uterine fibroids" class="wp-image-218720" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/a-medical-illustration-of-uterine-fibroids-16X9.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/a-medical-illustration-of-uterine-fibroids-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></figure>



<p><a href="http://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/uterine-fibroids/home/ovc-20212509" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Uterine fibroids</a>, noncancerous tumors of the uterus, affect about 70% of white women and up to 90% of Black women according to the <a href="https://www.nichd.nih.gov/newsroom/news/062124-two-fibroid-research-centers" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Institutes of Health (NIH)</a>. Fibroid symptoms may include heavy menstrual bleeding, pelvic pain, bowel and bladder problems, and sometimes infertility and miscarriage. For women of African descent, fibroids may develop at an earlier age and be more frequent and severe. Many women, particularly Black women, are likely to undergo hysterectomy to alleviate significant health issues.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/1664820_3928276_0023-200x300.jpg" alt="Dr. Elizabeth Stewart" class="wp-image-392000" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/1664820_3928276_0023-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/1664820_3928276_0023-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/1664820_3928276_0023-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/1664820_3928276_0023-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/1664820_3928276_0023-1365x2048.jpg 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Ebbie Stewart</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Uterine fibroids are so common that women tend to normalize the pain," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/stewart-ebbie-a-m-d/bio-00095802" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ebbie Stewart, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic gynecologist and researcher. "Further study is needed to fully understand the health disparities in diagnosis and treatment of fibroids. Improving care for all women and especially Black women is a key research goal."</p>



<p>The traditional approach to treating fibroids has been observation to avoid unnecessary intervention and hysterectomy for more serious cases. Understanding the barriers to wider use of conservative nonsurgical treatment options is needed.</p>



<p>Over many years, Dr. Stewart and collaborators have published extensive research on facets of  uterine fibroids that disproportionately affect the African American population, calling it a public health issue in a 2013 <a href="https://www.ajog.org/article/S0002-9378(13)00834-X/abstract">study</a> published in the American Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology. A 2021 <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s40615-021-01059-8" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> in the Journal of Racial Ethnic Health Disparities provides insight into the ethnoracial factors and cultural barriers that women of color experience in the management and treatment of uterine fibroids.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>New center to address a public health issue</strong></h2>



<p>To establish a specialized center for research on health disparities around uterine fibroids, Mayo Clinic was awarded a <a href="https://www.nichd.nih.gov/newsroom/news/062124-two-fibroid-research-centers" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">$7.5 million grant</a> from the <a href="https://www.nichd.nih.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development</a>, part of the NIH.</p>



<p>The new center at Mayo, named the Collaboration for Equity in Uterine Leiomyomas Center, will advance efforts to diagnose patients with fibroids earlier, identify barriers that make it difficult for patients to receive care, and increase communication between patients and healthcare providers, through the lens of health disparities. Dr. Stewart will lead the center’s effort and collaborate with researchers at the Fibroid Foundation; the University of Florida College of Medicine, Jacksonville; and the University of Mississippi Medical Center.</p>



<p>Community outreach is an important part of the project, including dissemination of material to women who suffer from fibroids and to healthcare providers, family members and policy makers. The collaboration involves researchers who participated in the COMPARE-UF fibroid registry project, a multicenter study to evaluate the effectiveness of different treatment strategies for uterine fibroids. Dr. Stewart was clinical leader of the <a href="https://www.ajog.org/article/S0002-9378(18)30396-X/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>, first published in 2018 in the American Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology.</p>



<p>Researchers will also explore strategies to see if electronic health records can help women with fibroids receive more timely care. The data will be used to develop risk prediction models to aid in screening for fibroids and in spotting signs of progression to hysterectomy following conservative therapy, and to improve diagnosis.</p>



<p>"We believe the findings of our research will impact every facet of uterine fibroid care and improve the experience for all women," says Dr. Stewart.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is one of two institutions to receive NIH funding to establish specialized centers for research on health disparities. The University of Michigan will lead the other center.</p>



<p>NIH grant <a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/notice-files/NOT-HD-23-017.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">RFA-HD-24-005</a>: Specialized Centers for Research on Health Disparities in Uterine Leiomyoma.</p>



<p><strong>Additional Resources:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treatment-for-uterine-fibroids-without-surgery/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Treatment for uterine fibroids without surgery</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-black-women-and-uterine-fibroids/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Black women and uterine fibroids</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-nonsurgical-treatment-for-uterine-fibroids/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Nonsurgical treatment for uterine fibroids</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/nih-award-supports-new-center-at-mayo-clinic-for-health-disparities-in-uterine-fibroid-treatment/">NIH award supports new center at Mayo Clinic for health disparities in uterine fibroid treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/a-medical-illustration-of-uterine-fibroids-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/a-medical-illustration-of-uterine-fibroids-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Ebbie Stewart]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Uterine Fibroids]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>What you need to know about listeria</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-you-need-to-know-about-listeria/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 17:54:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Infectious Diseases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nipunie Rajapakse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listeria]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=391897</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention has issued an alert after a listeria outbreak in several states. There have been at least two fatalities, and dozens have become sickened. Dr. Nipunie Rajapakse, a Mayo Clinic pediatric infectious diseases expert, discusses the risks associated with listeria. "Listeria is a type of bacteria that is usually [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-you-need-to-know-about-listeria/">What you need to know about listeria</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Deli-Meat-in-slicer-GettyImages-1169042625-16x9-1-1024x577.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-391924" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Deli-Meat-in-slicer-GettyImages-1169042625-16x9-1-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Deli-Meat-in-slicer-GettyImages-1169042625-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Deli-Meat-in-slicer-GettyImages-1169042625-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Deli-Meat-in-slicer-GettyImages-1169042625-16x9-1-1536x865.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Deli-Meat-in-slicer-GettyImages-1169042625-16x9-1-2048x1153.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/listeria/outbreaks/delimeats-7-24/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</a> has issued an alert after a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/listeria-infection/symptoms-causes/syc-20355269">listeria</a> outbreak in several states. There have been at least two fatalities, and dozens have become sickened.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/rajapakse-nipunie-s-m-d-m-p-h/bio-20308514" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Nipunie Rajapakse</a>, a Mayo Clinic pediatric infectious diseases expert, discusses the risks associated with listeria.</p>



<p>"Listeria is a type of bacteria that is usually transmitted through food and food products. It is especially a concern if you're pregnant, if you're elderly or if you have a weakened immune system for some reason," says Dr. Rajapakse.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/H68Rq00oQis" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Rajapakse talks about risks associated with listeria</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeH68Rq00oQis"  title="Dr. Nipunie Rajapakse - What is listeria and what are the symptoms?" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/H68Rq00oQis?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites with Dr. Rajapakse are available in the downloads at the end of the post. Name super/CG: Nipunie Rajapakse, M.D./Pediatric Infection Diseases/Mayo Clinic</strong></p>



<p>The contaminated food may be linked to sliced meats from deli counters. When it comes to deli meats and hot dogs, make sure they are cooked to 165 F. Fruits and vegetables should be washed well.</p>



<p>Dr. Rajapakse says listeria is a significant concern for people with compromised immune systems and pregnant women because of the risk of spreading it to the unborn child.</p>



<p>"It can have really severe outcomes for babies, including risks of stillbirth or death," says Dr. Rajapakse.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Meat-thermometer-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="meat thermometer, showing safe temperatures for food" class="wp-image-388329" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Meat-thermometer-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Meat-thermometer-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Meat-thermometer-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Meat-thermometer-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Meat-thermometer-16-x-9.jpg 1609w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Symptoms</strong></p>



<p>Symptoms of listeria can vary but may include fever, muscle aches, nausea, diarrhea, headache, stiff neck, confusion, loss of balance and convulsions. It also can cause a flu-like illness in pregnant women, joint aches and pains, and fatigue also can occur.</p>



<p>Contact your healthcare team if you suspect you have a foodborne illness.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-you-need-to-know-about-listeria/">What you need to know about listeria</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Deli-Meat-in-slicer-GettyImages-1169042625-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Deli-Meat-in-slicer-GettyImages-1169042625-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nipunie Rajapakse]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Listeria]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Pain relief for worn spinal disks</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/pain-relief-for-worn-spinal-disks/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Yannis Styliaras]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=391831</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The fluid-filled cushions between the bones in your spine are called disks. They provide flexibility, allow for spine movement like flexion and extension, and act as shock absorbers. Most young people have healthy disks. Each disk is flexible, with fluid-filled collagen fibers that fill the space between the vertebrae and provide the necessary cushion to [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/pain-relief-for-worn-spinal-disks/">Pain relief for worn spinal disks</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/farmer-bending-in-crop-field16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-391832" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/farmer-bending-in-crop-field16x9.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/farmer-bending-in-crop-field16x9-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></figure>



<p>The fluid-filled cushions between the bones in your spine are called disks. They provide flexibility, allow for spine movement like flexion and extension, and act as shock absorbers.</p>



<p>Most young people have healthy disks. Each disk is flexible, with fluid-filled collagen fibers that fill the space between the vertebrae and provide the necessary cushion to allow their spines to bend and flex fully without pain.</p>



<p>Disks can wear out with age and use, however, which causes the degeneration and dehydration of the collagen fibers. This is called degenerative disk disease, which usually is a slow degradation of disks over time. Here's what you need to know about this common condition.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Disk anatomy</h2>



<p>Understanding the structure or anatomy of disks is essential. There are 23 disks in the spinal column, running from the base of the skull to the tailbone.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Each disk is made up of two parts that work together to absorb and cushion the spine:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Annulus fibrosus</strong><br>This is the sturdy yet flexible outer layer of the disk. It forms a ring or circle around the inner core of the disk.</li>



<li><strong>Nucleus pulposus</strong><br>The center area of each disk is filled with a soft, gel-like substance that acts as the spine's shock absorber.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Degenerative disk disease causes</h2>



<p>Multiple factors cause degenerative disk disease, some of which can be controlled and others that cannot.</p>



<p>Age and time increase the odds of developing degenerative disk disease. About 20% of all U.S. adults have some amount of degeneration by age 65. This increases to about 35% by age 80. Sex plays a factor, as females are more likely than males to develop degenerative disk disease.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Contributing factors you can control include excess body weight and spine strain due to manual labor, poor posture and heavy lifting.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Degeneration progression</h2>



<p>Everyone has a degree of degeneration with time. It may or may not worsen or cause symptoms. Progression can be slow or fast, or the condition can remain stagnant.</p>



<p>As degenerative disk disease begins, the spinal disks start to lose fluidity. They become dehydrated and are less rubbery or soft. This leads to disk shrinking and a loss of disk height. Often, the disks that are low in the spine degenerate first.</p>



<p>As degeneration progresses further, the disks dry out even more or change shape, known as herniation. When this happens, they may begin pushing on nerves. A person may develop a ruptured or bulging disk.</p>



<p>A bulging disk happens when the outer layer of the disk, the annulus fibrosus, bulges into the spinal canal. A ruptured disk, sometimes called a herniated or slipped disk, happens when the inner part of the disk, the nucleus pulposus, leaks out of the disk through a crack in the annulus fibrosus.</p>



<p>Often, people have a bulging or ruptured disk with no symptoms, but sometimes, this can cause symptoms in one or both legs.&nbsp;</p>



<p>If a disk continues to degrade, it can result in a complete loss of the disk. Then, the person only has an air-filled space between the vertebrae or the bones of two vertebral bodies directly contact each other. A person with this level of progression can experience severe pain, stiffness and possibly nerve compression.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Degenerative disk disease treatment</h2>



<p>There are many treatment options for degenerative disk disease. Nonsurgical treatments are crucial throughout the continuum. Weight loss can be highly beneficial, along with decreasing manual labor to reduce stress on the spine. Injections, medications, physical therapy and strengthening your core can ease symptoms.</p>



<p>The majority of degenerative disc disease cases can successfully be treated with conservative treatment, including about 80% of acute radiculopathy, known as <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/sciatica-and-radiculopathy-peculiar-names" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">sciatica</a>.</p>



<p>Surgical intervention might be an option after nonsurgical treatments are exhausted first. A healthcare professional may recommend surgery if your condition is causing symptoms of nerve compression and these symptoms are progressing despite physical therapy, medications and injections. Symptoms from nerve compression may include pain, numbness or weakness that radiates into a limb. Surgery usually is not a good option for treating solely back pain from <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/pain-in-the-back-spinal-arthritis" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">osteoarthritis in the spine</a>.</p>



<p>Your healthcare team will explain other circumstances that might warrant surgery, such as when a disc herniation impinges the spinal cord or if there is severe weakness in an extremity, like foot drop.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Surgical options for degenerative disk disease include:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/understanding-types-of-back-surgery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Decompression surgery</a>, such as a laminectomy or diskectomy, relieves compression of the nerve root for the spinal cord.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/understanding-types-of-back-surgery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stabilization surgery</a>, such as a spinal fusion, improves stability by permanently connecting two or more vertebrae in the spine. It may be performed after a decompression surgery in certain cases.</li>



<li>Disk replacement surgery replaces a worn out disk with an artificial disk. Replacing a disk may help relieve pain in your arms or legs while maintaining motion and flexibility.</li>
</ul>



<p>Your healthcare team, including experts in pain management, physical medicine and rehabilitation, physical therapy and neurosurgery, will work together to tailor a treatment plan for you.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Next steps:</h2>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers?service=Neurosurgery&amp;populateTracking=True" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Find a neurosurgeon</a> near you.</li>



<li>Get <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/9-questions-to-ask-your-spine-surgeon" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">nine questions to ask your spine surgeon</a>.</li>



<li>Learn about <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/back-pain-self-care-tips" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">back pain self-care</a>.</li>



<li>Read about the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/not-all-low-back-pain-is-the-same" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">common causes of back pain</a>.</li>
</ul>



<p><em><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/yannis-styliaras-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Yannis Styliaras, M.D.</a>, is a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/neurosurgery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">neurosurgeon</a> in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/la-crosse" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">La Crosse</a>, Wisconsin.</em></p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/pain-relief-for-worn-spinal-disks" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/pain-relief-for-worn-spinal-disks/">Pain relief for worn spinal disks</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/farmer-bending-in-crop-field1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/farmer-bending-in-crop-field16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Yannis Styliaras]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Preventing traveler&#8217;s diarrhea</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-preventing-travelers-diarrhea/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jesse Bracamonte]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=389965</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Traveler's diarrhea&#160;is a common and uncomfortable digestive tract disorder that can affect people when they&#160;travel&#160;to new environments. According to the&#160;Centers for Disease Control and Prevention,&#160;up to 70% of travelers experience episodes. It's caused by eating contaminated food or water.&#160; Dr. Jesse Bracamonte, a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician, says traveler's diarrhea is not usually serious, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-preventing-travelers-diarrhea/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Preventing traveler&#8217;s diarrhea</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Travel-abroad-woman-eating-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="woman eating street food while traveling" class="wp-image-384515" style="width:834px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Travel-abroad-woman-eating-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Travel-abroad-woman-eating-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Travel-abroad-woman-eating-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Travel-abroad-woman-eating-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Travel-abroad-woman-eating-16-x-9.jpg 1824w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/travelers-diarrhea/symptoms-causes/syc-20352182" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Traveler's diarrhea</a>&nbsp;is a common and uncomfortable digestive tract disorder that can affect people when they&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/9-common-questions-about-vaccines-and-travel/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">travel</a>&nbsp;to new environments. According to the&nbsp;<a href="https://wwwnc.cdc.gov/travel/yellowbook/2024/preparing/travelers-diarrhea" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</a>,&nbsp;up to 70% of travelers experience episodes. It's caused by eating contaminated food or water.&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/bracamonte-jesse-d-d-o/bio-20432246" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Jesse Bracamonte</a>, a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician, says traveler's diarrhea is not usually serious, but can be highly unpleasant. He offers strategies to help you stay healthy and avoid it.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/_40H-zGTRdo" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutube40HzGTRdo"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Preventing traveler&#039;s diarrhea" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_40H-zGTRdo?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:58) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/SCRIPT-MCM-Travelers-diarrhea59.pdf">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>When you are on an adventure, the last thing you want is a bathroom emergency.</p>



<p>"When travelers are traveling abroad, they may experience traveler's diarrhea," says Dr. Bracamonte. "That usually is related to being exposed to bacteria,&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/norovirus-what-to-know-and-how-to-avoid-it/">viruses</a>&nbsp;or sometimes parasites when in a new country, and eating contaminated food or drinking contaminated water."</p>



<p>Symptoms can begin suddenly.</p>



<p>"Anywhere from loose, watery stools of up to like three stools per day; abdominal cramping; sometimes a low-grade fever; and sometimes nausea," explains Dr. Bracamonte.</p>



<p>Preventing illness is key. Start with eating properly cooked food and drinking sanitized water.</p>



<p>"There's an old adage: 'Cook it, boil it, peel it or forget it.'"</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Avoid traveler's diarrhea</h2>



<p></p>



<p>Whether on a cruise, eating at a buffet or from a street vendor, take precautions.</p>



<p>"Things that you can do to sometimes prevent it is drinking lots of fluids, making sure that you wash your hands adequately and, in some instances, having bismuth subsalicylate — either the pink tabs or the pink liquid — available sometimes helps," Dr. Bracamonte says.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Related posts:</strong></h2>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-wash-your-pets-food-and-water-bowls-to-prevent-salmonella/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Wash your pet’s food and water bowls to prevent salmonella</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/stay-healthy-abroad-why-you-should-see-a-travel-medicine-specialist-before-your-trip/">Stay healthy abroad: Why you should see a travel medicine specialist before your trip</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/hepatitis-b-vaccine-what-to-know-to-protect-yourself/">Hepatitis B vaccine: What to know to protect yourself</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-preventing-travelers-diarrhea/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Preventing traveler&#8217;s diarrhea</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/Multi-racial-man-with-stomach-pain-1-x1-square.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/Multi-racial-man-with-stomach-pain-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jesse Bracamonte]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-20/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jaynelle Ramon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=391823</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week. Can you prevent cancer with lifestyle changes? Nearly half of cancer deaths in the U.S. are associated with preventable risk factors — such as smoking and alcohol use — according to a new American Cancer Society study. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-20/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-2 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C9S75jbOShd/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="390441" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Man-pouring-water-on-head-GettyImages-2158556903-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-390441" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Man-pouring-water-on-head-GettyImages-2158556903-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Man-pouring-water-on-head-GettyImages-2158556903-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Man-pouring-water-on-head-GettyImages-2158556903-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Man-pouring-water-on-head-GettyImages-2158556903-16x9-1-1536x863.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Man-pouring-water-on-head-GettyImages-2158556903-16x9-1-2048x1151.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:ugcPost:7219053716354523137" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="624" height="351" data-id="333628" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/03/glioblastoma-illustration3-16-x-9_Fotor.jpg" alt="Medical illustration of glioblastoma, a type of brain tumor" class="wp-image-333628" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/03/glioblastoma-illustration3-16-x-9_Fotor.jpg 624w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/03/glioblastoma-illustration3-16-x-9_Fotor-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 624px) 100vw, 624px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C9VZ0ZoNZIy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img decoding="async" data-id="131432" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2015/05/shutterstock_221224405.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-131432" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C9U5NATNnA7/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="243485" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/shutterstock_299245511_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="closeup of a man smoking a cigarette in his mouth" class="wp-image-243485" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/shutterstock_299245511_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/shutterstock_299245511_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/shutterstock_299245511_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:ugcPost:7218767417022328832/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="391589" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-391589" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Larynx-transplant-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>
</figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week.</h2>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/can-you-prevent-cancer-with-lifestyle-changes/">Can you prevent cancer with lifestyle changes?</a></h2>



<p>Nearly half of cancer deaths in the U.S. are associated with preventable risk factors — such as smoking and alcohol use — according to a new American Cancer Society study. It's never too late to make lifestyle changes that can decrease your risk of cancer.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/teamwork-and-research-play-a-key-role-in-mayo-clinics-first-larynx-transplant/">Teamwork and research play a key role in Mayo Clinic's first larynx transplant</a></h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic envisions a day when regenerative science makes it possible to offer a total larynx transplant to anyone who needs one. The research team of David Lott, M.D., hopes to overcome a shortage of donor organs and minimize the need for lifelong drugs to prevent organ rejection.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-dangers-of-heat-related-illnesses/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Dangers of heat-related illnesses</a></h2>



<p>Scorching temperatures continue to blanket much of the U.S. in an ongoing summer heat wave. Prolonged exposure to both heat and humidity can lead to heat-related illnesses — from heat cramps to exhaustion to life-threatening heatstroke.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treatment-and-research-of-glioblastoma/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Treatment and research of glioblastoma</a></h2>



<p>Considered the most aggressive type of brain cancer, glioblastoma grows rapidly, destroying healthy tissue. Despite significant advances in surgery, chemotherapy, immunotherapy and radiation technology, the prognosis of glioblastoma remains poor.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-keeping-kids-safe-outside-during-summer-play/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Keeping kids safe outside during summer play</a></h2>



<p>Summer vacation for kids is well underway. From wearing bike helmets to keeping kids hydrated, Mayo Clinic's Dr. Steven Maher says there are a few things you can do to help keep kids safe during summer play. ⁠</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-20/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/shutterstock_299245511_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/web-top-5_07192024.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>