<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Health &amp; Wellness - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/health-and-wellness/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/health-and-wellness/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 13:11:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The W-Curve Model: Understanding a new college student&#8217;s experience</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/the-w-curve-model-understanding-a-new-college-students-experience/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 13:10:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[college freshmen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reese Druckenmiller]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[W-Curve Model]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=345798</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The W-Curve Model was first proposed in 1963 to explain adjustment to culture shock. Starting college is a culture shock for many young people. It is often the first time students are away from home for an extended period. Freshman year is known for new experiences, but it also presents various challenges. Each new college [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/the-w-curve-model-understanding-a-new-college-students-experience/">The W-Curve Model: Understanding a new college student&#8217;s experience</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/a-young-Black-teenage-boy-in-a-t-shirt-working-at-a-desk-with-a-notebook-and-a-pencil-perhaps-doing-homework-in-his-bedroom-or-college-dorm-room-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="a young Black teenage boy in a t-shirt working at a desk, with a notebook and a pencil, perhaps doing homework in his bedroom or college dorm room" class="wp-image-275438" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/a-young-Black-teenage-boy-in-a-t-shirt-working-at-a-desk-with-a-notebook-and-a-pencil-perhaps-doing-homework-in-his-bedroom-or-college-dorm-room-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/a-young-Black-teenage-boy-in-a-t-shirt-working-at-a-desk-with-a-notebook-and-a-pencil-perhaps-doing-homework-in-his-bedroom-or-college-dorm-room-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/a-young-Black-teenage-boy-in-a-t-shirt-working-at-a-desk-with-a-notebook-and-a-pencil-perhaps-doing-homework-in-his-bedroom-or-college-dorm-room-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/a-young-Black-teenage-boy-in-a-t-shirt-working-at-a-desk-with-a-notebook-and-a-pencil-perhaps-doing-homework-in-his-bedroom-or-college-dorm-room-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/a-young-Black-teenage-boy-in-a-t-shirt-working-at-a-desk-with-a-notebook-and-a-pencil-perhaps-doing-homework-in-his-bedroom-or-college-dorm-room-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The W-Curve Model was first proposed in 1963 to explain adjustment to culture shock. Starting college is a culture shock for many young people. It is often the first time students are away from home for an extended period.</p>



<p>Freshman year is known for new experiences, but it also presents various challenges. Each new college student's experience is unique. Parents should be aware of the predictable adjustment pattern to help students navigate difficult times.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The five stages of the W-Curve Model explain students' level of comfort, satisfaction and effectiveness during each stage:&nbsp;</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">1. Honeymoon: The excitement stage</h3>



<p>Often starting before students arrive at college, the honeymoon stage is full of excitement, stimulation and curiosity. There's increased enthusiasm to meet new people, and many cultural differences are intriguing.</p>



<p>Students desire independence and tend to lack homesickness during the first few days or weeks of college. New students are bombarded with events and activities, keeping the excitement level high.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">2. Culture Shock: Reality sets in</h3>



<p>At this stage, students may start to compare their expectations of college with reality. The differences that felt new and exciting start to feel isolating and overwhelming.</p>



<p>Students may feel lost and confused, noticing that the excitement of living on their own has worn off. Often, students will compare their experiences to others, finding that academic demands are more complex than anticipated.</p>



<p>Feeling homesick may lead students to wish to return home more often.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">3. Initial Adjustment: Settling into the demands of college life</h3>



<p>College gets better as students begin to manage experiences from culture shock. This can include making friends outside of their initial connections, developing a routine, gaining confidence in academic and social abilities, and finding one's roommate less bothersome.</p>



<p>This is when students start to reconnect to what they like about themselves and the new culture of college.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">4. Mental Isolation: Comparing home and college</h3>



<p>After students go home during an academic break, they may not feel as comfortable at home as they used to. Students may feel distressed at changes or events at home during their absence. This leads them to feel unsure about where they belong and miss the comfort that home used to provide. Beliefs and values are challenged as students attempt to find their place in the world.</p>



<p>At this time, peer conflicts may increase, and students may have a more tough time with roommates. Students in dating relationships that started in high school may have an increasingly hard time after seeing their partner during a break.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">5. Acceptance and Integration: Finally, balance emerges</h3>



<p>Students develop stronger ties to fellow students and faculty, get more involved in campus life, and understand how to succeed academically. Students often start referring to campus as their home and feel like a part of the culture. Roommate issues are addressed, and dependence on hometown connections begins to lessen. Students start to feel like an old hand at living the college life.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Making the first year of college a success</h2>



<p>The first year at college is not always easy. Being aware of the predictable adjustment pattern can make the transition less intimidating. If college is too overwhelming, help is always available, whether it's talking to a friend, family member, resident adviser, professor or a mental health professional. Understanding the W-Curve Model can help family members support their student’s success in college.</p>



<p>A version of this story was first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/the-w-curve-theory" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/the-w-curve-model-understanding-a-new-college-students-experience/">The W-Curve Model: Understanding a new college student&#8217;s experience</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/a-young-Black-teenage-boy-in-a-t-shirt-working-at-a-desk-with-a-notebook-and-a-pencil-perhaps-doing-homework-in-his-bedroom-or-college-dorm-room-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/a-young-Black-teenage-boy-in-a-t-shirt-working-at-a-desk-with-a-notebook-and-a-pencil-perhaps-doing-homework-in-his-bedroom-or-college-dorm-room-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[college freshmen]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Reese Druckenmiller]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[W-Curve Model]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Let&#8217;s talk low libido</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/lets-talk-low-libido/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Graham King]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[low libido]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=369507</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>It may feel uncomfortable to talk about low libido with your partner and your healthcare team. Unfortunately, it's a common problem that affects adults everywhere, yet many people have never been asked about their sexual health by their healthcare teams. Although it may be difficult to discuss, sexual health is important and factors that are [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/lets-talk-low-libido/">Let&#8217;s talk low libido</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/holding-hands-on-leg16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-369509" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/holding-hands-on-leg16x9.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/holding-hands-on-leg16x9-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></figure>



<p>It may feel uncomfortable to talk about low libido with your partner and your healthcare team. Unfortunately, it's a common problem that affects adults everywhere, yet many people have never been asked about their sexual health by their healthcare teams.</p>



<p>Although it may be difficult to discuss, sexual health is important and factors that are causing low libido should be addressed. Many primary care, psychology and OB-GYN professionals are trained to care for and treat hypoactive sexual desire disorder, or HSDD. This is the persistent or recurrent deficiency or absence of sexual fantasies and desire for sexual activity. It's often referred to as having a low libido and can cause significant distress and relationship problems.</p>



<p>There's no magic pill for low libido. The desire for sex is based on a complex interaction of many things that affect intimacy, including physical and emotional well-being, experiences, beliefs, lifestyle and relationship status. A thorough evaluation of your symptoms and possible causes, along with an individualized treatment plan, may put you in the mood more often.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Here's what you need to know about low libido.</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Low libido in men</h3>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Some of the most common causes of low libido in men include:</h4>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Physical issues</strong><br>Increased weight, diabetes, high blood pressure, endocrine disorders and high cholesterol can affect the&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/erectile-dysfunction/symptoms-causes/syc-20355776" target="_blank">ability to maintain an erection</a>&nbsp;or decrease sex drive. These conditions also can lead to low energy and low self-image which can cause a significant loss of libido. In many cases, this can be corrected through diet, exercise and medical management.</li>



<li><strong>Pornography</strong><br>This is a big cause for many men. Pornography permeates many committed relationships and can change how men view sexuality. For some, it causes pseudo-low libido, which is when a person is still interested in sex but not in a healthy way. This often leads to unrealistic expectations of body image, confusion about what an intimate encounter is and, in some cases, negative sexual behavior. The internet is a large contributor. Often, people who are committed to changing their behaviors are referred to sexual addiction counseling to manage this effectively.</li>



<li><strong>Loss of intimacy</strong><br>I'm always amazed at how dedicated and committed people are to their jobs, sports teams or extracurricular activities but treat relationships like a given, self-maintaining entity. This simply isn't the right approach. Relationships, intimacy and sexual health require work and effort. In many cases, a lack of emotional connection can lead to low libido in both partners.</li>



<li><strong>Medications</strong><br>Many medications used for anxiety and depression can lower libido in men and, in some cases, delay orgasm. While some men have no side effects, others may encounter significant issues. It's important to note that you should not stop taking any medication without first talking with your healthcare team.</li>



<li><strong>Alcohol and drug use</strong><br>Increased alcohol use can reduce testosterone levels and increase the risk of erectile dysfunction and low libido. Illicit drugs often increase sex drive in the short term but have significant long-term negative effects on sexual function. Depending on the substance, drug use can cause a decrease in testosterone levels and erectile dysfunction or change how the brain responds to activities that were previously viewed as pleasurable, like sex.</li>
</ul>



<p>Remember, the answer to treating a low libido is more than turning to medications. Acknowledging there's an issue and seeking professional help can be the start of getting back something great.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Low libido in women</h3>



<p>The issue of&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/low-sex-drive-in-women/symptoms-causes/syc-20374554" target="_blank">low libido in women</a>&nbsp;is even more complex, with causes ranging from past negative and abusive experiences with sex to fatigue and stress.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">The most common causes of low libido in women include:</h4>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Life stressors and fatigue</strong><br>After growing their families, many women are not only weeks behind on quality sleep but also haven't exercised in months and eat only when they can find a spare second. It's no wonder they say that they feel exhausted and sexually dead. They often confide that they don't feel like they could have a sexual or intimate encounter even after a long time.</li>



<li><strong>Medications</strong><br>Depression and anxiety lead to lowered libido. Yet, medications to treat these conditions could be making it worse or even causing it. This isn't a reason to stop taking an important medication, but it's definitely a topic to discuss with a sexual health specialist.</li>



<li><strong>Weight gain</strong><br>Weight gain can lead to low energy, negative self-image and loss of intimacy with your significant other.</li>



<li><strong>Hormone changes</strong><br>Estrogen levels drop during menopause and can greatly affect libido. It can cause vaginal dryness and lead to painful or uncomfortable sex. While not as common, hormonal contraceptives also can cause lower libido. In some women, they cause vaginal irritation which leads to a decreased willingness to initiate a sexual experience.</li>



<li><strong>Sexual pain or dyspareunia</strong><br>If it hurts, why would you do it? The good news is that pain during sex can often be treated. The first step is to be evaluated by a sexual health specialist who will recommend a treatment plan, which could include a referral to a psychology specialist or pelvic floor physical therapist.</li>



<li><strong>Relationship issues</strong><br>For many women, emotional closeness is essential for sexual intimacy. Problems in the relationship like a lack of connection, unresolved conflicts or trust issues can be a major contributor to a low sex drive.</li>



<li><strong>Previous trauma</strong><br>Previous physical or emotional trauma can affect the way people experience sex and lead to low libido. Sexual desire and arousal often are numbed in people who have been physically or sexually abused. Women who have been abused often avoid sexual contact because the neural networks in their brains associate sex with power, fear or pain. This makes intimacy difficult. Even a previous consensual, yet negative, sexual experience can reduce a woman's desire for sex in the future.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How to get help for low libido</h2>



<p>First, talk with a health care professional who specializes in and has been trained in treating sexual health. Your primary care provider will be able to recommend a trusted expert.&nbsp;</p>



<p>During your first appointment, the provider will conduct a comprehensive health history, evaluation and physical exam. Blood tests may be necessary to check hormone levels and check for thyroid problems, liver disorders or other conditions.</p>



<p>Treatment plans focus on the many causes of low libido. Sex education and counseling may be recommended, especially to address relationship issues. Medication and hormone therapy options are available to boost libido.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Tips to combat low libido</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Healthy lifestyle changes can make a difference and combat low libido:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Start an exercise program.</strong><br>Regular aerobic exercise and strength training can increase your stamina, improve your body image, lift your mood and boost your libido.</li>



<li><strong>Plan a trip — but leave the kids at home.</strong><br>Take a dedicated vacation for just yourself or with your significant other. Don't go with other couples. This can be a distraction as you look to reconnect. Setting aside time for intimacy can help put your sex drive back on track.</li>



<li><strong>Communicate.</strong><br>Yes, something as simple as sitting across from each other at a restaurant as you start to communicate again can do wonders. Make sure you keep topics light and have no expectation of an encounter later. Let the moment simply be about spending time with each other.</li>



<li><strong>Reduce stress.</strong><br>Find ways as a couple to better cope with work and home stress. Are there chores that can be stopped or done by someone else or commitments that can be skipped? Seek out&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/5-tips-to-manage-stress">ways to reduce stress</a>&nbsp;in daily life.</li>



<li><strong>Ditch bad habits.</strong><br>Smoking, illegal drugs and excess alcohol can all dampen your sex drive. Ditching these bad habits may help give your sex drive a boost and improve your overall health.</li>
</ul>



<p>People don't have to meet a specific medical definition or wait for low libido to worsen before seeking help. If you are bothered by low or decreased sex drive, there are changes and treatments that can move you in the right direction.</p>



<p><em><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/graham-king-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Graham King, M.D.</a>, is a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/family-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Family Medicine</a>&nbsp;physician specializing in sexual and women's health in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/mankato" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mankato</a>, Minnesota.</em></p>



<p>This article also appears on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/lets-talk-low-libido" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/lets-talk-low-libido/">Let&#8217;s talk low libido</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/holding-hands-on-leg1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/holding-hands-on-leg16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Graham King]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[low libido]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-28/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jaynelle Ramon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 12:56:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=394001</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week. Mayo Clinic Minute: What is whooping cough? The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) says cases of pertussis, also known as whooping cough, are on the rise. Roughly four times as many cases of pertussis have [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-28/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/706347941527986/posts/926841232811988" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img decoding="async" width="1000" height="562" data-id="190368" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/05/shutterstock_70876759_Fotor-16x9.jpg" alt="a happy looking senior couple walking with their bicycles" class="wp-image-190368" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/05/shutterstock_70876759_Fotor-16x9.jpg 1000w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/05/shutterstock_70876759_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/05/shutterstock_70876759_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C_041c-P-vs/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="393679" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Blood-Draw1-16x9-1-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-393679" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Blood-Draw1-16x9-1-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Blood-Draw1-16x9-1-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Blood-Draw1-16x9-1-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Blood-Draw1-16x9-1-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Blood-Draw1-16x9-1.png 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://x.com/MayoClinic/status/1835755736061636713" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" data-id="392312" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Nurse-Helping-patient-GettyImages-1473157220-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-392312" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Nurse-Helping-patient-GettyImages-1473157220-16x9-1.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Nurse-Helping-patient-GettyImages-1473157220-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Nurse-Helping-patient-GettyImages-1473157220-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=2307163922982101" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="393925" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Whooping-Cough-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-393925" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Whooping-Cough-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Whooping-Cough-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Whooping-Cough-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Whooping-Cough-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Whooping-Cough-16x9-1.jpg 1728w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DAB-k5ZqKwb/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="393876" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Til-Therapy1-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-393876" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Til-Therapy1-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Til-Therapy1-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Til-Therapy1-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Til-Therapy1-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Til-Therapy1-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>
</figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week.</h3>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-whooping-cough/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What is whooping cough?</a></h2>



<p>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) says cases of pertussis, also known as whooping cough, are on the rise. Roughly four times as many cases of pertussis have been reported in 2024 compared to the same time last year.⁠</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-til-therapy/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What is TIL therapy?</a></h2>



<p>Approximately 100,000 people in the U.S. will be diagnosed with melanoma this year, according to the American Cancer Society. A new treatment for advanced melanoma is called tumor-infiltrating lymphocyte therapy (TIL therapy).⁠</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-lifespan-vs-healthspan/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Lifespan vs. healthspan</a></h2>



<p>Lifespan refers to the total number of years a person lives, from birth to death. Healthspan is a concept that focuses on the number of those years that a person remains free of significant illness or disease. With lifespan, people are trying to add years to life. For healthspan, we are trying to add life to your years.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-you-should-know-about-prostate-cancer-screening/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What you should know about prostate cancer screening</a></h2>



<p>The prostate is a small gland in males that aids in reproduction. Prostate cancer is one the most common types of cancer, and when it's detected early, often by a simple blood test, it has the best chance for successful treatment. </p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-palliative-medicine-for-cancer-patients/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Palliative medicine for cancer patients</a></h2>



<p>Palliative medicine is a medical specialty whose main focus is supporting patients and families/caregivers who need help managing symptoms related to cancer or side effects related to the treatment of cancer, along with other life-limiting diseases.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-28/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Til-Therapy1-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/web-top-5_09202024.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: What is whooping cough?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-whooping-cough/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 14:19:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Infectious Diseases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jesse Bracamonte]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pertussis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whooping Cough]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=393776</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) says cases of pertussis, also known as whooping cough, are on the rise. The U.S. is beginning to return to the level of cases reported before the COVID-19 pandemic. The CDC says roughly four times as many cases of pertussis have been reported in 2024 compared to [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-whooping-cough/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What is whooping cough?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/pertussis/outbreaks/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)</a> says cases of pertussis, also known as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/whooping-cough/symptoms-causes/syc-20378973?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">whooping cough</a>, are on the rise. The U.S. is beginning to return to the level of cases reported before the COVID-19 pandemic. The CDC says roughly <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/pertussis/php/surveillance/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">four times as many cases of pertussis</a> have been reported in 2024 compared to the same time last year.</p>



<p>In this Mayo Clinic Minute, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/bracamonte-jesse-d-d-o/bio-20432246?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Jesse Bracamonte</a>, a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician, explains what whooping cough is and how to prevent it.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/KB0Z20VCQLw" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeKB0Z20VCQLw"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - What is whooping cough?" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/KB0Z20VCQLw?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:08) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/MCM_Whooping-cough.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></strong></p>



<p>It's the heart-wrenching sound of a young child with the highly contagious respiratory illness known as whooping cough.</p>



<p>"It's caused by the bacteria known as Bordetella pertussis. It gets the name whooping cough, typically, due to the characteristic cough or the "whoop" that, typically, children make," says Dr. Bracamonte.</p>



<p>He says that "whoop" sound is created when attempting to take in a breath after a severe hacking cough.</p>



<p>"Fortunately, there's a vaccine available for infants and children and adults to get immunized to prevent the Bordetella pertussis from occurring. It decreases the risk of transmission and protects your overall immunity," says Dr. Bracamonte.</p>



<p>The CDC recommends all young children should receive the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements/diphtheria-tetanus-and-acellular-pertussis-vaccine-intramuscular-route/description/drg-20071366?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">DTaP</a> vaccine in a series of five vaccinations at ages 2 months, 4 months, 6 months, 15 to 18 months, and 4 to 6 years. Adolescents, adults and anyone who is pregnant should have a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements/diphtheria-tetanus-and-acellular-pertussis-booster-vaccine-intramuscular-route/description/drg-20122575?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tdap</a> booster vaccination.</p>



<p>"I think this vaccine is very important for kids because, in most cases, the more severe illness of whooping cough affects children or younger children, particularly under a year of age, where sometimes hospitalization can occur," says Dr. Bracamonte.</p>



<p><strong>Additional Resources:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/understanding-whooping-cough-with-a-mayo-clinic-expert/">Understanding whooping cough with a Mayo Clinic expert</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/whooping-cough-pertussis-is-a-highly-contagious-respiratory-tract-infection/">Whooping cough (pertussis) is a highly contagious respiratory tract infection</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-whooping-cough/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What is whooping cough?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Whooping-Cough-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Whooping-Cough-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jesse Bracamonte]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Pertussis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Whooping Cough]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Palliative medicine for cancer patients</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-palliative-medicine-for-cancer-patients/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Toure Barksdale]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=392295</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Patients undergoing cancer treatments often use palliative medicine to cope with nausea, fatigue and other bothersome symptoms. Palliative medicine is a medical specialty whose main focus is supporting patients and families/caregivers who need help managing symptoms related to cancer or side effects related to the treatment of cancer, along with other life-limiting diseases. Dr. Touré [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-palliative-medicine-for-cancer-patients/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Palliative medicine for cancer patients</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Patients undergoing cancer treatments often use palliative medicine to cope with nausea, fatigue and other bothersome symptoms.</p>



<p>Palliative medicine is a medical specialty whose main focus is supporting patients and families/caregivers who need help managing symptoms related to cancer or side effects related to the treatment of cancer, along with other life-limiting diseases.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/barksdale-toure-m-d/bio-20517681">Dr. Touré Barksdale</a>, a Mayo Clinic cancer rehabilitation and palliative medicine specialist, explains the benefits of palliative care.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/wO0fIVPiCfM" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubewO0fIVPiCfM"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Palliative medicine for cancer patients" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wO0fIVPiCfM?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:03) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please "Courtesy: Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/SCRIPT-jthEDITS_MCM-palliative-care-version-1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Patients with cancer not only have to worry about fighting the disease, but they also must battle the cumbersome side effects, like fatigue and other symptoms related to cancer and its treatment.</p>



<p>"Side effects from cancer and treatment of cancer, such as pain, delirium, nausea, vomiting and debility, can also contribute to their cancer-related fatigue," says Dr. Barksdale.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Palliative care provides relief </h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/01/shutterstock_256121824_Fotor-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="a group of people, athletes outside in a park stretching and exercising, perhaps doing yoga or Tai chi" class="wp-image-260270" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/01/shutterstock_256121824_Fotor-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/01/shutterstock_256121824_Fotor-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/01/shutterstock_256121824_Fotor-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/01/shutterstock_256121824_Fotor-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/01/shutterstock_256121824_Fotor-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Tai Chi is often used in palliative medicine. </figcaption></figure>



<p>Palliative medicine is a crucial component of cancer treatment. Its main purpose is to improve the patient's overall well-being.</p>



<p>"Whether that's more holistic care through integrative and complementary medicine, more Western-based medicines, psychological care, music therapy, aromatherapy, Reiki, tai chi — we have lots of things we can do to help reduce suffering," explains Dr. Barksdale.</p>



<p>Palliative care is not the same as hospice care. The latter focuses on making patients comfortable and managing symptoms nearing the end of life when further curative treatments are no longer available.</p>



<p>"Palliative care, to me, is hope because what we're doing is we're improving your quality of life," says Dr. Barksdale.</p>



<p>This type of care is available at any stage of cancer treatment.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Related Content:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/transforming-cancer-care-with-treatments-at-home/">Transforming cancer care with treatments at home</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-creating-an-advance-directive-for-your-future-well-being/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Creating an advance directive for your future well-being</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-palliative-medicine-for-cancer-patients/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Palliative medicine for cancer patients</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Nurse-Helping-patient-GettyImages-1473157220_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2015/03/shutterstock_239820817.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Toure Barksdale]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Participate in Mayo Clinic Health System&#8217;s upcoming Transforming Community and Rural Healthcare 2024 symposium</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/participate-in-mayo-clinic-health-systems-upcoming-transforming-community-and-rural-healthcare-2024-symposium/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rural healthcare]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=393710</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic Health System will hold its second annual national symposium, Transforming Community and Rural Healthcare 2024: Inspiring Partnerships and Scaling Collaborative Impact, Oct. 21–22 at the Mayo Civic Center in Rochester, Minnesota, and by livestream. This unique event will bring together healthcare professionals, community organizations, educators and researchers. Presentations and discussions will address the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/participate-in-mayo-clinic-health-systems-upcoming-transforming-community-and-rural-healthcare-2024-symposium/">Participate in Mayo Clinic Health System&#8217;s upcoming Transforming Community and Rural Healthcare 2024 symposium</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="938" height="528" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Farm-couple-looking-over-fields-GettyImages-182939490_16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-388422" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Farm-couple-looking-over-fields-GettyImages-182939490_16x9.jpg 938w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Farm-couple-looking-over-fields-GettyImages-182939490_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Farm-couple-looking-over-fields-GettyImages-182939490_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 938px) 100vw, 938px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Getty Images</figcaption></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic Health System will hold its second annual national symposium, <a href="https://ce.mayo.edu/family-medicine/content/transforming-community-and-rural-healthcare-2024-inspiring-partnerships-and-scaling?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=generic&amp;utm_medium=e&amp;utm_content=organiccpd&amp;utm_campaign=medprof&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;cauid=104475&amp;elqTrackId=D870A4E9AAF489B00216E0B38782E02E&amp;elq=dd37d86a0c304ef796f11089ad1c7bb8&amp;elqaid=18163&amp;elqat=1&amp;elqCampaignId=10037" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Transforming Community and Rural Healthcare 2024: Inspiring Partnerships and Scaling Collaborative Impact</a>, Oct. 21<em>–</em>22 at the Mayo Civic Center in Rochester, Minnesota, and by livestream.</p>



<p>This unique event will bring together healthcare professionals, community organizations, educators and researchers. Presentations and discussions will address the most pressing healthcare issues facing&nbsp;rural America, including workforce shortages, challenges in coordination of care, behavioral health and health equity, and how community partnerships can help address these issues. &nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Calvin-Andrew-D._14765101_20240718-1-240x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-393712" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Calvin-Andrew-D._14765101_20240718-1-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Calvin-Andrew-D._14765101_20240718-1.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Andrew Calvin, M.D., M.P.H.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p></p>



<p>“Partnering together with community organizations, researchers, educators and other experts in rural healthcare delivery is the only way we can transform healthcare in our communities. Everyone deserves the best healthcare possible, and we hope to continue to work toward that goal," says Dr. Andrew Calvin, chair of Education for Mayo Clinic Health System. “Together, we can drive meaningful change that strengthens the health of rural communities across the country.”</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Event details</strong></h2>



<p>Session topics and speakers include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>“A conversation with the experts: Health policy and partnerships” </strong><ul><li><em>Tina Freese Decker, president and CEO of Corewell Health; chair-elect of the American Hospital Association</em></li></ul>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><em>Jim Snee, chairman of the board, president and CEO of Hormel Foods</em></li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>“National landscape of artificial intelligence” </strong><em>Dr. John Halamka, president of Mayo Clinic Platform </em></li>



<li><strong>“Advancing health equity in our rural communities” </strong><em>Dr. MayKao Y. Hang, vice president of strategic initiatives and founding dean of the Morrison Family College of Health, University of St. Thomas</em></li>



<li><strong>“Building a resilient rural healthcare workforce” </strong><em>Dr. Santo Cruz, senior vice president and chief legal officer of CentraCare</em></li>



<li><strong>“Partnering to promote food security in rural communities” </strong><ul><li><em>Dr. Craig Gundersen, Snee Family Endowed Chair, Baylor Collaborative on Hunger and Poverty</em></li></ul><ul><li><em>Jim Snee, chairman of the board, president and CEO of Hormel Foods</em></li></ul>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><em>Tammy Snee, registered nurse and community advocate, Hometown Food Security Project</em></li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>“Addressing diversity in cancer prevention, control and survivorship within rural communities” </strong><ul><li><em>Dr. Mark Doescher, Oklahoma University Health</em></li></ul><ul><li><em>Dr. Electra D. Paskett, distinguished professor and director of the Division of Cancer Prevention and Control in the Ohio State University College of Medicine</em></li></ul><ul><li><em>Dr. Wade T. Swenson, medical director of Lakewood Health System</em></li></ul><ul><li><em>Dr. Katherine Tossas, assistant professor and Harrison Endowed Scholar in Cancer Research Virginia Commonwealth University School of Medicine and Massey Cancer Center</em></li></ul>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><em>Dr. Robin C. Vanderpool, chief of the Health Communication and Informatics Research Branch of the National Cancer Institute</em></li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>“Rural healthcare looking forward” </strong><ul><li><em>Eric Borgerding, president and CEO of the Wisconsin Hospital Association</em></li></ul><ul><li><em>Lisa A. McConnell, chief nursing officer, Mayo Clinic Health System</em></li></ul>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><em>Zora Radosevich, director of the Office of Rural Health and Primary Care, Minnesota Department of Health</em></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<p>The course is eligible for continuing medical education credit. <em>Visit the </em><a href="https://ce.mayo.edu/family-medicine/content/transforming-community-and-rural-healthcare-2024-inspiring-partnerships-and-scaling?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=generic&amp;utm_medium=e&amp;utm_content=organiccpd&amp;utm_campaign=medprof&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;cauid=104475&amp;elqTrackId=D870A4E9AAF489B00216E0B38782E02E&amp;elq=dd37d86a0c304ef796f11089ad1c7bb8&amp;elqaid=18163&amp;elqat=1&amp;elqCampaignId=10037" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">course website</a><em> for more information and to register.</em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/participate-in-mayo-clinic-health-systems-upcoming-transforming-community-and-rural-healthcare-2024-symposium/">Participate in Mayo Clinic Health System&#8217;s upcoming Transforming Community and Rural Healthcare 2024 symposium</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Farm-couple-looking-over-fields-GettyImages-182939490_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Farm-couple-looking-over-fields-GettyImages-182939490_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Rural healthcare]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Lifespan vs. healthspan</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-lifespan-vs-healthspan/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Abby Smith]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nathan LeBrasseur]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=393716</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Editors Note: September is Healthy Aging Awareness Month DEAR MAYO CLINIC: I've been hearing a lot lately about healthspan versus lifespan when it comes to aging. What do they each mean? And what is the difference? ANSWER: We get a lot of questions about what distinguishes between lifespan and healthspan. The simplest answer is to [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-lifespan-vs-healthspan/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Lifespan vs. healthspan</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1000" height="562" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/05/shutterstock_70876759_Fotor-16x9.jpg" alt="a happy looking senior couple walking with their bicycles" class="wp-image-190368" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/05/shutterstock_70876759_Fotor-16x9.jpg 1000w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/05/shutterstock_70876759_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/05/shutterstock_70876759_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" /></figure>



<p><strong><em>Editors Note: September is Healthy Aging Awareness Month</em></strong></p>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> I've been hearing a lot lately about healthspan versus lifespan when it comes to aging. What do they each mean? And what is the difference?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong> We get a lot of questions about what distinguishes between lifespan and healthspan. The simplest answer is to paraphrase a quote from President John F. Kennedy, "It is not enough for a great nation merely to have added new years to life — our objective must also be to add new life to those years." With lifespan, people are trying to add years to life. For healthspan, we are trying to add life to your years. We are trying to optimize the number of active, healthy and productive years that you enjoy. Lifespan refers to the total number of years a person lives, from birth to death. Healthspan is a concept that focuses on the number of those years that a person remains free of significant illness or disease.</p>



<p>The <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-arlene-kogod-center-aging" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Robert and Arlene Kogod Center on Aging</a> at Mayo Clinic aims to improve healthspan through understanding the fundamental biological mechanisms of aging. It has dedicated research programs on musculoskeletal, cardiovascular, neurological, immunological and metabolic health. The intent is to better understand the aging process to come up with interventions that have the potential to delay the onset of age-related diseases as a group. Whether it's <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/alzheimers-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350447" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alzheimer's disease</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-failure/symptoms-causes/syc-20373142" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart failure</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiovascular disease</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stroke/symptoms-causes/syc-20350113" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stroke</a>, impaired bone health or kidney or liver function, most conditions or diseases are a result of getting older. In contrast to managing one disease at a time, targeting aging itself has the potential to postpone the onset of age-related diseases, extend healthspan and <em>reduce the length of disease and disability</em> in our final days.</p>



<p>There is a lot of interest surrounding the biology of aging. We often question what it is about getting older that leads to so many different health conditions ranging from osteoporosis to dementia, cancer and diabetes. We're starting to understand the biology of aging and how it contributes to these processes. One fundamental aspect of aging is a cell fate called senescence. A cell can become senescent in response to different forms of wear and tear on our cells. If a cell is unable to repair the damage, it can either die or transition into a state of senescence. Senescent cells, in a way, are a good thing because they help prevent the growth and spread of tumors. When we are young, they are effectively cleared by our immune system. But if they linger, they start contributing to deterioration, inflammation and age-related conditions. But they tend to accumulate as we age and if they linger, they start contributing to the deterioration and inflammation of tissues and cause age-related conditions.</p>



<p>As much as we're searching for the "magic pill," our studies show that lifestyle factors such as physical activity, healthy nutritional habits, social connectedness and sleep profoundly affect how well we age and extend our healthspan. What we've shown in our studies is that higher levels of physical activity and reduced calories while maintaining adequate nutrition have the potential to reduce the number and burden of the cells. Taking care of your body and incorporating some of these fundamental activities can improve your lifespan and build a foundation for healthy aging. <em>— </em><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/lebrasseur-nathan-k-ph-d-m-s/bio-20055350" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Nathan LeBrasseur, Ph.D.</strong></a><strong><em>, Director of the </em></strong><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-arlene-kogod-center-aging" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Robert and Arlene Kogod Center on Aging</strong></a><strong><em>, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota</em></strong></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-lifespan-vs-healthspan/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Lifespan vs. healthspan</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/08/two-senior-citizens-elderly-couple-walking-down-a-road-or-path-1x1-square.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/08/two-senior-citizens-elderly-couple-walking-down-a-road-or-path-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nathan LeBrasseur]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>(Video)Keeping an eye on avian influenza</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/videokeeping-an-eye-on-avian-influenza/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Infectious Diseases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[avian influenza]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bird flu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Binnicker]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=393644</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) has confirmed that a person from Missouri has become the 14th person in the U.S. to contract avian influenza, also called bird flu. This is believed to be the first case where the patient had no known contact with infected animals. "Why is this concerning? Because the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/videokeeping-an-eye-on-avian-influenza/">(Video)Keeping an eye on avian influenza</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Canada-Geese-16x9-GettyImages-172935907-1024x577.jpg" alt="Canada geese flying in formation, blue sky" class="wp-image-385420" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Canada-Geese-16x9-GettyImages-172935907-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Canada-Geese-16x9-GettyImages-172935907-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Canada-Geese-16x9-GettyImages-172935907-768x433.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Canada-Geese-16x9-GettyImages-172935907-1536x866.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Canada-Geese-16x9-GettyImages-172935907.jpg 1736w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Getty Images</figcaption></figure>



<p>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) has confirmed that a person from Missouri has become the 14<sup>th</sup> person in the U.S. to contract <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/bird-flu/symptoms-causes/syc-20568390" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">avian influenza</a>, also called bird flu. This is believed to be the first case where the patient had no known contact with infected animals.</p>



<p>"Why is this concerning? Because the more we see avian influenza move from a bird virus to a virus that can infect and be transmitted among mammals, the higher the concern of a virus gaining the ability to be efficiently spread from one human to another and cause serious disease," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/binnicker-matthew-j-ph-d/bio-20513862" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Matthew Binnicker</a>, director of the Clinical Virology Laboratory at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/cgwlA_WxyNU" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Matthew Binnicker discusses avian influenza</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubecgwlAWxyNU"  title="Keeping an eye on avian influenza" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cgwlA_WxyNU?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites are available in the downloads at the bottom of the posts. Name super/CG: Matthew Binnicker, Ph.D./Laboratory Medicine and Pathology/Mayo Clinic</strong></p>



<p>The good news, he adds, is that health officials are better prepared to respond to an avian influenza outbreak than they were to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/coronavirus/symptoms-causes/syc-20479963" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">COVID-19</a>, which was a brand-new virus. Bird flu has been recognized for several decades. Dr. Binnicker says that there is a candidate vaccine already available, which the CDC can share with vaccine manufacturers for rapid distribution.</p>



<p>When it comes to treatment, Dr. Binnicker says the world is also better prepared for bird flu compared to COVID-19. "The antivirals that we have to treat normal human influenza also seem to be effective at treating avian influenza," he says.</p>



<p>Dr. Binnicker says a lot was learned from the COVID-19 pandemic, including how to control the spread of respiratory disease by: "staying home if you're sick, wearing a mask if you go out in public, getting vaccinated against normal seasonal influenza, so there's no confusion about what virus you might be infected with."</p>



<p><strong>Additional Resources:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/monitoring-the-h5n1-avian-influenza-bird-flu-outbreak/">Monitoring the H5N1 avian influenza, bird flu, outbreak</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-virologist-offers-perspective-on-avian-influenza-bird-flu-outbreak/">Mayo Clinic virologist offers perspective on avian influenza, bird flu, outbreak</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/what-you-need-to-know-about-the-avian-influenza-outbreak/">What you need to know about the avian influenza outbreak</a><div class="wp-block-post-author__content" style="text-align: center"></div></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/videokeeping-an-eye-on-avian-influenza/">(Video)Keeping an eye on avian influenza</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Canada-Geese-1x1-GettyImages-172935907.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Canada-Geese-16x9-GettyImages-172935907.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[avian influenza]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[bird flu]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Binnicker]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-27/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jaynelle Ramon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=393685</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week. Mayo Clinic Minute: What does a diagnosis of dense breasts mean? Studies have shown that dense breast tissue can make it more difficult to detect breast cancer early. Women with dense breast tissue are at a slightly [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-27/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-2 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:ugcPost:7238985080516329472" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="393522" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Proton-Beam-Heart-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-393522" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Proton-Beam-Heart-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Proton-Beam-Heart-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Proton-Beam-Heart-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Proton-Beam-Heart-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Proton-Beam-Heart-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://x.com/MayoClinic/status/1832207304667668821" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" data-id="377373" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/knee_16x9_GettyImages-1148111603.png" alt="A black woman holds her sore knee." class="wp-image-377373" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/knee_16x9_GettyImages-1148111603.png 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/knee_16x9_GettyImages-1148111603-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/knee_16x9_GettyImages-1148111603-768x432.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/MayoClinic/videos/549614397727379" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="393607" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Flu-shots-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-393607" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Flu-shots-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Flu-shots-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Flu-shots-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Flu-shots-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Flu-shots-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C_vyvP1iBBp/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="319507" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2-1024x576.jpg" alt="a Black woman in a patient gown being prepared by a medical assistant for a breast mammogram" class="wp-image-319507" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-16x9-2.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C_i6yF4vVeC/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="392988" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Infusion-advanced-prostate-cancer-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Patient receiving treatment for advanced prostate cancer" class="wp-image-392988" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Infusion-advanced-prostate-cancer-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Infusion-advanced-prostate-cancer-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Infusion-advanced-prostate-cancer-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Infusion-advanced-prostate-cancer-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Infusion-advanced-prostate-cancer-16-x-9.jpg 1824w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>
</figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week.</h2>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-does-a-diagnosis-of-dense-breasts-mean/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What does a diagnosis of dense breasts mean?</a></h2>



<p>Studies have shown that dense breast tissue can make it more difficult to detect breast cancer early. Women with dense breast tissue are at a slightly increased risk of developing breast cancer compared to women without, and that's why early detection is so important.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-new-hope-for-patients-with-metastatic-prostate-cancer/">New hope for patients with metastatic prostate cancer</a></h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic is leading the way with a new treatment for advanced prostate cancer, specifically for prostate-specific membrane antigen-positive metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer (PSMA-positive mCRPC).</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-using-proton-beam-therapy-on-the-heart/">Using proton beam therapy on the heart</a></h2>



<p>Experts at Mayo Clinic recently completed the first clinical trial in humans using proton beam therapy, a type of radiation, to treat patients with potentially life-threatening arrhythmias. And they say initial results are encouraging.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-when-is-it-time-for-a-knee-replacement/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: When is it time for a knee replacement?</a></h2>



<p>When diagnosed with knee osteoarthritis, several treatment options are available. In general, nonoperative treatment is recommended first. Knee replacement is indicated when patients have tried several nonoperative treatments and they are no longer working.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-prepare-for-the-2024-25-influenza-season/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How to prepare for the 2024-25 influenza season</a></h2>



<p>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) recently recently released updated 2024-25 vaccine recommendations for the upcoming influenza season. As always, it's strongly recommended that everyone 6 months of age and older get vaccinated for influenza.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-27/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/09/a-Black-woman-in-a-patient-gown-being-prepared-by-a-medical-assistant-for-a-breast-mammogram-1x1-.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/web-top-5_09132024.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Consider TIME when dealing with sepsis</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/symptoms-of-sepsis/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Abby Smith]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 14:10:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Melissa Myers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=393609</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Editors Note: September is Sepsis Awareness Month DEAR MAYO CLINIC: My 86-year-old father was recently hospitalized with a severe infection. We were told he's at an increased risk for sepsis because of his age and medical history. What are the signs of sepsis to watch for now that he's returned home? ANSWER: Nearly 270,000 people [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/symptoms-of-sepsis/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Consider TIME when dealing with sepsis</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/a-medical-illustration-of-sepsis-16X9.jpg" alt="a medical illustration of sepsis" class="wp-image-222682" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/a-medical-illustration-of-sepsis-16X9.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/a-medical-illustration-of-sepsis-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></figure>



<p><em><strong>Editors Note: September is Sepsis Awareness Month</strong></em></p>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> My 86-year-old father was recently hospitalized with a severe infection. We were told he's at an increased risk for sepsis because of his age and medical history. What are the signs of sepsis to watch for now that he's returned home?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER: </strong>Nearly 270,000 people in the U.S. die annually because of sepsis — more than the number of people who die from prostate cancer, breast cancer and AIDS combined. Yet more than 40% of adults are unfamiliar with the danger of sepsis.</p>



<p>Sepsis occurs from an infection and can quickly become life-threatening. When your body has an infection, the natural response is for the immune system to fight the infection. If the body creates too much of a response to the infection, inflammation can develop, triggering sepsis.</p>



<p>Any type of infection that occurs anywhere in the body can lead to sepsis.</p>



<p>Infections that lead to sepsis most commonly occur in these parts of the body:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/listen-to-your-bladder" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bladder</a> and urinary tract</li>



<li>Gallbladder and biliary tract, which includes organs and ducts that make and store bile</li>



<li>Lungs</li>



<li>Skin</li>



<li>Soft tissues like fat or muscles</li>
</ul>



<p>There is a myth that only people who have been hospitalized are at risk of developing sepsis. In fact, 87% of cases originate outside of the hospital setting. Another myth is that sepsis is rare and only affects people with preexisting conditions.</p>



<p>Anyone can develop sepsis, but those at higher risk are:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Adults 65 or older</li>



<li>Children under 12 months</li>



<li>People with weakened immune systems</li>



<li>People with chronic medical conditions, such as diabetes, lung disease, cancer and <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/5-nutrition-tips-for-chronic-kidney-disease" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">kidney disease</a></li>



<li>People who have had a recent hospitalization</li>



<li>People who previously have had sepsis</li>
</ul>



<p>Symptoms of early sepsis can appear similar to other conditions, and survival depends on pinpointing the source of infection. Blood and urine tests and imaging scans may help identify the type and location of infection.</p>



<p>People at risk of sepsis or who previously have had sepsis should be proactive in talking with their healthcare team about the possibility of sepsis when they are feeling ill.</p>



<p>The acronym TIME is a helpful tool for recognizing and remembering the signs and symptoms of sepsis:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>T: Temperature</strong> — higher or lower than usual</li>



<li><strong>I: Infection</strong> — signs and symptoms of an infection</li>



<li><strong>M: Mental decline</strong> — sleepy, difficult to rouse, confused</li>



<li><strong>E: Extremely ill</strong> — severe pain, discomfort, shortness of breath</li>
</ul>



<p>Suspected sepsis should be handled as an emergency by calling 911 and going to a hospital, like you would do with a suspected <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/what-should-i-do-if-i-might-be-having-a-heart-attack" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart attack</a> or stroke. <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/patient-stories/sepsis-diagnosis-prompts-quick-action" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Urgent response</a> and rapid, aggressive treatment increase the rate of survival.</p>



<p>Treating sepsis as early as possible is crucial to prevent it from worsening. Determining where the infection is and eliminating it is vital to keeping sepsis from progressing to severe sepsis or septic shock. Even with treatment, sepsis can progress to severe sepsis or septic shock, causing organ damage.</p>



<p>Close monitoring and treatment for sepsis occur in the hospital setting, typically with a combination of antibiotics, intravenous fluids and other medications, including vasopressors, corticosteroids or pain relievers. Supportive therapy, such as oxygen, kidney dialysis or mechanical ventilation and surgery may be needed to drain or remove the infection.</p>



<p>Many people who recover from sepsis return to the same level of activity they had before their bout with sepsis. Some people, especially those with weakened immune systems or chronic illnesses, may experience long-term effects.</p>



<p>Talk with your primary care clinician to determine if you're at increased risk of developing sepsis.</p>



<p>Take these steps to reduce your risk:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Prevent infections.</strong><br>If you have chronic conditions, follow your healthcare team's directions to manage the conditions. Get recommended vaccines.</li>



<li><strong>Practice good hygiene.</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/5-ws-of-healthy-hands" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Wash your hands</a> regularly with soap and water or an alcohol-based hand sanitizer. Clean and cover cuts until they're entirely healed.</li>



<li><strong>Know the signs and symptoms.</strong><br>Temperature, infection, mental decline and an extremely ill feeling — TIME —  are reasons to suspect sepsis and get help fast.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>— </strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/melissa-myers-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>Melissa Myers, M.D.</em></strong></a><strong><em>, </em></strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/intensive-and-critical-care" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>Intensive Care</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Mayo Clinic Health System, </em></strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/la-crosse" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>La Crosse</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Wisconsin</em></strong></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/symptoms-of-sepsis/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Consider TIME when dealing with sepsis</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/a-medical-illustration-of-sepsis-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/a-medical-illustration-of-sepsis-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Melissa Myers]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>