<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Health &amp; Wellness - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/health-and-wellness/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/health-and-wellness/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 13:07:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Electrospinning biotherapies of tomorrow</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/electrospinning-biotherapies-of-tomorrow/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Buckles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biotherapeutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#biomedical research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Dr. Cheryl Myers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#electrospinner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Rotator cuff injuries]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Tissue engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Wound healing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=387257</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The future of healing disease may involve a syringe, a high voltage power supply and polymer solutions coming together to engineer tissue. Mayo Clinic researchers are studying these different elements now using an electrospinner, a device that whips biotherapeutic fibers into a scaffold — or platform — for spinning regenerative biotherapeutics. An electrospinner is almost [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/electrospinning-biotherapies-of-tomorrow/">Electrospinning biotherapies of tomorrow</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="760" height="428" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/16-x-9-Electrospinner-WF1299430_0035-fotor-20240503104531.jpg" alt="Image of an electrospinner, a machine used for engineering biotherapies" class="wp-image-387260" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/16-x-9-Electrospinner-WF1299430_0035-fotor-20240503104531.jpg 760w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/16-x-9-Electrospinner-WF1299430_0035-fotor-20240503104531-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 760px) 100vw, 760px" /></figure>



<p>The future of healing disease may involve a syringe, a high voltage power supply and polymer solutions coming together to engineer tissue. Mayo Clinic researchers are studying these different elements now using an electrospinner, a device that whips biotherapeutic fibers into a scaffold — or platform — for spinning regenerative biotherapeutics.</p>



<p>An electrospinner is almost like a medical spinning wheel or loom. An electrospinner unleashes electrical forces that churn chemical solutions into nano- or microscopic fibers. That, in turn, creates a porous base favorable for growing replacement cells.</p>



<p>"An electrospinner can mimic or produce a matrix of proteins and molecules that provide a platform for growth and to develop tissues, similar to what's found in our bodies," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/myers-cheryl-e-ph-d/bio-20042881" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cheryl Myers, Ph.D.</a>, an immunobiologist at Mayo Clinic in Arizona who studies regenerative science applications. "It's kind of like when you build a house, you need the foundation and the structure before you can start putting the siding on the on the walls. Electrospinning provides the foundation for cellular growth and tissue regeneration."</p>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Arizona-Electrospinner.mp4"></video></figure>



<p><strong>A researcher at Mayo Clinic in Arizona uses the electrospinner to study tissue regeneration.</strong></p>



<p>Mayo Clinic in Arizona has two electrospinners for regenerative science research. Mayo Clinic's <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about">Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</a> supports this work as part of its objective of delivering new cures.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Tissue engineering as a possible healing biotherapy</strong></h2>



<p>The body's ability to regenerate new cells and tissue varies greatly. Some tissue, such as skin, has strong ability to regenerate. However, tissue that is not connected to blood supply, such as cartilage, does not regrow and restore itself. The result can be conditions such as osteoarthritis in the knee or hip that have no therapy other than artificial joint replacement.</p>



<p>Tissue engineering is an emerging technology that offers hope for replacing and repairing damaged cells, tissue or organs. Scientists are also studying whether the electrospinner technology could be used to regenerate bones, cartilage and blood vessels.</p>



<p>"Depending upon the types of solvents and polymers (large molecules) you are using with the electrospinner, we can spin a small fiber structure that provides a platform for replacement tissue for to test therapeutics for damaged hearts, muscle or tendons," says Dr. Myers.</p>



<p>Dr. Myers and the rest of the team are using the electrospinner to test the ability to regenerate tissue for healing disorders that currently have few therapeutic options. For example, they are evaluating whether the machine could spin tissue that could grow into a 3D bioprinted larynx implant and restore function for patients who've lost part of their larynx to disease.</p>



<p>The team is also studying whether these healing solutions might become possible through electrospinner research:</p>



<ul>
<li>Skin patches to heal chronic, nonhealing wounds that have not responded to other treatments.<br><br></li>



<li>Orthopedic patches to regenerate damaged cartilage around the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/rotator-cuff-injury/symptoms-causes/syc-20350225" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">rotator cuff </a>in the shoulder.</li>
</ul>



<p>"It's very exciting research. We're limited only by our imagination when it comes to electrospinner research," says Dr. Myers. "We hope one day to incorporate cells from the patient for an individualized approach to tissue engineering."</p>



<p>As with most scientific studies, the researchers must address challenges as they bring new tools to clinical care. Dr. Myers and the team are trying to understand the proper chemical compounds, growth factors and cells needed to grow tissue. This technology would require additional testing in clinical trials if it were to advance toward patient care.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p>Related stories:</p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/bringing-regenerative-technology-of-the-future-to-patients-today/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bringing regenerative technology of the future to patients today</a></p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-opens-a-second-regenerative-medicine-therapeutic-suites/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic opens a second Regenerative Medicine Therapeutics Suites</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/electrospinning-biotherapies-of-tomorrow/">Electrospinning biotherapies of tomorrow</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/1x1-Electrospinner-WF1299430_0035-fotor-20240503104614.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/16-x-9-Electrospinner-WF1299430_0035-fotor-20240503104531.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#biomedical research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Dr. Cheryl Myers]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#electrospinner]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Rotator cuff injuries]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Tissue engineering]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Wound healing]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Can honey help my cough?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-can-honey-help-my-cough/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Abby Smith]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 10:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Angela Mattke]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Honey for cough]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386622</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: My family's colds are still lingering from the winter season, and I can't seem to kick this pesky cough. I've heard honey can help. Is it true? ANSWER: While we make think of honey as a pantry staple and natural sweetener for our morning tea or breakfast pastry, honey has long been [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-can-honey-help-my-cough/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Can honey help my cough?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/03/a-jar-of-honey-on-a-table-with-a-wooden-spindle-16x9--1024x576.jpg" alt="a jar of honey on a table with a wooden spindle" class="wp-image-116541" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/03/a-jar-of-honey-on-a-table-with-a-wooden-spindle-16x9--1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/03/a-jar-of-honey-on-a-table-with-a-wooden-spindle-16x9--300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/03/a-jar-of-honey-on-a-table-with-a-wooden-spindle-16x9--768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> My family's colds are still lingering from the winter season, and I can't seem to kick this pesky cough. I've heard honey can help. Is it true?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER: </strong>While we make think of honey as a pantry staple and natural sweetener for our morning tea or breakfast pastry, honey has long been used as an <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/want-to-ease-chronic-inflammation" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">anti-inflammatory</a> and antibacterial substance. Topical use of honey can aid in healing <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/burns/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20370545" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">burns</a>, and research says that honey can even help specific conditions such as reducing the risk of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart disease</a>, relieving gastrointestinal tract conditions such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/diarrhea/symptoms-causes/syc-20352241" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">diarrhea</a>, preventing <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/alzheimers-disease/in-depth/memory-loss/art-20046326" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">memory disorders</a> and even acting as an <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/depression/in-depth/antidepressants/art-20046273" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">antidepressant</a> with anti-<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/anxiety/symptoms-causes/syc-20350961" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">anxiety</a> benefits. </p>



<p>So, is this sticky liquid as beneficial for coughs?</p>



<p>There are a lot of different reasons why we think honey helps. Mainly, it helps soothe the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/sore-throat/symptoms-causes/syc-20351635" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">throat</a>. As we swallow and the honey moves down the throat, it can help coat some of the receptors that can trigger the cough. Some honey has been shown to be more effective than over-the-counter <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements/cough-and-cold-combinations-oral-route/proper-use/drg-20061164" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cough medications</a>.</p>



<p>Studies suggest that honey can act as a reliable cough suppressant for some people struggling with <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/7-tips-to-combat-viral-upper-respiratory-illness/">upper respiratory infections</a> and nighttime coughing. Honey is made of mostly sugar, but also contains a mix of vitamins, minerals, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements/iron-supplement-oral-route-parenteral-route/description/drg-20070148" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">iron</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements-zinc/art-20366112" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">zinc</a>, antioxidants and amino acids. Although there are over 300 different varieties of honey varying in flavor and color, the honey you have in your pantry will do the trick.</p>



<p>Honey has been shown to be effective and safe for both adults and children ages 1 and above. For young children, it's usually recommended that you start with half a teaspoon to a teaspoon in some type of warm liquid. As they get older and they're able to swallow the honey more easily, you can give it to them directly on a teaspoon. You can do about a teaspoon every two hours, which is the same dose for adults as well. Keep in mind that honey will affect your <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/diabetes/expert-answers/diabetes/faq-20058487" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">blood sugar levels</a> just as sugar does, so use it in moderation.</p>



<p>One of the reasons why infants should not have honey is the risk of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/botulism/symptoms-causes/syc-20370262" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">botulism</a>. Botulism is a rare but serious form of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/food-poisoning/symptoms-causes/syc-20356230" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">food poisoning</a>. The condition can occur when bacteria grow in the baby's intestines. It typically occurs in babies between the ages of 2 months and 8 months. In rare cases, this form of intestinal botulism also affects adults. Symptoms of botulism can include trouble swallowing or speaking, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/dry-mouth/symptoms-causes/syc-20356048" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dry mouth</a>, blurred or double vision, drooping eyelids, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/symptoms/shortness-of-breath/basics/definition/sym-20050890">trouble breathing</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/symptoms/shortness-of-breath/basics/definition/sym-20050890" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">nausea, vomiting</a>, facial weakness on both sides of the face, and paralysis. Symptoms can sometimes be life-threatening.</p>



<p><a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/blog/transplant/newsfeed-post/unpasteurized-foods-and-raw-honey/#:~:text=Pasteurization%20is%20a%20heating%20process,extreme%20danger%20to%20transplant%20patients." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Unpasteurized</a> honey puts younger children at higher risk for botulism. If you choose to use honey for cough suppression, we recommend that you use pasteurized honey to make sure that it's free of any kind of contaminants that could potentially affect you or your child. A bad cough can be really disruptive and get in the way of life, sleep, work and school. Honey can help. Feel better! <em>— </em><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mattke-angela-c-m-d/bio-20055584" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Angela Mattke, M.D.</em></a><em>, Pediatric and Adolescent Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota</em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-can-honey-help-my-cough/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Can honey help my cough?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/03/a-jar-of-honey-on-a-table-with-a-wooden-spindle-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/03/a-jar-of-honey-on-a-table-with-a-wooden-spindle-16x9-.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Angela Mattke]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Honey for cough]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-9/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jaynelle Ramon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386937</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week. Is emotional eating sabotaging your weight-loss efforts? Emotional eating is eating to suppress or soothe negative emotions, such as stress, anger, fear, boredom, sadness and loneliness. It often leads to eating too much, especially overeating foods that [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-9/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C6Xcw7TvMvg/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="385871" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Complex-carbs-whole-wheat-fruit-rice-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Complex carbs whole wheat, grain, banana, fruit, rice" class="wp-image-385871" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Complex-carbs-whole-wheat-fruit-rice-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Complex-carbs-whole-wheat-fruit-rice-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Complex-carbs-whole-wheat-fruit-rice-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Complex-carbs-whole-wheat-fruit-rice-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Complex-carbs-whole-wheat-fruit-rice-16-x-9.jpg 1604w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/MayoClinic/posts/pfbid02jYjTiBfNbw9tnuqYNVjqqQPVuSxCKbVCM1jAknh6mvRobYV9dXJkCBqAjg8hq86zl" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" data-id="229324" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/02/a-medical-illustration-of-Barretts-esophagus-16X9.jpg" alt="a medical illustration of Barrett's esophagus" class="wp-image-229324" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/02/a-medical-illustration-of-Barretts-esophagus-16X9.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/02/a-medical-illustration-of-Barretts-esophagus-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/mayo-clinic_exploring-the-exposome-activity-7191149710164856832-Uxmc/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="878" height="525" data-id="386944" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/people.png" alt="" class="wp-image-386944" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/people.png 878w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/people-300x179.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/people-768x459.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 878px) 100vw, 878px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C6SFbxDtc7J/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="175085" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/10/a-person-pulling-a-sweet-dessert-a-large-chocolate-cake-out-of-the-refrigerator-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a person pulling a sweet dessert, a large chocolate cake out of the refrigerator" class="wp-image-175085" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/10/a-person-pulling-a-sweet-dessert-a-large-chocolate-cake-out-of-the-refrigerator-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/10/a-person-pulling-a-sweet-dessert-a-large-chocolate-cake-out-of-the-refrigerator-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/10/a-person-pulling-a-sweet-dessert-a-large-chocolate-cake-out-of-the-refrigerator-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/MayoClinic/posts/pfbid0ffDT88g2nj81Wh31FRitTJMkoSfZFn8LRG6SdjWKywAFpR9wVeUXyGc7r3bB8Lnfl" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="386745" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="An ultrasound technician positions a patient for a mammogram" class="wp-image-386745" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9.jpg 1604w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>
</figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week.</h3>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-is-emotional-eating-sabotaging-your-weight-loss-efforts/">Is emotional eating sabotaging your weight-loss efforts?</a></h2>



<p>Emotional eating is eating to suppress or soothe negative emotions, such as stress, anger, fear, boredom, sadness and loneliness. It often leads to eating too much, especially overeating foods that are sweet, fatty and high in calories. And this can sabotage your weight-loss efforts.⁠</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/recommendations-to-begin-breast-cancer-screening-at-age-40/">Recommendations to begin breast cancer screening at age 40</a></h2>



<p>All women should begin breast cancer screening at the age of 40, says the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force. In a new recommendation, the task force advises cisgender women and all other people assigned female at birth aged 40 to 74 years get screened every other year.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-good-carbs-for-optimal-health/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Good carbs for optimal health</a></h2>



<p>Dr. Christine Nguyen, a Mayo Clinic family physician, says not all carbs are bad, and there are plenty of foods with good carbs. Fiber-rich foods like whole grains, fruits and vegetables are essential for health, aiding digestion, lowering cholesterol levels and reducing disease risk.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/ai-may-help-predict-risk-of-barretts-esophagus-and-esophageal-cancer/">AI may help predict risk of Barrett’s esophagus and esophageal cancer</a></h2>



<p>Esophageal cancer survival rates are low because it is often found at a later stage when symptoms such as difficulty swallowing, worsening heartburn, coughing and hoarseness have begun. Artificial intelligence may help predict the risk.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/exploring-the-exposome/">Exploring the exposome</a></h2>



<p>Environmental exposures can accumulate in your body from the air you breathe, the food you eat, products you touch, water you drink, and more. These sometimes-harmful exposures have the potential to interact with each person's genes to influence health. </p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-9/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Complex-carbs-whole-wheat-fruit-rice-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/web-top-5.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: What are gallstones?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-are-gallstones/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 13:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#socialsensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Irving Jorge]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gallbladder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gallbladder surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gallstones]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386042</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Gallstones are hardened deposits of digestive fluid, called bile, in your gallbladder. They range in size from as small as a grain of sand to as large as a golf ball. Dr. Irving Jorge, a Mayo Clinic general surgeon, says people who experience pain and other symptoms from gallstones usually require gallbladder removal surgery. Watch: [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-are-gallstones/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What are gallstones?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/gallstones/symptoms-causes/syc-20354214?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gallstones</a> are hardened deposits of digestive fluid, called bile, in your <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cholecystitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20364867?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gallbladder</a>. They range in size from as small as a grain of sand to as large as a golf ball.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/jorge-irving-a-m-d/bio-20514261?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Irving Jorge</a>, a Mayo Clinic general surgeon, says people who experience pain and other symptoms from gallstones usually require <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/cholecystectomy/about/pac-20384818?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gallbladder removal surgery</a>.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/o5Snl52wSps" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeo5Snl52wSps"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - What are gallstones?" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/o5Snl52wSps?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:08) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/MCM_Gallstones.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>You experience sudden, intense pain in your abdomen or back pain between your shoulder blades — maybe even nausea or vomiting. You could have gallstones.</p>



<p>"Typically, symptoms of gallbladder-related pain is pain associated with meals. Usually after you eat meals with fatty foods," says Dr. Jorge.</p>



<p>He says there are several reasons why your gallbladder can form gallstones. The most common cause is what you eat. A diet high in fiber and low in cholesterol and fat will reduce your risk.</p>



<p>"Native Americans and Hispanic populations have a higher risk of developing gallstones and so do women. And as we get older, we're at higher risk of developing gallstones," says Dr. Jorge.</p>



<p>He says, once you have gallstones, they won't go away on their own. Recommended treatment is surgery to remove your gallbladder.</p>



<p>"It's an organ that people can live without and not have any long-term consequences from," says Dr. Jorge. "We take out the gallbladder not just because it has stones, but it's because it's where most stones are formed. But there is a small percentage of patients that can develop stones within the bile ducts themselves."</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-are-gallstones/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What are gallstones?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Gallstone-Pain-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Gallstone-Pain-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#socialsensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Irving Jorge]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[gallbladder]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[gallbladder surgery]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[gallstones]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[General Surgery]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q &#038; A: Does collagen really help fight wrinkles and aging?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-does-collagen-really-help-fight-wrinkles-and-aging/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Abby Smith]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[collagen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Dawn Davis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386596</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: I see ads for collagen powder and supplements everywhere now, and my sister swears by it for fighting wrinkles. Does it actually help prevent aging? What exactly is collagen? ANSWER: Collagen has been seen in the media in regard to having anti-aging properties. At least 30% of your body — skin, bones, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-does-collagen-really-help-fight-wrinkles-and-aging/">Mayo Clinic Q &amp; A: Does collagen really help fight wrinkles and aging?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/07/a-woman-looking-in-a-mirror-touching-her-face-and-looking-for-wrinkles-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a woman looking in a mirror touching her face and looking for wrinkles" class="wp-image-168159" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/07/a-woman-looking-in-a-mirror-touching-her-face-and-looking-for-wrinkles-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/07/a-woman-looking-in-a-mirror-touching-her-face-and-looking-for-wrinkles-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/07/a-woman-looking-in-a-mirror-touching-her-face-and-looking-for-wrinkles-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> I see ads for collagen powder and supplements everywhere now, and my sister swears by it for fighting wrinkles. Does it actually help prevent aging? What exactly is collagen?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong> Collagen has been seen in the media in regard to having anti-aging properties. At least 30% of your body — skin, bones, tendons, organs — is made up of collagen. Collagen is a protein of the supportive tissue of the skin, which helps give it its tightness and suppleness. As you lose collagen over time, this can lead to sagging and thinning of the skin and the development of wrinkles, which can make you look aged. Much of the anti-aging industry focuses on maintaining or, hopefully, building collagen.</p>



<p>Collagen comes in the form of over-the-counter dietary <a href="https://mcpress.mayoclinic.org/nutrition-fitness/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-do-collagen-and-biotin-supplements-work/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">supplements</a> such as capsules or powder, but it also can be consumed through gelatin found in foods such as Jell-O and marshmallows. Studies are unclear as to whether taking collagen by mouth, either through diet or by supplement, is beneficial. Oftentimes when research on collagen is performed, it is not performed on humans, or it may be performed on humans but in an amount that is impractical for your daily diet or habits over time.</p>



<p>When considering topical collagen products such as serums and moisturizers, keep in mind that collagen is a large protein with a complex structure that cannot be absorbed directly through the skin. Over-the-counter products may be labeled with fancy words such as "high hydrolyzed collagen peptides," which claim that the collagen's chemical structure is more absorbable in the gut lining or on the top of the skin so that it seemingly would be more active.</p>



<p>Topical products that are not medications are not registered through the <a href="https://www.fda.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Food and Drug Administration</a> in the same way that prescription medication is. Similarly, oral supplements are not regulated by the FDA in the same way that food and oral medications are regulated. With numerous products available on the market, it is difficult to tell how it has been tested, what it contains and if those ingredients are helpful, neutral or potentially harmful.</p>



<p>Another thing to be aware of is that in <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/dermatology/sections/overview/ovc-20420526" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dermatology</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/plastic-reconstructive-surgery-mayo-clinic/sections/overview/ovc-20473067" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">plastic surgery</a>, as well as facial, ear, nose and throat surgery, collagen and fillers in the skin are given through other treatment methods in the office, such as by injection. So, if someone is interested in anti-aging properties and bringing more volume to the deeper layers of their skin, at this time, prescription or active medical intervention in a physician's office is suggested versus over-the-counter oral or topical treatment. If someone is interested in learning more, they should consult with their healthcare team.</p>



<p>The bottom line is, we don't know if topical or oral supplementation of collagen is beneficial for anti-aging purposes. There's no magic pill to reverse aging. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/sunburn/in-depth/sun-damage/art-20546834" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sun exposure</a> is a major cause of wrinkles, especially for people with fair skin. And <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/nicotine-dependence/symptoms-causes/syc-20351584#:~:text=In%20addition%2C%20smoking%20causes%20lung,and%20some%20types%20of%20leukemia." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">smoking</a> causes narrowing of the blood vessels in the outer layers of the skin and damages collagen. The most effective way to support your collagen for anti-aging is to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/quit-smoking/basics/quitsmoking-basics/hlv-20049487" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">avoid smoking</a> and exposure to secondhand smoke, limit alcohol use and consistently wear <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements/sunscreen-agent-topical-application-route/proper-use/drg-20070255" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">sunscreen</a>. <em>—</em><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/davis-dawn-marie-r-m-d/bio-20054974" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Dawn Davis, M.D.</strong></a><em><strong>, Dermatology, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota.</strong> </em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-does-collagen-really-help-fight-wrinkles-and-aging/">Mayo Clinic Q &amp; A: Does collagen really help fight wrinkles and aging?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/07/a-woman-looking-in-a-mirror-touching-her-face-and-looking-for-wrinkles-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/07/a-woman-looking-in-a-mirror-touching-her-face-and-looking-for-wrinkles-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[collagen]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Dawn Davis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hormone therapy: Four things a Mayo Clinic women&#8217;s health specialist wants you to know</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/hormone-therapy-four-things-a-mayo-clinic-womens-health-specialist-wants-you-to-know/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#socialsensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Taryn Smith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hormone Replacement Therapy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Menopause]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Women's Health]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386540</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Hormone therapy is a treatment that uses medications containing hormones like estrogen or progesterone to replace those the body stops producing during menopause. It can be a powerful tool for managing menopausal symptoms. &#160;"While hormone therapy can significantly improve quality of life and overall health for many women, it’s not a one-size-fits-all solution," says Dr. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/hormone-therapy-four-things-a-mayo-clinic-womens-health-specialist-wants-you-to-know/">Hormone therapy: Four things a Mayo Clinic women&#8217;s health specialist wants you to know</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Night-sweats-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Woman having night sweats, menopause, symptoms" class="wp-image-386606" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Night-sweats-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Night-sweats-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Night-sweats-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Night-sweats-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Night-sweats-16-x-9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Many women experience night sweats during menopause</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Hormone therapy is a treatment that uses medications containing hormones like estrogen or progesterone to replace those the body stops producing during <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/menopause/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20353401" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">menopause</a>. It can be a powerful tool for managing menopausal <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/menopause/symptoms-causes/syc-20353397" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">symptoms</a>.</p>



<p>&nbsp;"While hormone therapy can significantly improve quality of life and overall health for many women, it’s not a one-size-fits-all solution," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/smith-taryn-l-m-d/bio-20503248" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Taryn Smith</a>, a Mayo Clinic internist and women’s health specialist.</p>



<p>She emphasizes the importance of a personalized medicine approach to hormone therapy, allowing healthcare providers to consider your health and potential risks.</p>



<p>Having discussions around menopause is important because it's often not a topic that is openly discussed or acknowledged, despite its significance and importance, she says. Menopause is a natural biological process, marking the time that a woman ends her menstrual cycle. It's diagnosed after a woman goes 12 months without a menstrual period.</p>



<p>"Many women don’t know how to navigate menopause and the symptoms that come along with it, such as <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-help-with-hot-flashes-due-to-menopause/">hot flashes</a> and night sweats. Hormone therapy is used to manage many of these symptoms," says Dr. Smith. "But it's not for everybody."</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/BtwExPsaLgM" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Taryn Smith talks about hormone replacement therapy </a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeBtwExPsaLgM"  title="Hormone therapy - Four things a Mayo Clinic women&#039;s health specialist wants you to know." width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BtwExPsaLgM?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites with Dr. Smith are available in the downloads at the bottom of the posts. Name super/CG: Taryn Smith, M.D./Internal Medicine/Mayo Clinic</strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Four things Dr. Smith wants women to know about hormone therapy</h2>



<p><strong>Menopause symptoms and hormone therapy</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/menopause/in-depth/hormone-therapy/art-20046372" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hormone therapy</a> is used to manage symptoms of menopause, such as hot flashes, night sweats, trouble sleeping, and irritability.</p>



<p>"For the average healthy woman, these options are very safe. But if there are any concerns about these risk factors, it’s best to consult your physician or your women’s health specialist," she says.</p>



<p><strong>Treatment options </strong><br>Hormone therapy is a prescribed medication that can come in different forms, including patches, gels, sprays and oral medications.</p>



<p>Those options may include "A patch you wear on the skin, almost like a bandage in the lower groin or over the buttocks. We have gels that you can rub into the inner thigh and sprays that can be sprayed on the forearm. We also have some oral options.&nbsp; With all the options available, typically, we can find a good option that meets the average woman's needs," says Dr. Smith.</p>



<p><strong>Expected outcomes</strong><br>After starting hormone therapy, women can expect relief from symptoms. In many cases, hot flashes can be completely resolved, improving the woman’s quality of life.</p>



<p>"Often, we're able to completely resolve hot flashes. But if we cannot completely resolve them, we hope to get significant relief at least and help a woman restore her quality of life," she says.</p>



<p><strong>Safety concerns</strong><br>While there are safety concerns associated with hormone therapy, such as potential risks of breast cancer, stroke, or heart disease, it is generally safe for the average woman who is close to the menopause transition and younger than 60.</p>



<p>"For the average healthy woman, these options are very safe. But if there are any concerns about these risk factors, it's best to consult your physician or your women's health specialist," says Dr Smith.</p>



<p>For those who are unable to take hormone therapy or choose not to, there are FDA-approved <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/whats-the-best-nonhormonal-therapy-for-hot-flashes-experts-release-new-menopause-therapy-guidelines/">nonhormonal treatments</a> for menopause symptoms. Talk with your healthcare team to find out what is the best option.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Related post:</h3>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-managing-sleep-during-menopause/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Managing sleep during menopause</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/menopause-awareness-and-education-should-start-earlier-in-life/">Menopause awareness and education should start earlier in life</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-breast-health-during-menopause/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Breast health during menopause</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/hormone-therapy-four-things-a-mayo-clinic-womens-health-specialist-wants-you-to-know/">Hormone therapy: Four things a Mayo Clinic women&#8217;s health specialist wants you to know</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Women-diversity-original-1-x-1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Women-diversity-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#socialsensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Taryn Smith]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Hormone Replacement Therapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Menopause]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Women's Health]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q &#038; A: Supporting weight-loss medications with adequate, tailored nutrition</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-supporting-weight-loss-medications-with-adequate-tailored-nutrition/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Abby Smith]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tara Schmidt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[weight-loss]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386588</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: I have a family member taking a prescription weight-loss drug. She has been successful thus far, which I know is improving her health. She admitted, though, that she often eats less than 1,000 calories per day. How can I encourage her weight-loss journey, but also ensure she is getting adequate nutrition? ANSWER: [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-supporting-weight-loss-medications-with-adequate-tailored-nutrition/">Mayo Clinic Q &amp; A: Supporting weight-loss medications with adequate, tailored nutrition</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/08/a-smiling-overweight-middle-aged-woman-preparing-food-in-a-kitchen-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a smiling, overweight middle-aged woman preparing food in a kitchen" class="wp-image-97613" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/08/a-smiling-overweight-middle-aged-woman-preparing-food-in-a-kitchen-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/08/a-smiling-overweight-middle-aged-woman-preparing-food-in-a-kitchen-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/08/a-smiling-overweight-middle-aged-woman-preparing-food-in-a-kitchen-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC</strong>: I have a family member taking a prescription weight-loss drug. She has been successful thus far, which I know is improving her health. She admitted, though, that she often eats less than 1,000 calories per day. How can I encourage her weight-loss journey, but also ensure she is getting adequate nutrition?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong> While <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/weight-loss/in-depth/weight-loss-drugs/art-20044832" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">weight-loss medications</a> are truly having a positive effect on many Americans’ health, it is important to also talk about nutrition. Not just the "please eat healthy and exercise" narrative (despite its truth), but making sure that patients on weight-loss medications are able to manage side effects, stay hydrated and consume adequate nutrients.</p>



<p>Medications for obesity approved by the Food and Drug Administration often work by decreasing appetite and increasing fullness. Popular <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/type-2-diabetes/expert-answers/byetta/faq-20057955" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">glucagon-like peptide 1</a> medications slow gastric emptying, or the rate at which food leaves the stomach. This can lead to common side effects such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/symptoms/nausea/basics/definition/sym-20050736" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">nausea</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/constipation/symptoms-causes/syc-20354253" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">constipation</a> and vomiting. For most, these side effects are mild and temporary. They are likely to be most bothersome at medication start or with a dose increase, and they may resolve or improve within days to weeks. Keep your doctor informed about any severe side effects, and reach out if you are unable to eat or drink.</p>



<p>For many, side effects become manageable with time and intention. Users should eat slowly, avoid large meals, drink plenty of fluids and maintain protein intake. If calories become a concern (less than 1,200 a day), work on increased calorie and nutrient density with meals, beverages and snacks. Items such as Greek yogurt, smoothies, protein shakes and soups are often nutrient-dense and easy to digest. Soft, blended or liquid meals may be better tolerated. Remember that hydration is crucial because the lack of it may cause or worsen side effects including nausea, constipation, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/symptoms/headache/basics/definition/sym-20050800" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">headaches</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/symptoms/fatigue/basics/definition/sym-20050894" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">fatigue</a>. Make sure to have water or another healthy beverage on hand, and sip throughout the day.</p>



<p>Building a bank of habits is key for the long haul. While more medication options will be available in the coming years, it’s important to consider skillset, should someone need or choose to go off the weight-loss drug. Weight regain can be a scary and very real concept. Just as someone who relies on a medication to keep their blood pressure in a healthy range, eliminating the medication would likely result in <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-pressure/symptoms-causes/syc-20373410" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hypertension</a> again. That's why we use the word "tool" when it comes to weight-loss medications, procedures and surgeries. They are an added benefit, but that one tool is not doing all the work. By focusing on nutritious meals and establishing an exercise routine immediately, the groundwork is set for long-term success, regardless of whether the tool is being used in the future.</p>



<p>Rapid weight loss, whether from lifestyle changes, medications or procedures, will lead to some muscle mass loss. Focus on and divide sources of protein from food or beverages throughout the day. To not add volume to meals, brainstorm ways to add protein without adding bulk, like adding a protein powder or Greek yogurt to a morning smoothie, dipping veggies in cottage cheese or adding beans to a favorite soup. Eating protein as the first item in the meal is also a helpful strategy to make sure it's not left on the plate.</p>



<p>Engaging in <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/fitness/in-depth/strength-training/art-20046670" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">strength training</a> is equally as important. Start with body weight if needed, and increase weight or difficulty over time. Can't nail a push-up yet? That’s OK! Practice first by using the wall. Then try from the arm of a couch. Progress to your knees, and don't feel bad if a push-up from your toes just isn't going to happen. The goal here is to maintain and/or build all muscle groups, regardless of whether that pushup would get you through boot camp. Other <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/fitness/in-depth/strength-training/art-20046031" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">body-weight exercises</a> include squats, lunges, planks, triceps dips and wall sits. Lastly, enlist help. A multidisciplinary team is an excellent resource to address your needs and concerns. In addition to the medication prescriber, patients may benefit from programs designed specifically for weight-loss medication users. Visit the <a href="https://diet.mayoclinic.org/us/weight-loss-medication/rx-companion/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Diet Rx Companion</a> and <a href="https://diet.mayoclinic.org/us/weight-loss-medication/rx-medical-weight-loss/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Rx Medical Weight Loss</a> websites to learn more. <em>— </em><a href="https://mcpress.mayoclinic.org/authors/tara-schmidt-m-ed-rdn/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Tara Schmidt</strong></a><strong><em>, Registered Dietitian, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota</em></strong></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-supporting-weight-loss-medications-with-adequate-tailored-nutrition/">Mayo Clinic Q &amp; A: Supporting weight-loss medications with adequate, tailored nutrition</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/08/a-smiling-overweight-middle-aged-woman-preparing-food-in-a-kitchen-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/08/a-smiling-overweight-middle-aged-woman-preparing-food-in-a-kitchen-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Tara Schmidt]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[weight-loss]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic hospitals continue to score A grades for patient safety, 5-star ratings for patient experience</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-hospitals-continue-to-score-a-grades-for-patient-safety-5-star-ratings-for-patient-experience/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ann Schauer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sean Dowdy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sunanda Kane]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Leapfrog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Patient Experience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[patient safety]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386698</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>All nine eligible Mayo Clinic hospitals earned A grades from The Leapfrog Group, an independent national nonprofit organization that provides safety ratings. The ratings are intended to help patients choose their preferred healthcare destinations. "Our staff's dedication consistently reinforces Mayo Clinic as the global authority in healthcare because they deliver the highest quality, safety and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-hospitals-continue-to-score-a-grades-for-patient-safety-5-star-ratings-for-patient-experience/">Mayo Clinic hospitals continue to score A grades for patient safety, 5-star ratings for patient experience</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Hospital-patient-.GettyImages-1515280024-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-386773" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Hospital-patient-.GettyImages-1515280024-16x9-1.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Hospital-patient-.GettyImages-1515280024-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Hospital-patient-.GettyImages-1515280024-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>All nine eligible Mayo Clinic hospitals earned A grades from <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.leapfroggroup.org%2F&amp;data=05%7C01%7Clea.dan%40mayo.edu%7Ce9b1511dbd64401f8efa08dac7fac64c%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C638042177219464262%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=7SE6Xv0d1MmAEt%2FcayEnYIrmYt4j6Zaba7mvAjgjsj8%3D&amp;reserved=0">The Leapfrog Group</a>, an independent national nonprofit organization that provides safety ratings. The ratings are intended to help patients choose their preferred healthcare destinations.</p>



<p>"Our staff's dedication consistently reinforces Mayo Clinic as the global authority in healthcare because they deliver the highest quality, safety and experience," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/dowdy-sean-c-m-d/bio-20054619?_escaped_fragment_=escaped_fragment_%3D1&amp;p=1">Dr. Sean Dowdy,</a> Mayo Clinic's chief value officer. "Participating in the external review also helps validate staff commitment to continuously improve our Culture of Safety, along with our desire to influence industry standards for safety."</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Mayo Clinic hospitals that received an A grade are:</h3>



<ul>
<li>Mayo Clinic in Arizona</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic in Florida</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota</li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in Albert Lea and Austin, Minnesota</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in Eau Claire, Wisconsin</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in Fairmont, Minnesota</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in La Crosse, Wisconsin</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in Mankato, Minnesota</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in Red Wing, Minnesota</li>
</ul>



<p>The Leapfrog Group's Hospital Safety Score is updated and published twice each year. The score is based on 15 measures of publicly available hospital safety data and 12 self-reported survey answers, which are combined to produce a single safety score. A panel of patient safety experts developed the measures for the score.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Mayo hospitals also earn patients' trust, 5-star ratings for patient experience</strong></h2>



<p>Eleven Mayo Clinic hospitals also received four- and five-star ratings in patient experience in the latest Hospital Consumer Assessment of Healthcare Providers and Systems survey, conducted by the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services. The rankings reflect staff dedication to providing a supportive and excellent experience for patients.</p>



<p>"In the heart of Experience Week, staff rightfully deserve this timely recognition, as our hospitals continue to earn four- and five-star ratings for excellent patient experience," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/kane-sunanda-v-m-d/bio-20054986">Dr. Sunanda Kane,</a> Mayo Clinic's chief experience officer. "These achievements reflect staff's hard work and their commitment to upholding the timeless values of Mayo Clinic."</p>



<p>Hospitals received ratings of one to five stars, with five stars being the highest score. The ratings are based on data from patient experience surveys.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Here's how Mayo Clinic hospitals were rated:</h3>



<p><strong>Five stars</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Mayo Clinic in Arizona</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic in Florida</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System — Northland in Barron, Wisconsin</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System — Red Cedar in Menomonie, Wisconsin</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Four stars</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in Eau Claire, Wisconsin</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in Fairmont, Minnesota</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in La Crosse, Wisconsin</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in Mankato, Minnesota</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in New Prague, Minnesota</li>



<li>Mayo Clinic Health System in Red Wing, Minnesota</li>
</ul>



<p>Many agencies rate quality in healthcare, and Mayo Clinic is the only healthcare organization that consistently ranks among the top providers nationwide regardless of the quality measure used.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-hospitals-continue-to-score-a-grades-for-patient-safety-5-star-ratings-for-patient-experience/">Mayo Clinic hospitals continue to score A grades for patient safety, 5-star ratings for patient experience</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Hospital-patient-GettyImages-1515280024-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Hospital-patient-.GettyImages-1515280024-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Sean Dowdy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Sunanda Kane]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Leapfrog]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Patient Experience]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[patient safety]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q &#038; A: Seeing clearly: Understanding pink eye</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-seeing-clearly-understanding-pink-eye/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Abby Smith]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Tina Ardon]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pink eye]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386583</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: My entire family was recently affected by pink eye, including my mom, my nephews, my sister and even her dog! How is it so contagious? And what is it? ANSWER: Pink eye is an inflammation of the lining of the eyelid and eyeball. The medical term for pink eye is conjunctivitis. Just [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-seeing-clearly-understanding-pink-eye/">Mayo Clinic Q &amp; A: Seeing clearly: Understanding pink eye</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Pink-Eye-2-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-385480" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Pink-Eye-2-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Pink-Eye-2-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Pink-Eye-2-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Pink-Eye-2-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Pink-Eye-2-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> My entire family was recently affected by pink eye, including my mom, my nephews, my sister and even her dog! How is it so contagious? And what is it?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong> Pink eye is an inflammation of the lining of the eyelid and eyeball. The medical term for pink eye is <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pink-eye/symptoms-causes/syc-20376355" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">conjunctivitis</a>. Just as its name, pink eye, tells us, the most noticeable symptom will be a pink or red irritated eye or eyes. Other symptoms can include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Itchiness in one or both eyes.</li>



<li>A gritty feeling in one or both eyes.</li>



<li>Discharge in one or both eyes. This can form a crust overnight that can prevent one or both eyes from opening the next morning.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/symptoms/watery-eyes/basics/definition/sym-20050821" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watery eyes</a> or tearing.</li>
</ul>



<p>Pink eye is most commonly caused by a virus, but a bacterial infection or allergies also can be to blame. In babies, pink eye can be caused by a tear duct that is not completely opened. Most viruses will go away on their own. If the cause is bacterial, we will recommend treating the affected eye(s) with an antibiotic drop.</p>



<p>Unfortunately, pink eye is quite contagious, just like many other infectious diseases such as colds and influenza. Patients can be at risk of catching pink eye if they touch someone who is infected and then rub their eyes or face. For this reason, it is important to be consistent with hand hygiene and hand-washing, and avoid touching other things around someone who may be ill.</p>



<p>Pink eye can be a pain, but don't worry — it rarely affects your vision. If you do experience blurred vision, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/symptoms/eye-pain/basics/definition/sym-20050744" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">eye pain</a>, light sensitivity (photophobia) or feel as if something is stuck in your eye, seek urgent care. If you wear <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/contact-lenses/overview/ovc-20518723" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">contact lenses</a>, you should stop wearing them as soon as you notice pink eye symptoms. If your symptoms don't begin to improve within 12 to 24 hours, you should make an appointment with your eye doctor to make sure you don't have a more serious infection related to contact lens use.</p>



<p>Pink eye is one of our more common reasons to stay home from day care, school or even work if you're an adult, because even adults can get pink eye. If it's a bacterial infection, patients need at least 24 hours of antibiotic therapy before returning to normal activities. If it's viral in nature, you may have to wait at home a little bit longer since there is no treatment other than time. If it is allergic in nature, one can safely attend school and work since allergies are not contagious. We generally recommend those patients stay at home until they feel better.</p>



<p>Doing warm compresses on the eyes can help alleviate some of the symptoms. Rest will also help you heal. If your pink eye is from allergies, using appropriate <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/allergies/in-depth/allergy-medications/art-20047403" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">allergy medications</a> can help. Unfortunately, we are often contagious with viruses or bacteria that cause pink eye before we even have symptoms. That is why it's so important to be consistent and mindful about our <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/adult-health/in-depth/hand-washing/art-20046253" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hand hygiene</a> and careful about being around those who may not be feeling well. <em>— </em><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/ardon-tina-m-d/bio-20055713?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Tina Ardon, M.D.</strong></a><em><strong>,</strong> <strong>Family Medicine,</strong> <strong>Mayo Clinic, Jacksonville, Florida</strong></em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-seeing-clearly-understanding-pink-eye/">Mayo Clinic Q &amp; A: Seeing clearly: Understanding pink eye</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Pink-Eye-2-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Pink-Eye-2-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Tina Ardon]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[pink eye]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q &#038; A: Going plant-based: Exploring the myths, health benefits</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-going-plant-based-exploring-the-myths-health-benefits/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Abby Smith]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Christine Nguyen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[plant-based diet]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=386545</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: More and more of my friends are following the plant-based diet trend. Is that the same as going vegan? Is it healthy for you? What can I actually eat? ANSWER: Plant-based foods go beyond a "boring salad." With a whole-food plant-based diet, we focus on eating foods that are primarily coming from [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-going-plant-based-exploring-the-myths-health-benefits/">Mayo Clinic Q &amp; A: Going plant-based: Exploring the myths, health benefits</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/a-bucket-or-box-full-of-fresh-fruits-and-vegetables-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a bucket or box full of fresh fruits and vegetables" class="wp-image-176373" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/a-bucket-or-box-full-of-fresh-fruits-and-vegetables-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/a-bucket-or-box-full-of-fresh-fruits-and-vegetables-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/a-bucket-or-box-full-of-fresh-fruits-and-vegetables-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> More and more of my friends are following the plant-based diet trend. Is that the same as going vegan? Is it healthy for you? What can I actually eat?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong> Plant-based foods go beyond a "boring salad." With a <a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/blog/weight-management-1/newsfeed-post/choosing-whole-foods-for-a-healthier-you/">whole-food</a> <a href="https://mcpress.mayoclinic.org/nutrition-fitness/steps-to-start-eating-plant-based/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">plant-based</a> diet, we focus on eating foods that are primarily coming from plants and that occur in their natural state. Veganism also takes that into account but can incorporate other social and justice factors into that lifestyle.</p>



<p>Certainly, it can be difficult to go 100% whole-food plant-based, especially if that's something you're not used to. My recommendation is to start by introducing an additional fruit, vegetable or whole food into your diet slowly and one at a time. One of the things I recommend is taking what is part of your normal routine and simply adding to it. So, if you're a person who enjoys eating oatmeal for breakfast, perhaps you'll add an additional serving of fruit.</p>



<p>One of the biggest misconceptions people have when they hear about plant-based is that they might not get enough <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/are-you-getting-too-much-protein#:~:text=How%20much%20protein%20do%20you,per%20kilogram%20of%20body%20weight.">protein</a> because they're so used to eating meat, whether that's from animal protein, dairy products or eggs. But the fact is, we can get a lot of our protein from plant-based foods such as legumes, lentils, tofu, nuts and seeds.</p>



<p>Another way to look at protein needs is to look at what is on your plate. When building your plate, half of the plate should be vegetables, a quarter of the plate can be a protein and the last quarter of the plate could be a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/carbohydrates/art-20045705" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">carbohydrate</a>. The plate method is visualizing what's on your plate to help meet your daily needs. The protein of choice should be about the size of a deck of cards. Hopefully, in the future, you can supplement some of your animal proteins with plant protein.</p>



<p>Having a variety of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/dash-diet/art-20050989" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">fruits and vegetables</a> is equally important as meeting the recommended intake of five servings of fruits and vegetables per day. The colors of different fruits and vegetables signify phytonutrients that can boost your immune system. Buying seasonal products can get us to try new foods that we may not typically go for year-round. Sometimes we might find that we like (or maybe not like) those new foods that we try. We might want to dive deeper into, "Is it the flavor that I don't like or the texture? And if so, can I cook it or prepare it a different way to make it more enjoyable?"</p>



<p>For example, I am very sensitive to raw broccoli. It has a strange aftertaste to me. But then I discovered broccoli sprouts, which are broccoli plants that are 3-5 days old. Broccoli sprouts carry a cancer-protection effect. So I'm able to add broccoli sprouts in place of having the full adult broccoli. I'll typically use it on top of a salad or add it to a sandwich as an added crunch. It's a way I can get my broccoli nutrients in.</p>



<p>One of my favorite go-to ingredients for protein are lentils. Lentils provide an adequate amount of protein and are quite easy to add to any dish. I like to add lentils to any chilis or soups that I'm making as a thickener or as a meat alternative for meatless meatballs or tacos. Lentils are an important part of a plant-based diet because they're not only high in fiber but also contain great sources of potassium as well as protein. They've been shown to lower the lipid profile in people who are overweight or obese with type 2 diabetes. They're also a great source of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/expert-answers/probiotics/faq-20058065" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">prebiotics</a> to help diversify the gut and protect it from <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/digestive-diseases" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">digestive diseases</a>.</p>



<p>Another important part of the whole-food, plant-based diet is the incorporation of <a href="https://mcpress.mayoclinic.org/nutrition-fitness/can-fungi-flavor-better-health-what-to-know-about-mushroom-coffee/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">mushrooms</a>. Interestingly, mushrooms are not vegetables or fruit, but a fungus. These fungi have been well studied throughout medical nutrition, and they've been shown to have immune-boosting properties supporting brain health and antioxidant effects. Mushrooms have a high-flavor profile and can add extra flavor to any dish, especially when cooked. They also can take on all the flavors of the seasonings around them.</p>



<p>The ultimate goal is to nourish our bodies in a way that is sustainable and that works for us. Having a completely 100% whole-food, plant-based diet might not be for everyone, but we do know that incorporating fruits and vegetables in the diet serves beneficial and long-term health effects. So, if that means adding one thing at a time, or shying away from one of those foods that we typically avoid, such as red meats, dairy, or unnecessary <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-best-cooking-fats-for-healthy-cholesterol-levels/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">oils and fats</a>, then we do so slowly. If you get stuck at any point in the process, you can always talk to your healthcare team for extra assistance. <em>—</em> <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/nguyen-christine-q-d-o/bio-20536365" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>Christine Nguyen, D.O.</em></strong></a><em><strong>, Family Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Jacksonville, Florida</strong></em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-a-going-plant-based-exploring-the-myths-health-benefits/">Mayo Clinic Q &amp; A: Going plant-based: Exploring the myths, health benefits</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/a-bucket-or-box-full-of-fresh-fruits-and-vegetables-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/a-bucket-or-box-full-of-fresh-fruits-and-vegetables-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Christine Nguyen]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[plant-based diet]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>