<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Health &amp; Wellness - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/health-and-wellness/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/health-and-wellness/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 16:27:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Seasonal affective disorder: More than feeling sad</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/seasonal-affective-disorder-more-than-feeling-sad/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2024 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Janice Schreier]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395788</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>During certain seasons of the year, you may notice changes in your energy level, sleep and interest in activities. Seasonal affective disorder, or&#160;SAD, is a type of depression that is related to the changes in seasons. Symptoms typically appear in the fall, continue through the winter months and eventually go away in the spring or [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/seasonal-affective-disorder-more-than-feeling-sad/">Seasonal affective disorder: More than feeling sad</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/12/a-lonely-sad-looking-white-woman-wrapped-in-a-blanket-and-sitting-near-a-window-and-looking-out-thoughtfully-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="a lonely, sad looking white woman wrapped in a blanket and sitting near a window and looking out thoughtfully" class="wp-image-289001" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/12/a-lonely-sad-looking-white-woman-wrapped-in-a-blanket-and-sitting-near-a-window-and-looking-out-thoughtfully-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/12/a-lonely-sad-looking-white-woman-wrapped-in-a-blanket-and-sitting-near-a-window-and-looking-out-thoughtfully-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/12/a-lonely-sad-looking-white-woman-wrapped-in-a-blanket-and-sitting-near-a-window-and-looking-out-thoughtfully-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/12/a-lonely-sad-looking-white-woman-wrapped-in-a-blanket-and-sitting-near-a-window-and-looking-out-thoughtfully-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/12/a-lonely-sad-looking-white-woman-wrapped-in-a-blanket-and-sitting-near-a-window-and-looking-out-thoughtfully-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>During certain seasons of the year, you may notice changes in your energy level, sleep and interest in activities.</p>



<p><a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/seasonal-affective-disorder/symptoms-causes/syc-20364651" target="_blank">Seasonal affective disorder</a>, or&nbsp;SAD, is a type of depression that is related to the changes in seasons. Symptoms typically appear in the fall, continue through the winter months and eventually go away in the spring or summer.</p>



<p>Affective disorders are mood disorders that have an impactful change in emotions and affect. Affective disorders significantly affect feelings and responses to emotions.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What are the possible causes of SAD?</h2>



<p>While the exact cause is unknown, it may be linked to the reduced amount of sunlight affecting the natural chemicals like serotonin and <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/melatonin-use-in-children" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">melatonin</a> in your body that determine mood and energy levels and regulate sleep.</p>



<p>SAD is not simply a case of the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/seasonal-affective-disorder-not-just-the-winter-blues" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">winter blues</a>, a condition that is more mild and common. SAD symptoms are severe enough to make it difficult to function in social, work and home environments.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How does SAD differ from other types of depression?</h2>



<p>SAD has a seasonal pattern, with recurring episodes happening more predictably during certain seasons — most commonly during the winter months. SAD can have a predictable pattern to depression, which is helpful for the management of the disorder.</p>



<p>The criteria for diagnosing SAD are similar to diagnosing major depression, with the seasonal pattern as a key indicator.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Who is most at risk for experiencing symptoms of SAD?</h2>



<p>People who live in the northern half of the U.S., where daylight hours are shorter and there is less sunlight, are more at risk for SAD. It's estimated that about 1 in 20 people in the northern half of the U.S. could have symptoms suggestive of SAD.</p>



<p>While a person is not born with SAD, it's believed to run in families. It's more common in women, as are all depressive disorders.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What symptoms indicate seasonal affective disorder?</h2>



<p>On average, SAD will last about five months of the year. Typically, <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/seasonal-affective-disorder-explained" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">symptoms </a>will develop in October and worsen around the end of <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/how-to-manage-daylight-saving-time" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">daylight saving time</a>, followed by a more drastic decline in November. January and February tend to be the months with the most severe <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/depression/symptoms-causes/syc-20356007" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">symptoms of depression</a>.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Symptoms of seasonal affective disorder to watch for include:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Difficulty concentrating</li>



<li>Feeling persistently tired and fatigued, including feeling a loss of energy nearly every day of the affected months</li>



<li>Feelings of worthlessness</li>



<li>Losing interest in things you would typically enjoy, such as hobbies and social activities</li>



<li>Persistently feeling down or sad</li>



<li>Sleep disturbances, which could include hypersomnia (sleeping too much) or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/insomnia/symptoms-causes/syc-20355167" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">insomnia</a> (difficulty falling asleep)</li>



<li>Thoughts of <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/suicide-crisis-develop-safety-plan" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">suicide</a></li>



<li>Weight changes, including weight gain or weight loss</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Are there treatments available for SAD?</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Light therapy</h3>



<p>Bright&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/light-therapy/about/pac-20384604" target="_blank">light therapy</a>&nbsp;is considered an effective treatment for SAD. Research suggests that around half of people who use a bright light therapy box have good results with symptom reduction.</p>



<p>It's essential to meet with a healthcare professional familiar with bright light therapy to determine the type of device needed to be effective, how to correctly set it up and the length of time required in front of a light box.</p>



<p>Generally, the light box should provide an exposure of 10,000 lux of light and emit as little UV light as possible. The typical recommendation is to use the light box within the first hour of waking up in the morning for 20–30 minutes.</p>



<p>Some light boxes emit white light, and others emit blue light. There is no advantage to one color.</p>



<p>Talking with your healthcare team before using a light box is crucial if your skin or eyes are sensitive to light due to a medical condition or medication.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Medications</h3>



<p>An antidepressant prescribed by a healthcare professional can be an effective treatment option.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Physical activity</h3>



<p>Research has shown that exercising for 20 minutes at least three days a week has similar effectiveness to taking an antidepressant. Being active can help with serotonin production and boost your mood. <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/tips-for-cold-weather-training" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Exercising outdoors</a> during daylight hours increases the effectiveness of the activity.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT)</h3>



<p>CBT is an effective treatment for SAD and clinical depression. CBT helps people learn how to manage their symptoms of depression or reduce the severity of the symptoms. Talk with your primary care provider about CBT and how to find a provider skilled at delivering CBT for depression or anxiety.</p>



<p>Because SAD is tied to the changing seasons, the onset can be predicted, which sets a person up to better manage their symptoms. If you have SAD, there are preventive measures that you can put in place and steps you can begin taking before major depression develops.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Remember these tips:</h4>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Be physically active.</strong><br>Exercise helps relieve stress and anxiety. It's essential to <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/winter-weather-are-falls-and-slips-avoidable" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stay active during winter</a>, even if you are tempted to become less active during colder months.</li>



<li><strong>Get outside.</strong><br>Spend 15 to 20 minutes outside when the sun is out. If the weather allows, take a walk outside during the lunch hour when the sun is at its peak. Sunlight helps adjust your body's internal clock.</li>



<li><strong>Make your environment bright.</strong><br>Open the window blinds and allow sunlight into your home. Sit near a window while at home or work.</li>



<li><strong>Prioritize sleep.</strong>Go to bed and wake at the same time every day, with the goal of getting seven to nine hours of <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/5-ways-to-get-better-sleep">restful sleep</a>. Excessive napping and oversleeping beyond your typical schedule can disrupt your circadian rhythm.</li>



<li><strong>Stay connected to friends and family.</strong><br>Decreased mood can lead to a behavior of staying home and isolating. Engaging with friends, staying in a routine, and getting active at home and outside of the home are essential.</li>



<li><strong>Take care of your body and mind.</strong><br>Eat regular, healthy meals. Avoid drugs and alcohol, which can make depression worse. Manage stress with practices like deep breathing, <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/mindfulness-meditation-improve-your-quality-of-life" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">mindfulness and meditation</a>.</li>
</ul>



<p>If you have a history of SAD, talk with your healthcare team about a plan to better manage your mood during the winter months.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Watch this video to learn more about the type of depression linked to seasonal changes.</h4>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe id="videoid1Ujh9hHJhA"  title="Understanding seasonal affective disorder (SAD) - Mayo Clinic Health System" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1Ujh9hHJ-hA?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><em><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/janice-schreier-lcsw" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Janice Schreier</a> is a clinical therapist in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/psychiatry-and-psychology">Psychiatry &amp; Psychology</a> in <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/la-crosse" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">La Crosse</a>, Wisconsin.</em></p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/seasonal-affective-disorder-more" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/seasonal-affective-disorder-more-than-feeling-sad/">Seasonal affective disorder: More than feeling sad</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/12/a-lonely-sad-looking-white-woman-wrapped-in-a-blanket-and-sitting-near-a-window-and-looking-out-thoughtfully-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/12/a-lonely-sad-looking-white-woman-wrapped-in-a-blanket-and-sitting-near-a-window-and-looking-out-thoughtfully-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Janice Schreier]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Dancer reclaims her life after years of chronic pain</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/dancer-reclaims-her-life-after-years-of-chronic-pain/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tia R. Ford]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sam Farres]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395537</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Abbie Langton started dancing at age 3. Although she's trained across the spectrum of dance genres — including ballet, tap, hip hop and jazz — lyrical and contemporary are her favorites. Abbie's passion for performing led her to receive a scholarship for competitive dance at a university in Connecticut. But during her sophomore year, debilitating [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/dancer-reclaims-her-life-after-years-of-chronic-pain/">Dancer reclaims her life after years of chronic pain</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="1296" height="729" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Langton_2-16x9-1.jpg" alt="Abbie Langton in a dance pose in front of a building" class="wp-image-395542" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Langton_2-16x9-1.jpg 1296w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Langton_2-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Langton_2-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Langton_2-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1296px) 100vw, 1296px" /></figure>



<p>Abbie Langton started dancing at age 3. Although she's trained across the spectrum of dance genres — including ballet, tap, hip hop and jazz — lyrical and contemporary are her favorites.</p>



<p>Abbie's passion for performing led her to receive a scholarship for competitive dance at a university in Connecticut. But during her sophomore year, debilitating pain in her arm and neck forced her to hang up her dance shoes.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Trouble finding a root cause</h2>



<p>Pain wasn't new to Abbie. When she was in the third grade, she remembers experiencing swelling in her left arm, along with chest pain. Because she was so young, though, she couldn't articulate what she was feeling.</p>



<p>"My doctor ordered a bunch of tests, worried it might be congestive heart failure because of the swelling in my left arm and chest pain," Abbie says. "The test results ended up being inconclusive, so my doctor decided it wasn’t congestive heart failure, which was great news, but we still didn’t know what it was."</p>



<p>Next, the focus turned to lymphedema, a chronic condition caused by a buildup of lymph fluid in the body that causes tissues to swell. Still, because of Abbie's young age, her doctor decided to forego testing to confirm a diagnosis and, instead, gave her a compression sleeve to wear to reduce the swelling.</p>



<p>Yet even with the sleeve, Abbie's pain continued.</p>



<p>"At every physical, I'd tell them that I was still experiencing pain, but they'd brush it off and keep pushing my concerns aside," Abbie recalls.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A life on hold</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Langton_1-1x1-1-300x300.jpg" alt="Abbie Langton in a dance pose on a rooftop" class="wp-image-395540" style="width:377px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Langton_1-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Langton_1-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Langton_1-1x1-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Langton_1-1x1-1.jpg 864w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure></div>


<p>By the time Abbie got to college, she'd learned to live with — and dance through — the pain. But during her second year of college, when she started experiencing severe pain in the back of her neck in addition to her arm and chest, Abbie's roommate told her she needed to get help.</p>



<p>"My roommate told me, 'This isn't normal. You need to go somewhere,'" Abbie says.</p>



<p>Abbie started with an orthopedic doctor in Connecticut, who sent her to a vascular surgeon, who eventually recommended a doctor in Boston.</p>



<p>"That was the beginning of the downward spiral of medical appointments," Abbie says. "I was getting really frustrated. I felt like my entire life was on hold. I couldn't dance. I couldn't really work. I couldn't sit at a desk for a long period of time. And at 20 years old, that was my entire life — I was a student and a dancer, and I couldn't do either well. My mental health was plummeting."</p>



<p>Abbie heard from the doctor's office in Boston that they couldn't get her in for nine months. Although she lives in Massachusetts and attends school in Connecticut, Abbie started looking into <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a>. Her parents had recently bought a vacation home near the Jacksonville campus, and Abbie was at her wit's end.</p>



<p>Everything Abbie read about Mayo Clinic was positive. When she called, she was able to get an appointment quickly — much sooner than the nine months the Boston doctor's office had offered.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Finding help at Mayo Clinic</h2>



<p>Right away, Abbie's experience with Mayo Clinic matched everything she'd read about it.</p>



<p>"It's different from any other medical institution," she says. "For one, they didn't treat me like a hypochondriac. At that point, because I was young and petite and looked healthy, I felt like so many people were looking at me and assuming I just wanted attention, despite me saying over and over again that I had chronic pain."</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/farres-sam-m-d/bio-20055440" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Sam Farres</a>, chief of the Vascular Surgery Division at Mayo Clinic in Florida, and his team, which includes Michael Adalia, nurse practitioner, and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/clendenen-steven-r-m-d/bio-20054680" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Steven Clendenen</a>, anesthesiologist, ordered a full-body workup. The first discovery was a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/chiari-malformation/symptoms-causes/syc-20354010" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Chiari malformation</a>, which occurs when the lower part of the brain pushes down into the spinal canal. The second was <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/thoracic-outlet-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20353988" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">thoracic outlet syndrome</a>, or TOS, a rare disorder that involves compression of the nerves, arteries or veins in the lower neck and upper chest.</p>



<p>Dr. Farres says TOS is hard to diagnose. But it starts with believing what the patient tells you — and then performing a series of tests to rule out everything other than TOS.</p>



<p>Once Dr. Farres and his team had collected enough evidence that pointed to TOS, they started treatment: a nerve block followed by a rib resection (or removal of a rib) and scalenectomy (or removal of the scalene muscle, which passes through the thoracic outlet).</p>



<p>"I really trusted Dr. Farres," Abbie says. "He educated me a lot, taking the time to make me feel comfortable and explain things to me in a language I could understand. And he was the first person to say, 'This is what's wrong, and this is what we’re going to do about it.' He knew how important getting back to living my life was."</p>



<p>Dr. Farres points to TOS as a condition that steals people's passion. "It depletes their life's meaning, their identity," he says. "It can be very life-limiting."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Reclaiming her life</h2>



<p>Just two weeks after her surgery, Abbie returned to school. A few months later — because she wasn't able to lift weights or dance yet — she took up long-distance running, participating in 5Ks and other endurance events.</p>



<p>"I needed to do something active," Abbie says, noting that, just recently, at age 21, she was able to start dancing again. "I probably could've started a little bit sooner, but I didn't want to push myself."</p>



<p>Overall, Abbie says she's in a much better place today.</p>



<p>"I either saw or talked with close to 20 doctors in my pursuit of answers to my pain," she says. "I always knew something was wrong. And it was so defeating to hear time after time that it must be in my head. It wasn't until Mayo Clinic that I found answers and help."</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/dancer-reclaims-her-life-after-years-of-chronic-pain/">Dancer reclaims her life after years of chronic pain</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Langton_2-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Langton_2-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Sam Farres]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-34/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jaynelle Ramon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 13:15:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395725</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week. Mayo Clinic Minute: Stroke treatment Each year, an estimated 15 million people around the globe experience stroke, according to the World Health Organization, with one-third resulting in death. When the symptoms of stroke present, calling 911 and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-34/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/MayoClinic/videos/1582523209358942/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="388926" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Jessie-Boyd-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-388926" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Jessie-Boyd-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Jessie-Boyd-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Jessie-Boyd-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Jessie-Boyd-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/06/Jessie-Boyd-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/706347941527986/posts/960692779426833" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="178437" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/12/Red-heart-in-the-hand-of-a-physician_shutterstock_135683396_16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Red heart in the hand of a physician" class="wp-image-178437" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/12/Red-heart-in-the-hand-of-a-physician_shutterstock_135683396_16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/12/Red-heart-in-the-hand-of-a-physician_shutterstock_135683396_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/12/Red-heart-in-the-hand-of-a-physician_shutterstock_135683396_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DBxV5CRsFlI/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="395754" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/breast-cancer-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395754" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/breast-cancer-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/breast-cancer-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/breast-cancer-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/breast-cancer-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/breast-cancer-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DBg7c0RhG-r/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="179324" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/12/an-out-of-focus-blurred-picture-of-an-emergency-ambulance-crew-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="an out of focus blurred picture of an emergency ambulance crew" class="wp-image-179324" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/12/an-out-of-focus-blurred-picture-of-an-emergency-ambulance-crew-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/12/an-out-of-focus-blurred-picture-of-an-emergency-ambulance-crew-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/12/an-out-of-focus-blurred-picture-of-an-emergency-ambulance-crew-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DBuBHtdJtgR/?img_index=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="342450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/Woman-drinking-coffee-looking-out-the-window-thinking-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Woman drinking coffee, looking out the window, thinking" class="wp-image-342450" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/Woman-drinking-coffee-looking-out-the-window-thinking-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/Woman-drinking-coffee-looking-out-the-window-thinking-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/Woman-drinking-coffee-looking-out-the-window-thinking-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/Woman-drinking-coffee-looking-out-the-window-thinking-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/06/Woman-drinking-coffee-looking-out-the-window-thinking-16x9-1.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>
</figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week.</h3>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-stroke-treatment/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Stroke treatment</a></h2>



<p>Each year, an estimated 15 million people around the globe experience stroke, according to the World Health Organization, with one-third resulting in death. When the symptoms of stroke present, calling 911 and seeking care immediately is the most crucial step to prevent disability or death.⁠</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/the-4-types-of-systemic-therapy-for-breast-cancer/">The 4 types of systemic therapy for breast cancer</a></h2>



<p>Treatment for breast cancer can come in many forms. In addition to surgery to remove cancerous tissue and radiation therapy, breast cancer also is commonly treated with drugs that are taken orally or intravenously, as an infusion into a vein.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-jessies-journey/">Life after liver transplant — 'Fight… because it's worth it'</a></h2>



<p>Stomach pain is something everyone has probably had at some point in their life. But for Jessie Boyd, her stomach pain set in motion a journey that led her to Mayo Clinic and the experts who could perform a lifesaving surgery.⁠</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/research-shows-new-method-helps-doctors-safely-remove-dangerous-heart-infections-without-surgery/#/">Research shows new method helps doctors safely remove dangerous heart infections without surgery</a></h2>



<p>Doctors at&nbsp;Mayo Clinic&nbsp;used a new catheter-based approach to draw out resistant pockets of infection that settle in the heart, known as right-sided&nbsp;infective endocarditis, without surgery. The research is part of a Mayo Clinic-led study across 19 U.S. sites involving patients who were not good candidates for surgery and whose right-sided heart infections had not responded to antibiotics.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-experts-highlight-advances-in-breast-cancer-research-decreasing-the-need-for-chemotherapy-and-reducing-the-intensity-of-radiation-therapy/">Mayo Clinic experts highlight advances in breast cancer research</a></h2>



<p>Lifesaving cancer therapies can cause serious side effects, both immediately and later in life. With breast cancer rates rising among younger people, the need for treatments that provide excellent outcomes with fewer side effects is only increasing.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-34/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/12/an-out-of-focus-blurred-picture-of-an-emergency-ambulance-crew-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/web-top-5_11012024.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>(VIDEO) Harnessing the power of innovation and a patient&#8217;s will to survive</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/videoharnessing-the-power-of-innovation-and-a-patients-will-to-survive/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 19:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Healthcare Delivery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395496</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>At 27 years old, Shraddha Kalgutkar was told she had less than a year to live. Determined to prove everyone wrong, she turned to Mayo Clinic in Arizona. Now Shraddha is living proof of the power of innovation combined with a patient's will to survive. Watch: Harnessing the power of innovation and a patient's will [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/videoharnessing-the-power-of-innovation-and-a-patients-will-to-survive/">(VIDEO) Harnessing the power of innovation and a patient&#8217;s will to survive</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Close-up-of-shraddha-on-ECMO_16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395836" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Close-up-of-shraddha-on-ECMO_16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Close-up-of-shraddha-on-ECMO_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Close-up-of-shraddha-on-ECMO_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Close-up-of-shraddha-on-ECMO_16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Close-up-of-shraddha-on-ECMO_16x9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong><mark style="background-color:#ffffff" class="has-inline-color has-black-color">Shraddha Kaltgutar at Mayo Clinic in Phoenix, AZ</mark></strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>At 27 years old, Shraddha Kalgutkar was told she had less than a year to live. Determined to prove everyone wrong, she turned to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> in Arizona.</p>



<p>Now Shraddha is living proof of the power of innovation combined with a patient's will to survive.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LlFER2E3OEo" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Watch: Harnessing the power of innovation and a patient's will to survive</strong></a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidLlFER2E3OEo"  title="Harnessing the power of innovation and a patient&#039;s will to survive" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/LlFER2E3OEo?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (4:03) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Shraddhas-story.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a></strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Shraddha's Story</strong></h2>



<p>It was November 2022, just a month shy of her 28th birthday.</p>



<p>Shraddha was wrapping up another day at the medical clinic where she worked as an occupational therapist. Shraddha's job was to help patients regain the ability to perform day-to-day activities following a health challenge like a surgery.</p>



<p>Suddenly that afternoon, Shraddha became the patient who needed help.</p>



<p>"My co-worker looked at me and said, 'Why is your hand all purple and blue?'" Shraddha says. She admits she had been feeling exceptionally tired as of late, but attributed it to a thyroid condition.</p>



<p>Her co-worker checked Shraddha's vital signs and found her blood oxygen level was dangerously low. "I remember her saying, 'If this is right, you wouldn't even be standing.'" A repeat test showed the same result. "The next thing I remember was we were on our way to the hospital," says Shraddha.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="822" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach-822x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395502" style="width:650px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach-822x1024.jpg 822w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach-241x300.jpg 241w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach-768x957.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach-1233x1536.jpg 1233w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach-1643x2048.jpg 1643w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach.jpg 1812w" sizes="(max-width: 822px) 100vw, 822px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><mark style="background-color:#ffffff" class="has-inline-color has-black-color"><strong>Shraddha enjoying the California coastline two years after surviving a condition that nearly took her life</strong></mark></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>At the hospital doctors began looking for the cause of Shraddha's low blood oxygen level.  A series of tests traced Shraddha's condition all the way back to the day she was born.</p>



<p>"When I was born, doctors said I had fatty liver, but they didn't know why so they called it 'undiagnosed,'" says Shraddha. "The doctors thought it wouldn't be a problem because the liver has a tendency to heal itself." It didn't. Shraddha grew up seemingly in perfect health, unaware that her <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/the-silent-liver-disease-experts-warn-is-on-the-rise-among-hispanics-and-children/">liver disease</a> was silently doing damage to her body.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A little girl with a big dream</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="226" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-little-girl-pic-1-226x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395820" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-little-girl-pic-1-226x300.jpg 226w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-little-girl-pic-1-771x1024.jpg 771w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-little-girl-pic-1-768x1019.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-little-girl-pic-1.jpg 1054w" sizes="(max-width: 226px) 100vw, 226px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Shraddah at 5 years old in her childhood home in Mumbai, India</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Shraddha was born in Mumbai, India which is often called the "City of Dreams." At a young age, Shraddha had big dreams of her own.  She wanted to pursue a career in the medical field that would allow her to help others. </p>



<p>Every year Shraddha went to the doctor for her routine physical. Each time she was given a clean bill of health. "I used to do blood tests, but everything always looked good," says Shraddha. Still, the question of what caused her congenital liver condition lingered in her mind.</p>



<p>"I didn't have a family history of any liver condition. I've never had alcohol in my life," says Shraddha. "There was always a question mark. I needed to find out why this happened to me."</p>



<p>At 23, Shraddha became the first person in her family to leave India and go to the U.S. to attend college. She studied occupational therapy and got her master's degree at the University of Southern California. After college, Shraddha found her dream job at a medical clinic in California.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">'<strong>You have less than a year to live</strong>'</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="799" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-sad-1024x799.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395512" style="width:719px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-sad-1024x799.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-sad-300x234.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-sad-768x599.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-sad-1536x1199.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-sad.jpg 1848w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p>All was going well until Shraddha began to noticed she was unusually tired. "When my sister came to visit she noticed I got tired after walking short distances. I went to the doctor and they thought maybe it was my thyroid," recalls Shraddha.</p>



<p>Then came the day her hands turned purple and her blood oxygen level mysteriously dropped. "My co-worker is a nurse so she got the oximeter and checked and it was 78%," says Shraddha. "And I was like, No, that's not possible because I wouldn't be alive." Shraddha's co-worker checked again, looked at the reading and said, "That's it, you have to go to the hospital."</p>



<p>A series of tests at the hospital revealed shocking results. Shraddha's liver condition had silently led to a more serious condition called hepatopulmonary syndrome.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Hepatopulmonary syndrome</strong></h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hepatopulmonary-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20373350" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hepatopulmonary syndrome</a> is caused when liver disease shunts blood away from the lungs preventing the body from getting the appropriate amount of oxygen. Doctors told Shraddha the only way she would survive is with a liver transplant. However, she says she was told her condition was so severe and the risk so high, that she would likely not survive a transplant.</p>



<p>She was denied the transplant and given less than a year to live.</p>



<p>"I told the doctors 'that just can't be. I can't have just one year with nothing to bring to this world. I have not served my purpose,'" recalls Shraddha. </p>



<p>Refusing to give up, Shraddha turned to Mayo Clinic in Arizona.</p>



<p>"More than 40% of her blood was being shunted away from her lungs. Because of that she had extremely low oxygen levels in her blood," explains <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/aqel-bashar-a-m-d/bio-20055093" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bashar Aqel, M.D.</a>, director of the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/sections/expertise-ranking/orc-20203899?customer_id=173-378-9621&amp;mc_id=google&amp;campaign=20718088499&amp;geo=9030070&amp;kw=transplant%20center%20arizona&amp;ad=678670770145&amp;network=g&amp;sitetarget=&amp;adgroup=158054873227&amp;extension=&amp;target=kwd-1284412548384&amp;matchtype=p&amp;device=c&amp;account=1733789621&amp;invsrc=transplant&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;gclid=EAIaIQobChMI1bPG-JO5iQMVrjYIBR0f-AKlEAAYASAAEgKkU_D_BwE" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Transplant Center at Mayo Clinic in Arizona.</a> "Shraddha's case was one of the most severe cases of liver disease and hepatopulmonary syndrome."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="205" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Aqel-talking-about-Shraddha-300x205.png" alt="" class="wp-image-395516" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Aqel-talking-about-Shraddha-300x205.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Aqel-talking-about-Shraddha-1024x701.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Aqel-talking-about-Shraddha-768x526.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Aqel-talking-about-Shraddha-1536x1052.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Aqel-talking-about-Shraddha-2048x1403.png 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Bashar Aqel, M.D., Director, Mayo Clinic Transplant Center in Arizona</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Saving Shraddha</strong></h2>



<p>The liver transplant was Shraddha's only hope for survival. "Without a transplant, this disease was progressive and fatal. We don't like to use this word, but it is a very progressive disease," says Dr. Aqel. "There was no other cure than a liver transplant."</p>



<p>Dr. Aqel and his multidisciplinary team of experts at Mayo Clinic went to work on a strategy to save Shraddha. The team came up with a plan using a combination of some of the latest cutting-edge technologies in medicine. </p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">"<strong>Liver in a box</strong>"</h2>



<p>Transplanting any organ is a race agains the clock. Every second the donor organ is outside the body it begins to break down. Surgeons only have a limited time window to transplant the organ. Due to the complexity of Shraddha's case, Dr. Aqel's team knew they would need extra time. They decided to use one of the latest medical breakthroughs in transplant often referred to as <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-liver-in-a-box-is-saving-lives-with-new-technology/">"liver in a box."</a></p>



<p>Traditionally donor organs are kept cold until transplanted. "Liver in a box" uses a warm organ preservation method. The organ is placed in a container that pumps oxygenated, nutrient-rich blood through the liver simulating conditions in the human body. The innovative perfusion system gives surgeons more time to perform the transplant. </p>



<p>"Having the donor "liver in a box" allowed the donor liver to stay healthy while we performed this complex surgery," says Dr. Aqel.</p>



<p>Currently, this warm perfusion technology is primarily being used for <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-innovation-new-heart-in-a-box-technology-provides-gift-of-life-to-arizona-man-as-couple-prepares-to-celebrate-50-year-anniversary/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart, lungs and liver transplants</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Liver-In-a-box-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395567" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Liver-In-a-box-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Liver-In-a-box-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Liver-In-a-box-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Liver-In-a-box-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Liver-In-a-box-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">"<strong>Liver in a box" safely preserves donor organ at body temperature until transplant</strong></figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Saving lives with mobile ECMO</strong></h2>



<p>The next challenge was how to keep Shraddha's blood oxygen levels stable after her transplant. Dr. Aqel's team turned to a device called <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/young-patient-with-covid-19-recovering-after-hospital-stay-ecmo-support/">extracorporeal membrane oxygenation, or ECMO</a>. The device often is used when the lungs aren't working properly. ECMO helps with the appropriate gas exchange that must occur to keep the body's blood oxygen level safe.</p>



<p>"It helps in getting oxygen into the blood and carbon dioxide out of the blood through the machine," explains <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/sen-ayan-m-d/bio-20055718" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ayan Sen, M.D.</a>, medical director of Mayo Clinic's Intensive Care Unit in Arizona. "It helped us while her lungs recovered after her transplant."</p>



<p>The Mayo team also used one of the newest advancements in ECMO where the device is mobile. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="723" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-mobile-ECMO-3-723x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395506" style="width:558px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-mobile-ECMO-3-723x1024.jpg 723w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-mobile-ECMO-3-212x300.jpg 212w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-mobile-ECMO-3-768x1088.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-mobile-ECMO-3.jpg 826w" sizes="(max-width: 723px) 100vw, 723px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Shraddha walking on mobile ECMO on December 24, 2022</strong> <strong>- her 28th birthday</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"The best part of the mobile ECMO was that we do it in a way where she could actually walk around with the machine so that we could continue with her physical therapy, which is so important for the healing process after such a complex surgery," says Dr. Sen.</p>



<p>Shraddha was in the ICU for nearly two months. With mobile ECMO she walked nearly every day.</p>



<p>Dr. Sen says mobile ECMO has proved to be a game-changer in critical cases like Shraddha's.</p>



<p>"It is technology that has really expanded from what surgeons do when they do heart surgeries and transplants where now we can do this to save lives at any place that is not a complex environment, like the ICU or the operating rooms," explains Dr. Sen.</p>



<p>Mobile ECMO has become a lifesaving medical breakthrough for many patients.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="178" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Sen-close-up-headshot-300x178.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395520" style="width:312px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Sen-close-up-headshot-300x178.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Sen-close-up-headshot-1024x607.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Sen-close-up-headshot-768x455.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Sen-close-up-headshot-1536x910.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Sen-close-up-headshot-2048x1214.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Ayan Sen, M.D., Medical Director, Intensive Care Unit at Mayo Clinic in Arizona</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"It has enabled us to raise the bar when it comes to saving people, who, until now, could not have been saved in the absence of this heart-lung machine," says Dr. Sen.</p>



<p>A team of highly specialized experts escorted Shraddha on her daily walks, meticulously monitoring her vital signs. Each step required Shraddha to muster every bit of strength she had.</p>



<p>"From the first day, I thought even if it pains me, if it hurts, even if it feels impossible, I still need to put that step forward to do something better today than yesterday," recalls Shraddha. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p><strong>"I was in a race with myself every day"</strong></p><cite>-Shraddha</cite></blockquote></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>'Mayo's mission is now my purpose'</strong></h2>



<p>Almost two years after her harrowing experience, Shraddha is healthy and back at work. She continues her daily walks, only now, at the beach, in solitude, reflecting on how her own experience can make her a better healthcare professional.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="792" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-at-Mayo-792x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-395850" style="width:567px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-at-Mayo-792x1024.png 792w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-at-Mayo-232x300.png 232w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-at-Mayo-768x993.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-at-Mayo-1188x1536.png 1188w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-at-Mayo.png 1406w" sizes="(max-width: 792px) 100vw, 792px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Shraddha visiting Mayo Clinic after her lifesaving transplant</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Mayo Clinic doesn't like to say no. They set out to achieve the unachievable," says Shraddha. "My goal is to treat patients as they do, making them a priority."</p>



<p>Shraddha says words of thanks alone are not enough to convey her gratitude.</p>



<p>"Dr. Aqel and his team achieved something for me that everyone else thought was impossible," says Shraddha. "It was a gift. I will keep the mission of Mayo Clinic in mind when I am serving my patients. My purpose now is to put forward their purpose and help someone else."</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Related articles:</strong></h2>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-innovation-new-heart-in-a-box-technology-provides-gift-of-life-to-arizona-man-as-couple-prepares-to-celebrate-50-year-anniversary/">Heart Transplant Innovation: New ‘heart in a box’ technology provides gift of life to Arizona man, as couple prepares to celebrate 50-</a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-innovation-new-heart-in-a-box-technology-provides-gift-of-life-to-arizona-man-as-couple-prepares-to-celebrate-50-year-anniversary/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">year</a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-innovation-new-heart-in-a-box-technology-provides-gift-of-life-to-arizona-man-as-couple-prepares-to-celebrate-50-year-anniversary/"> anniversary</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-barriers-helping-native-americans-in-need-get-the-gift-of-life/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Breaking barriers: Helping Native Americans in need get the gift of life</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/organ-transplant-innovation-helping-more-people-get-the-gift-of-life/">Organ Transplant Innovation: Helping more people get the gift of life</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/videoharnessing-the-power-of-innovation-and-a-patients-will-to-survive/">(VIDEO) Harnessing the power of innovation and a patient&#8217;s will to survive</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: How change in sunlight can affect your mood</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-change-in-sunlight-can-affect-your-mood/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 16:02:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Daylight Saving Time]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jesse Bracamonte]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[light therapy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376261</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Many parts of the U.S. – and the world — will soon "fall back" as daylight saving time ends and clocks fall back one hour. This year, the change takes place in the U.S. at 2 a.m. local time on Sunday, Nov. 3. That means an extra hour of sleep – and earlier sunrises and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-change-in-sunlight-can-affect-your-mood/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How change in sunlight can affect your mood</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Many parts of the U.S. – and the world — will soon "fall back" as daylight saving time ends and clocks fall back one hour. This year, the change takes place in the U.S. at 2 a.m. local time on Sunday, Nov. 3. That means an extra hour of sleep – and earlier sunrises and sunsets. </p>



<p>How does less sun affect your mood and level of energy?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/bracamonte-jesus-jesse-d-d-o/bio-20432246" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Jesse Bracamonte,</a>&nbsp;a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician, says sunlight can influence the levels of neurochemicals in the brain.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/d3ySCLBD-j4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Mayo-Clinic-Minute-How-change-in-sunlight-can-affect-your-mood_CLEAN.mp4"></video></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:00) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/SCRIPT-MCM-Change-in-sunlight-affect-mood-FINAL29.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"People can feel more tired with less light due to the neurochemical or brain hormonal changes that occur with a change of season or less light. A common chemical that regulates that is called serotonin," says Dr. Bracamonte.</p>



<p>But what happens when you have less exposure to the sun and your serotonin levels are off?</p>



<p>"Your mood may be off, your sleep may be off, the way you regulate your mood cycle — whether you're happy or you're feeling a bit down — can be off. And that can have a downstream effect just the way you feel in general," he says.</p>



<p>Dr. Bracamonte says there are things you can do to feel better.</p>



<p>"If you can, get sunlight. Get plenty of&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-sleep-spoilers-tips-for-a-good-nights-rest/">rest.</a>&nbsp;Get exercise, be active. Make sure to eat a well-balanced diet full of fruits and veggies," he says.</p>



<p>And consider a light therapy lamp. They are designed to simulate natural sunlight.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/woman-sitting-with-a-light-therapy-lamp-for-SAD-or-depression-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="woman sitting with a light therapy lamp for SAD or depression" class="wp-image-104807" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/woman-sitting-with-a-light-therapy-lamp-for-SAD-or-depression-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/woman-sitting-with-a-light-therapy-lamp-for-SAD-or-depression-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/woman-sitting-with-a-light-therapy-lamp-for-SAD-or-depression-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Using light therapy can help with mood </figcaption></figure>



<p>"In many cases, I do recommend light therapy for people who aren't getting enough sun to help with mood and balance those neurochemicals out. It's one of the treatments for improving moods, particularly during the gloomy season," says Dr. Bracamonte.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Help your mood with good sleep</h3>



<p>As the time change date approaches, here are two things you can do to alleviate the sleep disturbance that may come along with it.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Adjust your internal clock gradually</strong><br>In the days leading up to the time change, adjust your sleep and wake times in small increments so your body can transition gradually. Shift your bedtime and wake time in 15- to 30-minute increments.</li>



<li><strong>Spend time outdoors</strong><br>Sunlight affects your body's circadian rhythm, and spending time outdoors can alleviate feelings of fatigue that often accompany time changes.</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-change-in-sunlight-can-affect-your-mood/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How change in sunlight can affect your mood</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/11/Autumn-Time-Change-Autumn-Leaves-and-Alarm-Clock-with-a-pumpkin-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/11/Autumn-Time-Change-Autumn-Leaves-and-Alarm-Clock-with-a-pumpkin-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Daylight Saving Time]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jesse Bracamonte]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[light therapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Boosting kids&#8217; health literacy</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-boosting-kids-health-literacy/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[DeeDee Stiepan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Children's Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dadily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Angela Mattke]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376047</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>October is National Health Literacy Month. Health literacy refers to the ability of people to find, understand, and use information and services to make informed health-related decisions and actions for themselves and others. In this Mayo Clinic Minute, Dr. Angela Mattke, a pediatrician with Mayo Clinic’s Children’s Center, explains how Mayo Clinic is leading the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-boosting-kids-health-literacy/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Boosting kids&#8217; health literacy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>October is National Health Literacy Month. Health literacy refers to the ability of people to find, understand, and use information and services to make informed health-related decisions and actions for themselves and others.</p>



<p>In this Mayo Clinic Minute, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mattke-angela-c-m-d/bio-20055584" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Angela Mattke</a>, a pediatrician with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/childrens-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic’s Children’s Center</a>, explains how <a href="https://mcpress.mayoclinic.org/parenting/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is leading the way to enhance health literacy for kids through engaging books to inform and inspire young people.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/jPCG_tjUUKU" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Mayo-Clinic-Minute-Boosting-kids-health-literacy-CLEAN.mp4"></video></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:07) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/SCRIPT-MCM-Health-literacy-for-kids.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Developing personal health literacy — which is the ability to find, understand, and use health-related information and services — is something that can begin early in life.</p>



<p>"Mayo Clinic is truly an expert in healthcare. And we have an opportunity to be there talking with children, getting them excited about their health and empowering them to have agency over their own health and the health of their communities," says Dr. Mattke.</p>



<p>Dr. Mattke says these types of books provide accessible information on a wide range of health and science-related topics.</p>



<p>"I think there's a lot of health topics that children struggle to understand — anything from immunizations to why they're feeling sick, especially when children have serious and complex diseases," says Dr. Mattke.</p>



<p>Understanding their disease can help them feel empowered and knowledgeable about how they can participate in their care. But it's not just kids with serious health conditions that can benefit from this education.</p>



<p>"My children have read all these books and have read them multiple and multiple times. And so, they can help understand these diseases. It's inspiring their passion to learn more about science and learn more about health," says Dr. Mattke.</p>



<p>Which is another goal of promoting health literacy in children.</p>



<p>"We need to get kids interested in STEM — science, engineering, technology and medicine. And these are really important topics. And so, we're bringing these topics to kids to get them interested at an early age and inspire that passion.," says Dr. Mattke.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-boosting-kids-health-literacy/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Boosting kids&#8217; health literacy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Health-Literacy-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Health-Literacy-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[dadily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Angela Mattke]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Adapting to life after spinal cord injury with rehab and determination</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/adapting-to-life-after-spinal-cord-injury-with-rehab-and-determination/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395473</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>What began as a creative backyard project changed Laurie Reese's life forever. An avid gardener, Laurie envisioned turning an unused outhouse on their property into an ideal garden shed. So on a November day in 2007, Laurie's husband, Pete, used their skid loader to move the structure. While Laurie was guiding Pete, she noticed the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/adapting-to-life-after-spinal-cord-injury-with-rehab-and-determination/">Adapting to life after spinal cord injury with rehab and determination</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/LauriePeteBella-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395475" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/LauriePeteBella-16x9-1.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/LauriePeteBella-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/LauriePeteBella-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>What began as a creative backyard project changed Laurie Reese's life forever.</p>



<p>An avid gardener, Laurie envisioned turning an unused outhouse on their property into an ideal garden shed. So on a November day in 2007, Laurie's husband, Pete, used their skid loader to move the structure. While Laurie was guiding Pete, she noticed the outhouse was wobbling, so she put her hands out to steady it. That’s when the structure fell over, trapping Laurie beneath it.</p>



<p>Pete was able to lift the outhouse just enough so that Laurie could pull herself most of the way out from under it, and Pete pulled her the rest of the way to safety. Paramedics took Laurie from her home in Oronoco, Minnesota, to&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/minnesota/campus-buildings-maps/mayo-clinic-hospital-saint-marys-campus" target="_blank">Mayo Clinic Hospital, Saint Marys Campus</a>&nbsp;in Rochester, Minnesota.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A sobering prognosis</h2>



<p>Laurie and Pete learned that two vertebrae in her thoracic (middle) spine were damaged. She had a fracture of the T12 vertebrae and a fracture dislocation of the T11 and T12 vertebrae.</p>



<p>The next day, she underwent nearly six hours of surgery. Her prognosis following the operation was dire: Laurie would have a 0-3% chance of walking again.</p>



<p>"I was in shock and not really thinking clearly. So many things were running through my head," Laurie says. "I was just 39 and wondered if this injury would shorten my life. Our daughter was pregnant with our first grandchild, and I thought, 'Well, I've still got use of my arms, so at least I can hold the baby.'"</p>



<p>Thoughts of her future grandchild spurred her to work especially hard in therapy to gain as much strength, movement and ability to do everyday tasks as possible. Laurie also knew two people who had quadriplegia, so she understood the reality of her situation.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Preparing for her new life&nbsp;</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="244" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/reese-walking-in-therapy.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395478" style="aspect-ratio:3/4;object-fit:cover;width:278px;height:auto" /></figure></div>


<p>Laurie began rehabilitation while still in the hospital, then transferred to the Mary Brigh Building on the Saint Marys Campus for intensive, inpatient rehabilitation to adapt to her new life. </p>



<p>In rehab, Laurie worked with physical and occupational therapists to practice and learn a wide range of skills and activities, including:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Stretching her legs.</li>



<li>Rolling over and sitting up.</li>



<li>Inserting a catheter.</li>



<li>Using a wheelchair.</li>



<li>Transferring in and out of vehicles.</li>



<li>Showering and dressing.</li>



<li>Using a machine that supported her, braced her legs and simulated walking.</li>



<li>Performing daily chores like cooking, doing the dishes and opening cupboards. </li>
</ul>



<p>"Before they let you leave rehabilitation, you go home for a day," Laurie says. "That's when the reality hits you that this is your life going forward."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Adapting, learning and doing what she wants </h2>



<p>By December 20, Laurie was ready to return home. Once home, outpatient therapy and occupational therapists make suggestions for adapting the house to meet her needs. To accommodate her wheelchair, the Reeses added a ramp to the house and eventually remodeled the kitchen.</p>



<p>Once the basics were manageable, Laurie focused on resuming the things she loved to do, such as gardening, horseback riding and snowmobiling.</p>



<p>Pete made modifications so she could indulge in her love of flowers. He revamped the garden beds to make them smaller and more manageable, built raised beds that Laurie could reach and added a fountain.</p>



<p>Another goal of Laurie's was to try horseback riding again. She was able to sit on her horse a couple of times but realized it wasn't feasible to safely ride.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/reese-posed-on-snowmobile.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395477" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/reese-posed-on-snowmobile.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/reese-posed-on-snowmobile-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></figure></div>


<p>Snowmobiling was a different story. After testing her comfort and ability on an older machine, she opted to get a new one with upgrades like an electric start, reverse gear, heated hand warmers and more. With a strap anchoring her legs, she's taken several trips — and even some spills — and continues to tinker with the design of her seat.</p>



<p>Since the accident, Laurie has been determined to live life on her own terms. With help from her therapists and plenty of practice, she stood for pictures at a daughter's wedding.</p>



<p>She holds, cares for and plays with her eight grandchildren. When she wants to see them, she loads her wheelchair onto the lift bed, gets into her pickup and drives to their homes.</p>



<p>Laurie also returned to work in cardiovascular education for Mayo Clinic in Rochester, a position she's held for 19 years. She provides digital education for medical staff needing board certification or recertification.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Nearly 20 years of success</h2>



<p>Although it's been 17 years since her accident, Laurie still battles issues like pressure sores that landed her in the hospital for three months this year. That hospitalization set her back, and she spent nearly three months in rehabilitation at <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/cannon-falls" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System in Cannon Falls</a>, Minnesota.</p>



<p>"It still can be rough. Some days are better than others, and I get jealous of those who can easily do something like picking up a baby," she says. "And nothing is as easy as you think it will be, but you make it work. You have to have the mindset and the drive to constantly adapt."</p>



<p>What helped Laurie develop that mindset and drive was a journal her rehab team encouraged her to write in the hospital after her initial injury. The journal evolved into a book, "My Life Beyond the Outhouse: The First Two Years." Laurie focused on the first two years because she was most likely to regain any mobility during that time.</p>



<p>"Publishing the book helped me talk about my injury, and my family and friends got a better understanding of what I was going through," Laurie says. "People who read it say they had no idea how much of your life is affected by being paralyzed."</p>



<p>While her life changed on that November day, it didn't end. Laurie attributes her success to her rehabilitation team and their ongoing care.</p>



<p>"I couldn't have asked for better people on my side. When I cried, they gave me a shoulder to cry on," she says. "I can't imagine not having the training they gave me. Because of them, I was able to start out in a new capacity, and today, I'm able to do almost whatever I want."</p>



<p>"Even now, when I go in for appointments, they remember me and know my story. It's so neat that out of the thousands of patients they've seen, we still have that connection."</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/patient-stories/spinal-cord-injury" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/adapting-to-life-after-spinal-cord-injury-with-rehab-and-determination/">Adapting to life after spinal cord injury with rehab and determination</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/LauriePeteBella-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/LauriePeteBella-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: 3 tips to avoid Halloween hand injuries</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-3-tips-to-avoid-halloween-hand-injuries/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sanj Kakar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[halloween]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hand injury]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=218012</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>There are plenty of frights to go around on Halloween, but a hand injury probably isn't one you'd expect. "Interestingly, it's the fourth busiest holiday for hand injuries," says Dr. Sanj Kakar, a Mayo Clinic orthopedic hand and wrist surgeon. Dr. Kakar says almost one-third of those Halloween hand injuries are among kids ages 10 [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-3-tips-to-avoid-halloween-hand-injuries/">Mayo Clinic Minute: 3 tips to avoid Halloween hand injuries</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>There are plenty of frights to go around on Halloween, but a hand injury probably isn't one you'd expect.</p>



<p>"Interestingly, it's the fourth busiest holiday for hand injuries," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/kakar-sanjeev-sanj-m-d/bio-20055340?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Dr. Sanj Kakar</a>, a Mayo Clinic orthopedic hand and wrist surgeon.</p>



<p>Dr. Kakar says almost one-third of those Halloween hand injuries are among kids ages 10 to 14. And most of them happen when people are carving pumpkins.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/XlWXkwaRfa4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Mayo-Clinic-Minute-3-tips-to-avoid-Halloween-hand-injuries_CLEAN.mp4"></video></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:00) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post.<br>Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/MCM-3-tips-to-avoid-Halloween-hand-injuries-SCRIPT3.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"It's primarily stabbing injuries where the knife may slip, and, so, they can cut things like tendons, which are the ropes that help move your hands," Dr. Kakar says. "But they can also break bones, and also they can burn themselves, as well, with candles."</p>



<p>But Dr. Kakar says most of the injuries are avoidable.</p>



<p>"A lot of people might just go to the kitchen and grab a sharp knife. But there's good studies out there showing that actual pumpkin-specific carving knives [are safer], [because] actually the force needed to injure yourself, is higher if you use one of those than if you use a standard knife," he says. "So I would use a pumpkin carving kit, No. 1."</p>



<p>No. 2, Dr. Kakar says, is to let kids handle designing the jack-o'-lantern, but make sure adults do all of the carving.</p>



<p>And No. 3, make sure you're always supporting the pumpkin with your noncutting hand.</p>



<p>"So if you're right-handed, use your left hand to support the pumpkin and carve from the top down as opposed to the bottom up," Dr. Kakar says. "It's very easy for the knife to slip and go into your hand."</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-3-tips-to-avoid-halloween-hand-injuries/">Mayo Clinic Minute: 3 tips to avoid Halloween hand injuries</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/shutterstock_306948755_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/shutterstock_306948755_Fotor-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Sanj Kakar]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[halloween]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[hand injury]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-33/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jaynelle Ramon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395417</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week. Mayo Clinic performs its first paired living liver donation People can donate up to 70% of their liver because the liver has the&#160;unique ability to regenerate itself within a month. While paired living donation is commonly used [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-33/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-2 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DBcID3ztlMy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="395013" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/GettyImages-1481914173.jpg1920-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395013" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/GettyImages-1481914173.jpg1920-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/GettyImages-1481914173.jpg1920-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/GettyImages-1481914173.jpg1920-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/GettyImages-1481914173.jpg1920-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/GettyImages-1481914173.jpg1920.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/MayoClinic/posts/pfbid0HMq3G9aGUrV79D3KHyyGUxEWKDh1xoDRchgshVD3pwtc3qsUEEqEvWTcvmSpGsTfl" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="395365" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395365" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/706347941527986/posts/950789440417167" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" data-id="116567" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/03/a-close-up-of-two-feet-one-on-the-floor-and-the-other-held-in-the-persons-hands-16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-116567" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/03/a-close-up-of-two-feet-one-on-the-floor-and-the-other-held-in-the-persons-hands-16x9.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/03/a-close-up-of-two-feet-one-on-the-floor-and-the-other-held-in-the-persons-hands-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DBeWp2dvA8l/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="395350" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Paired-Liver-Surgery1-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395350" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Paired-Liver-Surgery1-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Paired-Liver-Surgery1-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Paired-Liver-Surgery1-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Paired-Liver-Surgery1-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Paired-Liver-Surgery1-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DBZCpCtJX9r/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="395137" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395137" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>
</figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week.</h3>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-performs-its-first-paired-living-liver-donation/">Mayo Clinic performs its first paired living liver donation</a></h2>



<p>People can donate up to 70% of their liver because the liver has the&nbsp;unique ability to regenerate itself within a month. While paired living donation is commonly used for kidney transplants, it is relatively rare for liver transplants.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Surgeons recently performed Mayo Clinic's first paired living liver donation, a significant first step in helping more people with liver failure get a lifesaving transplant.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-radiation-therapy-for-patients-with-breast-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer</a></h2>



<p>Radiation therapy is a common component of breast cancer treatment for patients. The high-powered beams of intense energy kill cancer cells and reduce the risk of the cancer recurring.</p>



<p>Dr. Laura Vallow, chair of the Radiation Oncology Department at Mayo Clinic in Florida, explains how innovation is transforming radiation treatments.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-clean-out-old-medications-safely/#/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Clean out old medications safely</a></h2>



<p>Leftover or expired medications can be dangerous if not disposed of properly. Safely getting rid of unneeded prescriptions, like opioids or expired drugs, is essential to prevent&nbsp;misuse&nbsp;and accidental harm.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Tina Ardon, a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician, says proper medication disposal helps safeguard your home and community from unnecessary risks.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-what-standing-on-one-leg-can-tell-you/">What standing on one leg can tell you about aging</a></h2>



<p>How long a person can stand — on one leg — is a more telltale measure of aging than changes in strength or gait, according to new Mayo Clinic research. Good balance, muscle strength and an efficient gait contribute to people's independence and well-being as&nbsp;they age.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-shockwave-therapy-may-help-relieve-foot-problem/">Shockwave therapy may help relieve foot problem</a></h2>



<p>Shockwave therapy is a noninvasive treatment that uses sound waves to transmit energy to tissues to help with the healing process. It can be used for foot and ankle issues including plantar fasciitis, tendinitis, stress fractures and shin splints.⁠</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-33/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Paired-Liver-Surgery1-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/web-top-5_10252024.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic study: What standing on one leg can tell you</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-what-standing-on-one-leg-can-tell-you/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rhoda Madson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 18:04:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Aging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Kenton Kaufman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health and wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395368</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — How long a person can stand — on one leg — is a more telltale measure of aging than changes in strength or gait, according to new Mayo Clinic research. The study appears today in the journal PLOS ONE. Good balance, muscle strength and an efficient gait contribute to people's independence and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-what-standing-on-one-leg-can-tell-you/">Mayo Clinic study: What standing on one leg can tell you</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395365" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — How long a person can stand — on one leg — is a more telltale measure of aging than changes in strength or gait, according to new <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> research. The <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0310764" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> appears today in the journal PLOS ONE.</p>



<p>Good balance, muscle strength and an efficient gait contribute to people's independence and well-being as&nbsp;they age. How these factors change, and at what rate, can help clinicians develop programs to ensure healthy aging. Individually, people can train their balance without special equipment and work on maintaining it over time.</p>



<p>In this study, 40 healthy, independent people over 50 underwent walking, balance, grip strength and knee strength tests. Half of the participants were under 65; the other half were 65 and older.</p>



<p>In the balance tests, participants stood on force plates in different situations: on both feet with eyes open, on both feet with eyes closed, on the non-dominant leg with eyes open, and on the dominant leg with eyes open. In the one-legged tests, participants could hold the leg they weren't standing on where they wanted. The tests were 30 seconds each.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Kaufman-Kenton-R._10436286_202109151225-250x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395367" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Kaufman-Kenton-R._10436286_202109151225-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Kaufman-Kenton-R._10436286_202109151225-854x1024.jpg 854w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Kaufman-Kenton-R._10436286_202109151225-768x921.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Kaufman-Kenton-R._10436286_202109151225.jpg 938w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Kenton Kaufman</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Standing on one leg — specifically the nondominant leg — showed the highest rate of decline with age.</p>



<p>"Balance is an important measure because, in addition to muscle strength, it requires input from vision, the vestibular system and the somatosensory systems," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/kaufman-kenton-r-ph-d/bio-20054278?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kenton Kaufman, Ph.D.</a>, senior author of the study and director of the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/motion-analysis/overview?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Motion Analysis Laboratory</a> at Mayo Clinic. "Changes in balance are noteworthy. If you have poor balance, you're at risk of falling, whether or not you're moving. Falls are a severe health risk with serious consequences."</p>



<p>Unintentional falls are the leading cause of injuries among adults who are 65 and older. Most falls among older adults result from a loss of balance.</p>



<p>In the other tests:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Researchers used a custom-made device to measure participants' grip. For the knee strength test, participants were in a seated position and instructed to extend their knee as forcefully as possible. Both the grip and knee strength tests were on the dominant side. Grip and knee strength showed significant declines by decade but not as much as balance. Grip strength decreased at a faster rate than knee strength, making it better at predicting aging than other strength measures.</li>



<li>For the gait test, participants walked back and forth on an 8-meter, level walkway at their own pace and speed. Gait parameters didn't change with age. This was not a surprising result since participants were walking at their normal pace, not their maximum pace, Dr. Kaufman says.</li>



<li>There were no age-related declines in the strength tests that were specific to sex. This indicates that participants' grip and knee strength declined at a similar rate. Researchers did not identify sex differences in the gait and balance tests, which suggests that male and female subjects were equally affected by age.</li>
</ul>



<p>Dr. Kaufman says people can take steps to train their balance. For example, by standing on one leg, you can train yourself to coordinate your muscle and vestibular responses to maintain correct balance. If you can stand on one leg for 30 seconds, you are doing well, he says.</p>



<p>"If you don't use it, you lose it. If you use it, you maintain it," Dr. Kaufman says. "It's easy to do. It doesn't require special equipment, and you can do it every day."</p>



<p>Funding for this study includes the Robert and Arlene Kogod Professorship in Geriatric Medicine and W. Hall Wendel Jr. Musculoskeletal Professorship.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Rhoda Madson, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-what-standing-on-one-leg-can-tell-you/">Mayo Clinic study: What standing on one leg can tell you</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Aging]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Kenton Kaufman]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[health and wellness]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>