<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Health &amp; Wellness - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/health-and-wellness/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/health-and-wellness/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 12:47:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Emotional exhaustion: When your feelings feel overwhelming</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-emotional-exhaustion-when-your-feelings-feel-overwhelming/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Abby Smith]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 12:47:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=394102</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Editor's Note: Oct. 6-12 is Mental Illness Awareness Week DEAR MAYO CLINIC: Recently, I've been feeling physically and mentally drained from the demands of work, caregiving and other responsibilities. I struggle to find motivation and have trouble concentrating on tasks. Are there strategies to help me find emotional balance? ANSWER: Turning on the news or [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-emotional-exhaustion-when-your-feelings-feel-overwhelming/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Emotional exhaustion: When your feelings feel overwhelming</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/04/an-African-American-woman-sitting-at-a-desk-near-a-window-with-the-light-coming-in-and-resting-her-head-on-her-hands-in-a-prayer-like-position-perhaps-worried-or-stressed-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="an African American woman sitting at a desk near a window with the light coming in and resting her head on her hands in a prayer-like position, perhaps worried or stressed. Emotional." class="wp-image-272025" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/04/an-African-American-woman-sitting-at-a-desk-near-a-window-with-the-light-coming-in-and-resting-her-head-on-her-hands-in-a-prayer-like-position-perhaps-worried-or-stressed-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/04/an-African-American-woman-sitting-at-a-desk-near-a-window-with-the-light-coming-in-and-resting-her-head-on-her-hands-in-a-prayer-like-position-perhaps-worried-or-stressed-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/04/an-African-American-woman-sitting-at-a-desk-near-a-window-with-the-light-coming-in-and-resting-her-head-on-her-hands-in-a-prayer-like-position-perhaps-worried-or-stressed-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/04/an-African-American-woman-sitting-at-a-desk-near-a-window-with-the-light-coming-in-and-resting-her-head-on-her-hands-in-a-prayer-like-position-perhaps-worried-or-stressed-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/04/an-African-American-woman-sitting-at-a-desk-near-a-window-with-the-light-coming-in-and-resting-her-head-on-her-hands-in-a-prayer-like-position-perhaps-worried-or-stressed-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong><em>Editor's Note: Oct. 6-12 is Mental Illness Awareness Week</em></strong></p>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> Recently, I've been feeling physically and mentally drained from the demands of work, <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-palliative-medicine-for-cancer-patients/">caregiving </a>and other responsibilities. I struggle to find motivation and have trouble concentrating on tasks. Are there strategies to help me find emotional balance?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER: </strong>Turning on the news or opening a newspaper to see local and world events can bring out strong emotions and stressors. In addition to the social unrest happening around the world, you may face personal challenges from a high-pressure job, financial stress,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/featured-topic/caregiving-self-care-during-beyond-the-covid-19-pandemic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">being a caregiver</a>, parenting, grieving the death of a family member or friend, or a chronic illness.</p>



<p>You may wonder what's next or what else you can endure. With the sense of relentless struggles, you may begin to feel unwell and irritable, and struggle to concentrate and lack motivation. You may not even know what is causing these feelings. You can feel trapped or stuck. You're emotionally exhausted.</p>



<p>What is emotional exhaustion? When stress from adverse or challenging events in life occur continually, you can find yourself in a state of feeling emotionally worn out and drained. This is called emotional exhaustion. For most people, emotional exhaustion tends to build up slowly over time. Emotional exhaustion includes emotional, physical and performance symptoms.</p>



<p>Emotional symptoms include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Anxiety</li>



<li>Apathy</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/could-you-be-depressed" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Depression</a></li>



<li>Feeling hopeless</li>



<li>Feeling powerless or trapped</li>



<li>Irritability</li>



<li>Lack of focus or forgetfulness</li>



<li>Lack of motivation</li>



<li>Negative thinking</li>



<li>Nervousness</li>



<li>Tearfulness</li>
</ul>



<p>Physical symptoms include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Fatigue</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/common-questions-about-headaches" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Headaches</a></li>



<li>Lack of appetite</li>



<li>Nausea or upset stomach</li>



<li>Poor sleep</li>



<li>Sore muscles or muscle tension</li>
</ul>



<p>Performance symptoms include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Difficulty completing daily tasks for responsibilities</li>



<li>Failing to meet deadlines</li>



<li>Increased absences</li>



<li>Isolation or avoidance</li>



<li>Lower workplace commitment</li>



<li>Performing work duties more slowly</li>
</ul>



<p>How is emotional exhaustion treated? You can address emotional exhaustion by recognizing the stressors you're able to minimize or eliminate. When you're unable to change a stressor because it's out of your control, it's crucial to focus on the present moment. In the present, many neutral or positive events are occurring. When you focus on these types of events, it gives perspective about what's happening around you. This allows you to shift your focus away from the stressors.</p>



<p>Your body often interprets stress as a threat to survival. When this happens, your brain releases stress hormones throughout your body, further contributing to your experience of emotional exhaustion. When you're able to focus on small neutral or positive events, your brain learns that the threat is not as dire as it may first seem. The amount of stress hormone released is decreased, and you're able to feel more emotionally balanced.</p>



<p>Other strategies to reduce emotional exhaustion include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Eating a healthy, balanced diet.</strong> A well-balanced, healthy diet is at the core of well-being. Consume a variety of foods from all the food groups to get a range of nutrients to provide energy throughout the day.</li>



<li><strong>Eliminating or minimizing the stressor when possible.</strong> Consuming news is an important way to stay connected to what's happening in the world. Unfortunately, the news too frequently is filled with stories of suffering. These stories can skew your view of the world and cause you to focus on your worst fears instead of recognizing the good surrounding you. You can't avoid these stories altogether but try to minimize your exposure when you can, especially during trying times.</li>



<li><strong>Getting regular exercise.</strong> The Department of Health and Human Services recommends that adults complete at least 150 minutes of moderate-intensity physical activity each week. Contrary to what you might believe, this will add to your energy account and not subtract from it.</li>



<li><strong>Identifying and challenging unhelpful thoughts and replacing them with balanced thoughts</strong>. Do something you enjoy every day, even if it's a simple act such as cooking a healthy meal or listening to your favorite song. Putting effort into the things that matter most to you will help you use and reserve your energy in ways that will bring out the best in you.</li>
</ul>



<p>Talk with a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/psychiatry-and-psychology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">mental health professional</a>&nbsp;if you have signs of emotional exhaustion. A mental health professional&nbsp;can help you sort through the causes and symptoms you're experiencing to determine a plan that will help you regain a sense of well-being. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/jolene-hanson-licsw" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>Jolene Hanson</em></strong></a><strong><em>, </em></strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/psychiatry-and-psychology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>Psychiatry &amp; Psychology</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Mayo Clinic Health System,&nbsp;</em></strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/mankato" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>Mankato</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Minnesota</em></strong></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-emotional-exhaustion-when-your-feelings-feel-overwhelming/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Emotional exhaustion: When your feelings feel overwhelming</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/04/an-African-American-woman-sitting-at-a-desk-near-a-window-with-the-light-coming-in-and-resting-her-head-on-her-hands-in-a-prayer-like-position-perhaps-worried-or-stressed-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/04/an-African-American-woman-sitting-at-a-desk-near-a-window-with-the-light-coming-in-and-resting-her-head-on-her-hands-in-a-prayer-like-position-perhaps-worried-or-stressed-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Building resilience to tame anxiety</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-building-resilience-to-tame-anxiety/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=394108</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: I struggle with persistent anxiety, which often leaves me feeling drained mentally and physically. Minor setbacks or stressors can cause me to spiral into negative thinking. What techniques can help me manage my anxiety in a lasting way? ANSWER: Anxiety is a common and uncomfortable struggle for many people. The tendency to [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-building-resilience-to-tame-anxiety/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Building resilience to tame anxiety</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_1555238015_Fotor-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="a young white man sitting on the edge of a bed, with his hand on his face looking sad, concerned, worried, stressed and depressed" class="wp-image-265000" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_1555238015_Fotor-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_1555238015_Fotor-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_1555238015_Fotor-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_1555238015_Fotor-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_1555238015_Fotor-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> I struggle with persistent anxiety, which often leaves me feeling drained mentally and physically. Minor setbacks or stressors can cause me to spiral into negative thinking. What techniques can help me manage my anxiety in a lasting way?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER: </strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/anxiety/symptoms-causes/syc-20350961" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Anxiety</a> is a common and uncomfortable struggle for many people. The tendency to have anxiety comes from your genetics, your sense of security (or lack of it), the role modeling you received as a child, and, of course, the significant and challenging events that happen throughout your life.</p>



<p>Everyone has a point, no matter how resilient you are, where anxiety can overtake your emotions and life. Social fears, physical health issues, financial issues, loneliness, relationship issues and world affairs can collectively affect you to the point where you feel anxious.</p>



<p>Anxiety and fear are natural protectors. The fight-or-flight response they trigger motivates you to run, fight or possibly freeze to escape the danger. This response has kept humans alive for all of our history despite many risks in the world. It can become an issue, however, when you're not in physical danger, but your <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/anxiety-disorders-is-it-really-all-in-your-head" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">mental or emotional stress</a> still triggers that fight-or-flight response.</p>



<p>Anxiety affects you physically, along with your thoughts and actions. When you face physical danger, anxiety is designed to help you focus on the threat so you know where the danger is coming from and then respond in ways that help fight it or escape from it.</p>



<p>Anxiety can cause uncomfortable physical symptoms such as a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-palpitations/symptoms-causes/syc-20373196" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">racing heart</a>, inability to concentrate, shakiness, sweating or difficulty swallowing. These symptoms may not feel good, but they aren't dangerous in the short term. Feeling tense, irritable and impatient can be a part of anxiety. People may pace, space out or feel like they're spinning their wheels and not getting anything done.</p>



<p>Here are nine tips to build up your resilience when faced with anxious times:</p>



<ol class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Gather information.</strong><br>Knowledge of the threat, concerns, fears or issues can reduce anxiety. <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/cognitive-overload" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gather accurate, factual information</a> from trusted sources to better understand the source of your anxiety and help with problem-solving to gain a greater sense of control.</li>



<li><strong>Establish a new routine.</strong><br>Routine and structure can be helpful and calming. Mindfully create a daily and weekly flow of events, such as starting your morning with breakfast and a relaxing cup of coffee or tea. A routine of practical and enjoyable tasks may include making a list of projects you want to accomplish, reading inspirational books or writing in a journal to express your thoughts, hopes, emotions and concerns.</li>



<li><strong>Stay connected.</strong><br>Reaching out to loved ones is essential, whether through phone calls, texting, emailing, video calls or in person. <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/featured-topic/brushing-off-the-social-rust" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Human connection can lower stress</a> and anxiety levels and build relationships. Helping others and <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-health-benefits-of-volunteering/#:~:text=Improves%20physical%20and%20mental%20health.&amp;text=Volunteers%20report%20better%20physical%20health,releasing%20dopamine%20in%20the%20brain.">volunteering</a> for a cause can give you purpose and help you feel more fulfilled and less anxious.</li>



<li><strong>Practice self-care habits.</strong><br>Take a few moments to care for yourself each day, such as soaking in a soothing bath, listening to calming or upbeat music, getting <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/adult-health/expert-answers/how-many-hours-of-sleep-are-enough/faq-20057898" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">plenty of sleep</a>, and eating regular, balanced, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/expert-blog/hlv-20049477?p=1#:~:text=Healthy%20diets&amp;text=Includes%20a%20variety%20of%20foods,to%20choose%20from%20each%20group." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">nutritious meals</a> and snacks. These habits can help whether you work from home or outside the home.</li>



<li><strong>Look for the good.</strong><br>Acknowledge and accept that the good and bad often exist next to each other. A person can be sad about one thing but aware that there's goodness and happiness in the same moment for another thing. Intentionally look for those good things. Our thoughts can grow and feed on each other, so it can help to purposefully think hopeful, realistic and<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/managing-high-functioning-anxiety" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"> solution-focused thoughts</a>. Look for the beauty amid the difficulties in life.</li>



<li><strong>Exercise.</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/fitness/expert-answers/exercise/faq-20057916#:~:text=For%20even%20more%20health%20benefits,physical%20activity%20can%20be%20helpful." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Regular exercise</a> and movement help release the built-up fight-or-flight energy. Exercise also releases endorphins, which are feel-good chemicals in the brain. Using bigger muscle movements can help release more of this energy so you feel calmer. Try jumping jacks, pushups, walking, running, dancing, chopping wood, swimming or <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/no-matter-your-age-or-skill-level-its-never-too-late-to-start-weight-training" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lifting weights</a>. Stretching and yoga also can help reduce stress.</li>



<li><strong>Meditate.</strong><br>Meditation, mindfulness and breathing exercises are good ways to release stress. Now is an excellent time to learn and incorporate these approaches into your life until they become daily habits.</li>



<li><strong>Reflect.</strong><br>Take time to reflect on what is truly important. Explore your worldview, spirituality and belief system. Find meaning in your life. Identify what you're grateful for and express gratitude.</li>



<li><strong>Reach out.</strong><br>You aren't alone. If you feel alone, don't be silent. Instead, <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/overcoming-loneliness" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">reach out to a friend</a> or healthcare professional. Attend a support group that addresses your area of struggle. Communicating your hopes and fears and listening to others divides the burden and increases the connection. This can decrease your sense of anxiety. ― <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/linda-hubbard-lmft" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>Linda Hubbard</em></strong></a><strong><em>, </em></strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/psychiatry-and-psychology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>Psychiatry &amp; Psychology</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Mayo Clinic Health System, </em></strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/eau-claire" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>Eau Claire</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Wisconsin</em></strong></li>
</ol>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-building-resilience-to-tame-anxiety/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Building resilience to tame anxiety</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_1555238015_Fotor-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_1555238015_Fotor-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-30/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jaynelle Ramon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 12:33:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=394603</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week. Mayo Clinic Minute: Treating breast cancer through surgery Globally, 2.3 million women are diagnosed with breast cancer every year, according to the World Health Organization. Advances in treating breast cancer are improving care and quality of life.⁠⁠"There [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-30/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://x.com/MayoClinic/status/1839741978864398663" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="292769" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/01/An-African-American-man-in-blue-jeans-and-a-blue-sweater-blowing-his-nose-or-sneezing-because-hes-feeling-sick-with-a-cold-allergies-or-a-flu-bug-16x9-1-1024x576-2.jpg" alt="An African American man in blue jeans and a blue sweater blowing his nose into a tissue or sneezing, feeling sick with a cold, allergies or a flu bug" class="wp-image-292769" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/01/An-African-American-man-in-blue-jeans-and-a-blue-sweater-blowing-his-nose-or-sneezing-because-hes-feeling-sick-with-a-cold-allergies-or-a-flu-bug-16x9-1-1024x576-2.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/01/An-African-American-man-in-blue-jeans-and-a-blue-sweater-blowing-his-nose-or-sneezing-because-hes-feeling-sick-with-a-cold-allergies-or-a-flu-bug-16x9-1-1024x576-2-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/01/An-African-American-man-in-blue-jeans-and-a-blue-sweater-blowing-his-nose-or-sneezing-because-hes-feeling-sick-with-a-cold-allergies-or-a-flu-bug-16x9-1-1024x576-2-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DAlmYKvvjcr/?img_index=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="798" height="449" data-id="218343" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/MBI-Mammogram_side-by-side_Fotor-16x9.jpg" alt="Molecular Breast Imaging (right) detected 3.6 times as many invasive cancers as digital mammography (left)" class="wp-image-218343" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/MBI-Mammogram_side-by-side_Fotor-16x9.jpg 798w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/MBI-Mammogram_side-by-side_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/MBI-Mammogram_side-by-side_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 798px) 100vw, 798px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/MayoClinic/videos/2732364730255354" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="266374" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_289558754_Fotor-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="man with head down, depressed, despondent, sad, tired" class="wp-image-266374" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_289558754_Fotor-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_289558754_Fotor-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_289558754_Fotor-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_289558754_Fotor-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/03/shutterstock_289558754_Fotor-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=8071621999632232" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="386022" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Dr-Sarah-McLaughlin-surgery-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Sarah A. McLaughlin, M.D. Surgical Oncologist, breast cancer, surgery" class="wp-image-386022" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Dr-Sarah-McLaughlin-surgery-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Dr-Sarah-McLaughlin-surgery-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Dr-Sarah-McLaughlin-surgery-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Dr-Sarah-McLaughlin-surgery-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Dr-Sarah-McLaughlin-surgery-16-x-9.jpg 1602w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DAmI466BOpk/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="249702" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/09/shutterstock_1018158514_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Pipistrelle bat (Pipistrellus pipistrellus) flying on wooden ceiling of house in darkness" class="wp-image-249702" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/09/shutterstock_1018158514_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/09/shutterstock_1018158514_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/09/shutterstock_1018158514_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>
</figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week.</h3>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treating-breast-cancer-through-surgery/#/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Treating breast cancer through surgery</a></h2>



<p>Globally, 2.3 million women are diagnosed with breast cancer every year, according to the World Health Organization. Advances in treating breast cancer are improving care and quality of life.⁠<br>⁠<br>"There are only two surgical options: lumpectomy and mastectomy. But there are 100 reasons why women choose one thing or another," says Dr. Sarah McLaughlin, a Mayo Clinic breast surgical oncologist.⁠</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/infectious-diseases-a-z-understanding-rabies/">Understanding rabies</a></h2>



<p>A Minnesota man has died of rabies following exposure to a bat. Rabies is a deadly virus spread to people from the saliva of infected animals, usually through a bite. In the U.S., rabies is mostly found in wild animals, such as bats, raccoons, skunks and foxes.⁠</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-get-hay-fever-relief-from-fall-allergies/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How to get hay fever relief from fall allergies</a></h2>



<p>Autumn is the season of change, with green leaves turning color and temperatures cooling. It's also the season of&nbsp;hay fever, or allergic rhinitis. So how can people with fall&nbsp;allergies&nbsp;get relief?</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-health-system-discusses-advancements-in-breast-cancer-screenings/">Mayo Clinic Health System discusses advancements in breast cancer screenings</a></h2>



<p>Since the 1970s, mammograms have been shown to reduce the risk of dying of breast cancer and have saved countless lives. In recognition of Breast Cancer Awareness Month, you are encouraged to talk to your healthcare team about the right screening options for you and to get those screenings scheduled.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-excessive-daytime-sleepiness-can-affect-heart-health/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How excessive daytime sleepiness can affect heart health</a></h2>



<p>If you have a difficult time staying awake and alert during the day, you may be experiencing excessive daytime sleepiness.&nbsp;Dr. Virend Somers, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist with a focus on sleep medicine, explains the difference between being tired and being sleepy and how&nbsp;excessive daytime sleepiness&nbsp;can have a negative effect on the heart.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-30/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/09/shutterstock_1018158514_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/web-top-5_10042024.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Understanding rabies</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/infectious-diseases-a-z-understanding-rabies/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[DeeDee Stiepan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 16:05:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Infectious Diseases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Robert Jacobson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Infectious Diseases A-Z]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rabies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[vaccines]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=251233</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A person has died of rabies following exposure to a bat. According to the Minnesota Department of Health, this is the fourth case of human rabies in the state since 2000. The diagnosis was confirmed by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Rabies is a deadly virus spread to people from the saliva of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/infectious-diseases-a-z-understanding-rabies/">Understanding rabies</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/09/shutterstock_1018158514_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Pipistrelle bat (Pipistrellus pipistrellus) flying on wooden ceiling of house in darkness" class="wp-image-249702" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/09/shutterstock_1018158514_Fotor-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/09/shutterstock_1018158514_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/09/shutterstock_1018158514_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>A person has died of rabies following exposure to a bat. According to the <a href="https://www.health.state.mn.us/news/pressrel/2024/rabies092724.html">Minnesota Department of Health</a>, this is the fourth case of human rabies in the state since 2000. The diagnosis was confirmed by the <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/rabies/">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</a>.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/rabies/symptoms-causes/syc-20351821">Rabies</a> is a deadly virus spread to people from the saliva of infected animals, usually through a bite. In the U.S., rabies is mostly found in wild animals, such as bats, raccoons, skunks and foxes.</p>



<p>"This virus ascends the nerve up to the brain and then infects the brain," explains <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/jacobson-robert-m-m-d/bio-20053584?_ga=2.24975290.1250020765.1570726955-1215201726.1570726955">Dr. Robert Jacobson</a>, medical director for Mayo Clinic's Primary Care Immunization Program. "It causes inflammation that's overwhelming, and it causes changes in behavior — and then eventually leads to seizures, coma and then death."</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/IWU34qEuipg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Robert Jacobson discusses infant immunizations</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Jacobson-on-rabies.mp4"></video></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites with Dr. Robert Jacobson are in the downloads.&nbsp;Please "Courtesy: Mayo Clinic News Network."</strong></p>



<p>The first symptoms of rabies may be similar to those of the flu. But Dr. Jacobson says once someone starts showing signs and symptoms, it's too late.</p>



<p>"We can't do anything to prevent rabies once you've developed symptoms, and, so, we're actually asking people instead to recognize when they might have been exposed." </p>



<p>Someone who might have been exposed should seek medical care immediately to get a series of shots to prevent the infection from taking hold.</p>



<p>"One is called rabies immune globulin," says Dr. Jacobson. "This is a passive immunization of collected antibodies against rabies that the nurse will actually inject directly into the wound if it's an animal bite that is visible. This works immediately to give you protection while you're waiting for your body to respond to the vaccine." </p>



<p>Dr. Jacobson says that <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements/rabies-vaccine-intramuscular-route/proper-use/drg-20069868">rabies vaccine</a> is given on the day of the exposure, then a dose of vaccine given again on the third, seventh and fourteenth days.</p>



<p>"It's not the old series where you heard about being given in the stomach and how you needed 14 doses, and it was excruciating," Dr. Jacobson adds. "I want my patients to think about it as a preventative vaccine. It's going to hurt the way a flu vaccine hurts."</p>



<p>The U.S. averages one to three human cases of rabies each year, with around 55,000 people seeking rabies vaccinations after potential exposure, according to the <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/rabies/">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</a> . To reduce the risk of coming in contact with a rabid animal, Dr. Jacobson says that it's not just wildlife you should stay away from.</p>



<p>"We need to remind our parents to watch out for the children and remind them not to play with stray animals that might not have been vaccinated and might have been bitten by a raccoon, fox or skunk, and is actually exposing your child to possibly rabies," says Dr. Jacobson. "We ask that everyone who has pets to make sure that they have had their vaccines, including the rabies vaccine. That's how we keep your family safe. That's how we keep your pets safe."</p>



<p>"We also need everyone to take contacts with bats seriously," adds Dr. Jacobson. "Any physical contact should be treated as a bat bite. The bites leave no marks. In fact, if an adult wakes up and finds a bat in the same room, we need to treat that adult as though the adult was possibly bitten by a bat. If the bat can be tested for rabies, that's great. If not, we need to start the rabies prevention series. If a young child is found in a room with a bat — asleep or awake — we need to make the same assumptions. The same goes for an awake but inebriated adult."</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/infectious-diseases-a-z-understanding-rabies/">Understanding rabies</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/09/shutterstock_1018158514_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/09/shutterstock_1018158514_Fotor-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Robert Jacobson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Infectious Diseases A-Z]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Rabies]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[vaccines]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Setting boundaries for your well-being</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-setting-boundaries-for-your-well-being/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rich Oswald]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=394274</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: I'm a people-pleaser by nature and have difficulty saying no or setting limits in my relationships. How can I start to create healthier boundaries in a kind yet firm way? ANSWER: People have various types of relationships, including partners, spouses, children, friends, co-workers, neighbors and acquaintances. Different relationships involve different interactions, responsibilities [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-setting-boundaries-for-your-well-being/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Setting boundaries for your well-being</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/05/a-close-up-of-a-smiling-young-couple-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a close-up of a smiling young couple" class="wp-image-236629" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/05/a-close-up-of-a-smiling-young-couple-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/05/a-close-up-of-a-smiling-young-couple-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/05/a-close-up-of-a-smiling-young-couple-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: </strong>I'm a people-pleaser by nature and have difficulty saying no or setting limits in my relationships. How can I start to create healthier boundaries in a kind yet firm way?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER: </strong>People have various types of relationships, including partners, spouses, children, friends, co-workers, neighbors and acquaintances. Different relationships involve different interactions, responsibilities and influences.</p>



<p>Every relationship has boundaries or rules of engagement. You may be deliberate and conscientious about these boundaries, or they may have formed subconsciously.</p>



<p>Developing and maintaining healthy boundaries helps you establish and build healthy relationships and avoid unhealthy connections with people.</p>



<p>Setting healthy boundaries is necessary for your health and the health of your relationships. Living within these boundaries you create is crucial to lowering stress and increasing satisfaction in life, particularly with the responsibilities and tasks in your personal life and work.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/anxiety/symptoms-causes/syc-20350961" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Anxiety</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/stress-management/in-depth/stress-symptoms/art-20050987" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stress</a> develop when you take responsibility for others' emotions, behaviors and thoughts. Many <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/tips-to-help-ease-anxiety" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">anxieties people experience</a> are due to poor boundaries.</p>



<p>A principle I refer to is the "law of relationships." It identifies that you can't control what others think, feel or do, and you are solely responsible for what you think, feel and do. Identifying and stating the boundaries in relationships that support this law clarifies where your responsibilities and authority stop, and the other person's responsibilities start.</p>



<p>Consider how you feel when you're given a task to complete but not given the resources you need to do the task. That can leave you feeling anxious and worried. The same feelings can happen when someone tries to give you responsibility for their emotions, thoughts and behaviors. Healthy boundaries are critical for your well-being.</p>



<p>Boundary-setting can be challenging at first, especially when your education, training or personal experiences may have led you to establish unhealthy boundaries.</p>



<p>Boundaries are driven by our view of our value as a person. Your value shouldn't be based on your performance. It's necessary to recognize how you presently value yourself and determine if that view is accurate.</p>



<p>For example, consider how a parent loves their child versus how they respond to their child's behavior. Nothing the child does can change the parent's love for them. The parent may sometimes be displeased with the child's behavior, but their love is not altered based on the child's behavior.</p>



<p>Focus on practicing behaviors that support your positive self-worth. Determine healthy boundaries that you can clearly define. Mapping out boundaries for various aspects of your life takes time and attention. <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/maintaining-healthy-relationships-is-important-as-we-age" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Think about your relationships</a> with your partner, parents and children; your job and co-workers; and your finances.</p>



<p>Answer these questions to help you define the boundaries you want to set for yourself:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>What relationships are <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/5-tips-to-manage-stress" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bringing me stress</a> and anxiety?</li>



<li>Am I attempting to control someone's emotions, thoughts or behavior?</li>



<li>Do I feel mistreated or taken advantage of?</li>



<li>Does the value I feel from others change based on how well I fulfill their requests or obligations?</li>
</ul>



<p>Also, identify false beliefs that have driven you to have unhealthy boundaries in the past. You can do this by determining what experiences caused you to have feelings of guilt or disrespect. Think of times you have felt you would upset someone or cause anger if you didn't do a specific task.</p>



<p>Anxiousness involves anticipating something bad will happen and not having a healthy response to that feeling. Take note of what you can and can't control, and again, remember that you are not responsible for other people's emotions, actions or thoughts.</p>



<p>Unhealthy boundaries often are driven by believing you can't say no. Validating for yourself that saying no is a way you can grow your healthy boundaries. Saying yes to the activities and tasks within your boundaries is meaningful only when your no is equally valued.</p>



<p>Saying no to things outside your boundaries will likely cause more pressure to say yes. Have an action plan for how you will respond in a healthy way to something that <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/7-anger-management-tips-to-prevent-relationship-damage" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">violates your boundaries</a>. Your action plan may include practicing saying no in a firm, yet kind, way or choosing not to talk to someone who doesn't respect your boundaries.</p>



<p>Initially, healthier boundaries require much effort to establish and maintain. Over time, you'll find they become more habitual and require less effort. Your previous hurt from unhealthy boundaries will fade away. You also will notice that the pressure to appease others will diminish.</p>



<p>Regularly review your actions to ensure you are following the boundaries you've created, especially during stressful or busy times. A weekly or monthly check-in can help you track your goals and priorities.</p>



<p>Mapping out clear boundaries in your life will positively affect your <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/adult-health/in-depth/self-esteem/art-20045374" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">self-esteem</a> and overall well-being. Building your self-esteem will help establish healthier relationships. ― <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/richard-oswald-lpc"><strong><em>Rich Oswald</em></strong></a><strong><em>, </em></strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/psychiatry-and-psychology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>Psychiatry &amp; Psychology</em></strong></a><strong><em>, </em></strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/eau-claire" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>Eau Claire</em></strong></a><strong><em> and </em></strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/menomonie" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>Menomonie</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Wisconsin</em></strong></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-setting-boundaries-for-your-well-being/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Setting boundaries for your well-being</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/05/a-close-up-of-a-smiling-young-couple-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/05/a-close-up-of-a-smiling-young-couple-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Rich Oswald]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: How to get hay fever relief from fall allergies</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-get-hay-fever-relief-from-fall-allergies/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[allergic rhinitis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Allergy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Allergy Shots]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. James Li]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hay fever]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ragweed]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[seasonal allergies]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=349032</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Autumn is the season of change, with green leaves turning color and temperatures cooling. It's also the season of hay fever, or allergic rhinitis. So how can people with fall allergies get relief? Dr. James Li, a Mayo Clinic allergist, has more in this Mayo Clinic Minute. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute Journalists: Broadcast-quality video [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-get-hay-fever-relief-from-fall-allergies/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How to get hay fever relief from fall allergies</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Autumn is the season of change, with green leaves turning color and temperatures cooling. It's also the season of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hay-fever/symptoms-causes/syc-20373039?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hay fever</a>, or allergic rhinitis.</p>



<p>So how can people with fall <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/allergies/symptoms-causes/syc-20351497?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">allergies</a> get relief? <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/li-james-t-m-d-ph-d/bio-20053682?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. James Li</a>, a Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/allergies-allergic-diseases-mayo-clinic/sections/overview/ovc-20485278?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">allergist</a>, has more in this Mayo Clinic Minute.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/0OEAj1x6L-o" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/Mayo-Clinic-Minute-How-to-get-hay-fever-relief-from-fall-allergies_CLEAN.mp4"></video></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:06) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/MCM_How-to-get-hay-fever-relief-from-fall-allergies.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong> </p>



<p>"Fall is a very common season for seasonal allergies to kick in," says Dr. Li.</p>



<p>And ragweed is usually the biggest culprit.</p>



<p>"If an allergic person with ragweed sensitivity goes outside, they inhale ragweed pollen grains — little pollen plant proteins — that land in the lining of the nose," says Dr. Li. "And in that allergic person, there is an inflammatory response or an allergic response that causes the swelling, the runny nose and the mucus production …"</p>



<p>… making life miserable for people with seasonal allergies.</p>



<p>"Nasal congestion, sneezing, runny nose, maybe itching of the nose or the mouth, as well as similar eye symptoms — eyes water, turn red or get itchy," says Dr. Li.</p>



<p>The first step in getting relief: Reduce your exposure by limiting time outdoors when pollen counts are high. Second: Try over-the-counter medications, like antihistamines, decongestants and allergy nasal sprays, which can help control the symptoms. And if those don't help, make an appointment with a healthcare professional, like an allergist.</p>



<p>"We'll go through the allergy tests, and one of the treatments we will at least talk about would be <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/allergy-shots/about/pac-20392876?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">allergy shots</a>," says Dr. Li. "And the payoff is that their allergy symptoms can be significantly improved."</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-get-hay-fever-relief-from-fall-allergies/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How to get hay fever relief from fall allergies</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/04/a-man-outside-blowing-his-nose-perhaps-suffering-from-allergies-1X1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/04/a-man-outside-blowing-his-nose-perhaps-suffering-from-allergies-16X9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[allergic rhinitis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Allergy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Allergy Shots]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. James Li]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[hay fever]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[ragweed]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[seasonal allergies]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-29/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jaynelle Ramon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 13:46:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=394247</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week. Mayo Clinic Minute: What is CAR-T cell therapy? Survival rates for aggressive lymphomas&#160;have improved&#160;significantly thanks to advances&#160;in treatment, such as&#160;chimeric antigen receptor-T cell therapy (CAR-T cell therapy). Dr. Madiha Iqbal, a Mayo Clinic&#160;hematologist&#160;and&#160;oncologist, explains that&#160;CAR-T cell therapy&#160;is [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-29/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-2 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DAT5QRDNvhj/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="394147" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Valley-Fever-1-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-394147" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Valley-Fever-1-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Valley-Fever-1-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Valley-Fever-1-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Valley-Fever-1-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Valley-Fever-1-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DAKL1wVtQRj/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="374577" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374577" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/MayoClinic/posts/pfbid0mRNW6Us3hxbnicZw8YdzjfUQzAQ3uZDLVx5WzRAsgDVyKNkxpYSi28PbTFWAL1HEl" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="394007" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Newsweek-Smart-Hospitals-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-394007" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Newsweek-Smart-Hospitals-16x9-1.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Newsweek-Smart-Hospitals-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Newsweek-Smart-Hospitals-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/MayoClinic/videos/1497486394284282" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="310" data-id="336232" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/03/16x9_Nurse-preparing-for-CAR-T-cell-therapy-at-Mayo-Clinic-in-Florida-e1648482810841.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-336232" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DAMtJr8I2K-/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="660" height="370" data-id="369509" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/holding-hands-on-leg16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-369509" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/holding-hands-on-leg16x9.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/06/holding-hands-on-leg16x9-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></a></figure>
</figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week.</h2>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-car-t-cell-therapy/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What is CAR-T cell therapy?</a></h2>



<p>Survival rates for aggressive lymphomas&nbsp;have improved&nbsp;significantly thanks to advances<strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong>in treatment, such as&nbsp;chimeric antigen receptor-T cell therapy (CAR-T cell therapy). Dr. Madiha Iqbal, a Mayo Clinic&nbsp;hematologist&nbsp;and&nbsp;oncologist, explains that&nbsp;CAR-T cell therapy&nbsp;is a personalized and&nbsp;innovative treatment&nbsp;giving hope to patients diagnosed with various lymphomas.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/lets-talk-low-libido/">Let's talk low libido</a></h2>



<p>Although it may be difficult to discuss, sexual health is important, and factors that are causing low libido should be addressed. Many primary care, psychology and OB-GYN professionals are trained to care for and treat hypoactive sexual desire disorder, or HSDD. </p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-valley-fever/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What is valley fever?</a></h2>



<p>Some areas of the U.S. are experiencing a recent uptick in cases of a fungal lung infection called valley fever. Dr. Jesse Bracamonte, a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician, explains what you need to know about valley fever, how it's spread and how to avoid becoming infected.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mcm-why-more-preventive-screenings-are-needed-in-the-hispanic-community/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Why more preventive screenings are needed in the Hispanic community</a></h2>



<p>According to a recent study by the American Cancer Society, cancer is a leading cause of death among those of Hispanic heritage living in the U.S. Dr. Jesse Bracamonte,&nbsp;a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician, says preventive screenings for cancer and other diseases are effective ways to help reduce these burdens.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-tops-newsweeks-2025-rankings-for-worlds-best-smart-and-specialized-hospitals/">Mayo Clinic recognized in Newsweek's 2025 rankings for World's Best Smart and Specialized Hospitals</a></h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota, is recognized as a Best Smart Hospital and Best Specialized Hospital with seven No. 1 specialty rankings, more than any other hospital, according to Newsweek's "World's Best Smart Hospitals 2025" and "World's Best Specialized Hospitals 2025."</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-29/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/Newsweek-Smart-Hospitals-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/web-top-5_09272024-1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Minimally invasive options use energy to treat enlarged prostate</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-minimally-invasive-options-use-energy-to-treat-enlarged-prostate/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Abby Smith]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=394242</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: I'm a 64-year-old man who was recently diagnosed with an enlarged prostate after experiencing issues with frequent urination, especially during the night. What are the treatment options and potential side effects? ANSWER: An enlarged prostate, also called&#160;benign prostatic hyperplasia, or BPH, is a common condition as men get older. By age 60, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-minimally-invasive-options-use-energy-to-treat-enlarged-prostate/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Minimally invasive options use energy to treat enlarged prostate</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/09/Portrait-senior-man-outdoors_shutterstock_97559168_16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Portrait senior man outdoors" class="wp-image-171144" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/09/Portrait-senior-man-outdoors_shutterstock_97559168_16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/09/Portrait-senior-man-outdoors_shutterstock_97559168_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/09/Portrait-senior-man-outdoors_shutterstock_97559168_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> I'm a 64-year-old man who was recently diagnosed with an enlarged prostate after experiencing issues with frequent urination, especially during the night. What are the treatment options and potential side effects?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER: </strong>An enlarged prostate, also called&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/benign-prostatic-hyperplasia/symptoms-causes/syc-20370087" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">benign prostatic hyperplasia</a>, or BPH, is a common condition as men get older. By age 60, about 30% of men show moderate to severe symptoms of BPH; by age 80, it is 50%. An enlarged prostate gland can cause uncomfortable urinary symptoms, such as a weak urine stream, a stream that starts and stops, frequently getting up at night to urinate, or nocturia, and inability to empty the bladder.</p>



<p>There are multiple treatment options for BPH, ranging from behavior modifications to medications and surgery. One minimally invasive option that patients may be considering is bipolar enucleation of the prostate, or BipolEP.</p>



<p>The prostate is a small organ that sits beneath the bladder. The urethra, the tube that drains the bladder, runs through the middle of the prostate. Early in a man's life, the prostate is roughly the size of a walnut or a small tangerine. Often, around age 50, the prostate increases in size. For some men, this change closes off the urethra and makes it more difficult for them to empty their bladder.</p>



<p>The prostate has two parts: the adenoma and capsule. The adenoma is the inner part that surrounds the urethra. It's the part of the prostate that grows as men get older. The capsule is the outer part of the prostate and doesn't change in size over the course of life. A good analogy is to think of an orange. The peel represents the capsule, and the fruit represents the adenoma.</p>



<p>Using the orange analogy, enucleation aims to remove the fruit, or adenoma, from the inside while leaving the peel (the capsule) behind. This technique results in a wide-open channel for the urine to pass out of the bladder.</p>



<p>Transurethral enucleation can be performed with different energy sources:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>HoLEP</strong><br>A commonly used energy source is the holmium laser. This is called a holmium laser enucleation of the prostate, or HoLEP.</li>



<li><strong>BipolEP</strong><br>Another option is with bipolar energy, called BipolEP. It can be performed on any size prostate. This is the best procedure for patients who have larger prostates, usually over 80 milliliters, or who are unable to void their bladders without a catheter. Also, patients who have been offered an open surgery because their prostate is too large may benefit from BipolEP.</li>
</ul>



<p>BipolEP is performed in an operating room under either general or spinal anesthesia. During the procedure, a urologist inserts a specialized scope into the urethra. Using bipolar energy, the urologist enucleates all adenoma tissue, then cuts it into smaller pieces using the morcellator before easily removing it through the urethra. This procedure leaves the capsule intact and restores the urinary flow through the urethra. The length of the procedure depends on the prostate size but typically ranges from 45 minutes to two hours.</p>



<p>At the end of the operation, the patient receives a catheter and stays at the hospital overnight for bladder irrigation. For most patients, the catheter is removed the morning after surgery when their ability to urinate is tested.</p>



<p>Because BipolEP doesn't require an incision, patients recover faster and have a lower risk of infections and bleeding. In most cases, the catheter can be removed the day after the operation. In contrast, open or robotic surgeries require patients to use a catheter for several days.</p>



<p>Patients need to limit strenuous physical activity for two weeks and drink plenty of fluids. Most people can resume normal activities after two weeks but may still see occasional bits of tissue or bleeding in their urine after heavy activity.</p>



<p>Most instances of urinary incontinence improve in the first three months after the procedure. Patients receive education on <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/kegels-are-for-men-too" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kegel exercises</a>, and physical therapy focuses on strengthening the pelvic floor.</p>



<p>Some urinary symptoms such as urinary urgency, urinary frequency or nocturia may worsen for a few weeks after surgery as the bladder and prostate heal. These symptoms improve with time.</p>



<p>Other side effects are generally mild and comparable to <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/mens-health-how-is-benign-prostatic-hyperplasia-treated" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">other BPH treatments</a>. The risk of bleeding and infection is low. However, patients with smaller prostates have a higher rate of scar tissue formation after this procedure.</p>



<p>Talk with your primary care clinician and make an appointment if you're having trouble urinating and are looking for treatment strategies. ― <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/daniel-heslop-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>Daniel Heslop, M.D.</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Urology, Mayo Clinic Health System, </em></strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/la-crosse" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>La Crosse</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Wisconsin</em></strong></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-minimally-invasive-options-use-energy-to-treat-enlarged-prostate/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Minimally invasive options use energy to treat enlarged prostate</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/09/Portrait-senior-man-outdoors_shutterstock_97559168_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/09/Portrait-senior-man-outdoors_shutterstock_97559168_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Who is at risk for a brain aneurysm?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-who-is-at-risk-for-a-brain-aneurysm/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 15:10:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=392951</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Editors note: September is National Brain Aneurysm Awareness Month Brain aneurysms affect millions of people, with 6.7 million in the U.S. living with unruptured aneurysms. Globally, they can cause nearly 500,000 deaths annually. &#160;Dr. Chris Fox specializes in endovascular and cerebrovascular neurosurgery at Mayo Clinic. He says not all brain aneurysms need to be treated [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-who-is-at-risk-for-a-brain-aneurysm/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Who is at risk for a brain aneurysm?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong><em>Editors note: September is National Brain Aneurysm Awareness Month</em></strong></p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-the-difference-in-brain-aneurysms/">Brain aneurysms</a> affect millions of people, with 6.7 million in the U.S. living with unruptured aneurysms. Globally, they can cause nearly 500,000 deaths annually.</p>



<p>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/fox-chris-c-m-d/bio-20483751">Dr. Chris Fox</a> specializes in endovascular and cerebrovascular neurosurgery at Mayo Clinic. He says not all brain aneurysms need to be treated immediately. However, a brain aneurysm that bursts or ruptures causes a serious medical emergency. Dr. Fox explains who may be at higher risk for a brain aneurysm in this Mayo Clinic Minute.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/YFOoboPxBkA" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeYFOoboPxBkA"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Who is at risk for a brain aneurysm?" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YFOoboPxBkA?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:00) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/SCRIPT-MCM-Who-is-at-risk-for-a-brain-aneurysm_.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>A brain aneurysm is a weak spot in a blood vessel that bulges out. If it bursts, it can cause dangerous bleeding within the brain.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="463" height="482" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2014/07/Brain-aneurysm.jpg" alt="medical Illustration of unruptured and ruptured brain aneurysm" class="wp-image-47069" style="width:241px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2014/07/Brain-aneurysm.jpg 463w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2014/07/Brain-aneurysm-288x300.jpg 288w" sizes="(max-width: 463px) 100vw, 463px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Illustration shows a woman with an unruptured aneurysm. The inset shows the aneurysm before and after rupture.</figcaption></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Who is at risk?</h2>



<p>Some people are at higher risk says Dr. Fox.</p>



<p>"We think there's likely a genetic component, something that predisposes individuals to developing an aneurysm, and then perhaps a secondary injury to the blood vessel," he explains.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/neurology-neurosurgery/news/routine-screening-for-individuals-with-a-family-history-of-aneurysm/mac-20531273">Screening</a> is recommended for those who have a close relative with a brain aneurysm.</p>



<p>"That's usually done with an MRI of the blood vessels called an MRI angiogram," says Dr. Fox.</p>



<p>Along with genetics, there are other risk factors.</p>



<p>"The most common things that can cause that are high blood pressure, hypertension, smoking and perhaps some other environmental factors," he says.</p>



<p>Certain drugs can raise blood pressure quickly.</p>



<p>"Illegal, illicit drugs, like cocaine or methamphetamine — they can increase the risk of an aneurysm rupture," says Dr. Fox.</p>



<p>And that can be life-threatening.</p>



<p>"That's a neurosurgical emergency. We want to get the aneurysm taken care of and secured as soon as possible," Dr. Fox says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Lifestyle changes</h2>



<p>If you have an unruptured brain aneurysm, these changes may reduce the risk of rupture:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Quit smoking. </li>



<li>Manage high blood pressure.</li>



<li>Eat healthy and exercise to help lower blood pressure.</li>



<li>Avoid drugs like cocaine or meth.</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-who-is-at-risk-for-a-brain-aneurysm/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Who is at risk for a brain aneurysm?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/01/shutterstock_344191121_Fotor-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/01/shutterstock_344191121_Fotor-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The W-Curve Model: Understanding a new college student&#8217;s experience</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/the-w-curve-model-understanding-a-new-college-students-experience/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 13:10:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[college freshmen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reese Druckenmiller]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[W-Curve Model]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=345798</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The W-Curve Model was first proposed in 1963 to explain adjustment to culture shock. Starting college is a culture shock for many young people. It is often the first time students are away from home for an extended period. Freshman year is known for new experiences, but it also presents various challenges. Each new college [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/the-w-curve-model-understanding-a-new-college-students-experience/">The W-Curve Model: Understanding a new college student&#8217;s experience</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/a-young-Black-teenage-boy-in-a-t-shirt-working-at-a-desk-with-a-notebook-and-a-pencil-perhaps-doing-homework-in-his-bedroom-or-college-dorm-room-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="a young Black teenage boy in a t-shirt working at a desk, with a notebook and a pencil, perhaps doing homework in his bedroom or college dorm room" class="wp-image-275438" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/a-young-Black-teenage-boy-in-a-t-shirt-working-at-a-desk-with-a-notebook-and-a-pencil-perhaps-doing-homework-in-his-bedroom-or-college-dorm-room-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/a-young-Black-teenage-boy-in-a-t-shirt-working-at-a-desk-with-a-notebook-and-a-pencil-perhaps-doing-homework-in-his-bedroom-or-college-dorm-room-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/a-young-Black-teenage-boy-in-a-t-shirt-working-at-a-desk-with-a-notebook-and-a-pencil-perhaps-doing-homework-in-his-bedroom-or-college-dorm-room-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/a-young-Black-teenage-boy-in-a-t-shirt-working-at-a-desk-with-a-notebook-and-a-pencil-perhaps-doing-homework-in-his-bedroom-or-college-dorm-room-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/a-young-Black-teenage-boy-in-a-t-shirt-working-at-a-desk-with-a-notebook-and-a-pencil-perhaps-doing-homework-in-his-bedroom-or-college-dorm-room-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The W-Curve Model was first proposed in 1963 to explain adjustment to culture shock. Starting college is a culture shock for many young people. It is often the first time students are away from home for an extended period.</p>



<p>Freshman year is known for new experiences, but it also presents various challenges. Each new college student's experience is unique. Parents should be aware of the predictable adjustment pattern to help students navigate difficult times.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The five stages of the W-Curve Model explain students' level of comfort, satisfaction and effectiveness during each stage:&nbsp;</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">1. Honeymoon: The excitement stage</h3>



<p>Often starting before students arrive at college, the honeymoon stage is full of excitement, stimulation and curiosity. There's increased enthusiasm to meet new people, and many cultural differences are intriguing.</p>



<p>Students desire independence and tend to lack homesickness during the first few days or weeks of college. New students are bombarded with events and activities, keeping the excitement level high.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">2. Culture Shock: Reality sets in</h3>



<p>At this stage, students may start to compare their expectations of college with reality. The differences that felt new and exciting start to feel isolating and overwhelming.</p>



<p>Students may feel lost and confused, noticing that the excitement of living on their own has worn off. Often, students will compare their experiences to others, finding that academic demands are more complex than anticipated.</p>



<p>Feeling homesick may lead students to wish to return home more often.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">3. Initial Adjustment: Settling into the demands of college life</h3>



<p>College gets better as students begin to manage experiences from culture shock. This can include making friends outside of their initial connections, developing a routine, gaining confidence in academic and social abilities, and finding one's roommate less bothersome.</p>



<p>This is when students start to reconnect to what they like about themselves and the new culture of college.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">4. Mental Isolation: Comparing home and college</h3>



<p>After students go home during an academic break, they may not feel as comfortable at home as they used to. Students may feel distressed at changes or events at home during their absence. This leads them to feel unsure about where they belong and miss the comfort that home used to provide. Beliefs and values are challenged as students attempt to find their place in the world.</p>



<p>At this time, peer conflicts may increase, and students may have a more tough time with roommates. Students in dating relationships that started in high school may have an increasingly hard time after seeing their partner during a break.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">5. Acceptance and Integration: Finally, balance emerges</h3>



<p>Students develop stronger ties to fellow students and faculty, get more involved in campus life, and understand how to succeed academically. Students often start referring to campus as their home and feel like a part of the culture. Roommate issues are addressed, and dependence on hometown connections begins to lessen. Students start to feel like an old hand at living the college life.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Making the first year of college a success</h2>



<p>The first year at college is not always easy. Being aware of the predictable adjustment pattern can make the transition less intimidating. If college is too overwhelming, help is always available, whether it's talking to a friend, family member, resident adviser, professor or a mental health professional. Understanding the W-Curve Model can help family members support their student’s success in college.</p>



<p>A version of this story was first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/the-w-curve-theory" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/the-w-curve-model-understanding-a-new-college-students-experience/">The W-Curve Model: Understanding a new college student&#8217;s experience</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/a-young-Black-teenage-boy-in-a-t-shirt-working-at-a-desk-with-a-notebook-and-a-pencil-perhaps-doing-homework-in-his-bedroom-or-college-dorm-room-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/a-young-Black-teenage-boy-in-a-t-shirt-working-at-a-desk-with-a-notebook-and-a-pencil-perhaps-doing-homework-in-his-bedroom-or-college-dorm-room-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[college freshmen]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Reese Druckenmiller]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[W-Curve Model]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss><!-- Static page delivered by HubScale -->