<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Health &amp; Wellness - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/health-and-wellness/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/health-and-wellness/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 12:45:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Boosting kids&#8217; health literacy</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-boosting-kids-health-literacy/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[DeeDee Stiepan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Children's Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dadily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Angela Mattke]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376047</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>October is National Health Literacy Month. Health literacy refers to the ability of people to find, understand, and use information and services to make informed health-related decisions and actions for themselves and others. In this Mayo Clinic Minute, Dr. Angela Mattke, a pediatrician with Mayo Clinic’s Children’s Center, explains how Mayo Clinic is leading the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-boosting-kids-health-literacy/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Boosting kids&#8217; health literacy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>October is National Health Literacy Month. Health literacy refers to the ability of people to find, understand, and use information and services to make informed health-related decisions and actions for themselves and others.</p>



<p>In this Mayo Clinic Minute, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mattke-angela-c-m-d/bio-20055584" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Angela Mattke</a>, a pediatrician with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/childrens-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic’s Children’s Center</a>, explains how <a href="https://mcpress.mayoclinic.org/parenting/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is leading the way to enhance health literacy for kids through engaging books to inform and inspire young people.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/jPCG_tjUUKU" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Mayo-Clinic-Minute-Boosting-kids-health-literacy-CLEAN.mp4"></video></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:07) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/SCRIPT-MCM-Health-literacy-for-kids.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Developing personal health literacy — which is the ability to find, understand, and use health-related information and services — is something that can begin early in life.</p>



<p>"Mayo Clinic is truly an expert in healthcare. And we have an opportunity to be there talking with children, getting them excited about their health and empowering them to have agency over their own health and the health of their communities," says Dr. Mattke.</p>



<p>Dr. Mattke says these types of books provide accessible information on a wide range of health and science-related topics.</p>



<p>"I think there's a lot of health topics that children struggle to understand — anything from immunizations to why they're feeling sick, especially when children have serious and complex diseases," says Dr. Mattke.</p>



<p>Understanding their disease can help them feel empowered and knowledgeable about how they can participate in their care. But it's not just kids with serious health conditions that can benefit from this education.</p>



<p>"My children have read all these books and have read them multiple and multiple times. And so, they can help understand these diseases. It's inspiring their passion to learn more about science and learn more about health," says Dr. Mattke.</p>



<p>Which is another goal of promoting health literacy in children.</p>



<p>"We need to get kids interested in STEM — science, engineering, technology and medicine. And these are really important topics. And so, we're bringing these topics to kids to get them interested at an early age and inspire that passion.," says Dr. Mattke.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-boosting-kids-health-literacy/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Boosting kids&#8217; health literacy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Health-Literacy-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Health-Literacy-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[dadily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Angela Mattke]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Adapting to life after spinal cord injury with rehab and determination</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/adapting-to-life-after-spinal-cord-injury-with-rehab-and-determination/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395473</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>What began as a creative backyard project changed Laurie Reese's life forever. An avid gardener, Laurie envisioned turning an unused outhouse on their property into an ideal garden shed. So on a November day in 2007, Laurie's husband, Pete, used their skid loader to move the structure. While Laurie was guiding Pete, she noticed the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/adapting-to-life-after-spinal-cord-injury-with-rehab-and-determination/">Adapting to life after spinal cord injury with rehab and determination</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/LauriePeteBella-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395475" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/LauriePeteBella-16x9-1.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/LauriePeteBella-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/LauriePeteBella-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>What began as a creative backyard project changed Laurie Reese's life forever.</p>



<p>An avid gardener, Laurie envisioned turning an unused outhouse on their property into an ideal garden shed. So on a November day in 2007, Laurie's husband, Pete, used their skid loader to move the structure. While Laurie was guiding Pete, she noticed the outhouse was wobbling, so she put her hands out to steady it. That’s when the structure fell over, trapping Laurie beneath it.</p>



<p>Pete was able to lift the outhouse just enough so that Laurie could pull herself most of the way out from under it, and Pete pulled her the rest of the way to safety. Paramedics took Laurie from her home in Oronoco, Minnesota, to&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/minnesota/campus-buildings-maps/mayo-clinic-hospital-saint-marys-campus" target="_blank">Mayo Clinic Hospital, Saint Marys Campus</a>&nbsp;in Rochester, Minnesota.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A sobering prognosis</h2>



<p>Laurie and Pete learned that two vertebrae in her thoracic (middle) spine were damaged. She had a fracture of the T12 vertebrae and a fracture dislocation of the T11 and T12 vertebrae.</p>



<p>The next day, she underwent nearly six hours of surgery. Her prognosis following the operation was dire: Laurie would have a 0-3% chance of walking again.</p>



<p>"I was in shock and not really thinking clearly. So many things were running through my head," Laurie says. "I was just 39 and wondered if this injury would shorten my life. Our daughter was pregnant with our first grandchild, and I thought, 'Well, I've still got use of my arms, so at least I can hold the baby.'"</p>



<p>Thoughts of her future grandchild spurred her to work especially hard in therapy to gain as much strength, movement and ability to do everyday tasks as possible. Laurie also knew two people who had quadriplegia, so she understood the reality of her situation.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Preparing for her new life&nbsp;</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="244" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/reese-walking-in-therapy.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395478" style="aspect-ratio:3/4;object-fit:cover;width:278px;height:auto" /></figure></div>


<p>Laurie began rehabilitation while still in the hospital, then transferred to the Mary Brigh Building on the Saint Marys Campus for intensive, inpatient rehabilitation to adapt to her new life. </p>



<p>In rehab, Laurie worked with physical and occupational therapists to practice and learn a wide range of skills and activities, including:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Stretching her legs.</li>



<li>Rolling over and sitting up.</li>



<li>Inserting a catheter.</li>



<li>Using a wheelchair.</li>



<li>Transferring in and out of vehicles.</li>



<li>Showering and dressing.</li>



<li>Using a machine that supported her, braced her legs and simulated walking.</li>



<li>Performing daily chores like cooking, doing the dishes and opening cupboards. </li>
</ul>



<p>"Before they let you leave rehabilitation, you go home for a day," Laurie says. "That's when the reality hits you that this is your life going forward."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Adapting, learning and doing what she wants </h2>



<p>By December 20, Laurie was ready to return home. Once home, outpatient therapy and occupational therapists make suggestions for adapting the house to meet her needs. To accommodate her wheelchair, the Reeses added a ramp to the house and eventually remodeled the kitchen.</p>



<p>Once the basics were manageable, Laurie focused on resuming the things she loved to do, such as gardening, horseback riding and snowmobiling.</p>



<p>Pete made modifications so she could indulge in her love of flowers. He revamped the garden beds to make them smaller and more manageable, built raised beds that Laurie could reach and added a fountain.</p>



<p>Another goal of Laurie's was to try horseback riding again. She was able to sit on her horse a couple of times but realized it wasn't feasible to safely ride.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/reese-posed-on-snowmobile.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395477" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/reese-posed-on-snowmobile.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/reese-posed-on-snowmobile-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></figure></div>


<p>Snowmobiling was a different story. After testing her comfort and ability on an older machine, she opted to get a new one with upgrades like an electric start, reverse gear, heated hand warmers and more. With a strap anchoring her legs, she's taken several trips — and even some spills — and continues to tinker with the design of her seat.</p>



<p>Since the accident, Laurie has been determined to live life on her own terms. With help from her therapists and plenty of practice, she stood for pictures at a daughter's wedding.</p>



<p>She holds, cares for and plays with her eight grandchildren. When she wants to see them, she loads her wheelchair onto the lift bed, gets into her pickup and drives to their homes.</p>



<p>Laurie also returned to work in cardiovascular education for Mayo Clinic in Rochester, a position she's held for 19 years. She provides digital education for medical staff needing board certification or recertification.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Nearly 20 years of success</h2>



<p>Although it's been 17 years since her accident, Laurie still battles issues like pressure sores that landed her in the hospital for three months this year. That hospitalization set her back, and she spent nearly three months in rehabilitation at <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/cannon-falls" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System in Cannon Falls</a>, Minnesota.</p>



<p>"It still can be rough. Some days are better than others, and I get jealous of those who can easily do something like picking up a baby," she says. "And nothing is as easy as you think it will be, but you make it work. You have to have the mindset and the drive to constantly adapt."</p>



<p>What helped Laurie develop that mindset and drive was a journal her rehab team encouraged her to write in the hospital after her initial injury. The journal evolved into a book, "My Life Beyond the Outhouse: The First Two Years." Laurie focused on the first two years because she was most likely to regain any mobility during that time.</p>



<p>"Publishing the book helped me talk about my injury, and my family and friends got a better understanding of what I was going through," Laurie says. "People who read it say they had no idea how much of your life is affected by being paralyzed."</p>



<p>While her life changed on that November day, it didn't end. Laurie attributes her success to her rehabilitation team and their ongoing care.</p>



<p>"I couldn't have asked for better people on my side. When I cried, they gave me a shoulder to cry on," she says. "I can't imagine not having the training they gave me. Because of them, I was able to start out in a new capacity, and today, I'm able to do almost whatever I want."</p>



<p>"Even now, when I go in for appointments, they remember me and know my story. It's so neat that out of the thousands of patients they've seen, we still have that connection."</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/patient-stories/spinal-cord-injury" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/adapting-to-life-after-spinal-cord-injury-with-rehab-and-determination/">Adapting to life after spinal cord injury with rehab and determination</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/LauriePeteBella-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/LauriePeteBella-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: 3 tips to avoid Halloween hand injuries</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-3-tips-to-avoid-halloween-hand-injuries/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sanj Kakar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[halloween]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hand injury]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=218012</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>There are plenty of frights to go around on Halloween, but a hand injury probably isn't one you'd expect. "Interestingly, it's the fourth busiest holiday for hand injuries," says Dr. Sanj Kakar, a Mayo Clinic orthopedic hand and wrist surgeon. Dr. Kakar says almost one-third of those Halloween hand injuries are among kids ages 10 [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-3-tips-to-avoid-halloween-hand-injuries/">Mayo Clinic Minute: 3 tips to avoid Halloween hand injuries</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>There are plenty of frights to go around on Halloween, but a hand injury probably isn't one you'd expect.</p>



<p>"Interestingly, it's the fourth busiest holiday for hand injuries," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/kakar-sanjeev-sanj-m-d/bio-20055340?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Dr. Sanj Kakar</a>, a Mayo Clinic orthopedic hand and wrist surgeon.</p>



<p>Dr. Kakar says almost one-third of those Halloween hand injuries are among kids ages 10 to 14. And most of them happen when people are carving pumpkins.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/XlWXkwaRfa4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Mayo-Clinic-Minute-3-tips-to-avoid-Halloween-hand-injuries_CLEAN.mp4"></video></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:00) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post.<br>Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/MCM-3-tips-to-avoid-Halloween-hand-injuries-SCRIPT3.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"It's primarily stabbing injuries where the knife may slip, and, so, they can cut things like tendons, which are the ropes that help move your hands," Dr. Kakar says. "But they can also break bones, and also they can burn themselves, as well, with candles."</p>



<p>But Dr. Kakar says most of the injuries are avoidable.</p>



<p>"A lot of people might just go to the kitchen and grab a sharp knife. But there's good studies out there showing that actual pumpkin-specific carving knives [are safer], [because] actually the force needed to injure yourself, is higher if you use one of those than if you use a standard knife," he says. "So I would use a pumpkin carving kit, No. 1."</p>



<p>No. 2, Dr. Kakar says, is to let kids handle designing the jack-o'-lantern, but make sure adults do all of the carving.</p>



<p>And No. 3, make sure you're always supporting the pumpkin with your noncutting hand.</p>



<p>"So if you're right-handed, use your left hand to support the pumpkin and carve from the top down as opposed to the bottom up," Dr. Kakar says. "It's very easy for the knife to slip and go into your hand."</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-3-tips-to-avoid-halloween-hand-injuries/">Mayo Clinic Minute: 3 tips to avoid Halloween hand injuries</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/shutterstock_306948755_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/shutterstock_306948755_Fotor-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Sanj Kakar]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[halloween]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[hand injury]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-33/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jaynelle Ramon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395417</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week. Mayo Clinic performs its first paired living liver donation People can donate up to 70% of their liver because the liver has the&#160;unique ability to regenerate itself within a month. While paired living donation is commonly used [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-33/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DBcID3ztlMy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="395013" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/GettyImages-1481914173.jpg1920-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395013" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/GettyImages-1481914173.jpg1920-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/GettyImages-1481914173.jpg1920-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/GettyImages-1481914173.jpg1920-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/GettyImages-1481914173.jpg1920-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/GettyImages-1481914173.jpg1920.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/MayoClinic/posts/pfbid0HMq3G9aGUrV79D3KHyyGUxEWKDh1xoDRchgshVD3pwtc3qsUEEqEvWTcvmSpGsTfl" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="395365" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395365" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/706347941527986/posts/950789440417167" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" data-id="116567" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/03/a-close-up-of-two-feet-one-on-the-floor-and-the-other-held-in-the-persons-hands-16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-116567" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/03/a-close-up-of-two-feet-one-on-the-floor-and-the-other-held-in-the-persons-hands-16x9.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/03/a-close-up-of-two-feet-one-on-the-floor-and-the-other-held-in-the-persons-hands-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DBeWp2dvA8l/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="395350" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Paired-Liver-Surgery1-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395350" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Paired-Liver-Surgery1-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Paired-Liver-Surgery1-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Paired-Liver-Surgery1-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Paired-Liver-Surgery1-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Paired-Liver-Surgery1-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DBZCpCtJX9r/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="395137" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395137" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>
</figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week.</h3>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-performs-its-first-paired-living-liver-donation/">Mayo Clinic performs its first paired living liver donation</a></h2>



<p>People can donate up to 70% of their liver because the liver has the&nbsp;unique ability to regenerate itself within a month. While paired living donation is commonly used for kidney transplants, it is relatively rare for liver transplants.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Surgeons recently performed Mayo Clinic's first paired living liver donation, a significant first step in helping more people with liver failure get a lifesaving transplant.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-radiation-therapy-for-patients-with-breast-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer</a></h2>



<p>Radiation therapy is a common component of breast cancer treatment for patients. The high-powered beams of intense energy kill cancer cells and reduce the risk of the cancer recurring.</p>



<p>Dr. Laura Vallow, chair of the Radiation Oncology Department at Mayo Clinic in Florida, explains how innovation is transforming radiation treatments.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-clean-out-old-medications-safely/#/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Clean out old medications safely</a></h2>



<p>Leftover or expired medications can be dangerous if not disposed of properly. Safely getting rid of unneeded prescriptions, like opioids or expired drugs, is essential to prevent&nbsp;misuse&nbsp;and accidental harm.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Tina Ardon, a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician, says proper medication disposal helps safeguard your home and community from unnecessary risks.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-what-standing-on-one-leg-can-tell-you/">What standing on one leg can tell you about aging</a></h2>



<p>How long a person can stand — on one leg — is a more telltale measure of aging than changes in strength or gait, according to new Mayo Clinic research. Good balance, muscle strength and an efficient gait contribute to people's independence and well-being as&nbsp;they age.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-shockwave-therapy-may-help-relieve-foot-problem/">Shockwave therapy may help relieve foot problem</a></h2>



<p>Shockwave therapy is a noninvasive treatment that uses sound waves to transmit energy to tissues to help with the healing process. It can be used for foot and ankle issues including plantar fasciitis, tendinitis, stress fractures and shin splints.⁠</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-33/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Paired-Liver-Surgery1-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/web-top-5_10252024.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic study: What standing on one leg can tell you</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-what-standing-on-one-leg-can-tell-you/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rhoda Madson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 18:04:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Aging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Kenton Kaufman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health and wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395368</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — How long a person can stand — on one leg — is a more telltale measure of aging than changes in strength or gait, according to new Mayo Clinic research. The study appears today in the journal PLOS ONE. Good balance, muscle strength and an efficient gait contribute to people's independence and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-what-standing-on-one-leg-can-tell-you/">Mayo Clinic study: What standing on one leg can tell you</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395365" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — How long a person can stand — on one leg — is a more telltale measure of aging than changes in strength or gait, according to new <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> research. The <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0310764" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> appears today in the journal PLOS ONE.</p>



<p>Good balance, muscle strength and an efficient gait contribute to people's independence and well-being as&nbsp;they age. How these factors change, and at what rate, can help clinicians develop programs to ensure healthy aging. Individually, people can train their balance without special equipment and work on maintaining it over time.</p>



<p>In this study, 40 healthy, independent people over 50 underwent walking, balance, grip strength and knee strength tests. Half of the participants were under 65; the other half were 65 and older.</p>



<p>In the balance tests, participants stood on force plates in different situations: on both feet with eyes open, on both feet with eyes closed, on the non-dominant leg with eyes open, and on the dominant leg with eyes open. In the one-legged tests, participants could hold the leg they weren't standing on where they wanted. The tests were 30 seconds each.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Kaufman-Kenton-R._10436286_202109151225-250x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395367" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Kaufman-Kenton-R._10436286_202109151225-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Kaufman-Kenton-R._10436286_202109151225-854x1024.jpg 854w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Kaufman-Kenton-R._10436286_202109151225-768x921.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Kaufman-Kenton-R._10436286_202109151225.jpg 938w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Kenton Kaufman</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Standing on one leg — specifically the nondominant leg — showed the highest rate of decline with age.</p>



<p>"Balance is an important measure because, in addition to muscle strength, it requires input from vision, the vestibular system and the somatosensory systems," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/kaufman-kenton-r-ph-d/bio-20054278?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kenton Kaufman, Ph.D.</a>, senior author of the study and director of the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/motion-analysis/overview?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Motion Analysis Laboratory</a> at Mayo Clinic. "Changes in balance are noteworthy. If you have poor balance, you're at risk of falling, whether or not you're moving. Falls are a severe health risk with serious consequences."</p>



<p>Unintentional falls are the leading cause of injuries among adults who are 65 and older. Most falls among older adults result from a loss of balance.</p>



<p>In the other tests:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Researchers used a custom-made device to measure participants' grip. For the knee strength test, participants were in a seated position and instructed to extend their knee as forcefully as possible. Both the grip and knee strength tests were on the dominant side. Grip and knee strength showed significant declines by decade but not as much as balance. Grip strength decreased at a faster rate than knee strength, making it better at predicting aging than other strength measures.</li>



<li>For the gait test, participants walked back and forth on an 8-meter, level walkway at their own pace and speed. Gait parameters didn't change with age. This was not a surprising result since participants were walking at their normal pace, not their maximum pace, Dr. Kaufman says.</li>



<li>There were no age-related declines in the strength tests that were specific to sex. This indicates that participants' grip and knee strength declined at a similar rate. Researchers did not identify sex differences in the gait and balance tests, which suggests that male and female subjects were equally affected by age.</li>
</ul>



<p>Dr. Kaufman says people can take steps to train their balance. For example, by standing on one leg, you can train yourself to coordinate your muscle and vestibular responses to maintain correct balance. If you can stand on one leg for 30 seconds, you are doing well, he says.</p>



<p>"If you don't use it, you lose it. If you use it, you maintain it," Dr. Kaufman says. "It's easy to do. It doesn't require special equipment, and you can do it every day."</p>



<p>Funding for this study includes the Robert and Arlene Kogod Professorship in Geriatric Medicine and W. Hall Wendel Jr. Musculoskeletal Professorship.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Rhoda Madson, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-what-standing-on-one-leg-can-tell-you/">Mayo Clinic study: What standing on one leg can tell you</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Photo_Kaufman-balance-paper-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Aging]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Kenton Kaufman]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[health and wellness]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Clean out old medications safely </title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-clean-out-old-medications-safely/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=394399</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Note:&#160;National Prescription Drug Take Back Day is Oct. 26 Leftover or expired medications can be dangerous if not disposed of properly. Safely getting rid of unneeded prescriptions, like opioids or expired drugs, is essential to prevent&#160;misuse&#160;and accidental harm.&#160; Dr. Tina Ardon, a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician, says proper medication disposal helps safeguard your home [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-clean-out-old-medications-safely/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Clean out old medications safely </a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong><em>Note:&nbsp;</em></strong><em>National Prescription Drug Take Back Day is Oct. 26</em></p>



<p>Leftover or expired medications can be dangerous if not disposed of properly. Safely getting rid of unneeded prescriptions, like opioids or expired drugs, is essential to prevent&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prescription-drug-abuse/symptoms-causes/syc-20376813">misuse</a>&nbsp;and accidental harm.&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/ardon-tina-m-d/bio-20055713">Dr. Tina Ardon</a>, a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician, says proper medication disposal helps safeguard your home and community from unnecessary risks.&nbsp;Learn why it's important to clean out old medications safely.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/fxSGPSGcgJ4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubefxSGPSGcgJ4"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Safely dispose of unneeded or expired medications" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fxSGPSGcgJ4?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>J<strong>ournalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:02) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/SCRIPT-MCM-Dispose-of-unneeded-medications.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Is your medicine cabinet lined with prescriptions you're no longer using?&nbsp;</p>



<p>"It's not uncommon that I hear patients have a lot of leftover medications or medications they no longer need to use, and that can include opioid pain medications, maybe after surgery or an injury," says Dr. Ardon.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Leftover medications</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized is-style-center-align-caption"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/01/IMG_9913-1024x576.jpg" alt="a medicine cabinet with several prescription and medications pill bottles and a person taking one of them out of the cabinet" class="wp-image-181179" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/01/IMG_9913-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/01/IMG_9913-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/01/IMG_9913-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/01/IMG_9913.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Use medication as prescribed</figcaption></figure>



<p>Holding on to medication for potential future use is discouraged.</p>



<p>"There can be the tendency sometimes to reach for something that was used for another purpose, for a new pain. And we want to make sure, again, our patients are using medications that are right for their issue," she says.</p>



<p>And it's not just pain medication. Using any medicine for something it wasn't meant for may lead to side effects or other problems.</p>



<p>"A common example is using leftover antibiotics that can cause resistance to some of the bacteria that are out there. We want to make sure we are using our antibiotics appropriately," says Dr. Ardon.</p>



<p>She says take your medications completely as prescribed and safely dispose of those you are no longer using. You can check with your local pharmacy or …</p>



<p>"Consider National Take Back Day, which is a great way to be able to dispose of your medication safely, and we can all contribute to having safer practices with our medications," says Dr. Ardon.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-clean-out-old-medications-safely/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Clean out old medications safely </a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/02/pile-of-prescription-drug-bottles-1x1-square.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/04/a-collection-of-prescription-pill-bottles-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-radiation-therapy-for-patients-with-breast-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 13:58:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Laura Vallow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395065</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Radiation therapy is a common component of breast cancer treatment for patients. The high-powered beams of intense energy kill cancer cells and reduce the risk of the cancer recurring. Dr. Laura Vallow, chair of the Radiation Oncology Department at Mayo Clinic in Florida, explains how innovation is transforming radiation treatments. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-radiation-therapy-for-patients-with-breast-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Radiation therapy is a common component of breast cancer treatment for patients. The high-powered beams of intense energy kill cancer cells and reduce the risk of the cancer recurring.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/vallow-laura-a-m-d/bio-20054004">Dr. Laura Vallow</a>, chair of the Radiation Oncology Department at Mayo Clinic in Florida, explains how innovation is transforming radiation treatments.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/aCjypSH3cZw" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeaCjypSH3cZw"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/aCjypSH3cZw?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:05) is in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/MCM-Radiation-for-web-insert.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Patients with breast cancer now have more options when it comes to radiation treatments. The goal is to remove any remaining cancer cells following chemotherapy or surgery.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"In other situations, we use radiation if the cancer is more advanced, or spread to the lymph nodes," says Dr. Vallow.</p>



<p>Advancements in technology allow healthcare professionals to treat patients more safely. One technique called "prone positioning" reduces the chance of beams targeting other organs. For this procedure, patients lie on their stomachs.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1920" height="1080" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395137" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1.jpg 1920w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Breast-Image-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" /></figure>



<p>"We take advantage of gravity, the breast pulls away from the body, and we can treat the breast without exposing the underlying lung and heart to unnecessary radiation," explains Dr. Vallow.</p>



<p>Intensity-modulated radiation therapy is cutting-edge. Unlike traditional radiation, this procedure delivers X-rays directly to the targeted area from multiple angles, allowing for higher, more effective doses.</p>



<p>"Before intensity-modulated radiation therapy, we were not able to conform the dose around the chest wall," says Dr. Vallow.</p>



<p>For patients undergoing radiation therapy, it's crucial to stay hydrated and try to sleep well to fight fatigue. It's also important to use sunscreen after treatment.</p>



<p><strong>Related Posts:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-study-reveals-proton-beam-therapy-may-shorten-breast-cancer-treatment/">Mayo Clinic study reveals proton beam therapy may shorten breast cancer treatment</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-breaking-through-radiation-therapy-myths/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Breaking through radiation therapy myths</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-radiation-therapy-for-patients-with-breast-cancer/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Radiation therapy for patients with breast cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/patient-receiving-external-beam-radiation-therapy_GettyImages-108270897_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/01/a-medical-illustration-of-radiation-therapy-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Laura Vallow]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Patient drives 400 miles for second opinion, kidney stone surgery at Mayo Clinic in Florida </title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/patient-drives-400-miles-for-second-opinion-kidney-stone-surgery-at-mayo-clinic-in-florida/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Raymond Pak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharon Conoley]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395026</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Sharon Conoley had been feeling anxious since she received a diagnosis of a large kidney stone in a solitary kidney. But once she made the decision to drive the 400 miles to seek care at Mayo Clinic in Florida, her worries gave way to a sense of peace and comfort. Sharon Conoley and her husband [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/patient-drives-400-miles-for-second-opinion-kidney-stone-surgery-at-mayo-clinic-in-florida/">Patient drives 400 miles for second opinion, kidney stone surgery at Mayo Clinic in Florida </a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shanon-Conoley2-16x9-1-1024x577.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395033" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shanon-Conoley2-16x9-1-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shanon-Conoley2-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shanon-Conoley2-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shanon-Conoley2-16x9-1.jpg 1245w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading has-text-align-center">Sharon Conoley had been feeling anxious since she received a diagnosis of a large kidney stone in a solitary kidney. But once she made the decision to drive the 400 miles to seek care at Mayo Clinic in Florida, her worries gave way to a sense of peace and comfort.</h4>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p>Sharon Conoley and her husband have always been an active couple. Their shared love of running brought them together in college. And over the years, they’ve kept pace with each other in running and in life.</p>



<p>When they traded running for long-distance hiking, they began enjoying many hikes on the Appalachian Trail together — until, one day, Sharon started experiencing pain in her lower back.</p>



<p>She made an appointment with her chiropractor to investigate the discomfort. An X-ray revealed an unexpected culprit: a large <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/kidney-stones/symptoms-causes/syc-20355755" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">kidney stone</a>.</p>



<p>"Sharon, this is one for the textbooks," her chiropractor told her.</p>



<p>A follow-up visit with her primary care physician and an ultrasound confirmed the presence of the stone.</p>



<p>A close friend who is a nephrologist advised Sharon to see a kidney stone specialist.</p>



<p>Sharon initially sought care in her home state of North Carolina in January 2024. The stone specialist she consulted with seemed surprised by the size and location of the stone, especially given that Sharon had only one kidney.</p>



<p>It soon became clear that the size and location of Sharon's kidney stone would prove to pose more complications than she wanted.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Concerns about risky procedure</strong></h2>



<p>The local doctor indicated the best approach for Sharon's case was a percutaneous nephrolithotomy — a minimally invasive procedure to remove kidney stones through a small incision in the side of the body. The specialist explained the procedure and the risks involved, which included a high risk of bleeding during the surgery and up to 10 days following the procedure. Sharon would also face the possibility of a blood transfusion and the risk of losing her only kidney.</p>



<p>Sharon came away from the visit with many concerns. She had always focused on healthy lifestyle choices — including a vegetarian diet and daily exercise — and did not understand why this was happening. All lab results indicated that she had excellent kidney function, but the stone was large and posed a danger.</p>



<p>Sharon shared her concerns with a neighbor, who recommended that she seek a second opinion at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>Mayo Clinic employs the most competent, patient-centered staff members of any institution I have visited.  <em>Sharon Conoley</em></p>
</blockquote>



<p>He said, "I have a niece who works at Mayo Clinic in Rochester. She’s the most wonderful patient advocate and the kindest person you will ever meet."</p>



<p>Within 48 hours, that niece — Sara Lee, a communications manager — connected Sharon with staff at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a> to begin the process of becoming a new patient.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Traveling for a second opinion</strong></h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic's Nephrology Department contacted Sharon, listened to her concerns, and helped her begin her treatment journey. She says she felt at peace in her earliest interactions with Mayo staff and decided to make an appointment and travel 400 miles to Jacksonville to see firsthand what Mayo Clinic was all about.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Every facet of her visit impressed her, from the cleanliness of the facilities and grounds to the caring and accommodating nature of every person she met.</p>



<p>"Mayo Clinic employs the most competent, patient-centered staff members of any institution I have visited," says Sharon, who managed senior living communities for 30 years.</p>



<p>She specifically recalls an interaction with a Mayo Clinic's Food Services director she met during her initial visit to the on-site café. Sharon was impressed by his credentials and experience in food service management. She also appreciated that he took the time to discuss the menu and answer her questions about a renal diet, even offering a brochure with nutritional specifics.</p>



<p>After her in-person visit, Sharon met virtually with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/pak-raymond-w-m-d-m-b-a/bio-20204872" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Raymond Pak, M.D.</a>, chair of the Department of Urology, to discuss the steps required for removing the kidney stone.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>They were determined to provide comfort and minimize the risk of neck issues occurring during the procedure. They were unbelievable.Sharon Conoley</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Despite feeling like she would be in good hands at Mayo Clinic, Sharon backed out of the procedure many times.</p>



<p>"With excellent kidney function, why should I subject my kidney to surgery to remove this large stone and risk losing the only kidney that I have?" she would ask herself.</p>



<p>Yet Sharon knew that the stakes were high if the kidney stone moved and resulted in a blockage. She could risk losing the kidney and subsequently require a kidney transplant. She trusted the Mayo team and knew that there was only one choice.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Reflecting on empathetic, personalized care</strong></h2>



<p>In May, Sharon had surgery to remove the kidney stone.</p>



<p>She remembers how the medical team demonstrated care and compassion toward her from the moment she arrived.</p>



<p>On her pre-op day, she met Leigh Midkiff, a physician assistant, who provided the reassurance Sharon needed to proceed with the procedure.</p>



<p>"I could hear in her voice how important this surgery was to both her and my surgeon," Sharon says. "She acknowledged that I had only one kidney and the importance of completing the surgery with absolute precision. She put me completely at peace with everything."</p>



<p>On the day of surgery, the Interventional Radiology team took extra time to personalize Sharon's care.</p>



<p>"I shared with the team that, after many years of running, I developed mild degenerative disc changes in my neck," she says. "When I mentioned this, the team immediately began creating a cervical device out of foam for my neck. They placed the device, then made modifications, placed it again, and modified it again. This process continued, adding at least 10–15 minutes to my time in Interventional Radiology. The team could have said, 'We need to get this show on the road,' but they were determined to provide comfort and minimize the risk of neck issues occurring during the procedure. They were unbelievable."</p>



<p>She was met with the same extraordinary level of care when she proceeded to the operating room.</p>



<p>Sensing Sharon's apprehension about anesthesia, the anesthesiologist asked her what he could do to make her less fearful.</p>



<p>"He offered at least four different approaches to anesthesia. He said, 'There are many ways we can do this, so let me know what you're most comfortable with,'" Sharon says. "He introduced and demonstrated each approach to anesthesia. This personalized care added 5–10 minutes of accommodation. I will never forget the kindness and empathy of this person. It meant so much to me."</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>You can hire employees and teach them a new job, but you cannot teach them to care. Mayo Clinic has accomplished all these things in such an amazing way.Sharon Conoley</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Finally, in recovery, she had the most meaningful surprise of all.</p>



<p>Weeks before the procedure, Sharon had lunch with her former employees and mentioned her upcoming surgery — including her fears and anxieties.</p>



<p>One of Sharon's former colleagues offered to reach out to a friend, Susan McMillen, who is a nurse at Mayo to see if she might be able to check on Sharon during her hospitalization.</p>



<p>"I said that would be nice, but I wasn’t sure what, if anything, would come of that conversation," Sharon says.</p>



<p>She soon learned differently.</p>



<p>"This nurse had changed her schedule so that she could care for me," Sharon says. "It was the sweetest thing. She was so kind and patient. Each time she left my room, she would reassure me that she was nearby."</p>



<p>Those simple gestures moved Sharon to tears.</p>



<p>McMillen was touched to hear Sharon had such positive things to say about her care at Mayo. She says her approach to nursing is to treat her patients how she would like herself or her loved ones to be treated if they were in the hospital bed.</p>



<p>"It is meaningful to hear such kind words from any patient, but when it comes from someone entrusted to my care via a friend's recommendation, that is even more special," McMillen says. "Sometimes in nursing, a thank you doesn't come along often, but it is gratifying when it does."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Returning to the trails</strong></h2>



<p>Five days after her surgery, Sharon returned to Mayo Clinic for the removal of her nephrostomy tube, a thin, flexible tube that drains urine from the kidney through an opening in the lower back.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shanon-Conoley1-1x1-1-300x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395036" style="width:336px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shanon-Conoley1-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shanon-Conoley1-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shanon-Conoley1-1x1-1.jpg 498w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure></div>


<p>Afterward, she began her journey home.</p>



<p>Now, nearly three months later, Sharon says she is feeling wonderful. She is back into gardening. She has started hiking again on the Appalachian Trail and plans to start trail running soon. Next year, she and her husband plan to tackle a few trails in the Greek Islands.</p>



<p>Sharon says she is grateful to Mayo Clinic and "a team of prayer warriors" for making it possible for her to continue having these adventures.</p>



<p>"It gives me such confidence knowing that a medical institution is out there setting the bar so high and consistently delivering exceptional care," Sharon says. "I have never experienced a place that can prioritize the patient's needs, as well as Mayo Clinic. My sentiment remains: You can hire employees and teach them a new job, but you cannot teach them to care. Mayo Clinic has accomplished all these things in such an amazing way."</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/patient-drives-400-miles-for-second-opinion-kidney-stone-surgery-at-mayo-clinic-in-florida/">Patient drives 400 miles for second opinion, kidney stone surgery at Mayo Clinic in Florida </a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shanon-Conoley2_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shanon-Conoley2-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Raymond Pak]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Patient Story]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Sharon Conoley]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-32/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jaynelle Ramon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 12:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395150</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week. Mayo Clinic Minute: The importance of breast cancer screening A recent report from the American Cancer Society calculates that 1 in 50 women will develop invasive breast cancer by the age of 50. Early detection through screening [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-32/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-2 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DBHGOGRBuNs/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="374577" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374577" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/MayoClinic/videos/577815948142026/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="395019" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Braxton-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395019" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Braxton-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Braxton-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Braxton-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Braxton-16x9-1.jpg 1361w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DBHtuvWsaXm/?img_index=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="682" data-id="381097" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Pertussis-bacteria-1024x682.jpg" alt="(3D) illustration of the bacteria Bordetella pertussis, which causes whooping cough infection." class="wp-image-381097" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Pertussis-bacteria-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Pertussis-bacteria-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Pertussis-bacteria-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Pertussis-bacteria-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Pertussis-bacteria.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DA87oP-s5CQ/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="386745" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="An ultrasound technician positions a patient for a mammogram" class="wp-image-386745" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Woman-gets-mammogram-16-x-9.jpg 1604w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DBMHRd7tpTj/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="388329" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Meat-thermometer-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="meat thermometer, showing safe temperatures for food" class="wp-image-388329" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Meat-thermometer-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Meat-thermometer-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Meat-thermometer-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Meat-thermometer-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/05/Meat-thermometer-16-x-9.jpg 1609w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>
</figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Check out a few of the most popular News Network stories on @mayoclinic social media this past week.</h3>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-the-importance-of-breast-cancer-screening/">Mayo Clinic Minute: The importance of breast cancer screening</a></h2>



<p>A recent report from the American Cancer Society calculates that 1 in 50 women will develop invasive breast cancer by the age of 50. Early detection through screening can lead to more treatable and curable breast cancers. Dr. Elizabeth Cathcart-Rake&nbsp;clears up confusion about who should be screened and when.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-food-recalls-and-sickness/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Food recalls and sickness</a></h2>



<p>Nearly 10 million pounds of meat and poultry products are being recalled because of possible listeria contamination, according to the Department of Agriculture's Food Safety and Inspection Service. Dr. Nipunie Rajapakse, a pediatric infectious diseases physician, explains the risks associated with listeria and how to best avoid foodborne illness.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-health-screenings-in-underserved-populations/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Health screenings in underserved populations</a></h2>



<p>Cancer is a leading cause of death among Hispanic people in the U.S., according to the&nbsp;American Cancer Society.&nbsp;Early detection through screening can prevent serious health issues.&nbsp;Dr. Jesse Bracamonte, a Mayo Clinic family medicine physician, stresses the need for healthcare workers to discuss the importance of health screenings with patients, especially in&nbsp;underserved communities.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-the-blink-of-an-eye-healthy-teen-needs-new-heart/">'In the blink of an eye,' healthy teen needs new heart</a></h2>



<p>Braxton Wohlferd went from being a healthy teenager celebrating his 16th birthday to suddenly needing a heart transplant. And it was all caused by a rare reaction to a common childhood virus that usually only results in a mild rash.⁠</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/understanding-whooping-cough-with-a-mayo-clinic-expert/">Understanding whooping cough with a Mayo Clinic expert</a></h2>



<p>Cases of pertussis, commonly known as whooping cough, continue to rise in the U.S.&nbsp; New numbers from the&nbsp;Centers for Disease Control and Prevention&nbsp;(CDC) show nearly 18,000 cases through Oct. 5. Whooping cough is an infectious respiratory illness caused by Bordetella pertussis bacteria. It spreads through the air when an infected person coughs or sneezes.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/in-case-you-missed-it-this-weeks-top-5-stories-on-social-media-32/">In case you missed it: This week&#8217;s Top 5 stories on social media</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hispanic-blood-pressure-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/web-top-5_10182024.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[In case you missed it]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Shockwave therapy may help relieve foot problem</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-shockwave-therapy-may-help-relieve-foot-problem/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Barber Lindquist]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 14:27:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Elizabeth Bondi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[shockwave therapy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=394341</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: I've had some foot issues, and I heard that shockwave therapy might be appropriate. How does it work? And how can it help? ANSWER: This noninvasive treatment uses sound waves to transmit energy to tissues to help with the healing process. You may hear it referred to as extracorporeal shockwave treatment. Extracorporeal [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-shockwave-therapy-may-help-relieve-foot-problem/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Shockwave therapy may help relieve foot problem</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/03/a-close-up-of-two-feet-one-on-the-floor-and-the-other-held-in-the-persons-hands-1024x576-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="a closeup of person barefoot showing toes and two feet, one on the floor and the other held in the person's hands" class="wp-image-186245" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/03/a-close-up-of-two-feet-one-on-the-floor-and-the-other-held-in-the-persons-hands-1024x576-1.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/03/a-close-up-of-two-feet-one-on-the-floor-and-the-other-held-in-the-persons-hands-1024x576-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/03/a-close-up-of-two-feet-one-on-the-floor-and-the-other-held-in-the-persons-hands-1024x576-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: </strong>I've had some foot issues, and I heard that shockwave therapy might be appropriate. How does it work? And how can it help?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong> This noninvasive treatment uses sound waves to transmit energy to tissues to help with the healing process. You may hear it referred to as extracorporeal shockwave treatment. Extracorporeal means the treatment occurs outside the body, through the skin, rather than a treatment provided internally. Originally used to treat kidney stones, shockwave therapy also is used to treat some orthopedic conditions.</p>



<p>The sound waves jump-start the healing process, reduce pain and inflammation, break up scar tissue and adhesions, stimulate bone healing, release growth factors and improve blood flow to damaged tissue. Additionally, shockwave treatment can aid in muscle relaxation and activation of connective tissue.</p>



<p>This treatment is administered through a small, hand-held apparatus. There are two different types of shockwave devices: radial and focused. They can be used separately or combined, depending on the condition being treated.</p>



<p>A radial shockwave device generates pressure waves when in contact with the skin and transmits energy into the targeted tissue. Focused shockwave treatment works through the principle of electromagnetic induction, similar to how loudspeakers work.</p>



<p>Differences between these two devices include the depth of energy penetration and location of their maximum effects. Radial pressure waves can cover a broader area, but their effects occur within the tissue, closer to the surface of the body. Focused shockwaves pinpoint their energy toward a smaller area. Additionally, focused shockwaves have a greater treatment depth, and their effects are more at the cellular level.</p>



<p>Shockwave therapy can be used to treat orthopedic conditions such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/tennis-elbow/symptoms-causes/syc-20351987" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">tennis elbow</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/golfers-elbow/symptoms-causes/syc-20372868" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">golfer's elbow</a> or a pulled <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hamstring-injury/symptoms-causes/syc-20372985">hamstring</a>. As a podiatrist, I use shockwave therapy for foot and ankle conditions, including but not limited to:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/plantar-fasciitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20354846" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Plantar fasciitis</a>: Inflammation of the thick band of tissue known as the plantar fascia that runs across the bottom of each foot and connects the heel bone to the toes.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/tendinitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20378243" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tendinitis</a>: Inflammation of the thick fibrous cords that attach muscle to bone.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/sprains/symptoms-causes/syc-20377938#:~:text=Overview,%2C%20ice%2C%20compression%20and%20elevation." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ligament sprain</a>: A stretching or tearing of fibrous tissue that connects two bones together in your joints.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stress-fractures/symptoms-causes/syc-20354057" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stress fractures</a>: Tiny bone cracks caused by repetitive force, often related to overuse.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/broken-foot/symptoms-causes/syc-20355492" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Acute fractures:</a> A crack or a break of a bone.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/shin-splints/symptoms-causes/syc-20354105" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Shin splints</a>: Pain along the shin bone (tibia), the bone in the front of the lower leg.</li>
</ul>



<p>&nbsp;Some of the benefits of shockwave therapy include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>No surgery.</li>



<li>No anesthesia.</li>



<li>No downtime or activity/sport restrictions after treatment.</li>
</ul>



<p>Shockwave therapy is performed as an outpatient procedure and is usually done in a series of three to six treatments spaced three to seven days apart. The treatment has minimal risks or side effects, including slight bruising or mild swelling at the treatment site. Sometimes, maintenance treatment is performed four to six weeks after the last treatment. While receiving treatment, anti-inflammatory medications may need to be discontinued.</p>



<p>The full effects of shockwave therapy can be seen up to 10 to 15 weeks after the final treatment.</p>



<p>If you sustained a new foot injury or are suffering from a chronic foot condition that is not responding to other nonoperative care, shockwave might be another alternative treatment to help alleviate your symptoms. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/bondi-elizabeth-d-p-m/bio-20540960" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>Elizabeth Bondi, D.P.M.</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Podiatry, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota</em></strong></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-shockwave-therapy-may-help-relieve-foot-problem/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Shockwave therapy may help relieve foot problem</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/03/shutterstock_103288814-original-683x1024_Fotor1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/03/a-close-up-of-two-feet-one-on-the-floor-and-the-other-held-in-the-persons-hands-1024x576-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Elizabeth Bondi]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[shockwave therapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>