<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Orthopedics/Sports - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/orthopedics-sports/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/orthopedics-sports/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 16:00:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Can taking a plunge in icy water after your workout be beneficial?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/can-taking-a-plunge-in-icy-water-after-your-workout-be-beneficial/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2024 14:30:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cold water plunges]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Andrew Jagim]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381448</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>From ice bucket challenges to polar plunges, people have embraced being doused with or dunked in icy water to raise money for their favorite causes. But can cold water immersion have benefits beyond fundraising? Research indicates that icy water may have a positive effect on recovery after exercise by reducing inflammation and soreness. It also [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/can-taking-a-plunge-in-icy-water-after-your-workout-be-beneficial/">Can taking a plunge in icy water after your workout be beneficial?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/person-in-icy-water-wearing-hat-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381450" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/person-in-icy-water-wearing-hat-16x9-1.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/person-in-icy-water-wearing-hat-16x9-1-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></figure>



<p>From ice bucket challenges to polar plunges, people have embraced being doused with or dunked in icy water to raise money for their favorite causes. But can cold water immersion have benefits beyond fundraising?</p>



<p>Research indicates that icy water may have a positive effect on recovery after exercise by reducing inflammation and soreness. It also may help build resiliency, restore balance to the nervous system and improve cognitive function and mood.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What are the basics of cold-water immersion?</h2>



<p>A cold plunge or cold water immersion involves partially or totally submerging yourself in cold water for a few minutes at a time. It can be as simple as sitting in a bathtub filled with cold water and ice cubes or jumping into a cold lake or the ocean. You also can go to a cold-plunge center or create or buy your own cold-plunge tank, which, if it has all the options, can cost up to $20,000.</p>



<p>Be sure not to plunge into icy waters that have a current, such as a river, to avoid being swept downstream or trapped under ice.</p>



<p>Water should be 50 F or colder. Keep in mind that the water in a frozen lake will be much colder. That's why it's a good idea to measure the temperature before you jump in. The plunge can be done as one continuous session or multiple sessions with breaks between the sessions. Typically, cold-water plungers start with 30 seconds to a minute and work up to five to 10 minutes at a time.</p>



<p>Researchers are still determining the optimum process and timing for cold-water immersion sessions.</p>



<p>You can do cold plunging every day. However, if you're doing it after training, daily plunges could compromise the potential for long-term performance improvements.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What are the benefits for workout recovery or athletic performance?</h2>



<p>Research on cold water immersion has found evidence that it helps reduce the degree of exercise-induced muscle damage that can occur after physically challenging activities. Less damage leads to less inflammation, which in turn reduces soreness and helps restore physical performance the next day.</p>



<p>These benefits may be the result of rapid constriction of the blood vessels due to the cold water. The cold can trigger responses in your body, such as decreased metabolic activity, alterations in hormone production and blood flow, and activation of the immune system.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What are the drawbacks of cold plunges?</h2>



<p>The most obvious drawback is the cold and discomfort, although frequent plungers report becoming more comfortable and tolerant of the cold with regular exposure. Depending on the environment, such as plunging into an ice and snow covered lake, you also may be at risk for <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/frostbite/symptoms-causes/syc-20372656" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">frostbite</a>. Too long exposure also can lead to hypothermia, so make sure you have towels and warm clothing close at hand if you're doing cold plunges outdoors.</p>



<p>For athletes, cold water immersion may affect different types of training in different ways. For those engaged in resistance training, cold water may turn down the molecular signaling pathways that are normally activated after exercise. This may hinder long-term improvements in strength, muscle growth and performance. However, cold-water immersion doesn't appear to negatively affect endurance training in the same way.</p>



<p>If you want to give cold water immersion a try, start by consulting an expert, such as a <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers?service=Sports%20Medicine">sports medicine specialist</a>, to ensure you're plunging appropriately and following the right protocol. If you have risk factors associated with <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/cardiology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiovascular disease</a>, such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/know-your-numbers-blood-pressure" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">high blood pressure</a>, check with your <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers?service=Sports%20Medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">primary care provider</a> or <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/cardiology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiologist</a> so you know it's safe for you to cold plunge.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/andrew-jagim-phd" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Andrew Jagim, Ph.D.</em></a><em>, specializes in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/sports-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">sports medicine</a>&nbsp;in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/la-crosse" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">La Crosse</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/onalaska" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Onalaska</a>, Wisconsin.</em></p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/cold-plunge-after-workouts" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/can-taking-a-plunge-in-icy-water-after-your-workout-be-beneficial/">Can taking a plunge in icy water after your workout be beneficial?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/person-in-icy-water-wearing-hat-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/person-in-icy-water-wearing-hat-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cold water plunges]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Andrew Jagim]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic expert: Warm climates offer mobility options for snowbirds after surgery</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-expert-warm-climates-offer-mobility-options-for-snowbirds-after-surgery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sharon Theimer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 21:07:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Mark Spangehl]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=380914</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>PHOENIX — For snowbirds who need joint replacement surgery, places like Arizona and Florida offer an enticing prospect in the dead of winter — the opportunity to recuperate in a warmer climate without fear of slipping and falling on ice. Snowbirds are people who typically seek out warm winter climates to escape Arctic-like conditions at [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-expert-warm-climates-offer-mobility-options-for-snowbirds-after-surgery/">Mayo Clinic expert: Warm climates offer mobility options for snowbirds after surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/16x9_Featured-image_EN-snowbird-post_GettyImages-1445061226-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-380495" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/16x9_Featured-image_EN-snowbird-post_GettyImages-1445061226-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/16x9_Featured-image_EN-snowbird-post_GettyImages-1445061226-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/16x9_Featured-image_EN-snowbird-post_GettyImages-1445061226-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/16x9_Featured-image_EN-snowbird-post_GettyImages-1445061226-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/16x9_Featured-image_EN-snowbird-post_GettyImages-1445061226-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>PHOENIX — For snowbirds who need joint replacement surgery, places like Arizona and Florida offer an enticing prospect in the dead of winter — the opportunity to recuperate in a warmer climate without fear of slipping and falling on ice.</p>



<p>Snowbirds are people who typically seek out warm winter climates to escape Arctic-like conditions at home, but there are also benefits from a medical standpoint. Regaining mobility after joint replacement is an important milestone for patients, and walking is one way to help them get there. Think flat sidewalks instead of potholes or bumps in your path caused by ice and snow melting and refreezing.</p>



<p>"After joint replacement, we strongly encourage patients to walk, walk, walk and gradually increase their activities," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/spangehl-mark-j-m-d/bio-20054096?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mark Spangehl, M.D.</a>, an orthopedic surgeon and chair of the Adult Reconstruction Division at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/arizona?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Arizona</a>. "We get some rain occasionally, but for the most part, they can be outside every day that they want to be outside. And that's part of the recovery."</p>



<p>According to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, Phoenix's average temperature is 68 degrees in December and January, 72 degrees in February, and 77 degrees in March. In Jacksonville, the location of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a>, the average temperature is 68 degrees in December, 66 degrees in January, 69 degrees in February, and 75 degrees in March.</p>



<p>In addition to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/knee-replacement/about/pac-20385276?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">knee</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/hip-replacement/about/pac-20385042?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hip</a> replacement or surgeries for other musculoskeletal conditions, moving is important after procedures such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/minimally-invasive-heart-surgery/about/pac-20384895?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart surgery</a>.</p>



<p>Planning is essential for any surgery, but it's especially important for a surgery <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/international?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">away from home</a>. If patients get on the surgical schedule earlier during their stays, they have the rest of their time to recuperate. Patients come a few days before surgery to meet with their surgeon and learn more about what to expect before, during and after the procedure. The surgeon also will go over any potential risks and complications, which are small. After surgery, patients can expect to receive some follow-up care in person, Dr. Spangehl says.</p>



<p>How long patients need to stay nearby the hospital to recover after surgery depends on the person. People who are fit and active may not need to stay as long as someone with comorbidities that affect their mobility. Those comorbidities include having arthritis in other joints, Parkinson's disease, or heart or lung issues that affect stamina.</p>



<p>After surgery, patients should plan to have appropriate support — such as a family member — available nearby, Dr. Spangehl says.</p>



<p>"If you're traveling some distance for the procedure, you'll need someone who you're comfortable with and who can be there for a while to help you after surgery," he says.</p>



<p>Typically, once the person is mobile and can get around safely, they can return home, Dr. Spangehl says.</p>



<p>Mayo's snowbird connection to Arizona goes back decades. During their retirement years in the 1930s, Mayo Clinic's founders, brothers William J. Mayo, M.D., and Charles H. Mayo, M.D., and their wives headed to Arizona when the Minnesota winter set in. Their love of the Southwest came full circle when Mayo Clinic in Scottsdale, Arizona, opened in 1987.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Rhoda Madson, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-expert-warm-climates-offer-mobility-options-for-snowbirds-after-surgery/">Mayo Clinic expert: Warm climates offer mobility options for snowbirds after surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/1x1-Featured-image_EN-snowbird-post_GettyImages-1445061226.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/16x9_Featured-image_EN-snowbird-post_GettyImages-1445061226.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Mark Spangehl]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[International News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mcthumb >https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/16x9_Featured-image_EN-snowbird-post_GettyImages-1445061226-150x150.jpg</mayoclinic:mcthumb >	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Walk like a penguin: Keeping your winter balance</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/walk-like-a-penguin-keeping-your-winter-balance/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Balance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kariline Bringe]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[winter walking]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=357422</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>When winter storms hit, good balance can prevent falls and injuries — ranging from broken arms, legs or hips to back injuries and concussions. The National Center for Injury Prevention and Control says slips and falls are the leading cause of nonfatal injury across all age groups, except the 10–24 group. One in every 5 [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/walk-like-a-penguin-keeping-your-winter-balance/">Walk like a penguin: Keeping your winter balance</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/01/walking-on-ice-with-boots16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-357423" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/01/walking-on-ice-with-boots16x9.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/01/walking-on-ice-with-boots16x9-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></figure>



<p>When winter storms hit, good balance can prevent falls and injuries — ranging from broken arms, legs or hips to back injuries and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/concussion/symptoms-causes/syc-20355594" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">concussions</a>.</p>



<p>The National Center for Injury Prevention and Control says slips and falls are the leading cause of nonfatal injury across all age groups, except the 10–24 group. One in every 5 falls results in a serious injury, such as head trauma or broken bones. That’s more than 800,000 people being hospitalized each year.</p>



<p>To remain upright and steady, the even distribution of weight over your feet is vital. Many parts of your body play key roles in your&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/balance-problems/symptoms-causes/syc-20350474" target="_blank">balance</a>. Muscles, bones, joints, eyes, the balance organ in the inner ear, nerves, heart and blood vessels must work normally to maintain your balance. When these systems aren't functioning well, balance problems can arise.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Keeping your balance no matter the weather</h2>



<p>Your arms are one of the greatest aids in maintaining your balance, especially when it's icy. Start with your hands, and wear gloves. Gloves keep your hands warm and out of your pockets, which frees up your arms so you can extend them out from your sides to improve your ability to stay upright.</p>



<p>Your feet also aid in balance. Assume that all wet, dark areas on pavements are slippery and icy. Slow down, take short, careful steps at first, and then adjust your pace to surface conditions. Or walk like a penguin. Point your feet slightly outward, and put your center of gravity directly over your feet as much as possible.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Other tips to tackle tricky walking conditions include:</h4>



<ul>
<li>Use a backpack or a cross-body bag when carrying something to free up your hands.&nbsp;If you need to carry groceries or heavy bags, take them one at a time.</li>



<li>Wear winter assistive devices with built-in grippers over your shoes or boots. Or wear lace-up shoes that fit well and have deep-grooved, nonskid, rubber treads.</li>



<li>Wipe your shoes and boots thoroughly on the floor mat when coming inside.</li>



<li>Use a cane or walking poles when out in winter weather.</li>



<li>Avoid texting when walking on snow or ice. It can be an accident waiting to happen.</li>



<li>Get in and out of your vehicle slowly, holding onto the door and steering wheel while stepping on or off a slippery surface.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Getting back on your feet</h2>



<p>If you do fall, make sure you're not injured. Then, roll onto your hands and knees. Take one foot and place it between your hands, then bring the other foot between your hands. Keep your feet shoulder-width apart, and push yourself up from there.</p>



<p>If you think you might be hurt or are unsure if an injury is serious, seek medical care immediately.</p>



<p>Once you've recovered, think back on the fall and ask yourself: "What was I doing?" and "What could I have done differently to help prevent that fall from happening?"</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/kariline-bringe-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kariline Bringe, M.D.</a>, is an&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/orthopedic-surgery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">orthopedic surgeon</a>&nbsp;in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/la-crosse" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">La Crosse</a>, Wisconsin.</p>



<p>This article first appeared on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/keeping-your-winter-balance" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/walk-like-a-penguin-keeping-your-winter-balance/">Walk like a penguin: Keeping your winter balance</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/01/walking-on-ice-with-boots1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/01/walking-on-ice-with-boots16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Balance]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Kariline Bringe]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[winter walking]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Mixed reality provides precise path during shoulder surgery</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-mixed-reality-provides-precise-path-during-shoulder-surgery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Joaquin Sanchez-Sotelo]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mixed reality technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Shoulder Replacement]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=380031</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Holograms and virtual reality (VR) headsets can be part of a great gaming experience. But did you know that the same technology can make for a better healthcare experience too? Dr. Joaquin Sanchez-Sotelo, a Mayo Clinic orthopedic surgeon, explains how, for the first time ever, mixed reality played a vital role in a recent shoulder [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-mixed-reality-provides-precise-path-during-shoulder-surgery/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Mixed reality provides precise path during shoulder surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Mixed-reality2-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-380126" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Mixed-reality2-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Mixed-reality2-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Mixed-reality2-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Mixed-reality2-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Mixed-reality2-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Holograms and virtual reality (VR) headsets can be part of a great gaming experience. But did you know that the same technology can make for a better healthcare experience too?</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/sanchez-sotelo-joaquin-m-d-ph-d/bio-20054571?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Joaquin Sanchez-Sotelo</a>, a Mayo Clinic orthopedic surgeon, explains how, for the first time ever, mixed reality played a vital role in a recent shoulder surgery he performed.</p>



<p>Shoulder arthroplasty, or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/shoulder-replacement/about/pac-20519121?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">shoulder replacement surgery</a>, is a complex procedure where damaged bone is replaced by metal and plastic implants. Computer software helps doctors create a surgical plan as to where those implants should be placed.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/62q-iWE4Y28" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutube62qiWE4Y28"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Mixed reality provides a precise path during shoulder surgery" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/62q-iWE4Y28?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:59) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/SCRIPT-MCM-Mixed-reality-shoulder.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"But we didn't have a way to easily translate that plan, which is very accurate, to the operating room", says Dr. Sanchez-Sotelo, division chair of Shoulder and Elbow Surgery at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>That is, until now. Recently, he performed the first-ever mixed reality navigated shoulder replacement surgery. Specially designed tools and goggles create a highly accurate hologram of the joint. He says that together, they "allow us to place a component exactly where it belongs."</p>



<p>And that’s important, he adds, because "placing the implant exactly where it belongs has a direct impact on complications, outcomes and longevity."</p>



<p>Dr. Sanchez-Sotelo has seen a lot of change over his career. But he says this may be the most exciting. "This technology is going to allow us to do things that were unthinkable before."</p>



<p><em>Mayo Clinic has a financial interest in the technology referenced in this story. Mayo Clinic will use any revenue it receives to support its not-for-profit mission in patient care, education and research. Dr. Joaquin Sanchez-Sotelo is a paid consultant of Stryker Trauma and Extremities</em>.</p>



<p>Related resources</p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/orthopedic-surgeons-have-another-tool-for-knee-replacement-augmented-reality/">Orthopedic surgeons have another tool for knee replacement: augmented reality</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-augmented-reality-spine-surgery/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What is augmented reality spine surgery?</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-mixed-reality-provides-precise-path-during-shoulder-surgery/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Mixed reality provides precise path during shoulder surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Mixed-reality1-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Mixed-reality1-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Joaquin Sanchez-Sotelo]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[mixed reality technology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Shoulder Replacement]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: How to jump-start your workout</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-jump-start-your-workout/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 16:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nathan LeBrasseur]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=379614</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Many people promise to exercise more in the new year, but jump-starting your workout routine can be challenging if you've been sitting on the couch for a while. It can seem like a daunting task. Dr. Nathan LeBrasseur, director of the Robert and Arlene Kogod Center on Aging at Mayo Clinic, says it's never too [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-jump-start-your-workout/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How to jump-start your workout</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Many people promise to exercise more in the new year, but jump-starting your workout routine can be challenging if you've been sitting on the couch for a while. It can seem like a daunting task.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/lebrasseur-nathan-k-ph-d-m-s/bio-00055041" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Nathan LeBrasseur</a>, director of the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-arlene-kogod-center-aging" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Robert and Arlene Kogod Center on Aging</a> at Mayo Clinic, says it's never too late to get moving, even if you're an older adult.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/mEkRo550oKg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubemEkRo550oKg"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: How to jump-start your workout" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mEkRo550oKg?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (0:55) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/SCRIPT-MCM-Jump-start-your-workout.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Starting a workout program or being physically active takes motivation and commitment. The key is to start slowly and do something you take pleasure in.</p>



<p>"If you hate swimming, don't try to start to become a swimmer. But (if) you enjoy dancing or other activities (such as) gardening, those are forms of activity that once you engage in, you increase your consistency and compliance that will have the most health benefits," says Dr. LeBrasseur.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/12/a-smiling-older-woman-seated-on-a-yoga-mat-doing-stretches-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a smiling older woman seated on a yoga mat, doing stretches" class="wp-image-256796" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/12/a-smiling-older-woman-seated-on-a-yoga-mat-doing-stretches-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/12/a-smiling-older-woman-seated-on-a-yoga-mat-doing-stretches-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/12/a-smiling-older-woman-seated-on-a-yoga-mat-doing-stretches-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/12/a-smiling-older-woman-seated-on-a-yoga-mat-doing-stretches-16X9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/12/a-smiling-older-woman-seated-on-a-yoga-mat-doing-stretches-16X9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Being active can build muscle strength and improve cognitive and cardiovascular health.</p>



<p>"Three percent or 30 minutes a day of our waking hours, if we commit that to physical activity, will have huge benefits," explains Dr. LeBrasseur.</p>



<p>And for those young at heart, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention recommends 150 minutes of moderate exercise a week.</p>



<p>"As we get older, dedicating time, purposeful time, to getting some form of aerobic exercise or endurance exercise, like walking or cycling or swimming, and also getting some form of strength training is critically important," says Dr. LeBrasseur.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Tips to get started and stick with a workout plan:</strong></h3>



<ul>
<li>Research workout routines.</li>



<li>Schedule your workouts.</li>



<li>Find an exercise buddy.</li>



<li>Be consistent.</li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-jump-start-your-workout/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How to jump-start your workout</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/a-young-or-middle-aged-Asian-man-in-a-workout-gym-lifting-weights-and-exercising-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/08/a-smiling-older-woman-in-the-pool-in-a-swimming-or-water-fitness-class-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nathan LeBrasseur]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Tips to help a frozen shoulder</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-whats-frozen-shoulder/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2023 17:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Adhesive capsulitis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Christopher Camp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[frozen shoulder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[physical therapy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[shoulder pain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sports Medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=314831</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Pain and stiffness in your shoulder can make every activity, including sleep, difficult. Worsening shoulder pain, especially at night, could mean you have a&#160;frozen shoulder, says Dr. Christopher Camp, a Mayo Clinic orthopedic surgeon. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (0:59) is in the downloads&#160;at the end of the post.&#160;Please courtesy: "Mayo [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-whats-frozen-shoulder/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Tips to help a frozen shoulder</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Pain and stiffness in your shoulder can make every activity, including sleep, difficult. Worsening shoulder pain, especially at night, could mean you have a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/frozen-shoulder/symptoms-causes/syc-20372684?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">frozen shoulder</a>, says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/camp-christopher-l-m-d/bio-20348631?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Christopher Camp</a>, a Mayo Clinic orthopedic surgeon.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OU6-i4dKPKs" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeOU6i4dKPKs"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Tips to help a frozen shoulder" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/OU6-i4dKPKs?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (0:59) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post.&nbsp;Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/MCM-Frozen-shoulder-script.pdf" target="_blank">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"The scientific name that we give it is adhesive capsulitis, and, basically, it's a condition when the shoulder gets tight and you can't move it very well," says Dr. Camp. </p>



<p>He says frozen shoulder happens when the lining that goes around the shoulder joint gets inflamed, possibly the result of a small injury. It thickens over time, forming scar tissue.</p>



<p>"Frozen shoulder exists in three stages, and the symptoms and treatment options depend on which stage you're in. So the first one is an inflammatory stage," says Dr. Camp.</p>



<p>That's the painful stage. Rest and steroid injections may help. The second stage is when the shoulder is less painful but starts to stiffen. Physical therapy works well then. The third phase …</p>



<p>"… is what we call thawing, which means it finally starts to relax, loosen up and gain motion back again," says Dr. Camp.</p>



<p>If it doesn't resolve in six to 12 months, surgery may be an option.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>____________________________</strong></p>



<p><strong>For the safety of its patients, staff and visitors, Mayo Clinic has strict masking policies in place.&nbsp;Anyone shown without a mask was either recorded prior to COVID-19 or recorded in a nonpatient care area where social distancing and other safety protocols were followed.</strong></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-whats-frozen-shoulder/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Tips to help a frozen shoulder</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/06/a-woman-in-pain-holding-her-shoulder-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/06/a-woman-in-pain-holding-her-shoulder-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Adhesive capsulitis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Christopher Camp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[frozen shoulder]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[physical therapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[shoulder pain]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Sports Medicine]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: What&#8217;s going on with my kneecap?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-whats-going-on-with-my-kneecap/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Abby Ashbacher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2023 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chronic dislocation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dislocated kneecap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Douglas Bartels]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[knee pain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q&A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sports med]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377424</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: I was playing a pickup game of football with my kids, took a tumble, and my kneecap made a popping sound. It really hurt, then seemed to get better, but something's not right. Any idea what might be going on? ANSWER: If your kneecap pops or slides to the outside of your [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-whats-going-on-with-my-kneecap/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: What&#8217;s going on with my kneecap?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/knee_16x9_GettyImages-1148111603.png" alt="A black woman holds her sore knee." class="wp-image-377373" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/knee_16x9_GettyImages-1148111603.png 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/knee_16x9_GettyImages-1148111603-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/knee_16x9_GettyImages-1148111603-768x432.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> I was playing a pickup game of football with my kids, took a tumble, and my kneecap made a popping sound. It really hurt, then seemed to get better, but something's not right. Any idea what might be going on?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER: </strong>If your kneecap pops or slides to the outside of your knee, you'll definitely know that something's going on. Typically, that "something" is a partial or full dislocation, which means the kneecap, also known as the patella, has slipped partly or all the way out of its groove over the knee joint.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/first-aid/first-aid-dislocation/basics/art-20056693?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">Dislocation</a> can be caused by a sudden blow, such as taking a hard hit playing a contact sport like football or hockey, or by a chronic condition, such as a stretched ligament. Some people have a particular knee anatomy that makes it more common. In those cases, a dislocation could be caused by something as simple as normal walking or standing up from a chair. With chronic dislocation, it may feel as though your knee is buckling or giving way. There's often no pattern or regular causes of the dislocations.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What happens when a kneecap dislocates?</strong></h2>



<p>When the <a href="https://sportsmedicine.mayoclinic.org/condition/multi-ligament-injuries-knee-dislocation/">kneecap dislocates</a>, it's painful, and the knee area may swell. Whether it happens from an acute or chronic situation, dislocation can damage the cartilage of the groove that the kneecap sits in or the cartilage underneath the kneecap.</p>



<p>Acute or chronic dislocation indicates you have a stretched or torn medial patellofemoral ligament, or MPFL, a tough band of tissue that connects to the inside of the kneecap and prevents it from sliding to the outside of the knee.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Treating acute dislocation</strong></h2>



<p>If the dislocation is caused by an acute injury, you may be able to ease the kneecap back into place, or you may need to go an emergency department where healthcare professionals can correct the dislocation and evaluate if there's additional injury to your knee. Following the dislocation, you should see an orthopedic specialist.</p>



<p>An X-ray provides an overall view of the anatomy of the kneecap and knee joint. The orthopedic specialist can determine if there is damage to the groove the kneecap rests in, how high the kneecap sits above the joint and if the patellar tendon, which connects below the kneecap, is pulling to one side.</p>



<p>If this is the first time your kneecap has dislocated, the X-ray also can help determine if you're at risk of it happening again. Your orthopedic specialist also may order an MRI to check if a piece of the cartilage has broken off.</p>



<p>Younger patients may need to undergo surgery to remove or fix a cartilage piece that has broken off and reconstruct the MPFL. Recovery following surgery typically involves wearing a brace, physical therapy and limited weight bearing to give the cartilage the best chance to heal. It may take up to six months before you're able to fully return to sports.</p>



<p>For older patients, cartilage is less likely to heal, so surgery isn't always recommended. However, if you're experiencing a catching sensation in your knee, an orthopedic surgeon may decide to surgically remove the piece of cartilage. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/physical-medicine-rehabilitation-mayo-clinic/sections/overview/ovc-20467039?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">Rehabilitation</a> will include limited weight bearing, using a brace and physical therapy.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Treating chronic dislocation</strong></h2>



<p>The first time your knee dislocates — unrelated to an injury — it may slide back into place on its own. However, you should see an orthopedic specialist who can evaluate if there has been any injury to the cartilage and determine your risk for dislocations happening again. If there isn't any cartilage damage, the orthopedic specialist may order physical therapy to strengthen your hip and quadricep muscles. This can help overcome any stretch in the MPFL ligament and stabilize your kneecap, as well as decrease the risk of arthritis over time.</p>



<p>However, you eventually still may require surgery to reconstruct the MPFL, as well as other procedures to correct chronic dislocations. These include deepening the groove where the kneecap sits or moving the location where the patellar tendon connects.</p>



<p>Recovery from MPFL reconstruction may take several months before you're able to return to normal activities and regain your range of motion. Overall recovery for more complex surgeries may take four to six months.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Preventing kneecap dislocations</strong></h2>



<p>The best way to lessen your chance of acute and chronic kneecap dislocations is to maintain overall leg, quadricep and hip strength. For chronic dislocations, learn what tends to cause them, such as twisting, and avoid those motions. A physical therapist also can work with you to improve overall leg strength and teach you how to correct a kneecap dislocation on your own.</p>



<p>For athletes who have suffered an acute dislocation, prompt care, possible surgery and rehabilitation can get you back to playing again. <em>— </em><strong><em><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/doug-bartels-md">Dr. Douglas Bartels</a>, Orthopedics &amp; Orthopedic Surgery, Sports Medicine, Mayo Clinic Health System, </em></strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/eau-claire"><strong><em>Eau Claire, Wisconsin</em></strong></a></p>



<p>________________________</p>



<p><em><strong>Related Articles&nbsp;</strong></em></p>



<ul>
<li><strong><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-in-florida-awarded-top-national-certification-for-advanced-total-hip-knee-replacement/"><span class="s1">Mayo Clinic in Florida awarded top national certification for advanced total hip, knee replacement</span></a></strong></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-managing-osteoarthritis-for-hips-and-knees/"><strong><span class="s1">Mayo Clinic Q and A:&nbsp;Managing osteoarthritis for hips and knees</span></strong></a></li>



<li><strong><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/patient-resumes-active-life-after-knee-surgeries/">Patient resumes active life after knee surgeries</a></strong></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-whats-going-on-with-my-kneecap/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: What&#8217;s going on with my kneecap?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/knee_1x1_GettyImages-1148111603.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/knee_16x9_GettyImages-1148111603.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[chronic dislocation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[dislocated kneecap]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Douglas Bartels]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[knee pain]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[sports med]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Be careful when carving on Thanksgiving</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-be-careful-when-carving-on-thanksgiving/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sanj Kakar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Food]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hand injury]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[knife safety]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thanksgiving]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey carving safety]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=352906</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Food tends to be the focus on Thanksgiving, but preparing that food is often trickier than many people expect. Dr. Sanj Kakar, a Mayo Clinic orthopedic hand surgeon, says far too many people accidentally carve up their hands while trying to carve up the turkey. Dr. Kakar offers these tips to help keep you out [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-be-careful-when-carving-on-thanksgiving/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Be careful when carving on Thanksgiving</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Food tends to be the focus on Thanksgiving, but preparing that food is often trickier than many people expect. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/kakar-sanjeev-sanj-m-d/bio-20055340?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Sanj Kakar</a>, a Mayo Clinic orthopedic hand surgeon, says far too many people accidentally carve up their hands while trying to carve up the turkey. Dr. Kakar offers these tips to help keep you out of the emergency department this Thanksgiving. </p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/2KhkklTfV1E" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutube2KhkklTfV1E"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Be careful when carving on Thanksgiving" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/2KhkklTfV1E?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (0:59) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post.<br>Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/MCM-Be-careful-while-carving-this-Thanksgiving.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>This Thanksgiving, don't let a poke, stab or slice prevent you and your family from enjoying turkey time.</p>



<p>"We see a lot of turkey-cutting injuries," Dr. Kakar says.</p>



<p>Thanksgiving is supposed to be a time dedicated to family, football and food, but too often, it turns into a day of finger and hand injuries.</p>



<p>"In terms of what happens is that people who aren't familiar with using a knife tend to do it, and their hand ... slips," Dr. Kakar says. "And if you actually think about how you're cutting, ... the knife can actually slip and puncture your hand."</p>



<p>Dr. Kakar sees patients who have injuries related to turkey carving that range from deep slices to cut tendons, and even fingers cut off.</p>



<p>"Well, I think the No. 1 risk factor is alcohol," he says.</p>



<p>So if you've been drinking, leave the carving to someone else.</p>



<p>"Another common cause for injuries is with distraction," he says. "So the whole family is gathered around. There's a lot of excitement. The turkey comes out, and one can be distracted when you're doing it."</p>



<p>That's why he recommends doing the carving in the kitchen away from distractions, then bringing the sliced turkey to the table.</p>



<p>Dr. Kakar's third tip comes from the fact that many people serve foods on Thanksgiving that they don't eat or prepare other times of the year. He's seen patients who tried to prepare a squash or some other vegetable, but didn't know the proper way to cut it. His recommendation is that if you don't know the proper way to cut something, just use it as a centerpiece on the dining room table.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-be-careful-when-carving-on-thanksgiving/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Be careful when carving on Thanksgiving</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/shutterstock_116262541_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/shutterstock_116262541_Fotor-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Sanj Kakar]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Food]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[hand injury]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[knife safety]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Thanksgiving]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Turkey carving safety]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Stacking your exercise over the weekend</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-stacking-your-exercise-over-the-weekend/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Osiadacz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Wesley Troyer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sports injuries]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[weekend warrior]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=351715</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Researchers have found that condensing exercise into a few days is as effective as spreading activity out across a week. Dr. Wes Troyer, a Mayo Clinic physical medicine and rehabilitation physician, explains how people who stack their workouts can avoid common injuries and reap the benefits of their activity. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute Journalists: [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-stacking-your-exercise-over-the-weekend/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Stacking your exercise over the weekend</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Researchers have found that condensing <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/troyer-wesley-wes-d-d-o/bio-20509040?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">exercise</a> into a few days is as effective as spreading activity out across a week. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/troyer-wesley-wes-d-d-o/bio-20509040">Dr. Wes Troyer</a>, a Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/physical-medicine-rehabilitation-mayo-clinic/sections/overview/ovc-20467039?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">physical medicine and rehabilitation</a> physician, explains how people who stack their workouts can avoid common injuries and reap the benefits of their activity.</p>



<p><a href="https://youtu.be/MVa2mkwL7dw" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</strong></a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeMVa2mkwL7dw"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Stacking your exercise over the weekend" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/MVa2mkwL7dw?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:57) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post.&nbsp;Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network."&nbsp;Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/Script-MCM-Weekend-Warrior-Exercising.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Exercise is key to a healthy lifestyle.</p>



<p>For those on a time crunch, stacking weekly exercise into a couple of days comes with the title "weekend warrior."</p>



<p>“Things like running, jogging, high-intensity workouts, ideally, the more that you can do, the better. People that did this, lowered mortality, lowered cardiovascular events," says Dr. Troyer.</p>



<p>At least <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/fitness/expert-answers/exercise/faq-20057916?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">150 minutes</a> of moderate-intensity exercise or 75 minutes of vigorous activity is recommended for adults each week.</p>



<p>"We don't expect people that have gone from a sedentary activity of not doing anything to jumping into 150 minutes a week. So taking days of break in between, assessing how your body responds to that activity," says Dr. Troyer.</p>



<p>Repeating the same motions or ramping up too quickly could lead to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/fitness/in-depth/overuse-injury/art-20045875?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">overuse injuries</a>, inflammation and pain.</p>



<p>“If you take a couple days off and it's still persistent pain with daily activity — pain that keeps you up at night or keeps you from sleeping — these are all things that we typically recommend people coming in to be evaluated," he says.</p>



<p><strong>Related articles:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-tips-to-avoid-weekend-warrior-athlete-sports-injuries/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Tips to avoid 'weekend warrior athlete' sports injuries</a>"</li>



<li>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-weekend-warrior-exercise-tips/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Weekend warrior exercise tips</a>"</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-stacking-your-exercise-over-the-weekend/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Stacking your exercise over the weekend</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/10/healthy-woman-running-on-street-for-exercise-and-wellness-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/10/healthy-woman-running-on-street-for-exercise-and-wellness-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Wesley Troyer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Exercise]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[sports injuries]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[weekend warrior]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Advanced treatments target advanced shoulder issues</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advanced-treatments-target-advanced-shoulder-issues/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Scott Kuzma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Shoulder Surgery]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376840</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Shoulder pain, weakness and range of motion loss can keep you from the activities you need and love to do, whether it's lifting boxes on the job, putting away dishes in the kitchen or hitting that powerful tennis serve. Wear and tear, injury, certain medical conditions and age can take a toll on how your [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advanced-treatments-target-advanced-shoulder-issues/">Advanced treatments target advanced shoulder issues</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/12/AchingShoulder16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-355069" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/12/AchingShoulder16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/12/AchingShoulder16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/12/AchingShoulder16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/12/AchingShoulder16x9.jpg 1120w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Shoulder pain, weakness and range of motion loss can keep you from the activities you need and love to do, whether it's lifting boxes on the job, putting away dishes in the kitchen or hitting that powerful tennis serve.</p>



<p>Wear and tear, injury, certain medical conditions and age can take a toll on how your shoulder functions. Sometimes, the treatment is pretty straightforward, with options ranging from physical therapy to injections or surgery.</p>



<p>But other times, the condition of your shoulder has advanced beyond those options. Now, there are treatments designed especially for more advanced shoulder issues.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Inserting a balloon for stabilization</h2>



<p>When a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/rotator-cuff-injury/symptoms-causes/syc-20350225" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">rotator cuff tear </a>is so severe it can't be repaired, your orthopedic surgeon may use a subacromial balloon spacer. This small device is inserted into the space where the damaged rotator cuff lies using minimally invasive arthroscopic surgical techniques. Once in place, the device is inflated with saline to cushion and stabilize the joint.</p>



<p>After six to 12 months, the balloon dissolves. In the meantime, a physical therapist will help you retrain your muscles to move the shoulder using more optimal mechanics. Recovery tends to be faster since the tendons don't need to heal, as they would in traditional rotator cuff surgery. You can return to your daily activities with improved function, range of motion and less pain.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">3D printing for reverse shoulder replacement</h2>



<p><a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/shoulder-replacement/about/pac-20519121" target="_blank">Reverse shoulder replacement</a>&nbsp;is another surgical method for treating patients with severe arthritis, unrepairable rotator cuff tears or other damage. Basically, your surgeon changes the mechanics of the shoulder to allow other muscles to move it.</p>



<p>Since no shoulder is the same, how closely the replacement implant fits your shoulder's anatomy and how the implant is placed play key roles in the success of a reverse shoulder replacement. Your surgeon is able to choose from metal and plastic implants that are available in a few different shapes and a range of sizes. A 3D-printed model of your shoulder can help your orthopedic surgeon precisely place the implant.</p>



<p>The process begins with a CT scan before surgery to create a 3D model of your shoulder on a computer. This allows your surgeon to see how the implant should be placed, how to preserve as much bone as possible and how to identify the best way to secure the implant. A 3D guide is printed that duplicates the template from the computer.</p>



<p>During surgery, your surgeon places the 3D guide on the bone so the implant can be placed precisely as planned.</p>



<p>3D modeling also helps your surgeon determine if you need a customized implant.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Creating a customized 3D implant</h2>



<p>In most cases, your surgeon can choose a standard implant that will give you the shoulder function you need. But for some patients, their anatomy or bone damage won't allow a standard implant to fit appropriately. An implant that doesn't fit well can fail, leading to more surgery.</p>



<p>In these cases, an implant can be created to precisely fit a patient. Using a computer-generated 3D model, the custom implant designed for the patient is printed using the same materials as a standard implant. While this is only being used in special cases, it may become the standard in time.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Wider spectrum of customized treatments</h2>



<p>There are new options to provide a wide spectrum of treatments for patients with advanced shoulder issues. Having multiple options allows your orthopedic surgeon to choose the one that targets your specific issues to achieve the best outcome.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/scott-kuzma-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Scott Kuzma, M.D.</em></a><em>, is an&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/orthopedic-surgery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">orthopedic surgeon</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/sports-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">sports medicine</a>&nbsp;specialist in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/la-crosse" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">La&nbsp;Crosse</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/onalaska" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Onalaska</a>, Wisconsin.</em></p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/speaking-of-health/advanced-treatments-for-shoulder-pain" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advanced-treatments-target-advanced-shoulder-issues/">Advanced treatments target advanced shoulder issues</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/12/AchingShoulder1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/12/AchingShoulder16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Scott Kuzma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Shoulder Surgery]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss><!-- Static page delivered by HubScale -->