<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Orthopedics/Sports - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/orthopedics-sports/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/orthopedics-sports/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 14:49:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: What to know about aging and joint replacements</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-to-know-about-aging-and-joint-replacements/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 14:49:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Aging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Rafael Sierra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hip replacement]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joint Replacement]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[knee replacement]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376540</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>As people age, their joints change. Sometimes, this can lead to arthritis, causing pain in areas like the knees and hips.&#160;Dr. Rafael Sierra, a Mayo Clinic orthopedic surgeon, says&#160;arthritis and joint replacements are not inevitable. However, conditions like birth defects and structural issues can increase the risk of hip or knee problems that may result [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-to-know-about-aging-and-joint-replacements/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What to know about aging and joint replacements</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As people age, their joints change. Sometimes, this can lead to arthritis, causing pain in areas like the knees and hips.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/sierra-rafael-j-m-d/bio-20054877?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">Dr. Rafael Sierra</a>, a Mayo Clinic orthopedic surgeon, says&nbsp;arthritis and joint replacements are not inevitable. However, conditions like birth defects and structural issues can increase the risk of hip or knee problems that may result in the need for replacement.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/t7BJPq17UWs" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe id="videoidhttpsyoutubet7BJPq17UWs"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: What to know about aging and joint replacements" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/t7BJPq17UWs?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:59) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/SCRIPT-MCM-Age-and-Joint-Replacements.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Dr. Sierra wants to set the record straight about aging and joint replacements.</p>



<p>"The perception out there is that everybody's going to need a hip replacement down the road, whether it's knee or hip, everybody's going to need some form of replacement. That's not necessarily true," he says.</p>



<p>He says it's not aging but anatomy that will predispose people to knee or hip replacements down the road.</p>



<p>"This is a perfect example. This a patient that had a slip when they were very young. See, there's an abnormal shape to the femur. And this abnormal shape will cause damage of this affected bone into the socket that would lead to hip arthritis," says Dr. Sierra.</p>



<p>Joint replacements today are more successful than ever — thanks to precision robotic surgery.&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/07/robotic-knee-surgery-16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="robotic knee surgery" class="wp-image-168124" style="aspect-ratio:1.7777777777777777;width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/07/robotic-knee-surgery-16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/07/robotic-knee-surgery-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/07/robotic-knee-surgery-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/07/robotic-knee-surgery-16x9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">A Mayo Clinic orthopedic surgeon using robotics during knee surgery </figcaption></figure>



<p>"And today, with navigation systems, robotic systems, precision is what is now achievable in almost every patient," Dr. Sierra says.</p>



<p></p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related stories:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/10-11mayo-clinic-expert-offers-tips-on-how-to-keep-joints-healthy-as-you-age/">Mayo Clinic expert offers tips on how to keep joints healthy as you age</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-proper-posture-and-body-alignment/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Proper posture and body alignment</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-to-know-about-aging-and-joint-replacements/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What to know about aging and joint replacements</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/an-African-American-middle-aged-couple-holding-hands-and-walking-exercising-on-the-beach-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/an-African-American-middle-aged-couple-holding-hands-and-walking-exercising-on-the-beach-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Aging]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Rafael Sierra]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[hip replacement]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Joint Replacement]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[knee replacement]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Orthopedic expertise powers Tom Brown&#8217;s epic trek</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/orthopedic-expertise-powers-tom-browns-epic-trek/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Health System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Achilles Tendon]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Charles Nolte]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. James Mannion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tom Brown]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376127</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>When people retire, they often plan to spend more time with their grandkids, or on activities like volunteering, gardening, traveling and hobbies. Christine Brown came up with something far more epic. After thinking about what she and her husband, Tom, enjoyed doing together, she proposed that they spend the next five years hiking the 2,190 [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/orthopedic-expertise-powers-tom-browns-epic-trek/">Orthopedic expertise powers Tom Brown&#8217;s epic trek</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="660" height="370" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/tom-brown-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376130" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/tom-brown-16x9-1.jpg 660w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/tom-brown-16x9-1-300x168.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></figure>



<p>When people retire, they often plan to spend more time with their grandkids, or on activities like volunteering, gardening, traveling and hobbies. Christine Brown came up with something far more epic.</p>



<p>After thinking about what she and her husband, Tom, enjoyed doing together, she proposed that they spend the next five years hiking the 2,190 miles of the <a href="https://appalachiantrail.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Appalachian Trail</a> (AT). Stretching from Springer Mountain, Georgia, to Katahdin, Maine, it's the longest hiking-only trail in the world.</p>



<p>Tom's response was, "Absolutely!"</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Retirement challenge: Tackling the Appalachian Trail</h2>



<p>So in 2018, the La Crosse, Wisconsin, couple laced up their boots, hoisted their backpacks, grabbed their hiking sticks and headed north from the trail's southernmost point. Their five-year plan called for hiking the Appalachian Trail in 400- to 550-mile segments. That schedule meant 12 to 18 miles per day over rough terrain, up and down mountains through all kinds of weather, from sweltering heat to snow and sleet. According to the Browns, that breaks down to 30,000 to 40,000 steps a day.</p>



<p>"It's a physical challenge, but it's also a mental challenge," says Tom. "Some days, you see quite a few hikers; on other days, you're completely alone. Some days, the hiking is challenging, and some days you're walking down a small town's Main Street. You meet people of all backgrounds and ages on the AT. The hikers become a community and are always willing to help each other."</p>



<p>Even before the start of their epic trek, Tom, 63, had been experiencing pain in his right knee brought on by years of work at his excavating and snowplowing business. He'd undergone hyaluronate injections to relieve the pain and help the joint move more smoothly. Those treatments meant the pain wasn't enough to delay or trim back their plan.</p>



<p>Then came May 2022.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A slippery stone leads to surgery</h2>



<p>Christine, whose trail name is Beanbuster, and Tom, whose trail name is Traverse, were hiking the Appalachian Trail as it wove through the Green Mountains of Vermont. It was a drizzly day. They were climbing up a mountain, and the stones underfoot were slippery. A stone shifted, and Tom felt something stretch and pop: the Achilles tendon in his right leg.</p>



<p>The couple worked their way to a hotel, began icing the tendon and contacted&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/james-mannion-md" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">James Mannion, M.D.</a>, Tom's&nbsp;Family Medicine&nbsp;physician in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/la-crosse" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">La Crosse</a>, for advice on caring for the injury. The Browns decided to head home and a few days later, Tom's <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/achilles-tendon-rupture/symptoms-causes/syc-20353234" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Achilles tendon ruptured</a>. Repairing the tendon now took precedence over his aching, arthritic knee.</p>



<p>To address this critical injury, which turned out to be particularly complicated, Tom reached out to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/charles-nolte-do" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Charles Nolte, D.O.</a>, his long-time&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/services-and-treatments/orthopedic-surgery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">orthopedics specialist</a>, who practices at Mayo Clinic Health System in La Crosse and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/locations/onalaska" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Onalaska</a>, Wisconsin.</p>



<p>"This wasn't just an Achilles rupture," Dr. Nolte says. "Tom had a completely calcified tendon, probably due to an earlier injury. We had to perform a complex reconstruction of the tendon, which involved cutting out much of it, then reconnecting it."</p>



<p>Dr. Nolte says they weren't sure if the tendon would heal, much less heal well enough for Tom to return to the trail. Dr. Nolte told Tom it would be a slow recovery. But Tom tackled his rehabilitation and recovery with the same can-do spirit as he tackled the trail with Christine.</p>



<p>"At one point, there was no guarantee if the surgery would hold, if I'd have a drop foot or get my range of motion back," he says. "The physical therapists knew I wanted to be back on the AT by May 2023, so they set up a program that focused on strength, range of motion and stretching the tendon. They kept me on track and didn't let me get ahead of my healing."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Time to address chronic pain</h2>



<p>After six months of recovery from the Achilles rupture, it was time to start phase two of Tom's plan to get back to the trail: a total <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/knee-replacement/about/pac-20385276" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">replacement of his right knee</a>.</p>



<p>"Tom had dealt with his arthritic right knee for years and undergone nonoperative treatments to relieve the pain," says Dr. Nolte. "We planned to do a total knee replacement during his off-season from the trail, but then the Achilles rupture happened."</p>



<p>In February, Dr. Nolte performed a robotic-assisted total knee replacement of Tom's right knee.</p>



<p>"The robot takes a really good, successful procedure and makes it better," says Dr. Nolte. "The accuracy of cuts and component alignment are close to perfect, which reduces pain and speeds recovery."</p>



<p>Dr. Nolte adds that after completing about 300 robotic-assisted total knee replacements, he's seen a considerable difference in the postoperative recovery phase, with patients getting back more quickly to what they love to do.</p>



<p>Once again after surgery, Tom went into aggressive rehabilitation mode, following the plan of his&nbsp;physical therapists, and buying an exercise bike to continue building strength and range of motion at home. His goal was to be back on the Appalachian Trail by early May.</p>



<p>"I want to thank Dr. Nolte and my physical therapists,&nbsp;for all they did to help me reach my goals," Tom says. "They were amazing."</p>



<p>Dr. Nolte also credits Tom with doing the hard work to get better.</p>



<p>"Tom's a highly motivated patient. He did physical therapy before and after both surgeries, and followed his recovery plans," says Dr. Nolte. "Christine is a real go-getter, and he wanted to make sure he could keep up with her."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Postcards to the hometown care team</h2>



<p>On May 5, almost one year to the day since his Achilles injury and less than three months since his knee replacement, Tom and Christine were back hiking a grueling 400-mile segment of the Appalachian Trail, including summiting 6,288-foot-high Mount Washington in New Hampshire's White Mountains during a snow and sleet storm.</p>



<p>"We had two weeks of nice weather," says Christine, "followed by five-and-a-half weeks of rain."</p>



<p>Despite the weather and continual up-and-down mountain climbing, Christine noticed a difference in Tom.</p>



<p>"He had been in pain for a long time with that knee. Pain is insidious, and affects you physically and mentally," she says. "It was great having my cheerful, good-humored husband back."</p>



<p>Throughout their 2023 trek of the trail, Christine sent postcards to Dr. Nolte. He shared the cards with his team members, who took pride and satisfaction in Tom's accomplishments. While the scenes on the cards varied, the message was always the same: "Dear Dr. Frankenstein-Nolte. Your surgery was such a success that you've created a monster. My husband sees a mountain, wants to climb it and makes me go with him. I'm cold and tired. Make him stop. Christine."</p>



<p>Christine will get her wish in June 2024 when she and Tom reach Katahdin, Maine, and officially complete the last 170-mile segment of their epic trek. To mark making it to the trail's end, they're planning to fly family members to Bar Harbor, Maine, for a grand finale celebration of their great adventure on the Appalachian Trail.</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/hometown-health/patient-stories/orthopedic-expertise-powers-epic-trek" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/orthopedic-expertise-powers-tom-browns-epic-trek/">Orthopedic expertise powers Tom Brown&#8217;s epic trek</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/tom-brown1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/tom-brown-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Achilles Tendon]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Charles Nolte]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. James Mannion]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Tom Brown]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: 3 tips to avoid Halloween hand injuries</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-3-tips-to-avoid-halloween-hand-injuries/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 14:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sanj Kakar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[halloween]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hand injury]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=218012</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>There are plenty of frights to go around on Halloween, but a hand injury probably isn't one you'd expect. "Interestingly, it's the fourth busiest holiday for hand injuries," says Dr. Sanj Kakar, a Mayo Clinic orthopedic hand and wrist surgeon. Dr. Kakar says almost one-third of those Halloween hand injuries are among kids 10 to [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-3-tips-to-avoid-halloween-hand-injuries/">Mayo Clinic Minute: 3 tips to avoid Halloween hand injuries</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>There are plenty of frights to go around on Halloween, but a hand injury probably isn't one you'd expect.</p>



<p>"Interestingly, it's the fourth busiest holiday for hand injuries," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/kakar-sanjeev-sanj-m-d/bio-20055340?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Dr. Sanj Kakar</a>, a Mayo Clinic orthopedic hand and wrist surgeon.</p>



<p>Dr. Kakar says almost one-third of those Halloween hand injuries are among kids 10 to 14. And most of them happen when people are carving pumpkins.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/XlWXkwaRfa4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeXlWXkwaRfa4"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - 3 tips to avoid Halloween hand injuries" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/XlWXkwaRfa4?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:00) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post.<br>Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/MCM-3-tips-to-avoid-Halloween-hand-injuries-SCRIPT3.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"It's primarily stabbing injuries where the knife may slip, and, so, they can cut things like tendons, which are the ropes that help move your hands," Dr. Kakar says. "But they can also break bones, and also they can burn themselves, as well, with candles."</p>



<p>But Dr. Kakar says most of the injuries are avoidable.</p>



<p>"A lot of people might just go to the kitchen and grab a sharp knife. But there's good studies out there showing that actual pumpkin-specific carving knives [are safer], [because] actually the force needed to injure yourself, is higher if you use one of those than if you use a standard knife," he says. "So I would use a pumpkin carving kit, No. 1."</p>



<p>No. 2, Dr. Kakar says, is to let kids handle designing the jack-o'-lantern, but make sure adults do all of the carving.</p>



<p>And No. 3, make sure you're always supporting the pumpkin with your noncutting hand.</p>



<p>"So if you're right-handed, use your left hand to support the pumpkin and carve from the top down as opposed to the bottom up," Dr. Kakar says. "It's very easy for the knife to slip and go into your hand."</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-3-tips-to-avoid-halloween-hand-injuries/">Mayo Clinic Minute: 3 tips to avoid Halloween hand injuries</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/shutterstock_306948755_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/10/shutterstock_306948755_Fotor-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Sanj Kakar]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[halloween]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[hand injury]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Surgical options to treat brachial plexus injuries</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-surgical-options-to-treat-brachial-plexus-injuries/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 13:22:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[brachial plexus injury]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[brachial plexus surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Shelley Noland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nerve damage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Surgery]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=346363</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Severe damage to the brachial plexus­ — the group of nerves that control the movements of your hands, arms and wrists­­­ — can leave your entire hand and arm paralyzed. While sports injuries, cancer and radiation therapy are risk factors for damage to the brachial plexus, motorcycle accidents account for nearly 70% of injuries that may [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-surgical-options-to-treat-brachial-plexus-injuries/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Surgical options to treat brachial plexus injuries</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Severe damage to the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/brachial-plexus-injury/symptoms-causes/syc-20350235?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">brachial plexus</a>­ — the group of nerves that control the movements of your hands, arms and wrists­­­ — can leave your entire hand and arm paralyzed.<br><br>While sports injuries, cancer and radiation therapy are risk factors for damage to the brachial plexus, motorcycle accidents account for nearly 70% of injuries that may need surgical intervention.<br><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/noland-shelley-s-m-d/bio-20155635?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Shelley Noland</a>, a Mayo Clinic hand and peripheral nerve surgeon, has more on surgical options to treat brachial plexus injuries.<br><br><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/e6q1JC7dQ8I" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoide6q1JC7dQ8Iampfeature"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute -  Surgical options to treat brachial plexus injuries" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/e6q1JC7dQ8I?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:00) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post.&nbsp;Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network."&nbsp;Read the&nbsp;</strong><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/08/Script_MCM-Surgical-options-to-treat-brachial-plexus-injuries10.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>script</strong></a><strong>.<br></strong><br>As nerves exit the spinal cord and enter the arm, they form what is called the brachial plexus.<br><br>"This collection of nerves powers the entire arm and hand, so it provides all of the motor function to the arm and hand, and all the capabilities of the arm and hand are powered by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/brachial-plexus-injury/care-at-mayo-clinic/mac-20350243?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">brachial plexus</a>," says Dr. Noland.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/brachial-plexus-injury/care-at-mayo-clinic/mac-20350243"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/06/medical-illustration-of-brachial-plexus-16-x-9.jpg" alt="medical illustration of brachial plexus" class="wp-image-193110" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/06/medical-illustration-of-brachial-plexus-16-x-9.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/06/medical-illustration-of-brachial-plexus-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></a></figure></div>


<p><br>Damage to these nerves needs to be cared for in a timely manner to avoid problems. Dr. Noland says if too much time has passed, then the options become more limited for repair and reconstruction.<br></p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Treatment options</h3>



<p>The most common&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/brachial-plexus-injury/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20350241?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">surgical options</a>&nbsp;are nerve reconstruction, nerve repair, nerve grafting and nerve transfers.<br></p>



<p>"We treat brachial plexus injuries primarily through the use of what's called a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/brachial-plexus-injury/multimedia/nerve-transfer/img-20008552?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">nerve transfer</a>. And a nerve transfer can be thought of as rewiring the injured nerves with good nerves that are nearby and functioning, but also expendable," says Dr. Noland.<br><br>Postoperative rehabilitation or physical therapy are crucial to healing.<br><br>"That includes what I like to think of as rewiring the brain and training the brain for the new function. So essentially training one nerve to perform the function of another nerve," she says.</p>



<p><strong>Read more: </strong></p>



<ul>
<li>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/11-25-treatment-strikes-a-chord-with-patient-after-life-altering-accident/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Treatment strikes a chord with patient after life-altering accident</a>."</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-surgical-options-to-treat-brachial-plexus-injuries/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Surgical options to treat brachial plexus injuries</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/08/Brachial-Plexus-Surgery-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/08/Brachial-Plexus-Surgery-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[brachial plexus injury]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[brachial plexus surgery]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Shelley Noland]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[nerve damage]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Surgery]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Is your thumb pain de Quervain&#8217;s tenosynovitis?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-is-your-thumb-pain-de-quervains-tenosynovitis/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 13:37:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sanj Kakar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gamer thumb]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hand pain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mommy wrist]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedic Surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[orthopedics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[thumb pain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wrist pain]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=244806</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>De Quervain's tenosynovitis (pronounced da-KWUHR-vanes teena-sine-ah-VITE-us) is a complicated name for a condition that's been referred to&#160;as "mother's thumb," "mommy wrist" and "gamer's thumb" — all associated with repetitive use of the hands and wrist. It is a&#160;condition that causes extreme pain in the wrist and thumb area. While the exact cause is not known, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-is-your-thumb-pain-de-quervains-tenosynovitis/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Is your thumb pain de Quervain&#8217;s tenosynovitis?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/de-quervains-tenosynovitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20371332?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank">De Quervain's tenosynovitis</a>  (pronounced da-KWUHR-vanes teena-sine-ah-VITE-us) is a complicated name for a condition that's been referred to&nbsp;as "mother's thumb," "mommy wrist" and "gamer's thumb" — all associated with repetitive use of the hands and wrist. It is a&nbsp;condition that causes extreme pain in the wrist and thumb area. While the exact cause is not known, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/kakar-sanjeev-sanj-m-d/bio-20055340">Dr. Sanjeev Kakar</a>, a Mayo Clinic orthopedic surgeon, says that there are specific <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/de-quervains-tenosynovitis/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20371337">treatment options</a> that can help.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/o0KSfDuy3i0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeo0KSfDuy3i0"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Is your thumb pain de Quervain&#039;s tenosynovitis?" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/o0KSfDuy3i0?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (0:59) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post. Please "Courtesy: Mayo Clinic News Network." Read th</strong>e <strong><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/08/DeQuervains-MCM.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="script (opens in a new tab)">script</a>. </strong></p>



<p>When a simple hand movement, such as making a fist or moving the thumb, becomes <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/wrist-pain/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20366215">painful,</a> it could be from daily overuse.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"One of the most common is something called de Quervain's tenosynovitis," says Dr. Kakar.</p>



<p>He says it's primarily a tendon problem.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"If you think of the wrist, basically what we have here is that we have the tendons, which move your thumb. And they are covered by this band, and this is natural. We all have this, but in certain patients, they can have inflammation in this area," says Dr. Kakar.</p>



<p>When the tendons underneath this band become inflamed, they can cause intense pain.</p>



<p>"Now, luckily, the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/de-quervains-tenosynovitis/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20371337">treatment</a> for this is relatively straightforward."</p>



<p>Hand therapy and wearing a splint may help.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Sometimes we need to do a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/cortisone-shots/about/pac-20384794?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">corticosteroid injection</a> to decrease inflammation, and most of the times, it gets better. But sometimes we need to do surgery," says Dr. Kakar.</p>



<p>It's an outpatient procedure that involves opening the sheath surrounding the tendon to release pressure, and allow the tendons to glide more freely and pain-free.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Related posts:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-avoiding-overuse-wrist-injuries/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Avoiding overuse wrist injuries</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-relief-for-achy-wrists/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Relief for achy wrists</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-tennis-is-great-for-the-heart-and-mind-but-rough-on-the-wrist/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Why tennis is great for the heart and mind but rough on the wrist</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-is-your-thumb-pain-de-quervains-tenosynovitis/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Is your thumb pain de Quervain&#8217;s tenosynovitis?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/02/shutterstock_1120519535_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/02/shutterstock_1120519535_Fotor-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Sanj Kakar]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[gamer thumb]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[hand pain]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[mommy wrist]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Orthopedic Surgery]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[orthopedics]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[thumb pain]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[wrist pain]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic orthopedic surgeon named AOA pillar of profession</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-orthopedic-surgeon-named-aoa-pillar-of-profession/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rhoda Madson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 13:13:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Bernard Morrey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374883</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Bernard Morrey, M.D., professor, emeritus chair of the Department of Orthopedic Surgery at Mayo Clinic and former member of the Mayo Clinic Board of Governors, was recently named a 2023 "Pillar of the Orthopaedic Profession" by the American Orthopaedic Association (AOA). Dr. Morrey is recognized for his leadership, mentoring and lifelong contributions [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-orthopedic-surgeon-named-aoa-pillar-of-profession/">Mayo Clinic orthopedic surgeon named AOA pillar of profession</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Bernard Morrey, M.D., professor, emeritus chair of the Department of Orthopedic Surgery at Mayo Clinic and former member of the Mayo Clinic Board of Governors, was recently named a 2023 "Pillar of the Orthopaedic Profession" by the American Orthopaedic Association (AOA).</p>



<p>Dr. Morrey is recognized for his leadership, mentoring and lifelong contributions to the orthopedic&nbsp;community. He practiced at Mayo Clinic from 1978 to 2009, specializing in elbow, hip and knee surgery.</p>



<p>"[At Mayo] we became interested in an 'unknown joint,' which was the elbow, and that kind of set me in my career academically, along with hip and knee surgery," Dr. Morrey says in AOA's tribute video. "The career is reflected in the opportunity to help individuals from all walks of life regain their function, which is what orthopedics is all about."</p>



<p>Dr. Morrey attended medical school at the University of Texas Medical Branch and completed his residency at Mayo Clinic. He was named a distinguished alumnus of Mayo Clinic and emeritus John and Posy Krehbiel Professor of Orthopaedic Surgery at Mayo. He holds nine patents and has authored 15 major textbooks under four different titles, translated into six languages. He has written over 450 peer-reviewed publications.</p>



<p>Dr. Morrey is the third orthopedic surgeon from Mayo Clinic to receive this national pillar of profession recognition. The others are the late Mark Coventry, M.D., and the late Patrick Kelly, M.D.</p>



<p>More information about Dr. Morrey's recognition is available in the AOA <a href="https://www.aoassn.org/aoa-pillars-of-the-orthopaedic-profession/">news release</a>.</p>



<p>##</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Rhoda Madson, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p><a id="_msocom_1"></a></p>



<p> </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-orthopedic-surgeon-named-aoa-pillar-of-profession/">Mayo Clinic orthopedic surgeon named AOA pillar of profession</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Morrey-Bernard-MD-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Morrey-Bernard-MD-16x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Bernard Morrey]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic expert: Joint replacement surgery, arthritis are not inevitable</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-expert-joint-replacement-surgery-arthritis-are-not-inevitable/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rhoda Madson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2023 12:25:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374006</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Don't worry about your hips or knees as you age. Arthritis in those joints isn't inevitable. Keep doing the activities you enjoy. Those hopeful words come from Rafael Sierra, M.D., an orthopedic surgeon at Mayo Clinic specializing in hip and knee reconstruction. Dr. Sierra says there is no need to curtail your [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-expert-joint-replacement-surgery-arthritis-are-not-inevitable/">Mayo Clinic expert: Joint replacement surgery, arthritis are not inevitable</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/Senior-couple-walking-along-suburban-street-shutterstock_795091624_16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Senior couple walking along suburban street holding hands" class="wp-image-244193" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/Senior-couple-walking-along-suburban-street-shutterstock_795091624_16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/Senior-couple-walking-along-suburban-street-shutterstock_795091624_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/Senior-couple-walking-along-suburban-street-shutterstock_795091624_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Don't worry about your hips or knees as you age. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/arthritis/symptoms-causes/syc-20350772?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Arthritis</a> in those joints isn't inevitable. Keep doing the activities you enjoy. Those hopeful words come from <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/sierra-rafael-j-m-d/bio-20054877?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Rafael Sierra, M.D.</a>, an orthopedic surgeon at Mayo Clinic specializing in hip and knee reconstruction. Dr. Sierra says there is no need to curtail your activities out of fear that you'll wear out those joints as you age and need joint replacement.</p>



<p>However, certain conditions, such as birth defects and anatomical issues, may predispose a person to have hip or knee problems. Untreated, hip dysplasia and hip impingement are leading causes of hip replacement in people under 50. Having bowlegs, knock knees — or other structural issues­ — can hasten the need for knee replacement.</p>



<p>"But it's not like the rest of us have to be worried and say, 'OK, at age 50, maybe I should have my hips or knees examined by a doctor,'" Dr. Sierra says. "In general, your body — your musculoskeletal system — will let you know when you have issues."</p>



<p>There are no preventive screenings for hips or knees, so pain is a major tip-off that trouble may be brewing. Some people don't even realize they have hip or knee issues until they experience pain doing new activities or movements.</p>



<p>Over the years, innovations in hip and knee implants and surgical techniques have made the operations even more technically precise, Dr. Sierra says. New plastics used in hip and knee replacements are extremely durable.</p>



<p>Changes in anesthesia and pain control techniques have improved the care given to patients before, during and after surgery. More people are having outpatient hip and knee replacement surgery. If you do get a knee or hip replacement, your doctor will likely recommend being conservative with your activities.</p>



<p>Looking ahead, Dr. Sierra says avascular necrosis, or the death of bone tissue, remains one of the unsolved issues in hip surgery, with much research still ahead. Also, research continues into abductor tears or tears of the muscles around the hip. Women are especially prone to this condition.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact: </strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Rhoda Madson, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-expert-joint-replacement-surgery-arthritis-are-not-inevitable/">Mayo Clinic expert: Joint replacement surgery, arthritis are not inevitable</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/Senior-couple-walking-along-suburban-street-shutterstock_795091624_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/07/Senior-couple-walking-along-suburban-street-shutterstock_795091624_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: How young athletes can reduce their risk of injury</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-young-athletes-can-reduce-their-risk-of-injury/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Osiadacz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[back to school]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[children]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Wesley Troyer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kids sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sports injuries]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=344321</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>More than half of children in the U.S. ages 6 to 17 participate in sports. With participation also comes the painful reality of injuries that happen during gameplay. Dr. Wes Troyer, a Mayo Clinic physical medicine and rehabilitation physician, explains how to reduce children's risk of sports injuries. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute Journalists: Broadcast-quality [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-young-athletes-can-reduce-their-risk-of-injury/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How young athletes can reduce their risk of injury</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>More than <a href="https://health.gov/sites/default/files/2019-10/National_Youth_Sports_Strategy.pdf">half</a> of children in the U.S. ages 6 to 17 participate in sports. With participation also comes the painful reality of injuries that happen during gameplay.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/troyer-wesley-wes-d-d-o/bio-20509040?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Wes Troyer</a>, a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/physical-medicine-rehabilitation-mayo-clinic/sections/overview/ovc-20467039?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">physical medicine and rehabilitation</a> physician, explains how to reduce children's risk of sports injuries.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=idMbUDc6ozQ" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoididMbUDc6ozQ"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - How young athletes can reduce their risk of injury" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/idMbUDc6ozQ?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (0:57) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post.&nbsp;Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network."&nbsp;Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/08/Mayo-Clinic-Minute_How-young-athletes-can-reduce-their-risk-of-injury.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>From strikes and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/muscle-strains/symptoms-causes/syc-20450507?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">strains</a> to footwork and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/stress-fractures/symptoms-causes/syc-20354057?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">fractures</a>, injuries can happen to any young athlete.</p>



<p>Reducing the risk of injury starts with an annual physical to make sure children can participate. When it's time to play, warm up muscles by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/fitness/basics/stretching-and-flexibility/hlv-20049447?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stretching</a>, and use protective equipment, when appropriate.</p>



<p>"It's important to try out your equipment before you get into game-time situations to make sure it works properly, so that it's actually protecting you when you're going out there to perform the sport," says Dr. Troyer.</p>



<p>Try to avoid <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/fitness/in-depth/overuse-injury/art-20045875?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">overusing</a> certain muscles over others. Repeated motions can happen around <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/growth-plate-fractures/symptoms-causes/syc-20351979?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">growth plates</a> and may require young athletes to pause certain activities.</p>



<p>"They need time to rest because they've put too much stress on the area. And without that, they just don't heal," says Dr. Troyer.</p>



<p>If children are injured playing a sport, keep them out of competition until they can be evaluated.</p>



<p>"The worst thing that you can do is get up and try to play through these things and make the injury worse," says Dr. Troyer.</p>



<p><strong>Related articles:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-are-the-health-benefits-when-kids-play-sports/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">"Mayo Clinic Minute: Health benefits of kids and sports</a>."</li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-kids-shouldnt-specialize-in-one-sport/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">"Mayo Clinic Minute: Why kids shouldn't specialize in one sport</a>."</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-young-athletes-can-reduce-their-risk-of-injury/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How young athletes can reduce their risk of injury</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/08/1x1_Boy-throwing-baseball.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/08/16x9_Boy-throwing-baseball.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[back to school]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[children]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Wesley Troyer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[kids sports]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[sports injuries]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: A parent&#8217;s playbook for sports screenings</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-a-parents-playbook-for-sports-screenings/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2023 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Anastasi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sports screenings]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=372982</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Summer is winding down, and soon kids will be heading onto the field to play their favorite fall sports. But before they can check into the game, they have to head into the doctor's office for sports screenings. It's generally required that young athletes get a preparticipation exam before participating in organized activities.&#160;The exams aren't [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-a-parents-playbook-for-sports-screenings/">Mayo Clinic Minute: A parent&#8217;s playbook for sports screenings</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Summer is winding down, and soon kids will be heading onto the field to play their favorite fall sports. But before they can check into the game, they have to head into the doctor's office for sports screenings.</p>



<p>It's generally required that young athletes get a preparticipation exam before participating in organized activities.&nbsp;The exams aren't just a formality. It's to ensure your child's safety and check to see if they are physically able to play.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/anastasi-matthew-b-m-d/bio-20448240">Dr. Matthew Anastasi</a>, a Mayo Clinic <a href="https://sportsmedicine.mayoclinic.org/">sports medicine</a> physician, explains what parents should look for when it comes to sports exams.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/40iNCw5LQDk" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutube40iNCw5LQDk"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute  - A parent&#039;s playbook for sports screenings" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/40iNCw5LQDk?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:07) is in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the</strong> <strong><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/MCM-Sports-Physical_.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1000" height="562" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/09/shutterstock_79346773_Fotor-16x9.jpg" alt="young boys with pads and helmets playing football with a referee on the field" class="wp-image-215188" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/09/shutterstock_79346773_Fotor-16x9.jpg 1000w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/09/shutterstock_79346773_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/09/shutterstock_79346773_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" /></figure>



<p>"It's very important to identify any potential risk that they may be exposed to before their participation in the respective sport," says Dr. Anastasi.</p>



<p>A typical sports screening includes assessing vision, heart and lungs. Sports medicine specialists also will look at the joints.</p>



<p>"Really focusing on all the joints, ranging from neck, shoulders, elbows, and then moving down to lower extremity hips, knees, ankles," says Dr. Anastasi.</p>



<p>A thorough exam also includes going over medical and family history. This will help identify underlying conditions that might put a child at risk during physical activity.</p>



<p>Dr. Anastasi says sports screenings are not substitutes for health maintenance exams. He also recommends young athletes get a yearly sports physical. </p>



<p>"It's a great opportunity to really identify if something is normal or abnormal, and also to help that athlete succeed at the highest level of his or her ability," says Dr. Anastasi.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p><a id="_msocom_1"></a></p>



<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-a-parents-playbook-for-sports-screenings/">Mayo Clinic Minute: A parent&#8217;s playbook for sports screenings</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/02/a-diverse-high-school-girls-basketball-team-playing-on-a-court-in-uniforms-and-wearing-face-masks-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/11/male-high-school-basketball-players-playing-game_shutterstock_199288139_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Anastasi]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[sports screenings]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Health benefits of kids and sports</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-are-the-health-benefits-when-kids-play-sports/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Children's Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Athletics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[children]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kids]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pediatrics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sports Medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=245863</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Some children are back in the classroom, and others are getting ready. An important tool for keeping kids healthy is participation in youth sports, and it's not just because of physical activity. Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:58) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-are-the-health-benefits-when-kids-play-sports/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Health benefits of kids and sports</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Some children are back in the classroom, and others are getting ready. An important tool for keeping kids healthy is participation in youth sports, and it's not just because of physical activity.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/4dzpba9GP0w" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutube4dzpba9GP0w"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: What are the health benefits when kids play sports?" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4dzpba9GP0w?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (0:58) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a aria-label="script (opens in a new tab)" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/08/MCM-EDITS-sports-benefits.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong>  </p>



<p>There are the obvious physical benefits when kids play sports. It improves cardiovascular health and prevents obesity. But that's not all.</p>



<p>"There can be social benefits where you make friends. You have an opportunity to connect with other people," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/soma-david-b-m-d/bio-20135572?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">Dr. David Soma</a>, a Mayo Clinic pediatric sports medicine specialist.</p>



<p>He says there also are emotional benefits.</p>



<p>"So you learn ... that teamwork piece or that perseverance — learning how to win, learning how to lose."</p>



<p>He says a way to get your kids involved in sports is to start young by just getting them active and outdoors.</p>



<p>"We live in a society where people want to stay inside and stare at screens," says Dr. Soma. "But get outside. Go for a bike ride as a family. Go for a run. Kick the ball around the yard. Just get them moving and seeing what they like to do."</p>



<p>And don't focus on just one individual sport, especially at a younger age.</p>



<p>"There's really good evidence that you should not do that," says Dr. Soma. "It's best to have a kid in the elementary school-aged years really do multiple sports. Expose them to as many different things that they're interested in as possible."</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-are-the-health-benefits-when-kids-play-sports/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Health benefits of kids and sports</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/08/two-little-boys-on-a-sports-field-wearing-baseball-caps-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/08/two-little-boys-on-a-sports-field-wearing-baseball-caps-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Athletics]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[children]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Children's Center]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Jason Howland]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[kids]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Pediatrics]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[sports]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Sports Medicine]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>