<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Research - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 13:32:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: How environmental exposures affect your health</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-how-environmental-exposures-affect-your-health/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Abby Smith]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q &amp; A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Konstantinos Lazaridis]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=397508</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&amp;#160;I'm hearing more about the exposome and the role of the environment on our health. Can you tell me more about how it is being studied? I'm worried about the future when I read about studies that show microplastics and chemicals accumulating in our environment.&amp;#160; ANSWER:&amp;#160;The&amp;#160;Centers for Disease Control and Prevention&amp;#160;defines the exposome [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-how-environmental-exposures-affect-your-health/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: How environmental exposures affect your health</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/young-woman-walking-in-a-park_GettyImages-1447434304_16x9.jpg" alt="young woman walking in a park" class="wp-image-365395" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/young-woman-walking-in-a-park_GettyImages-1447434304_16x9.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/young-woman-walking-in-a-park_GettyImages-1447434304_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/young-woman-walking-in-a-park_GettyImages-1447434304_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure></div>


<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong>&amp;nbsp;I'm hearing more about the exposome and the role of the environment on our health. Can you tell me more about how it is being studied? I'm worried about the future when I read about studies that show microplastics and chemicals accumulating in our environment.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong>&amp;nbsp;The&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://blogs.cdc.gov/genomics/2022/09/06/from-the-genome-to-the-exposome/">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</a>&amp;nbsp;defines the exposome as the measure of all environmental exposures, from prenatal stages through a person's lifetime, and how those exposures interact with genetic factors to affect health. The term is very inclusive. It includes, for example, diet; pollution; and natural substances, such as radiation. Everyone's exposome is unique.</p>



<p>I appreciate your concern about <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/exploring-the-exposome/">environmental exposures.</a> The point I like to make is that not all exposures are harmful. Some exposures may protect us from disease. When we're talking about the exposome, it includes elements that are a risk for health, such as tobacco use, and elements protecting us from illness, such as access to green space.</p>



<p>Historically, researchers have studied some environmental exposures. Epidemiological studies in the past have told us that excessive alcohol use, for example, has an effect on the human body, and this relates to disease. We have also known that exposures to some bacteria cause disease, such as salmonella or tuberculosis.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Exposome-16-x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Graphic: The exposome is the measure of a person's lifetime of environmental expsures and impact on health.
" class="wp-image-386729" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Exposome-16-x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Exposome-16-x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Exposome-16-x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Exposome-16-x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Exposome-16-x9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>But given that there are millions of different types of environmental exposures, better and more systematic studies are needed to understand what this means to our health.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>As a scientific field, the exposome explores exposures that have an effect on humans biology. For me, as a physician and researcher, I would like to know more about exposures that affect our genes, cells and organs, or, in other words, how exposures affect human biology. Your exposome is the environmental complement to your complete set of DNA, called your genome.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Scientists have more recently realized that only about 15% of most disease risk can be attributed to genetic elements. So we are left with the question: What else contributes to disease? Families, of course, share not only genes but their environment. They live in the same household. And this is how exposome science started, to try to be able to assess environmental exposures.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Over the last roughly 50 years, chemicals have been mass produced by humans. Decades ago, we couldn't measure chemicals in our bloodstream in a scalable and affordable way. So we used questionnaires to ask, "Do you smoke?" "Do you drink?" "Have you been exposed to pesticides?" We were looking for the outcomes of those exposures to human health.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>For example, in my laboratory, we were studying a rare liver disease called&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/primary-sclerosing-cholangitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20355797">primary sclerosing cholangitis</a>, and we asked a decade ago whether patients were exposed to pesticides, as well as other environmental elements. But the questionnaires didn't show a difference between healthy people and those with primary sclerosing cholangitis.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Years later, when we could use blood tests to measure chemicals in the bloodstream, we found a significant difference in a specific pesticide present among primary sclerosing cholangitis patients compared with healthy people.</p>



<p>So, based on several studies, we now know that pesticides are in our food chain and in our bloodstream in small amounts, and we need to know how they affect human biology and disease.</p>



<p>Also, massive plastic production within the last 70 years also has created microparticles that can be found inside people's tissues. We need to study these exposures both in health and in diseases such as cancer, heart disease, stroke, respiratory illness and autoimmune disease.</p>



<p>Nevertheless, when we do studies, often we find chemicals that are more prevalent in healthy people compared to patients with diseases. Scientists are working to identify those elements associated with wellness or with a lack of disease because these substances may protect us from illness. For example, some studies have shown that drinking coffee may reduce risk of neurological disease or liver disease. We need to understand this in more depth for therapeutic opportunities.</p>



<p>Current methodologies enable us to measure the exposome better than before through blood, urine, saliva and hair. I envision that 10 years from now, if not earlier, we will have screens of exposures that we will measure in our bloodstream. That will become part of a person's care at some point in the future and help us guide lifestyle changes, prevention strategies and make diagnosis as well as treatment decisions for patients. —&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/lazaridis-konstantinos-n-m-d/bio-20054459"><strong><em>Konstantinos Lazaridis, M.D.</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Gastroenterology/Hepatology and Center for Individualized Medicine</em></strong></p>



<p><strong>Learn more about the exposome:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-how-a-lifetime-of-exposures-impact-health-exposome-explained/">Tomorrow’s Cure: How a lifetime of exposures impact health – exposome explained</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/exploring-the-exposome/">Researchers link environmental exposures to liver disease</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-how-environmental-exposures-affect-your-health/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: How environmental exposures affect your health</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/10/a-pair-of-hands-holding-a-bright-blue-and-green-globe-world-earth-with-black-universe-in-background-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/10/a-pair-of-hands-holding-a-bright-blue-and-green-globe-world-earth-with-black-universe-in-background-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Konstantinos Lazaridis]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Skin disease patients show response to targeted treatment</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/skin-disease-patients-show-response-to-targeted-treatment/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Colette Gallagher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 17:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Discovery Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Aaron Mangold]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=398974</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have identified a targeted therapy that could bring relief to people living with lichen planus, a chronic inflammatory skin condition of the skin, hair, nails, mouth and genitals. They described their findings in a study recently published in the Journal of Clinical Investigation that described their first-in-human, phase 2 clinical trial. The [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/skin-disease-patients-show-response-to-targeted-treatment/">Skin disease patients show response to targeted treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/lichen-planus-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Photo of ankle and leg with skin disease, lichen planus" class="wp-image-399020" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/lichen-planus-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/lichen-planus-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/lichen-planus-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/lichen-planus-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/lichen-planus-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have identified a targeted therapy that could bring relief to people living with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lichen-planus/symptoms-causes/syc-20351378" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lichen planus</a>, a chronic inflammatory skin condition of the skin, hair, nails, mouth and genitals.</p>



<p>They described their findings in a study recently published in the <a href="https://www.jci.org/articles/view/179436" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Journal of Clinical Investigation</a> that described their first-in-human, phase 2 clinical trial.</p>



<p>The researchers identified unique molecular and cellular changes in the skin with lichen planus, particularly an overactive immune response involving specific types of T cells, a crucial immune system component.</p>



<p>The researchers then used baricitinib, a medication that selectively blocks the specific inflammatory pathways of lichen planus, to treat patients in the study.</p>



<p>Cytokines are small proteins that are crucial in controlling the growth and activity of other immune system cells and blood cells. They include interferon-gamma, a critical signal in normal antiviral responses and aberrant in lichen planus, which leads to immune cells attacking normal cells.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="819" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Skin-disease-1024x819.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-398975" style="width:451px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Skin-disease-1024x819.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Skin-disease-300x240.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Skin-disease-768x614.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Skin-disease-1536x1228.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Skin-disease-2048x1637.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p>Janus kinase (JAK) enzymes play a crucial role in the body's inflammatory response. Baricitinib is an oral JAK 1/2 inhibitor that interrupts the signaling pathway of interferon-gamma by blocking these enzymes. This helps reduce inflammation and suppress the overactive immune response that contributes to these conditions.</p>



<p>The patients with treatment-refractory disease experienced early and sustained clinical response to the treatment, resulting in an 83% improvement in symptom responsiveness within 16 weeks of treatment, a marked improvement over baseline. The therapy also rapidly reduced interferon activity, a key signaling molecule in the disease, as well as reduced the specific, pathogenic T-cells.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="853" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Mangold-Aaron-R._15518477_202101281105-1-853x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-398980" style="width:202px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Mangold-Aaron-R._15518477_202101281105-1-853x1024.jpg 853w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Mangold-Aaron-R._15518477_202101281105-1-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Mangold-Aaron-R._15518477_202101281105-1-768x922.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Mangold-Aaron-R._15518477_202101281105-1.jpg 1250w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 853px) 100vw, 853px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Aaron Mangold, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"This research is an important step in connecting the dots in understanding — and treating —autoimmune and inflammatory diseases," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/mangold-aaron-r-m-d/bio-20537781" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Aaron R. Mangold, M.D.</a>, senior author of the study. "These findings provide a potential new, effective, disease-specific treatment option for lichen planus and therapeutic targets for other inflammatory diseases."</p>



<p>Lichen planus affects 1 to 2% of the general population, altering the quality of life for patients due to intense itching or pain. On the skin, lichen planus often appears as purple, itchy, flat bumps that develop over several weeks. In the mouth and genital mucosa, lichen planus forms lacy white patches, sometimes with painful sores.</p>



<p>Treatment of lichen planus is challenging, and therapeutic options have remained stagnant. To date, researchers have not developed any disease-specific medications for lichen planus. While there is no cure, various treatments can help manage symptoms. However, these treatments can come with common side effects including skin thinning, weakened immune system and increased risk of infection. There is also a need for options for those who don’t respond to treatment. Specific subtypes, such as hypertrophic and mucosal lichen planus, are chronic and may not respond to treatment.</p>



<p>This research provides valuable insights into the pathophysiology of lichen planus and demonstrates the potential of baricitinib as a promising treatment option, says Dr. Mangold, a Mayo Clinic consultant in the Department of Dermatology who studies rare inflammatory conditions and new therapeutics, and conducted an earlier phase 2 Mayo Clinic-led clinical trial to target these cells.</p>



<p>Review the <a href="//www.jci.org/articles/view/179436" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p><strong>Dr. Mangold's other research on lichen planus</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Faccessmedicine.mhmedical.com%2Fcontent.aspx%3Fbookid%3D2570%26sectionid%3D210422573&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7CGallagher.Colette%40mayo.edu%7C9e2b1a825c7a4a133d4d08dd357392a9%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C638725492673915245%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=gLF70RkpBGeau85tJNBRu4d014HxmbjHEEugKQAuyeE%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lichen Planus | Fitzpatrick's Dermatology</a></li>



<li><a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.incytemi.com%2Fdocument%2FPoster%2FEADV%25202024_Mangold_Phase%25202%2520Rux%2520Cream%2520in%2520Cutaneous%2520LP%2520Study.pdf&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7CGallagher.Colette%40mayo.edu%7C9e2b1a825c7a4a133d4d08dd357392a9%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C638725492674098148%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=Flb3bu0qNX9nDA4Pj%2FeTwTDD%2B0FYJVLkFJXpzIvQGe8%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">EADV 2024_Mangold_Phase 2 Rux Cream in Cutaneous </a></li>



<li><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35131254/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ruxolitinib Cream in the Treatment of Cutaneous Lichen Planus</a></li>



<li><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36715723/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Development of the lichen planus quality of life questionnaire</a></li>



<li><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36529946/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Availability of a validated cutaneous lichen planus disease index</a></li>



<li><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24588858/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Good syndrome and lichen planus: case and review</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/skin-disease-patients-show-response-to-targeted-treatment/">Skin disease patients show response to targeted treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/lichen-planus-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/lichen-planus-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Aaron Mangold]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic accelerates personalized medicine through foundation models with Microsoft Research and Cerebras Systems</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-accelerates-personalized-medicine-through-foundation-models-with-microsoft-research-and-cerebras-systems/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Terri Malloy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 17:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AI and Digital Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individualized Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[artificial intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cerebras]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chest X-ray]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Callstrom]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[foundation model]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gen AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[generative AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[genomic foundation model]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genomics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[human gemone]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Platform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Microsoft Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[personalized medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[radiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rheumatoid Arthritis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rochester news releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=398951</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic today unveiled separate groundbreaking collaborations with Microsoft Research and with Cerebras Systems in the field of generative artificial intelligence (AI), designed to personalize patient care, significantly accelerate diagnostic time and improve accuracy. Announced during the 43rd Annual J.P. Morgan Healthcare Conference, the projects focus on developing and testing foundation models [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-accelerates-personalized-medicine-through-foundation-models-with-microsoft-research-and-cerebras-systems/">Mayo Clinic accelerates personalized medicine through foundation models with Microsoft Research and Cerebras Systems</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="602" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Deoxyribonucleic-acid-DNA-profile-graphics-are-reflected-from-a-computer-screen-into-a-persons-eyeglasses-in-a-dark-room_GettyImages-1150968776.jpg" alt="Deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) profile graphics are reflected from a computer screen into a person's eyeglasses, in a dark room" class="wp-image-398961" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Deoxyribonucleic-acid-DNA-profile-graphics-are-reflected-from-a-computer-screen-into-a-persons-eyeglasses-in-a-dark-room_GettyImages-1150968776.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Deoxyribonucleic-acid-DNA-profile-graphics-are-reflected-from-a-computer-screen-into-a-persons-eyeglasses-in-a-dark-room_GettyImages-1150968776-300x226.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Deoxyribonucleic-acid-DNA-profile-graphics-are-reflected-from-a-computer-screen-into-a-persons-eyeglasses-in-a-dark-room_GettyImages-1150968776-768x578.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> today unveiled separate groundbreaking collaborations with <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/?msockid=27380b1436646fc81ab6184f374f6e7d" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Research</a> and with <a href="https://cerebras.ai/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cerebras Systems</a> in the field of generative artificial intelligence (AI), designed to personalize patient care, significantly accelerate diagnostic time and improve accuracy.</p>



<p>Announced during the 43<sup>rd</sup> Annual J.P. Morgan Healthcare Conference, the projects focus on developing and testing foundation models customized for various applications, leveraging the power of multimodal radiology images and data (including CT scans and MRIs) with Microsoft Research and genomic sequencing data with Cerebras. The innovations have the potential to transform how clinicians approach diagnosis and treatment, ultimately leading to better patient outcomes.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Foundation AI models are large, pre-trained models capable of adapting to and carrying out many tasks with minimal extra training. They learn from massive datasets, acquiring general knowledge that can be used across diverse applications. This adaptability makes them efficient and versatile building blocks for numerous AI systems.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Mayo Clinic and Microsoft Research advance AI for chest X-rays</h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic and Microsoft Research are collaboratively developing foundation models that integrate text and images. For this use case, Mayo and Microsoft Research are working together to explore the use of generative AI in radiology using Microsoft Research’s AI technology and Mayo Clinic’s X-ray data.</p>



<p>"Multimodal foundation models hold immense promise in tackling significant roadblocks across the radiology ecosystem. The innovations we’re creating with Microsoft Research will help unlock valuable insights for the future of medical imaging to improve how radiologists work and how patients are cared for," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/callstrom-matthew-r-m-d-ph-d/bio-00085927" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Matthew Callstrom, M.D. Ph.D.</a>, chair of Mayo Clinic Radiology in the Midwest and medical director for Generative AI and Strategy. "Focusing on chest X-ray reports, Mayo's clinical teams and Microsoft researchers will collaborate to advance the state-of-the-art in multimodal AI radiology, helping bring innovation to real-world application faster and at scale, which is key to making exemplary healthcare more accessible."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Empowering clinicians with instant access to the information they need is at the heart of this research project. Mayo Clinic aims to develop a model that can automatically generate reports, evaluate tube and line placement in chest X-rays, and detect changes from prior images. This proof-of-concept model seeks to improve clinician workflow and patient care by providing a more efficient and comprehensive analysis of radiographic images.</p>



<p>"This collaboration is a crucial step towards our mutual goal of developing generative AI that improves patient outcomes and the clinician experience," says Jonathan Carlson, Ph.D., managing director, Health Futures at Microsoft Research. "The fusion of Microsoft's <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s42256-024-00965-w">recognized research innovations</a> in biomedical AI and Mayo Clinic's radiology excellence will empower clinicians with the tools they need to deliver more precise and accessible care and <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/industry/blog/healthcare/2024/10/10/unlocking-next-generation-ai-capabilities-with-healthcare-ai-models/">furthers Microsoft’s commitment</a> to bringing the power of emerging AI to clinical researchers worldwide."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Mayo Clinic and Cerebras create a world-leading genomic foundation model</h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic and Cerebras have created a genomic foundation model that combines publicly available human reference genome data that represents an ideal version of the human genome, with Mayo's comprehensive patient exome data and the power of its <a href="https://www.mayoclinicplatform.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Platform</a>. Exome data focuses on the protein-coding region of the genome where several disease-causing mutations take place. Cerebras's high-powered computing and generative AI capabilities make it possible to train and develop the model at scale, positioning it to be further refined for more specific uses.</p>



<p>"The genomic foundation model represents a significant advancement in personalized medicine," says Dr. Callstrom. "Its ability to analyze genomic data and compare them in almost real-time with patients with similar traits allows for more precise prediction of disease and treatment response, leading to faster diagnoses and the selection of targeted therapies for patients."</p>



<p>For example, rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is a debilitating autoimmune disease, and the standard treatment approach often requires trials of different therapies to achieve disease remission. It can take several months to know if a therapy is working. A new genomic model developed by Mayo Clinic and Cerebras offers a potential solution to shorten the time to identify effective treatment and avoid long-term morbidity associated with the untreated disease. Early findings demonstrate high performance against benchmarks and show early promise in identifying patient response to therapy. As more patient data is added, the model's predictive power is expected to increase, leading to faster, more effective personalized treatment for RA patients. &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"Mayo’s genomic foundation model sets a new bar for genomic models, excelling not only in standard tasks like predicting functional and regulatory properties of DNA but also enabling discoveries of complex correlations between genetic variants and medical conditions," says Natalia Vassilieva, Field CTO at Cerebras Systems. "Unlike current approaches focused on single-variant associations, this model enables the discovery of connections where collections of variants contribute to a particular condition."</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> <br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-accelerates-personalized-medicine-through-foundation-models-with-microsoft-research-and-cerebras-systems/">Mayo Clinic accelerates personalized medicine through foundation models with Microsoft Research and Cerebras Systems</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Deoxyribonucleic-acid-DNA-profile-graphics-are-reflected-from-a-computer-screen-into-a-persons-eyeglasses-in-a-dark-room_GettyImages-1150968776_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Deoxyribonucleic-acid-DNA-profile-graphics-are-reflected-from-a-computer-screen-into-a-persons-eyeglasses-in-a-dark-room_GettyImages-1150968776_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[AI]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[artificial intelligence]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cerebras]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[chest X-ray]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Callstrom]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[foundation model]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[gen AI]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[generative AI]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[genomic foundation model]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Genomics]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[human gemone]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Platform]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Microsoft Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[personalized medicine]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[radiology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Rheumatoid Arthritis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Rochester news releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>8 common health conditions midlife women face</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-race-ethnicity-and-neighborhood-may-affect-midlife-womens-health/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Colette Gallagher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health &amp; Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Healthcare Delivery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jennifer St. Sauver]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Stephanie Faubion]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=398574</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A study published in Menopause provides a comprehensive overview of the most common conditions diagnosed in clinical practice among women in the U.S. Upper Midwest during their critical midlife transition. Overall, eight conditions increased by 45% or more between the ages of 40 and 59, and several conditions were more common in Black women and [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-race-ethnicity-and-neighborhood-may-affect-midlife-womens-health/">8 common health conditions midlife women face</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/GettyImages-72420363-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Photo of group of diverse women" class="wp-image-398650" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/GettyImages-72420363-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/GettyImages-72420363-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/GettyImages-72420363-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/GettyImages-72420363-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/GettyImages-72420363-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Getty Images</figcaption></figure>



<p>A study published in <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/39689245/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Menopause</a> provides a comprehensive overview of the most common conditions diagnosed in clinical practice among women in the U.S. Upper Midwest during their critical midlife transition.</p>



<p>Overall, eight conditions increased by 45% or more between the ages of 40 and 59, and several conditions were more common in Black women and women living in more socioeconomically deprived neighborhoods.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="534" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Jennifer-St-Sauver-WF4773701_0060.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-398636" style="width:212px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Jennifer-St-Sauver-WF4773701_0060.jpg 534w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Jennifer-St-Sauver-WF4773701_0060-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 534px) 100vw, 534px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Jennifer St. Sauver, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/st-sauver-jennifer-ph-d/bio-00027743" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jennifer St. Sauver, Ph.D.</a>, the study's first author and professor of epidemiology at Mayo Clinic, says that the health of women in midlife is understudied, and comprehensive data about women between the ages of 40 and 59 are lacking.</p>



<p>"Most studies examine men and women together. However, we know that men and women age differently, so it's important to do separate studies to understand these differences," she explains.</p>



<p>Researchers know that hypertension and high cholesterol increase rapidly in both men and women during midlife. However, in this study, the researchers were surprised to see such a significant increase in sleep disorders, acid reflux and conditions related to joint and muscle pain in midlife women, according to Dr. St. Sauver.</p>



<p>Together, these data provide a picture of the most common health conditions that come to medical attention in midlife women and the most rapidly increasing, medically diagnosed conditions during the menopause transition.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Key findings</strong></h2>



<p>Eight conditions became significantly more common and increased in women during midlife (ages 40-59).</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/high-blood-cholesterol/symptoms-causes/syc-20350800" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Disorders of lipid metabolism (high cholesterol)</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=398574" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hypertension (high blood pressure)</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/sleep-disorders/symptoms-causes/syc-20354018" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sleep/wake disorders</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hypothyroidism/symptoms-causes/syc-20350284" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Thyroid disorders</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/esophagitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20361224" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Esophageal disorders</a> (especially acid reflux)</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/osteoarthritis/symptoms-causes/syc-20351925" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Osteoarthritis</a> (joint wear and tear)</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/tendinitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20378243" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tendon and synovial disorders</a> (problems with joints and connective tissues)</li>



<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/menopause/symptoms-causes/syc-20353397" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Menopausal disorders</a> (especially hot flashes)</li>
</ul>



<p>Black women and women living in socioeconomically deprived neighborhoods were more likely to have many of these conditions. Black women were more likely to have high blood pressure and esophageal disorders (especially acid reflux) compared to white women across all age groups. Women living in more deprived neighborhoods had a significantly higher prevalence of high cholesterol, high blood pressure, sleep disorders and esophageal disorders.</p>



<p>"Our data provide a comprehensive picture of the most common conditions coming to medical attention in midlife women. They are useful for understanding common diagnoses in women during the menopause transition and suggest that additional attention should be focused on Black women and women with lower socioeconomic status to ensure that common midlife conditions are identified and addressed," says women's health researcher and coauthor <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/faubion-stephanie-s-m-d-m-b-a/bio-20199366" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stephanie Faubion, M.D.</a>, Mayo Clinic in Florida.</p>



<p>The findings also underscore the need for increased research to understand underlying biological changes in women at midlife and how these changes contribute to the development of many conditions throughout the aging process. Such research may suggest future treatments that could be beneficial for multiple conditions. In addition, the findings highlight the need for increased attention to the health needs of Black women and women with lower socioeconomic status to ensure early diagnosis and treatment of common midlife health conditions.</p>



<p>The study used data from the Rochester Epidemiology Project in Minnesota, including medical records from approximately 1.4 million people in the Upper Midwest. Researchers analyzed data from 86,946 women between the ages of 40 and 59. They examined diagnoses recorded in electronic health records between 2016 and 2019.</p>



<p>Review the <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/39689245/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p><strong>Related: </strong><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/managing-menopause-symptoms/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Managing menopause symptoms</a></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-race-ethnicity-and-neighborhood-may-affect-midlife-womens-health/">8 common health conditions midlife women face</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/GettyImages-72420363-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/GettyImages-72420363-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diverserepresentation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jennifer St. Sauver]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Stephanie Faubion]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: How personalized vaccines target cancer tumors</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-personalized-vaccines-target-cancer-tumors/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cancer vaccine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Keith Knutson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lung Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vaccine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=398412</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Vaccines are helpful in protecting against the flu and COVID-19, but could they also play a role in the fight against cancer? Imagine a future where every cancer treatment is personalized to each patient, precisely targeting their unique cancer cells.&amp;#160; Dr. Keith Knutson,&nbsp;a cancer vaccine researcher at Mayo Clinic, explains how the development of personalized [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-personalized-vaccines-target-cancer-tumors/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How personalized vaccines target cancer tumors</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Vaccines are helpful in protecting against the flu and COVID-19, but could they also play a role in the fight against cancer? Imagine a future where every cancer treatment is personalized to each patient, precisely targeting their unique cancer cells.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/knutson-keith-l-ph-d/bio-00026672" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Keith Knutson,</a>&nbsp;a cancer vaccine researcher at Mayo Clinic, explains how the development of personalized lung&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/cancer/news/cancer-vaccines-illuminate-more-personalized-treatment-and-prevention-strategies/mac-20539115" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer vaccines</a>&nbsp;is giving hope to patients.</p>



<p><a href="https://youtu.be/TVqLoobmvG0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</strong></a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeTVqLoobmvG0"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - How personalized vaccines target cancer tumors" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TVqLoobmvG0?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (:58) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/SCRIPT-MCM-Personalized-vaccines-target-cancer-tumors.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script.</a>&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>It may sound like something out of a science fiction movie, but it is reality. Mayo Clinic researchers are developing personalized lung cancer vaccines.</p>



<p>"We actually make a vaccine that's specific for each individual's cancers," says Dr. Knutson.</p>



<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Cancer-Vaccine-1-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Dr. Keith Knutson, cancer vaccine lab" class="wp-image-398440" style="width:690px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Cancer-Vaccine-1-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Cancer-Vaccine-1-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Cancer-Vaccine-1-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Cancer-Vaccine-1-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Cancer-Vaccine-1-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p>The process involves analyzing cancer cells to create a one-of-a-kind vaccine.</p>



<p>"We can take a small part of that cancer and sequence that cancer and get the information that we need to design the vaccine," he explains.</p>



<p>The vaccine uses the immune system to identify and combat cancer.</p>



<p>"We can use that vaccine to hopefully prevent the disease from coming back, or we can use it to help shrink a tumor when given with other types of therapies," Dr. Knutson says.</p>



<p>You can reduce your risk of lung cancer by quitting smoking and avoiding exposure to secondhand smoke.</p>



<p>Read more about Dr. Knutson's work on the&nbsp;<a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/11/19/vaccines-the-next-frontier-of-lung-cancer-treatment-and-prevention/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center blog</a>.</p>



<p></p>



<p><strong>Related posts:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/innovation-in-lung-cancer-screening-treatment/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Innovation in lung cancer screening, treatment</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/tomorrows-cure-how-personalized-vaccines-combat-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tomorrow's Cure podcast: How personalized vaccines combat cancer</a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-personalized-vaccines-target-cancer-tumors/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How personalized vaccines target cancer tumors</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Cancer-Vaccine-2-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Cancer-Vaccine-2-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cancer vaccine]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Keith Knutson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Lung Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Vaccine]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic contributes to national Alzheimer&amp;#8217;s disease research priorities in new report</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-contributes-to-national-alzheimers-disease-research-priorities-in-new-report/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lynda De Widt]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Aging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Discovery Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nilufer Ertekin-Taner]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=398885</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Experts make recommendations for federal funding of research projects over the next 10 years Alzheimer's disease affects nearly seven million Americans over the age of 65, or 1 in 9 people in this age group, according to the Alzheimer's Association. Symptoms such as memory loss, trouble concentrating and performing familiar tasks, and personality changes start [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-contributes-to-national-alzheimers-disease-research-priorities-in-new-report/">Mayo Clinic contributes to national Alzheimer&amp;#8217;s disease research priorities in new report</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong><em>Experts make recommendations for federal funding of research projects over the next 10 years</em></strong></h2>



<p></p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/alzheimers-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350447" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alzheimer's disease</a> affects nearly seven million Americans over the age of 65, or 1 in 9 people in this age group, according to the <a href="https://www.alz.org/media/Documents/alzheimers-facts-and-figures.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alzheimer's Association</a>. Symptoms such as memory loss, trouble concentrating and performing familiar tasks, and personality changes start slowly and progress. Researchers have come a long way in understanding Alzheimer's disease and Alzheimer's Disease Related Dementias (AD/ADRD). A new <a href="https://nap.nationalacademies.org/resource/28588/Highlights_Dementia_Research.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">consensus study report</a>, "Preventing and Treating Dementia: Research Priorities to Accelerate Progress," identifies prevention and treatment strategies for the next decade. &nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="533" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/Taner1-WF531935_0015.jpg" alt="portrait of Dr. Nilufer Taner" class="wp-image-362465" style="width:253px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/Taner1-WF531935_0015.jpg 533w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/Taner1-WF531935_0015-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 533px) 100vw, 533px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Nilüfer Ertekin-Taner, M.D., Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We need cutting-edge treatments to help improve the lives of patients who are suffering from debilitating symptoms of dementia and prevention for those at risk," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/ertekin-taner-nilufer-m-d-ph-d/bio-00027318" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nilüfer Ertekin-Taner, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, chair of the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/departments-divisions/department-neuroscience-florida/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Neuroscience</a> at Mayo Clinic and leader of the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/genetics-of-alzheimers-disease-and-endophenotypes/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Genetics of Alzheimer's Disease and Endophenotypes Laboratory</a> at Mayo Clinic's campus in Florida. "Neurodegenerative diseases not only affect patients but also the friends and family who care for them."</p>



<p>Dr. Ertekin-Taner served on the select <a href="https://www.nationalacademies.org/our-work/research-priorities-for-preventing-and-treating-alzheimers-disease-and-related-dementias#sectionCommittee" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ad hoc committee</a> of the <a href="https://www.nationalacademies.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (NASEM)</a> which conducted a study assessing <a href="https://www.nationalacademies.org/news/2024/12/report-identifies-research-priorities-for-alzheimers-disease-and-related-dementias-more-innovative-and-integrative-research-approaches-needed-to-speed-progress" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">the state of research</a> on AD/ADRD and outlined critical research priorities for treatment and prevention, as well as potential barriers to progress. The National Institutes of Health, National Institute on Aging, and National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke asked NASEM to form the committee in response to a request from the U.S. Congress to accelerate research into these diseases.</p>



<p>Researchers looked broadly at the field, including basic to translational to clinical research; lifestyle interventions aimed at preventing and treating AD/ADRD; barriers to advancing progress in the field; and the most promising areas of research. The study looked at Alzheimer's disease, frontotemporal dementia, Lewy body dementia and other vascular causes of cognitive impairment and dementia.</p>



<p>The report identified 11 research priorities for further NIH-funded biomedical research, including:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Developing better tools, including novel biomarker tests and digital assessment technologies, to monitor brain health across the life course and to screen, predict and diagnose AD/ADRD at scale.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Implementing advances in clinical research methods and tools to generate data from real-world clinical practice settings that can inform future research.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Identifying factors driving AD/ADRD risk in diverse populations, particularly understudied and disproportionately affected groups, to better understand disease heterogeneity — including molecular subtypes and disparities in environmental exposures — and to identify prevention opportunities and advance health research equity.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Characterizing the exposome and gene-environment interactions across the life course to gain insights into biological mechanisms and identify opportunities to reduce AD/ADRD risk and increase resilience.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Integrating innovative approaches and novel tools into the planning, design and execution of studies to accelerate the identification of effective interventions.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Advancing the development and evaluation of combination therapies (including pharmacological and nonpharmacological approaches) to better address the multifactorial nature of AD/ADRD.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Evaluating precision medicine approaches for the prevention and treatment of AD/ADRD to better identify interventions likely to benefit specific groups of individuals.</li>
</ul>



<p>The report calls for breaking down silos for more collaborative, multidisciplinary research; fostering inclusive research to eliminate health disparities; developing innovative funding strategies; and increasing innovation in research through the expansion of public-private partnerships, among others.</p>



<p>"The past decade of research investments in AD/ADRD has led to significant progress in our understanding of these diseases, bringing us closer to treatments," Dr. Taner said. "In the next decade, we must maintain the momentum of research and innovation to translate these advances to cures for millions of patients and caregivers affected by the dementia epidemic."</p>



<p><strong>Note: Dr. Ertekin-Taner will participate in a <a href="https://www.nationalacademies.org/event/44277_01-2025_research-priorities-for-preventing-and-treating-alzheimers-disease-and-related-dementias-report-release-webinar" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">webinar</a> on Jan. 15 with other committee members to discuss the report.</strong></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-contributes-to-national-alzheimers-disease-research-priorities-in-new-report/">Mayo Clinic contributes to national Alzheimer&amp;#8217;s disease research priorities in new report</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Dementia-GettyImages-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Dementia-GettyImages-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nilufer Ertekin-Taner]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic launches Mayo Clinic Digital Pathology to modernize pathology, speed medical breakthroughs</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-launches-mayo-clinic-digital-pathology-to-modernize-pathology-speed-medical-breakthroughs/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Terri Malloy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AI and Digital Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individualized Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Laboratories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Aignostics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[artificial intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Callstrom]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[individualized medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[J.P. Morgan Healthcare Conference]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jim Rogers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Digital Pathology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Platform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NVIDIA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pathology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[personalized medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=398906</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Against the backdrop of the 43rd Annual J.P. Morgan Healthcare Conference, Mayo Clinic announced the formation of Mayo Clinic Digital Pathology, designed on a platform architecture to boldly unlock the power of its extensive archive of digital slides to revolutionize pathology and accelerate medical breakthroughs. Mayo Clinic's expertise, de-identified clinical data, and [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-launches-mayo-clinic-digital-pathology-to-modernize-pathology-speed-medical-breakthroughs/">Mayo Clinic launches Mayo Clinic Digital Pathology to modernize pathology, speed medical breakthroughs</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="600" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/WF4739820_0315.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-398899" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/WF4739820_0315.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/WF4739820_0315-300x225.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/WF4739820_0315-768x576.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Against the backdrop of the 43<sup>rd</sup> Annual J.P. Morgan Healthcare Conference, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> announced the formation of Mayo Clinic Digital Pathology, designed on a platform architecture to boldly unlock the power of its extensive archive of digital slides to revolutionize pathology and accelerate medical breakthroughs.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic's expertise, de-identified clinical data, and its Platform architecture, combined with technical expertise and resources of <a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">NVIDIA</a>, a world leader in accelerated computing, is powering the ability to accelerate this transformation. In addition, to improve performance and scalability of generative AI in pathology, Mayo Clinic is collaborating with <a href="https://www.aignostics.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Aignostics</a>, an industry leader in building artificial intelligence (AI) models for digital solutions in precision medicine in a way that mirrors its established approach to patient care. This collaborative, multidisciplinary effort leverages both medical and technological strengths, and the early achievements are promising.</p>



<p>"Mayo Clinic is reimagining what is possible in disease detection and prediction, both within its own system and globally. We are doing this by using large, diverse datasets to build powerful artificial intelligence models in pathology. This will make diagnoses faster, more accurate, and more efficient, improving treatment approaches and speeding new cures to patients," says Jim Rogers, CEO, Mayo Clinic Digital Pathology.</p>



<p>"AI-driven insights can accelerate diagnostics, enhance precision medicine and revolutionize patient care," said Kimberly Powell, VP of Healthcare and Life Sciences, NVIDIA. "By digitizing and harnessing the power of vast datasets through its Digital Pathology platform, powered by NVIDIA's accelerated computing, Mayo Clinic is helping pave the way for a future with faster medical breakthroughs, better treatments and improved outcomes for patients across the globe."</p>



<p>"Merging Mayo Clinic's data and expertise with our advanced machine learning capabilities will produce breakthrough foundation models and AI products that advance the field of precision medicine and meaningfully improve patient care," says Viktor Matayas, CEO of Aignostics.</p>



<p>The vast majority of pathology practices remain tethered to analog processes, hindering access to critical diagnostic data that could be used to expand diagnostics and treatments and speed the development of new therapies to benefit patients. To address this challenge, Mayo Clinic has moved quickly, investing in digitizing its pathology practice and by scanning its extensive archive of pathology slides, as well as prospectively scanning pathology slides from current patients. To date, Mayo Clinic Digital Pathology has leveraged 20 million digital slide images linked to 10 million patient records that incorporate treatments, medications, imaging, clinical notes, genomic data and more.</p>



<p>In less than two months, Mayo Clinic and Aignostics developed a leading foundation model built on 1.2 million deidentified slides from Mayo Clinic and Charité – Universitätsmedizin Berlin, findings of which were published in a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05409" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">paper</a> on Jan. 9. Current efforts include developing and deploying new solutions enabled by this model. Future plans are focused on building new models, including one being trained on 5 million slides. &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The NVIDIA collaboration will create a first-in-class infrastructure for building and deploying foundation models to accelerate generative AI advances in pathology and beyond. With NVIDIA's healthcare-specific full stack computing architecture for artificial intelligence, <a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/clara/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">NVIDIA Clara</a>, Mayo Clinic is building models that will open new frontiers in medicine and lay the foundation for more personalized patient experiences.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The development of Mayo Clinic Digital Pathology has been a planned process over many years. The pathology platform takes advantage of the portfolios of <a href="https://www.mayoclinicplatform.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Platform</a>, a global network that drives digital innovation around diagnosis, treatment and operational improvements worldwide, and <a href="https://www.mayocliniclabs.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Laboratories</a>, which provides advanced testing and pathology services for healthcare organizations worldwide. Continuing its efforts to transform healthcare, Mayo Clinic is working with investors and data providers to continue building a pathology platform that spurs innovation and transforms the medical practice for the benefit of healthcare systems and patients worldwide.</p>



<p>"These new capabilities using digital pathology data will unlock this critically important clinical information for building AI solutions for advanced diagnosis and care of patients and that will improve the lives of patients globally," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/callstrom-matthew-r-m-d-ph-d/bio-00085927" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Matthew Callstrom, M.D. Ph.D.</a>, chair of Mayo Clinic Radiology in the Midwest and medical director for Generative AI and Strategy.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> <br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-launches-mayo-clinic-digital-pathology-to-modernize-pathology-speed-medical-breakthroughs/">Mayo Clinic launches Mayo Clinic Digital Pathology to modernize pathology, speed medical breakthroughs</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/WF4739820_0315_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/WF4739820_0315_16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[AI]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Aignostics]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[artificial intelligence]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Callstrom]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[individualized medicine]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[J.P. Morgan Healthcare Conference]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Jim Rogers]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Digital Pathology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Laboratories]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Platform]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[NVIDIA]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[pathology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[personalized medicine]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic research may bring change to women&amp;#8217;s wrestling policies</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-research-may-bring-change-to-womens-wrestling-policies/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Katie Helwig]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orthopedics/Sports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Andrew Jagim]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=398450</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In 2020, the National Collegiate Athletics Association (NCAA) approved women's wrestling as an emerging sport. Since then, athletes, coaches and other leaders have recognized that its policies need to differ from those of men's wrestling. Wrestling is a sport that divides competitors into weight classes or weight categories; how much athletes weigh at the time [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-research-may-bring-change-to-womens-wrestling-policies/">Mayo Clinic research may bring change to women&amp;#8217;s wrestling policies</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="575" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Wrestler_16x9-1024x575.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-398453" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Wrestler_16x9-1024x575.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Wrestler_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Wrestler_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Wrestler_16x9.jpg 1500w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Minnesota high school wrestler Abby Gindele of the Annandale/Maple Lake Lightning. Photo courtesy of Mary Christen.<br></figcaption></figure>



<p>In 2020, the National Collegiate Athletics Association (NCAA) approved women's wrestling as an emerging sport. Since then, athletes, coaches and other leaders have recognized that its policies need to differ from those of men's wrestling.</p>



<p>Wrestling is a sport that divides competitors into weight classes or weight categories; how much athletes weigh at the time of competition is a vital component to determining the most equal opponent. Wrestlers at the high school and collegiate levels are required to complete a pre-season weight certification — consisting of a hydration test, a weigh-in and a body composition assessment — to determine the wrestler's minimal wrestling weight, which then dictates the lowest weight class they will be eligible to compete in.</p>



<p>When creating the initial weight policy for women's wrestling, the NCAA set the body fat percentage to determine an athlete's minimal wrestling weight at 12%. However, recent research led by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/providers/andrew-jagim-phd" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Andrew Jagim, Ph.D.</a>, the director of Sports Medicine Research at Mayo Clinic, has determined that a 17% body fat percentage may be a more reasonable and safer alternative to use.</p>



<p>"There has been scrutiny and concern among sports medicine professionals that the 12% value may be too low." Dr. Jagim says. "It could predispose female wrestlers to disordered eating patterns, frequent weight cycling and risks of certain health conditions such as the Female Athlete Triad."</p>



<p>Dr. Jagim says the Female Athlete Triad is a condition that consists of a trio of health issues including menstrual dysfunction, hormonal imbalance and reductions in bone health.</p>



<p>Here, Dr. Jagim answers questions about his findings.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What has your research shown about the current state of determining minimum weight for female wrestlers?</strong></h2>



<p>Values calculated during the preseason weight certification are established to discourage excessive weight cutting and frequent weight cycling throughout the season. Previously, a body fat percentage threshold of 12% was used for female wrestlers, which meant that a wrestler could reduce their weight to a point that would equate to a body fat percentage of 12%.&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/15502783.2024.2304561#d1e537" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Our work</a>, however, has identified that 95% of current female wrestlers have a body fat percentage above 17%, which indicates that not a lot of female wrestlers are engaging in excessive weight cutting to achieve the lower body fat percentage of 12%. Our work on this topic has helped provide evidence to the National Collegiate Athletics Association to encourage revision of their policies and adopt a new threshold of 17% for collegiate wrestlers. In the spring of 2025, I will be presenting our research to the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.nfhs.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Federation of State High School Associations</a>&amp;nbsp;and recommending a threshold of 19% for high school wrestlers.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Why is it important to change how the minimum weight for these athletes is calculated?</strong></h2>



<p>It is important to continually evaluate sports policies to help promote a safe sporting environment for athletes. With the emergence and rapid growth of women's wrestling, we are learning more about the sport and subsequently have more information to make more informed decisions regarding safety policies. While it doesn't appear to be a major issue yet, as the sport continues to grow, we will likely see wrestlers face more pressure to gain a competitive advantage — and in wrestling, that often means trying to compete in the lowest allowable weight class. If the 12% body fat threshold were to remain in existence, we may see an increase in female wrestlers engaging in excessive weight-cutting practices that could significantly increase health risks and lead to various negative outcomes such as the Female Athlete Triad and an increased risk of injury and illnesses.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What can athletes, coaches and parents do better to protect the athletes' health?</strong></h2>



<p>Some of the most important and effective things that can be done to protect the athletes' health is to follow evidence-based guidelines regarding optimal performance strategies. In brief, this means:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Getting at least eight hours of sleep per night as frequently as possible.</li>



<li>Following sports-specific fueling strategies (i.e., eating enough overall calories to support the high level of training and eating enough of the right macro and micronutrients to support the growth, development and recovery needs of a highly active young athlete).</li>



<li>Properly managing the training loads of an athlete, meaning trying to avoid excessive amounts of high-intensity training year-round and making sure to incorporate planned periods of rest or active recovery.</li>
</ul>



<p>From a wrestling-specific perspective, it's important to find the optimal weight and body fat percentage that allows the wrestler to feel their best, reduces the pressure of having to frequently cut weight throughout the season, and allows them to eat a healthy diet that provides the essential nutrients that their bodies require.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-research-may-bring-change-to-womens-wrestling-policies/">Mayo Clinic research may bring change to women&amp;#8217;s wrestling policies</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Wrestler_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Wrestler_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Andrew Jagim]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Vaginal microbiome may predict post-surgery urinary tract infections&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/vaginal-microbiome-may-predict-postoperative-urinary-tract-infections/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individualized Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. John Occhino]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Marina R. Walther-Antonio]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=398550</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Each year, many women undergo surgery for pelvic organ prolapse, a condition where weakened muscles and tissues allow organs like the bladder or uterus to shift and press against the vaginal wall. This typically results in feelings of tissue bulging from the vagina, pelvic pressure or urinary issues. While the surgical procedure often alleviates symptoms, [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/vaginal-microbiome-may-predict-postoperative-urinary-tract-infections/">Vaginal microbiome may predict post-surgery urinary tract infections&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-cover is-light has-black-color has-text-color has-link-color wp-elements-93c60ba537573698c850eeedec35292a"><span aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-cover__background has-white-background-color has-background-dim"></span><video class="wp-block-cover__video-background intrinsic-ignore" autoplay muted loop playsinline src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/GettyImages-1293799839-1.mp4" style="object-position:65% 38%" data-object-fit="cover" data-object-position="65% 38%"></video><div class="wp-block-cover__inner-container is-layout-constrained wp-block-cover-is-layout-constrained">
<p class="has-text-align-center has-medium-font-size"><strong>A new Mayo Clinic study links specific microbial patterns to urinary tract infection risk following pelvic organ prolapse surgery</strong></p>
</div></div>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Each year, many women undergo surgery for <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pelvic-organ-prolapse/symptoms-causes/syc-20360557">pelvic organ prolapse</a>, a condition where weakened muscles and tissues allow organs like the bladder or uterus to shift and press against the vaginal wall. This typically results in feelings of tissue bulging from the vagina, pelvic pressure or urinary issues.</p>



<p>While the surgical procedure often alleviates symptoms, many women experience a common post-surgical complication: <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/urinary-tract-infection/symptoms-causes/syc-20353447">urinary tract infections</a>. &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Now, researchers at Mayo Clinic, led by <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/walther-antonio-marina-r-ph-d/bio-20087609" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Marina Walther-Antonio, Ph.D.</a>, and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/occhino-john-a-m-d-m-s/bio-20055145" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">John Occhino, M.D.</a>, have found a way to potentially predict who will develop these infections before surgery even begins. </p>



<p>Their <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1038/s41598-024-78809-1?utm_source=rct_congratemailt&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_campaign=oa_20241122&amp;amp;utm_content=10.1038%2Fs41598-024-78809-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> reveals that specific patterns in the vaginal microbiome — a community of microorganisms, including bacteria, fungi and viruses — could serve as early indicators of urinary tract infection risk.&nbsp;Their findings are published in Nature Scientific Reports.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Zeroing in on key bacteria</strong></h2>



<p>Their findings show that women with lower levels of the protective bacterial species <em>Lactobacillus</em> were more likely to develop urinary tract infections following pelvic organ prolapse surgery. In addition, they found that higher levels of <em>Prevotella</em> and <em>Gardnerella</em> — bacteria linked to inflammation and infection — are also associated with an increased risk of postoperative complications.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-core-columns-is-layout-1 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/16x9Lactobacillus-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-398566" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/16x9Lactobacillus-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/16x9Lactobacillus-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/16x9Lactobacillus-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/16x9Lactobacillus-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/16x9Lactobacillus.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong><em>Lactobacillus</em>, shown in this illustration, is a protective bacterial species. The study found that lower levels in the vaginal microbiome are linked to a higher risk of urinary tract infections after pelvic organ prolapse surgery.<br><br></strong></figcaption></figure>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/16x9-Prevotella-bacteria-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-398564" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/16x9-Prevotella-bacteria-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/16x9-Prevotella-bacteria-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/16x9-Prevotella-bacteria-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/16x9-Prevotella-bacteria-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/16x9-Prevotella-bacteria.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong><em>Prevotella</em> and <em>Gardnerella</em> bacteria, shown in this illustration, are associated with inflammation and infection. The study found that higher levels in the vaginal microbiome are linked to a greater risk of urinary tract infections after pelvic organ prolapse surgery.</strong></figcaption></figure>
</div>
</div>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity is-style-wide" />



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>The research also provides insights on how surgery itself impacts the microbiome. Samples taken after surgery showed notable disruptions to both the vaginal and urinary microbiomes. These changes included lower microbial diversity, which can leave the body more vulnerable to infection.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The reasons for the changes are likely multifactorial and may include preoperative antibiotic administration, vaginal cleansing prior to surgery and surgery itself.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-core-columns-is-layout-2 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full has-custom-border is-style-default" style="margin-top:0;margin-bottom:0"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="533" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/WALTHER-ANTONIO2.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-398707" style="border-style:none;border-width:0px;border-radius:0px" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/WALTHER-ANTONIO2.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/WALTHER-ANTONIO2-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/WALTHER-ANTONIO2-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-pullquote has-medium-font-size" style="margin-top:0;margin-bottom:0;padding-top:0;padding-right:0;padding-bottom:0;padding-left:0;line-height:0"><blockquote><p>"Our ability to detect these microbiome patterns provides a potential opportunity to personalize treatment strategies and improve outcomes."</p><cite>Marina Walther-Antonio, Ph.d.</cite></blockquote></figure>
</div>
</div>



<div style="margin-top:0;margin-bottom:0;height:0px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>"Our ability to detect these microbiome patterns provides a potential opportunity to personalize treatment strategies and improve outcomes," says Dr. Walther-Antonio, a microbiome researcher at Microbiomics Program at <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine">Mayo Clinic's Center for Individualized Medicine</a>. Dr. Walther-Antonio also conducts research in the Departments of Surgery and Obstetrics and Gynecology, as well as the Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Walther-Antonio's collaboration with Dr. Occhino bridges a gap between cutting-edge research and clinical practice.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"Understanding the microbiome's role in post-surgical infections gives us a unique opportunity to possibly prevent these complications altogether," says Dr. Occhino, a Mayo Clinic urogynecologic surgeon. Dr. Occhino specializes in treating pelvic floor disorders, including conditions like pelvic organ prolapse and urinary incontinence.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Turning microbiome data into action</strong>&amp;nbsp;</h2>



<p>The study analyzed microbiome samples from postmenopausal women undergoing a vaginal hysterectomy with pelvic reconstruction. Researchers collected samples using vaginal swabs or urine collection at five stages, including before surgery, immediately after and during recovery. Advanced sequencing techniques were used to map the genetic material of the microbes and identify changes in the microbial communities.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-core-columns-is-layout-3 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium is-resized has-custom-border is-style-rounded" style="margin-top:0;margin-bottom:0"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="252" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/OCCHINO-300x252.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-398711" style="border-radius:0px;width:325px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/OCCHINO-300x252.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/OCCHINO.jpg 533w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-pullquote has-medium-font-size" style="border-radius:0px;margin-right:0;margin-left:0;padding-top:0;padding-bottom:0;line-height:0"><blockquote><p>"Understanding the microbiome's role in post-surgical infections gives us a unique opportunity to possibly prevent these complications altogether."</p><cite>John Occhino, M.D.</cite></blockquote></figure>
</div>
</div>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Dr. Walther-Antonio and Dr. Occhino plan to expand their research to include larger and more diverse patient groups. This effort aims to confirm their findings and explore interventions. This could include using probiotics to restore microbial balance before surgery or adjusting surgical timing for at-risk patients.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Dr. Walther-Antonio's other recent microbiome discoveries</strong></h2>



<p>Dr. Walther-Antonio's expertise in microbiome research extends beyond surgical outcomes. Her work also focuses on specific microbial communities associated with gynecologic cancers, including<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/science-saturday-uterine-microbe-found-to-have-disease-causing-behavior-in-endometrial-cancer/"> endometrial </a>and <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-link-ovarian-cancer-to-bacteria-colonization-in-microbiome/">ovarian cancers</a>. She has also investigated how these microbes may contribute to disease progression and influence treatment responses. These discoveries have driven the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/5-23-mayo-scientists-explore-swabs-for-early-endometrial-ovarian-cancer-detection/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">development of noninvasive swab tests</a> designed for earlier detection to improve outcomes.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Review the <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1038/s41598-024-78809-1?utm_source=rct_congratemailt&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_campaign=oa_20241122&amp;amp;utm_content=10.1038%2Fs41598-024-78809-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"></h2>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/vaginal-microbiome-may-predict-postoperative-urinary-tract-infections/">Vaginal microbiome may predict post-surgery urinary tract infections&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/1x1bacteria3.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/16x9-bacteria3.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. John Occhino]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Marina R. Walther-Antonio]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Researchers resolve uncertainty in BRCA2 testing, improving cancer risk assessment and patient care</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/researchers-resolve-uncertainty-in-brca2-testing-improving-cancer-risk-assessment-and-patient-care/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelley Luckstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 16:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=398641</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Findings will help identify patients with breast, ovarian, pancreatic or prostate cancer who may benefit from targeted therapies ROCHESTER, Minn. — Findings from a multi-institutional, international study led by researchers from the Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center have significantly advanced the understanding of genetic alterations in the BRCA2 gene, a key player in hereditary cancer [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/researchers-resolve-uncertainty-in-brca2-testing-improving-cancer-risk-assessment-and-patient-care/">Researchers resolve uncertainty in BRCA2 testing, improving cancer risk assessment and patient care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="682" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1319763211-1024x682.jpg" alt="a middle aged woman with a neutral expression, staring thoughtfully out a window" class="wp-image-371382" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1319763211-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1319763211-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1319763211-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1319763211-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/GettyImages-1319763211.jpg 1688w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><em>Findings will help identify patients with breast, ovarian, pancreatic or prostate cancer who may benefit from targeted therapies </em></p>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Findings from a multi-institutional, international study led by researchers from the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> have significantly advanced the understanding of genetic alterations in the BRCA2 gene, a key player in hereditary cancer risk. The researchers completed a comprehensive functional assessment of all possible variants within the crucial DNA-binding domain of BRCA2, resulting in the clinical classification of 91% of variants of uncertain significance (VUS) in this part of the gene. This finding dramatically improves the accuracy of genetic testing and will allow healthcare professionals to offer more precise risk assessments and personalized treatment plans for people carrying these variants.</p>



<p>The study, published in <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-08388-8" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nature</a>, utilized CRISPR-Cas9 gene-editing technology to analyze the functional impact of almost 7,000 BRCA2 variants, definitively identifying those that increase cancer risk and those that do not. This new information will eliminate much of the uncertainty surrounding VUS, allowing for more informed decisions regarding cancer screening, preventive measures and treatment strategies.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Couch-Fergus-J._12923222_20220906-240x300.jpg" alt="Dr. Fergus Couch" class="wp-image-398743" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Couch-Fergus-J._12923222_20220906-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2025/01/Couch-Fergus-J._12923222_20220906.jpg 640w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><sup>Fergus Couch, Ph.D.</sup></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"This research is a major advancement in understanding the role of many BRCA2 variants in cancer predisposition," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/couch-fergus-j-ph-d/bio-00027515" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Fergus Couch, Ph.D.</a>, the Zbigniew and Anna M. Scheller Professor of Medical Research at Mayo Clinic. "Until now, patients who carried VUS often worried if they would develop cancer, but now with the classification of these variants, we can provide a clearer picture of cancer risk and tailor both prevention strategies as well as breast cancer treatment accordingly."</p>



<p>The findings have immediate implications for genetic testing laboratories and healthcare professionals, aiding them in offering more precise and personalized care to patients with VUS. Many people with VUS may be notified about the reclassification of their VUS as the ClinVar BRCA1/2 expert panel and testing laboratories use the new information in testing reports and updates.&nbsp; In addition, this new insight will aid in identifying patients with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/brca-gene-test/about/pac-20384815" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast, ovarian</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pancreatic-cancer/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20355427#:~:text=The%20connection%20between%20breast%20cancer%20and%20pancreatic%20cancer,to%20see%20if%20there%20is%20a%20mutation%20present." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pancreatic</a> or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/prostate-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353087" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">prostate cancer</a> who might benefit from targeted therapies such as PARP inhibitors.</p>



<p>&amp;nbsp;"We now have a catalog of every possible VUS in this part of BRCA2 that can be used to guide clinical care," says Dr. Couch.</p>



<p>The researchers say that this research lays the groundwork for future studies characterizing and classifying all BRCA2 variants across diverse populations and cancer types, improving risk assessment for everyone.</p>



<p>The study involved collaborators at Ambry Genetics Inc., Duke University, H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center, the University of Pennsylvania and several contributing studies from the CARRIERS consortium. The study was supported by funding from the National Cancer Institute, Mayo Clinic Breast Cancer SPORE (P50 CA116201) and R35 Outstanding Investigator Programs, the Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, and the Breast Cancer Research Foundation.</p>



<p>For a full list of funding, disclosures and contributing authors, see the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-08388-8" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">paper</a>.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;amp;utm_medium=l&amp;amp;utm_content=content&amp;amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;amp;geo=national&amp;amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;amp;invsrc=other&amp;amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&amp;nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&amp;nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&amp;nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> is defining the cancer center of the future, focused on delivering the world's most exceptional patient-centered cancer care for everyone. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs in cancer detection, prevention and treatment to change lives.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/researchers-resolve-uncertainty-in-brca2-testing-improving-cancer-risk-assessment-and-patient-care/">Researchers resolve uncertainty in BRCA2 testing, improving cancer risk assessment and patient care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-middle-aged-woman-with-a-neutral-expression-staring-thoughtfully-out-a-window-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/07/a-middle-aged-woman-with-a-neutral-expression-staring-thoughtfully-out-a-window-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss> 