<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Research - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research-2/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research-2/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2023 19:24:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Unleashing viruses aimed at killing cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/unleashing-viruses-aimed-at-killing-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Buckles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CAR-T cell therapy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Richard Vile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[viruses]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377675</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>During breaks from his doctoral research in London, Richard Vile, Ph.D., would visit a pediatric brain tumor clinic next to his lab for inspiration. Seeing children suffer changed the course of his career, igniting his passion for finding cancer treatments that would be easier for people to tolerate. "I became very, very motivated to try and apply the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/unleashing-viruses-aimed-at-killing-cancer/">Unleashing viruses aimed at killing cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/07/a-medical-illustation-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-T-CAR-T-cell-therapy-16X9.jpg" alt="a medical illustation of chimeric antigen receptor-T (CAR-T) cell therapy" class="wp-image-343592" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/07/a-medical-illustation-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-T-CAR-T-cell-therapy-16X9.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/07/a-medical-illustation-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-T-CAR-T-cell-therapy-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/07/a-medical-illustation-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-T-CAR-T-cell-therapy-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p>During breaks from his doctoral research in London, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/vile-richard-g-ph-d/bio-00027663" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Richard Vile, Ph.D.</a>, would visit a pediatric brain tumor clinic next to his lab for inspiration. Seeing children suffer changed the course of his career, igniting his passion for finding <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer</a> treatments that would be easier for people to tolerate.</p>



<p>"I became very, very motivated to try and apply the science I learned to make cancer treatments gentler," says Dr. Vile. "My goal was to deliver an option that would extend and improve quality of life."</p>



<p>Decades later, Dr. Vile is leading research into genetically engineered viruses aimed at unleashing a two-pronged attack on cancer. One part of this technology, known as an <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/cancer/news/oncolytic-virus-optimizes-car-t-cell-therapy-for-solid-tumors/mac-20537878" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">oncolytic virus</a>, is designed to infect, break open and destroy cancer cells while sparing healthy tissue. Dr. Vile's <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/scitranslmed.abn2231" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">preclinical studies</a> have shown that oncolytic viruses replicated in cancer cells and cascaded to kill other diseased cells. That, in turn, triggered an immune response in which the patient’s own T cells, stimulated by the virus, recognized and targeted metastasized tumors for a second wave of cancer destruction.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="800" height="533" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Vile_1620845_3874783_0005.jpg" alt="Richard Vile, Ph.D." class="wp-image-377676" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Vile_1620845_3874783_0005.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Vile_1620845_3874783_0005-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Vile_1620845_3874783_0005-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Richard Vile, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure>



<p>"Oncolytic viruses are a way to alert the immune system and mobilize it to kill cells infected with cancer," says Dr. Vile. "There's the direct killing of cancer cells with the virus, and then there's the major effect of immune activation. The immune system is incredibly well evolved to recognize infection, clear infection and kill all the cells around it that could be harboring infection."</p>



<p>In groundbreaking research, Dr. Vile's team is combining oncolytic viruses with&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/car-t-cell-therapy-program/home/orc-20404317" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chimeric antigen receptor T-cell therapy (CAR-T cell therapy</a>) to target solid tumors from liver cancer. This experimental approach of loading CAR-T cells with oncolytic virus is a new way to expand CAR-T cell therapy beyond treatment for blood cancers into treatment for solid tumors.</p>



<p>CAR-T cell therapy is a regenerative immunotherapy in which a patient's T-cells are genetically modified to recognize and stop cancer. It has shown great promise by putting some B-cell lymphomas and leukemias into remission. CAR-T cells are highly targeted to tumor cells, with the goal of having fewer side effects than cancer treatments that also kill nearby healthy tissue.</p>



<p>"Loading the oncolytic virus onto CAR-T cells may give us three levels of killing. First, the CAR-T cells target the tumor and kill some of the cells," says Dr. Vile. "Next, it delivers the oncolytic virus, which infects tumor cells, replicates and kills them. Third, that alerts the immune system of the patient to the fact that there's something majorly wrong. The immune system starts to see the cancer and starts to react against it and kill it."</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic's&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</a>&nbsp;supports Dr. Vile's research as part of its objective of delivering new cell therapies to people with complex disorders such as cancer.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Addressing the challenges</strong></h2>



<p>Oncolytic viruses are advancing from the lab to first-in-human clinical trials. Dr. Vile is working with the Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics to biomanufacture oncolytic viruses onsite in Mayo Clinic's Current Good Manufacturing Practices (CGMP) facilities. CGMP facilities are sterile rooms that help ensure that the therapy meets the identity, strength, quality and purity standards that the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) requires for testing new therapeutics.</p>



<p>On-site biomanufacturing could lower production costs, allow for more individualized treatment and deliver the treatment to patients sooner than might be possible with an outside manufacturer.</p>



<p>"We are completing our studies in the lab and are transitioning to safety studies in the patient," explained Dr. Vile. "At the same time, we will manufacture the virus at a level of cleanliness (sterility) to meet FDA standards."</p>



<p>Oncolytic virus therapy is evolving, with more research needed to validate its safety and effectiveness. Dr. Vile hopes to test oncolytic viruses with CAR-T cell therapy for liver cancer in a phase 1 clinical trial in the next year or two.</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://regenerativemedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/11/10/unleashing-viruses-aimed-at-killing-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Regenerative Medicine blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/unleashing-viruses-aimed-at-killing-cancer/">Unleashing viruses aimed at killing cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/07/a-medical-illustation-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-T-CAR-T-cell-therapy-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/07/a-medical-illustation-of-chimeric-antigen-receptor-T-CAR-T-cell-therapy-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[CAR-T cell therapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Richard Vile]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[viruses]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Telehealth&#8217;s lasting impact on cancer care delivery</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/telehealths-lasting-impact-on-cancer-care-delivery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Vincent Jacobbi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2023 13:05:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Joshua Pritchett]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Tufia Haddad]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=378072</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A recent Mayo Clinic retrospective&#160;study&#160;shows that cancer practices can integrate telehealth without duplicative care, allowing for a more streamlined healthcare experience for patients and their caregivers. Researchers analyzed trends in telehealth use from 2019 to 2021 across&#160;Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center. The study looked at hematology and oncology visits conducted across Mayo Clinic campuses in [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/telehealths-lasting-impact-on-cancer-care-delivery/">Telehealth&#8217;s lasting impact on cancer care delivery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="800" height="533" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Telehealth-GettyImages-1280371057-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378075" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Telehealth-GettyImages-1280371057-16x9-1.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Telehealth-GettyImages-1280371057-16x9-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Telehealth-GettyImages-1280371057-16x9-1-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p>A recent Mayo Clinic retrospective&nbsp;<a href="https://ascopubs.org/doi/10.1200/OP.23.00118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;shows that cancer practices can integrate telehealth without duplicative care, allowing for a more streamlined healthcare experience for patients and their caregivers.</p>



<p>Researchers analyzed trends in telehealth use from 2019 to 2021 across&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>. The study looked at hematology and oncology visits conducted across Mayo Clinic campuses in Minnesota, Florida and Arizona, as well as at community-based clinics across&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System</a>.</p>



<p>In 2019, telehealth visits accounted for fewer than 0.01% of all visits. In 2020, a significant rise in telehealth use occurred in response to the COVID-19 pandemic, with the portion of visits conducted via telehealth increasing to 11%. By 2021, that figure rose to 14%, demonstrating a continued turn toward telehealth beyond the immediate pandemic response.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Pritchett_Joshua_C._16081960_20230925-240x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378074" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Pritchett_Joshua_C._16081960_20230925-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Pritchett_Joshua_C._16081960_20230925.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Joshua C. Pritchett, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We're showing that not only did our providers continue to use telehealth after the initial surge, but adoption (of the technology) increased over time and did not lead to increases in per-patient or per-provider care volumes," says lead author of the study, Joshua C. Pritchett, M.D., a hematology and oncology fellow at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>Overall, researchers examined over 100,000 visits conducted from 2019 to 2021, representing one of the largest analyses of telehealth use trends among cancer patients to date. Among people receiving established, ongoing care during the study, it found that 39.4% took part in at least one telehealth visit, demonstrating the critical role telehealth has played in the care of patients with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer</a> since the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>



<p>Researchers note that the study demonstrates that patient satisfaction ratings for telehealth visits remained similar to satisfaction with in-person care.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Digital health tools provide in-between visit care for patients</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Haddad_Tufia_C._10120386_20220907-240x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378073" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Haddad_Tufia_C._10120386_20220907-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Haddad_Tufia_C._10120386_20220907.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Tufia C. Haddad, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Beyond telehealth, the Mayo Clinic remote patient monitoring program is continuing to expand into the cancer space, allowing us to provide tablets and wearable devices for improved monitoring and in-between visit care," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/haddad-tufia-c-m-d/bio-20055534" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tufia C. Haddad, M.D.,</a> a Mayo Clinic medical oncologist and the study's senior author. "This will continue to help us understand how our patients are doing, how their symptoms and vital signs are tracking so that we can intervene earlier when things are not trending in a favorable direction."</p>



<p>With the many challenges of needing to get to and from appointments, telehealth has proved to be a worthy resource for many patients and their caregivers. The study showed that 52% of all visits by people undergoing treatment for various forms of brain cancer were conducted by video or phone technologies, demonstrating how access to care from home can be invaluable for many.</p>



<p>"The home is where healthcare happens," says Dr. Haddad. "Increasingly, we are seeing a continued shift in care to the home environment where smart homes enabled by digital technologies help assess and monitor patients. In the future, I think that will be more commonplace, and from there, we will only see the continued growth of virtual care delivery."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Reimbursement structures may affect the future of telehealth growth</strong></h2>



<p>Researchers noted that 20% of the U.S. population lives and works in rural areas; however, only 3% of oncology practices provide care there. For those in rural areas finding it difficult to travel for cancer care, telehealth has proven to be a lifeline when available.</p>



<p>The study showed a significantly higher rate of phone visits in rural populations versus video visits. Dr. Pritchett says the increased use of telehealth through phone visits is encouraging and shows a willingness by rural patients with cancer to engage with telehealth overall.</p>



<p>However, he notes that with the end of the Public Health Emergency Declaration applied in response to COVID-19, there has been a decline in reimbursement for phone visits compared to video visits. This change has the potential to create a widening disparity between urban, suburban and rural residents, and shows a need for future studies to examine how to increase video visit use among rural populations, he says.</p>



<p>"Telehealth in cancer care isn't simply a byproduct of the pandemic response. Patients desire this type of care, and it has become an integral part of patient-centered cancer care that continues to evolve," says Dr. Pritchett. "I think a big takeaway from this work is going to be how we make sure that it continues to be equitable and accessible to patients, as well as sustainable for practices."</p>



<p>The Mayo Clinic&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</a>&nbsp;supported this research. Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://ascopubs.org/doi/10.1200/OP.23.00118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p>This article first published on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/11/17/telehealths-lasting-impact-on-cancer-care-delivery/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/telehealths-lasting-impact-on-cancer-care-delivery/">Telehealth&#8217;s lasting impact on cancer care delivery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Telehealth-GettyImages-1280371057-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Telehealth-GettyImages-1280371057-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Joshua Pritchett]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Tufia Haddad]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers demonstrate nearly 20% boost in adolescent HPV vaccination rates using comprehensive strategy</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-demonstrate-nearly-20-boost-in-adolescent-hpv-vaccination-rates-using-comprehensive-strategy/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2023 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Lila Finney Rutten]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Robert Jacobson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HPV]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HPV vaccination]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vaccine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377625</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic researchers demonstrated a nearly 20% increase in human papillomavirus (HPV) vaccination rates among adolescents through a combination intervention approach, a new Mayo Clinic study finds. The strategy involved mailing reminders to parents about their child's eligibility for the HPV vaccine and simultaneously giving healthcare providers feedback about successful HPV vaccine [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-demonstrate-nearly-20-boost-in-adolescent-hpv-vaccination-rates-using-comprehensive-strategy/">Mayo Clinic researchers demonstrate nearly 20% boost in adolescent HPV vaccination rates using comprehensive strategy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="vial of human papillomavirus vaccine" class="wp-image-103619" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic researchers demonstrated a nearly 20% increase in <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hpv-infection/symptoms-causes/syc-20351596" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">human papillomavirus (HPV)</a> vaccination rates among adolescents through a combination intervention approach, a new Mayo Clinic study finds. The strategy involved mailing reminders to parents about their child's eligibility for the HPV vaccine and simultaneously giving healthcare providers feedback about successful HPV vaccine administration among the patients they had recently seen.</p>



<p>The findings, published in <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamapediatrics/fullarticle/2812161">JAMA Pediatrics</a>, suggest healthcare practices could adopt this evidence-based approach to boost HPV vaccination uptake in 11- and 12-year-olds.</p>



<p>"HPV vaccine uptake at 60% of eligible adolescents falls short of national public health goals and lags other adolescent vaccines," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/jacobson-robert-m-m-d/bio-00083020" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Robert Jacobson, M.D.</a>, a pediatrician in the Mayo Clinic Division of Community Pediatric and Adolescent Medicine. Dr. Jacobson is a co-principal investigator of the study.</p>



<p>Human papillomaviruses cause viral infections transmitted sexually through skin-to-skin contact. HPV infections may occur without symptoms or signs in late adolescence or early adulthood and affect both males and females. The virus can cause several types of cancers, including of the cervix, anus, genital area, mouth and throat.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/cancer/hpv/statistics/cases.htm" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">estimates</a> 37,000 HPV-linked cancers occur each year in the U.S., all of which may be prevented by the HPV vaccination.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For the study, the researchers evaluated their intervention strategy at six Mayo Clinic primary care practices in Southeastern Minnesota. The investigation involved 9,242 adolescents who were due to receive at least one dose of the HPV vaccine. When parents received reminders in the mail and providers were simultaneously given feedback, 39.7% of patients got their doses due in the months that followed the interventions, as contrasted to 21.9% without the interventions.</p>



<p>“Our study investigated both parent- and provider-facing interventions. By targeting parents and providers, we achieved much higher improvements in HPV vaccine uptake than the use of these strategies in isolation,” says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/rutten-lila-j-ph-d/bio-20551780" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lila Finney Rutten, Ph.D.</a>, lead author and chair of the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/departments-divisions/quantitative-health-sciences/divisions/epidemiology/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Division of Epidemiology</a>.</p>



<p>The researchers say the study not only addresses the low HPV vaccination rate but also holds the potential to reshape other public health and vaccination campaigns.</p>



<p>Review the&nbsp;study&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures, and funding.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> &nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and to providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.  &nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong>  &nbsp;</p>



<ul>
<li>Susan Murphy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>  &nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-demonstrate-nearly-20-boost-in-adolescent-hpv-vaccination-rates-using-comprehensive-strategy/">Mayo Clinic researchers demonstrate nearly 20% boost in adolescent HPV vaccination rates using comprehensive strategy</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Lila Finney Rutten]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Robert Jacobson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[HPV]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[HPV vaccination]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Vaccine]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Study shows immune molecule may play key role in the progression of ALS</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/study-shows-immune-molecule-may-play-key-role-in-the-progression-of-als/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Julie Vera]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[brain bank]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Bjorn Oskarsson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Dennis Dickson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Shanu F. Roemer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377667</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researchers and collaborators have identified a protein expressed by immune cells that may play a key role in the development of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS), also known as Lou Gehrig's disease. The team also found that an immunomodulatory treatment that blocks the protein was able to restore motor function in preclinical models. The findings [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/study-shows-immune-molecule-may-play-key-role-in-the-progression-of-als/">Study shows immune molecule may play key role in the progression of ALS</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Neuron-Cell-GettyImages-1328955938-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377668" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Neuron-Cell-GettyImages-1328955938-16x9-1.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Neuron-Cell-GettyImages-1328955938-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Neuron-Cell-GettyImages-1328955938-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers and collaborators have identified a protein expressed by immune cells that may play a key role in the development of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/amyotrophic-lateral-sclerosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20354022" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS)</a>, also known as Lou Gehrig's disease. The team also found that an immunomodulatory treatment that blocks the protein was able to restore motor function in preclinical models. The findings suggest that the protein, known as α5 integrin (pronounced alpha 5 integrin), is a potential therapeutic target for ALS.</p>



<p>The&nbsp;<a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/full/10.1073/pnas.2306731120" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;was published in the journal Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Fatal disease</strong></h2>



<p>ALS is a fatal motor neuron disease. People with ALS often die within three years of diagnosis. While there have been advances in understanding ALS, there is no cure or treatment that significantly improves motor function or extends survival in those with the disease. Although loss of motor neurons is the hallmark of ALS, the immune system also is involved in most people.</p>



<p>The disease involves activation of immune cells, including microglial cells and macrophages, which have pro-inflammatory properties. Microglial cells are immune cells specific to the nervous system. Macrophages are general immune system "cleanup" cells that are present in the peripheral nervous system.</p>



<p>The research team found the protein α5 integrin, which is expressed by microglial cells and macrophages, is present in abundance in the motor system in people with ALS, including in those with a genetic cause of the disease.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Roemer_Shanu_F._MD_14535025_201806200421-250x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377670" style="width:187px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Roemer_Shanu_F._MD_14535025_201806200421-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Roemer_Shanu_F._MD_14535025_201806200421.jpg 667w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Shanu F. Roemer, M.D., Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Our study found α5 integrin to be expressed in immune cells and also in blood vessels in active stages of the disease, as well as in end-stage disease,” says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/neuropathology-microscopy/about/team-bios" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Shanu F. Roemer, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic neuropathologist and co-first author of the study. The team also found that α5 integrin is not expressed in brain tissue from people without ALS or other neurodegenerative or inflammatory disorders such as Alzheimer’s disease, Progressive Supranuclear Palsy (a Parkinsonian disorder) or sepsis.</p>



<p>"The findings suggest α5 integrin plays a role in the pathology of ALS," says Dr. Roemer. "Because α5 integrin appears selective to ALS and is upregulated in brain and nerve fibers outside of the spinal cord in ALS, it opens up the possibility of exploring α5 integrin as a diagnostic and treatment biomarker."</p>



<p>In addition to preclinical models, the researchers examined human tissue from the Mayo Clinic&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/departments-divisions/department-neuroscience-florida/biorepositories/als-brain-bank-autopsy-program" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ALS Brain Bank and Autopsy Program</a>&nbsp;to determine the pervasiveness of α5 integrin in ALS.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/dickson-dennis-w-m-d/bio-00027499" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dennis W. Dickson, M.D.</a>, the Robert E. Jacoby Professor of Alzheimer's Research and a neuroscientist in Mayo Clinic's Department of Neuroscience in Florida, directs the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/departments-divisions/department-neuroscience-florida/biorepositories/mayo-clinic-brain-bank" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">brain bank</a>&nbsp;and also is a co-author of the study.&nbsp;The brain bank works closely with&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/oskarsson-bjorn-e-m-d/bio-20486118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bjorn Oskarsson, M.D.</a>, director of Mayo Clinic’s ALS clinic, and includes a large collection of brain and spinal cord tissue from people with ALS who donated their brains to Mayo Clinic for ALS research. The researchers used more than 100 ALS tissue samples in the study.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Possible novel pathway</strong></h2>



<p>The study team also explored a pathway for potential treatment. They found that a monoclonal antibody that blocks α5 integrin was able to preserve motor function in mice models. Monoclonal antibodies are synthesized immune system proteins used as a treatment for a wide range of diseases.</p>



<p>"Our findings showed that the antibody treatment against α5 integrin seemed to protect motor function, delay disease progression and increase survival," says Dr. Roemer. "Taken together, the findings regarding the upregulation of α5 integrin and its response to a monoclonal antibody suggest α5 integrin may be a potential therapeutic target for modulation of neuroinflammation in ALS."</p>



<p>Because several drugs exist that target other integrins for different diseases, the researchers suggest that a clinical trial to test α5 integrin as a drug target in ALS might be worthwhile. Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/full/10.1073/pnas.2306731120" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This article first published on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/11/08/study-shows-immune-molecule-may-play-key-role-in-the-progression-of-als/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/study-shows-immune-molecule-may-play-key-role-in-the-progression-of-als/">Study shows immune molecule may play key role in the progression of ALS</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Neuron-Cell-GettyImages-1328955938-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Neuron-Cell-GettyImages-1328955938-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[ALS]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[brain bank]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Bjorn Oskarsson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Dennis Dickson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Shanu F. Roemer]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Clinical research shows AI-enabled digital stethoscope can detect pregnancy-related heart disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/clinical-research-shows-ai-enabled-digital-stethoscope-can-detect-pregnancy-related-heart-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Terri Malloy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 15:56:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[artificial intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[digital stethescope]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Demilade Adedinsewo]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ECG]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ECG-AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[echocardiogram]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Electrocardiogram]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Failure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[left ventricular dysfunction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[peripartum cardiomyopathy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[phonocardiogram]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pregnancy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[weak heart pump]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377238</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>New research from Mayo Clinic suggests that artificial intelligence (AI) could improve the diagnosis of peripartum cardiomyopathy, a potentially life-threatening and treatable condition that weakens the heart muscle of women during pregnancy or in the months after giving birth. Researchers used an AI-enabled digital stethoscope that captures electrocardiogram (ECG) data and heart sounds to identify [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/clinical-research-shows-ai-enabled-digital-stethoscope-can-detect-pregnancy-related-heart-disease/">Clinical research shows AI-enabled digital stethoscope can detect pregnancy-related heart disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/closeup-of-the-hand-of-a-white-medical-worker-holding-a-stethoscope-up-to-a-transparent-graphic-of-medical-symbols-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="closeup of the hand of a white medical worker holding a stethoscope up to a transparent graphic of medical symbols" class="wp-image-366542" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/closeup-of-the-hand-of-a-white-medical-worker-holding-a-stethoscope-up-to-a-transparent-graphic-of-medical-symbols-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/closeup-of-the-hand-of-a-white-medical-worker-holding-a-stethoscope-up-to-a-transparent-graphic-of-medical-symbols-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/closeup-of-the-hand-of-a-white-medical-worker-holding-a-stethoscope-up-to-a-transparent-graphic-of-medical-symbols-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/closeup-of-the-hand-of-a-white-medical-worker-holding-a-stethoscope-up-to-a-transparent-graphic-of-medical-symbols-16X9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/closeup-of-the-hand-of-a-white-medical-worker-holding-a-stethoscope-up-to-a-transparent-graphic-of-medical-symbols-16X9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>New research from <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic">Mayo Clinic</a> suggests that artificial intelligence (AI) could improve the diagnosis of peripartum <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cardiomyopathy/symptoms-causes/syc-20370709?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">cardiomyopathy</a>, a potentially life-threatening and treatable condition that weakens the heart muscle of women during pregnancy or in the months after giving birth. Researchers used an AI-enabled digital stethoscope that captures <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ekg/about/pac-20384983">electrocardiogram</a> (ECG) data and heart sounds to identify twice as many cases of peripartum cardiomyopathy as compared to regular care, <a href="https://newsroom.heart.org/news/ai-technology-improved-detection-of-heart-disease-during-and-after-pregnancy">according to a news</a> release from the American Heart Association.</p>



<p>Identifying a weak heart pump caused by pregnancy is important because the symptoms, such as shortness of breath when lying down, swelling of hands and feet, weight gain, and rapid heartbeat, can be confused with normal symptoms of pregnancy.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/adedinsewo-demilade-a-m-b-ch-b/bio-20502753">Dr. Demilade Adedinsewo</a>, a cardiologist at Mayo Clinic, shared research insights during a late-breaking science presentation at the American Heart Association's Scientific Sessions 2023.</p>



<p>Women in Nigeria have the highest reported incidence of peripartum cardiomyopathy. The randomized pragmatic clinical trial enrolled 1,195 women receiving pregnancy care in Nigeria. Approximately half were evaluated with AI-guided screening using the digital stethoscope, and half received usual obstetric care in addition to a clinical ECG. An <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/echocardiogram/about/pac-20393856">echocardiogram</a> was used to confirm when the AI-enabled digital stethoscope predicted peripartum cardiomyopathy. Overall, 4% of the pregnant and postpartum women in the intervention arm of the clinical trial had cardiomyopathy compared to 2% in the control arm, suggesting that half are likely undetected with usual care.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/DCgDX2yvUc0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch:&nbsp;Dr. Adedinsewo explains the red flags for heart failure during pregnancy</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidDCgDX2yvUc0"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Red flags for heart failure during pregnancy" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/DCgDX2yvUc0?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/clinical-research-shows-ai-enabled-digital-stethoscope-can-detect-pregnancy-related-heart-disease/">Clinical research shows AI-enabled digital stethoscope can detect pregnancy-related heart disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/closeup-of-the-hand-of-a-white-medical-worker-holding-a-stethoscope-up-to-a-transparent-graphic-of-medical-symbols-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/closeup-of-the-hand-of-a-white-medical-worker-holding-a-stethoscope-up-to-a-transparent-graphic-of-medical-symbols-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[AI]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[artificial intelligence]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cardiology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[digital stethescope]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Demilade Adedinsewo]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[ECG]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[ECG-AI]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[echocardiogram]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Electrocardiogram]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Heart Disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Heart Failure]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[left ventricular dysfunction]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[peripartum cardiomyopathy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[phonocardiogram]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Pregnancy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[weak heart pump]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Engineering stem cells to treat liver disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/engineering-stem-cells-to-treat-liver-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Buckles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Alexander Revzin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kianna Nguyen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Liver Failure]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376859</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>During clinical rotations in medical school, Kianna Nguyen encountered many patients with&#160;liver failure&#160;and was struck by a grim reality: Their only hope was a transplant. The shortage of donor organs and therapeutic options was at once frustrating and inspirational, triggering her research interest in cellular therapies for liver failure. "Research provides us with the understanding [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/engineering-stem-cells-to-treat-liver-disease/">Engineering stem cells to treat liver disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="718" height="404" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/embryonic_stem_cells_shutterstock_768933475_16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376861" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/embryonic_stem_cells_shutterstock_768933475_16x9.jpg 718w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/embryonic_stem_cells_shutterstock_768933475_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 718px) 100vw, 718px" /></figure>



<p>During clinical rotations in medical school, Kianna Nguyen encountered many patients with&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/liver-problems/symptoms-causes/syc-20374502" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">liver failure</a>&nbsp;and was struck by a grim reality: Their only hope was a transplant. The shortage of donor organs and therapeutic options was at once frustrating and inspirational, triggering her research interest in cellular therapies for liver failure.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="667" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Nguyen-Kianna-M._21458961_201906170422.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376863" style="aspect-ratio:0.83375;width:197px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Nguyen-Kianna-M._21458961_201906170422.jpg 667w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Nguyen-Kianna-M._21458961_201906170422-250x300.jpg 250w" sizes="(max-width: 667px) 100vw, 667px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Kianna Nguyen<br></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Research provides us with the understanding to develop tools to make big changes in clinical problems like those facing patients with liver failure," says Nguyen. "I want to be on the forefront of developing medical technologies that provide alternatives. I derive a lot of passion for research through thinking about the future patients I will be treating in the clinic."</p>



<p>Nguyen is a fifth-year M.D.-Ph.D. student in the&nbsp;<a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/mayo-clinic-alix-school-of-medicine/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Alix School of Medicine</a>, who is also completing her Ph.D. in regenerative sciences through the&nbsp;<a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/">Mayo Clinic Graduate School o</a><a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">f</a><a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/">&nbsp;Biomedical Sciences</a>. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Her research is focused on redirecting human embryonic stem cells to become liver cells with the potential for cell, tissue and organ repair. This research is aimed at providing an alternative to a liver transplant.</p>



<p>Supervising her research is mentor&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/revzin-alexander-ph-d/bio-20359633" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alexander Revzin, Ph.D.</a>, who leads Mayo Clinic's&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/cellular-microsystems-biosensors/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cellular Microsystems and Biosensors Laboratory</a>. Dr Revzin is a biomedical engineer and scientist whose lab has developed a technique to encapsulate stem cells and reprogram them to become different cell types with therapeutic potential. The stem cells reside in a microcapsule — &nbsp;a microscopic plastic container filled with an aqueous solution. The microcapsule protects the cells from physical damage during bioprocessing and may be used to deliver signals that direct stem cells toward a desired tissue such as pancreas or liver tissue. The goal of the project is to use microcapsules to make liver tissue in sufficient quantities for use in humans. The hope is to one day transplant these cells as a treatment for complex diseases such as liver failure.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="667" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Revzin-Alexander-PhD_20130571_201610040336.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376864" style="aspect-ratio:0.83375;width:251px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Revzin-Alexander-PhD_20130571_201610040336.jpg 667w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Revzin-Alexander-PhD_20130571_201610040336-250x300.jpg 250w" sizes="(max-width: 667px) 100vw, 667px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Alexander Revzin, Ph.D.<br></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Encapsulation is an exciting new way to allow for scalable manufacturing of cellular therapies while decreasing the cost," says Dr. Revzin. “Kianna Nguyen has a unique skill set to work on this project. She is trained as a chemical engineer and biomaterials scientist and is well-positioned to develop encapsulation strategies. She is passionate about improving outcomes for patients with end-stage liver disease."</p>



<p>"The additional advantage of growing liver cells inside of capsules is they are provided with a protective shell so that they are not destroyed by the immune system when they are transplanted into the body," adds Nguyen. "Ultimately, the goal of this project is to be able to redirect liver cells on a large scale."</p>



<p>Regenerative sciences is an emerging field aimed at delivering new medicines from biological sources such as blood and cells to address conditions with few therapeutic options. The goal is to cure disease rather than treat symptoms. Mayo Clinic's&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</a>&nbsp;is leading efforts to develop groundbreaking curricula to train physicians and scientists for this potentially transformative medical care. &nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>A disease with complications</strong></p>



<p>More than 100 million people in the U.S. have some form of liver disease, according to the&nbsp;<a href="https://liverfoundation.org/about-your-liver/facts-about-liver-disease/how-many-people-have-liver-disease/#:~:text=More%20than%20100%20million%20people,been%20diagnosed%20with%20liver%20disease." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">American Liver Foundation</a>.&nbsp;While the liver has a remarkable ability to regenerate, chronic conditions such as cirrhosis, hepatitis and fatty liver disease can quickly progress to end-stage disease. Without a transplant, many patients will die.</p>



<p>Some people with cancer or alcohol use disorder are not suitable for transplantation. Those who are transplant candidates face complications including rejection, infection and risk of cancer.</p>



<p>"Stem cell-derived liver cells could provide a renewable source of liver cells to serve as a treatment for patients with liver failure. This could open the door to treatment for many liver patients who previously did not have any options," says Nguyen.</p>



<p>A native of Colorado, Nguyen was attracted to Mayo by the opportunity to train in clinical and laboratory settings with some of the most accomplished clinicians and researchers in the world.</p>



<p>"Mayo Clinic has so many exemplary physician-scientists. There is no shortage of mentors because faculty here are all so happy to share their expertise with you," she says. "I have been able to grow so much as both a budding clinician and scientist. I am thankful to continue my education here."</p>



<p>Nguyen aspires to specialize her practice and research in gastroenterology with a focus on hepatology (liver) transplantation. She is on a path to graduate with her M.D. and Ph.D. in 2027.</p>



<p>This article first appeared on the <a href="https://regenerativemedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/10/27/engineering-stem-cells-to-treat-liver-disease/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">blog of the Mayo Clinic Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</a>.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/engineering-stem-cells-to-treat-liver-disease/">Engineering stem cells to treat liver disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/embryonic_stem_cells_shutterstock_768933475_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/embryonic_stem_cells_shutterstock_768933475_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Alexander Revzin]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Kianna Nguyen]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Liver Failure]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mapping cell behaviors in high-grade glioma to improve treatment</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mapping-cell-behaviors-in-high-grade-glioma-to-improve-treatment/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Gerri Kelly]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Leland Hu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nhan Tran]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[high-grade glioma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neuroradiology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377191</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>High-grade gliomas are cancerous tumors that spread quickly in the brain or spinal cord. In a new study led by Mayo Clinic, researchers found invasive brain tumor margins of high-grade glioma (HGG) contain biologically distinct genetic and molecular alterations that point to aggressive behavior and disease recurrence. The findings suggest insights into potential treatments that could modify [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mapping-cell-behaviors-in-high-grade-glioma-to-improve-treatment/">Mapping cell behaviors in high-grade glioma to improve treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377192" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1.jpg 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The researchers profiled 313 tumor biopsies from 68 high-grade glioma (HGG) patients. This image is a representation of the 3-dimensional relationship of multiple tissue biopsies from a single patient’s HGG tumor. The different colors depict different versions of genetic mutations relative to the epidermal growth factor receptor gene.<br></figcaption></figure>



<p>High-grade gliomas are cancerous tumors that spread quickly in the brain or spinal cord. In a new study led by Mayo Clinic, researchers found invasive brain tumor margins of high-grade <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/glioma/symptoms-causes/syc-20350251" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">glioma</a> (HGG) contain biologically distinct genetic and molecular alterations that point to aggressive behavior and disease recurrence. The findings suggest insights into potential treatments that could modify the course of the disease.</p>



<p>The&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-023-41559-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;published in Nature Communications, profiled 313 tumor biopsies from 68 HGG patients using genomics (study of genes), transcriptomics (study of gene expression at the mRNA level) and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).</p>



<p>Glioma is a growth of cells that starts in the brain or spinal cord. The invasive margins of HGG have long remained a mystery due to the difficulties in surgical biopsy of these regions. The aggressive nature of most gliomas, and the visual and textural similarities between the affected regions and normal tissue, create a challenge for neurosurgeons during removal of the tumor. Some glioma cells may get left behind.</p>



<p>The cells in a glioma look like healthy brain cells called glial cells. As a glioma grows, it forms a mass of cells called a tumor. The tumor can grow to press on brain or spinal cord tissue, causing a range of symptoms. There are many types of glioma. Some grow slowly and aren't considered to be cancers. Others are considered cancerous. Malignant gliomas grow quickly and can invade healthy brain tissue.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Hu_Leland_S._13803611_20230703-240x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377194" style="width:198px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Hu_Leland_S._13803611_20230703-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Hu_Leland_S._13803611_20230703.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Leland Hu, M.D., a neuroradiologist at Mayo Clinic in Arizona.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/hu-leland-s-m-d/bio-20055165" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Leland Hu, M.D.</a>, a neuroradiologist at Mayo Clinic in Arizona, says the study also shows that MRI techniques, such as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/neurology-neurosurgery/news/radiogenomics-exploring-mris-potential-for-predicting-heterogeneous-tumor-biology/mac-20529911" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dynamic susceptibility contrast</a>&nbsp;and diffusion tensor imaging, can help distinguish between the genetic and molecular alterations of invasive tumors, which is important for clinically characterizing areas that are difficult to surgically biopsy.</p>



<p>"We need to understand what is driving tumor progression," says Dr. Hu. "Our results demonstrate an expanded role of advanced MRI for clinical decision-making for high-grade glioma."</p>



<p>The study also provides insight into resistance to treatment that could improve future outcomes.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Tran_Nhan_L._16076010_202106230849-250x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377195" style="width:181px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Tran_Nhan_L._16076010_202106230849-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Tran_Nhan_L._16076010_202106230849.jpg 667w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Nhan Tran, Ph.D., cancer biologist in the Department of Cancer Biology at Mayo Clinic in Arizona.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Our hope is that these clinical MRI techniques will lead to improved diagnosis, prognosis and treatment," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/tran-nhan-l-ph-d/bio-20305146" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nhan Tran, Ph.D.</a>, a cancer biologist in the Department of Cancer Biology at Mayo Clinic in Arizona. "We are looking at this research through the lens of therapeutic decision-making for patients."</p>



<p>The entire dataset, including genomics, transcriptomics and MRI, is publicly available to other groups and institutions as a resource to fuel new discoveries beyond what Dr. Hu and colleagues have reported in the initial manuscript.</p>



<p>Review the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-023-41559-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding. </p>



<p>This article originally appeared on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/11/09/mapping-cell-behaviors-in-high-grade-glioma-to-improve-treatment/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mapping-cell-behaviors-in-high-grade-glioma-to-improve-treatment/">Mapping cell behaviors in high-grade glioma to improve treatment</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Image_of_multiple_tissue_biopsies_from_a_single_patients_HGG_tumor-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Leland Hu]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nhan Tran]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[high-grade glioma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Neuroradiology]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic study suggests lower extremity lymphedema is a risk factor for multiple types of skin cancer</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-suggests-lower-extremity-lymphedema-is-a-risk-factor-for-multiple-types-of-skin-cancer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jay Furst]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[basal cell carcinoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dermatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lymphedema]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Proceedings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skin Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[squamous cell carcinoma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377039</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — New research from Mayo Clinic finds that patients with lymphedema —swelling of the limbs caused by the accumulation of protein-rich fluids of the immune system — had twice the risk of developing skin cancer than patients without lymphedema. Patients with lymphedema had a significantly higher frequency of developing basal cell carcinomas and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-suggests-lower-extremity-lymphedema-is-a-risk-factor-for-multiple-types-of-skin-cancer/">Mayo Clinic study suggests lower extremity lymphedema is a risk factor for multiple types of skin cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="682" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Physician-puts-compression-wrap-on-patient_WF2635704_0183-1024x682.jpg" alt="Physician puts compression wrap on patient" class="wp-image-377059" style="aspect-ratio:16/9;object-fit:cover" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Physician-puts-compression-wrap-on-patient_WF2635704_0183-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Physician-puts-compression-wrap-on-patient_WF2635704_0183-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Physician-puts-compression-wrap-on-patient_WF2635704_0183-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Physician-puts-compression-wrap-on-patient_WF2635704_0183-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Physician-puts-compression-wrap-on-patient_WF2635704_0183.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — New research from <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> finds that patients with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lymphedema/symptoms-causes/syc-20374682?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymphedema</a> —swelling of the limbs caused by the accumulation of protein-rich fluids of the immune system — had twice the risk of developing skin cancer than patients without lymphedema.</p>



<p>Patients with lymphedema had a significantly higher frequency of developing <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/basal-cell-carcinoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20354187?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">basal cell carcinomas</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/squamous-cell-carcinoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20352480?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">squamous cell carcinomas</a> on the lower extremities, according to the retrospective study published in <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/article/S0025-6196(23)00117-9/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a>. The study contributes to growing information linking lymphedema to localized changes in immunity and a predisposition for cancer.</p>



<p>The study reviewed data from 4,437 patients who were diagnosed with lower extremity lymphedema at Mayo Clinic in Rochester from 2000 to 2020. Compared with a matched control group, the group with lymphedema had an increased risk of skin cancer, and for patients who had lymphedema in one leg, that extremity was nearly three times as likely to have skin cancer compared with the other leg.</p>



<p>Lymphedema can be caused by surgery or cancer treatments that remove or damage the lymph nodes, which carry fluids of the immune system. Less commonly, lymphedema can be caused by inherited conditions.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Alavi-Afsaneh_30007478_202008311058-250x300.jpg" alt="portrait of Dr. Afsaneh Alavi" class="wp-image-377062" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Alavi-Afsaneh_30007478_202008311058-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Alavi-Afsaneh_30007478_202008311058-854x1024.jpg 854w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Alavi-Afsaneh_30007478_202008311058-768x921.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Alavi-Afsaneh_30007478_202008311058.jpg 938w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Afsaneh Alavi, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Patients with lymphedema are not screened routinely by dermatologists, and inadequate screening may lead to delayed diagnosis and treatment," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/alavi-afsaneh-m-d/bio-20492616?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Afsaneh Alavi, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic dermatologist and the study's senior author. "Our findings suggest the need for a relatively high degree of suspicion of skin cancer at sites with lymphedema. There is a need for raising awareness in clinicians seeing patients with lymphedema, and these patients may need regular skin cancer screenings, since early detection of skin cancer is critical."</p>



<p>View this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wPfNerwjd6I" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">video</a> of Dr. Alavi discussing the findings.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/skin-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20377605?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Skin cancer</a> is the most common cancer worldwide, but few studies have looked at the prevalence of lower extremity skin cancer, according to the article. The study found that all common forms of skin cancer, including squamous cell carcinoma, basal cell carcinoma, melanoma and angiosarcoma, were more common in patients with lower extremity lymphedema.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Proceedings</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a> is a monthly, peer-reviewed journal that publishes original articles and reviews on clinical and laboratory medicine, clinical research, basic science research and clinical epidemiology. The journal, sponsored by Mayo Foundation for Medical Education and Research as part of its commitment to physician education, has been published for 97 years and has a circulation of 127,000.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Jay Furst, Mayo Clinic Research and Education Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-suggests-lower-extremity-lymphedema-is-a-risk-factor-for-multiple-types-of-skin-cancer/">Mayo Clinic study suggests lower extremity lymphedema is a risk factor for multiple types of skin cancer</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Physician-puts-compression-wrap-on-patient_WF2635704_0183_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Physician-puts-compression-wrap-on-patient_WF2635704_0183_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[basal cell carcinoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dermatology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Lymphedema]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Proceedings]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Melanoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[screening]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Skin Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[squamous cell carcinoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Researchers identify new criteria to detect rapidly progressive dementia</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/researchers-identify-new-criteria-to-detect-rapidly-progressive-dementia/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lynda De Widt]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Gregory Day]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nihal Satyadev]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rapidly progressive dementia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376953</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have identified new scoring criteria allowing for the detection of treatable forms of rapidly progressive dementia (RPD) with reasonably high confidence during a patient's first clinical visit. This scoring criteria may allow physicians to substantially reduce the time it takes to begin treatment. The findings are published in the&#160;Annals of Neurology. Rapidly [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/researchers-identify-new-criteria-to-detect-rapidly-progressive-dementia/">Researchers identify new criteria to detect rapidly progressive dementia</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/MRI_brain_scans_GettyImages-1158800046-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376958" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/MRI_brain_scans_GettyImages-1158800046-16x9-1.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/MRI_brain_scans_GettyImages-1158800046-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/MRI_brain_scans_GettyImages-1158800046-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have identified new scoring criteria allowing for the detection of treatable forms of rapidly progressive dementia (RPD) with reasonably high confidence during a patient's first clinical visit. This scoring criteria may allow physicians to substantially reduce the time it takes to begin treatment. The findings are published in the&nbsp;<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ana.26812" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Annals of Neurology</a>.</p>



<p>Rapidly progressive dementia is caused by several disorders that quickly impair intellectual functioning and interfere with normal activities and relationships. If patients' symptoms appear suddenly and they decline quickly, a physician may make the diagnosis of RPD. These patients can progress from initial symptoms of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/dementia/symptoms-causes/syc-20352013" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dementia</a>&nbsp;to complete incapacitation, requiring full-time care, in less than two years.</p>



<p>The study analyzed data from 155 patients with RPD who were diagnosed at Mayo Clinic in Florida and Washington University in St. Louis. The median age of patients at the time of symptom onset was 69 years old. Patients underwent a standard evaluation, including brain&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mri/about/pac-20384768" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">MRI</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/eeg/about/pac-20393875" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">electroencephalogram</a>, blood tests and a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/lumbar-puncture/about/pac-20394631" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">spinal tap</a>. They then were followed for up to two years. The study team reviewed the data, assigned clinical diagnoses and determined which diseases would be considered potentially treatment-responsive. The team then compared symptoms and test results between patients with treatment-responsive and non-treatment-responsive causes. This identified key factors that were present at the time of the patient's first visit and were associated with treatment-responsive causes of RPD.</p>



<p>Seizures, tumors, MRI features of autoimmune encephalitis, movement abnormalities and other conditions were each associated with treatment-responsive causes of RPD in the study. Ninety-five percent of patients with these conditions were captured through a screening score developed by the Mayo researchers. The score was calculated by assigning points for clinical findings present during a patient's first visit for evaluation of cognitive decline.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Gregory_Day_WF430770_0015-300x200.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376962" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Gregory_Day_WF430770_0015-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Gregory_Day_WF430770_0015-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Gregory_Day_WF430770_0015.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Gregory Day, M.D., is a neurologist and vice chair of research in the Department of Neurology at Mayo Clinic in Florida.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Many conditions that cause rapidly progressive dementia can be treated and even reversed. We found that more than half of the patients in our study with rapidly progressive dementia had a treatable underlying condition. We may be able to identify many of these patients early in the symptomatic course by intentionally searching for key clinical symptoms and exam findings and integrating these with results of a brain MRI and spinal tap," says the study's senior author,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/day-gregory-gregg-s-m-d/bio-20545897" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gregory Day, M.D.</a>, a clinical researcher, neurologist and vice chair of research of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/neurology/home/orc-20117057" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Neurology</a>&nbsp;at&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a>.</p>



<p>Dr. Day's previous research found that&nbsp;<a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2022/10/31/researchers-find-other-diseases-may-mimic-rare-brain-disorder-linked-to-dementia/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">other diseases may mimic</a>&nbsp;a rare brain disorder called&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/creutzfeldt-jakob-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20371226" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Creutzfeldt-Jakob's disease</a>, which also is linked to dementia.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Satyadev_Nihal_30218471_20230620-240x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376960" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Satyadev_Nihal_30218471_20230620-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Satyadev_Nihal_30218471_20230620.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Nihal Satyadev, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"It's crucial to treat patients sooner by identifying a condition that is causing their rapidly progressive dementia," says Nihal Satyadev, M.D., a neurology resident at Mayo Clinic in Florida and the study's first author. "It's equally important to recognize patients who are less likely to benefit from treatment, as this can allow the focus of care to shift to supporting quality of life and appropriate counseling."</p>



<p>The study authors plan to continue research to improve diagnosis and treatment of patients with RPD, and to make it easier for clinicians to apply their tool to recognize patients with RPD. The team has already completed a project considering spinal fluid biomarkers that may improve diagnosis and early recognition of treatable patients. These findings are also published in the&nbsp;<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ana.26822" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Annals of Neurology</a>.</p>



<p>This research was supported in part by a grant from the National Institute on Aging of the National Institutes of Health under award K23AG064029. For a full list of authors, funding and conflicts of interest, see the&nbsp;<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ana.26812" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">paper</a>.</p>



<p>This article was originally published on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/11/03/researchers-identify-new-criteria-to-detect-rapidly-progressive-dementia/">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/researchers-identify-new-criteria-to-detect-rapidly-progressive-dementia/">Researchers identify new criteria to detect rapidly progressive dementia</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/MRI_brain_scans_GettyImages-1158800046-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/MRI_brain_scans_GettyImages-1158800046-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Gregory Day]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nihal Satyadev]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[rapidly progressive dementia]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic&#8217;s DNA study reveals BRCA1 mutations in 3 sisters, prompts life-changing decisions</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-dna-study-reveals-brca1-mutations-in-3-sisters-prompts-life-changing-decisions/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amy Scheid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[BRCA1]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Carrie Patnode]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chris Swatfager]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cindy Larson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sandhya Pruthi]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376834</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Sisters often share certain genetic traits, such as hair color and facial features. But for three sisters from Minnesota, they discovered a much deeper connection — a shared genetic mutation known to dramatically increase their risk for breast and ovarian cancer. Their BRCA1 variants came to light through a Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine DNA sequencing [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-dna-study-reveals-brca1-mutations-in-3-sisters-prompts-life-changing-decisions/">Mayo Clinic&#8217;s DNA study reveals BRCA1 mutations in 3 sisters, prompts life-changing decisions</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/SISTERS2-BRCA1-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376836" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/SISTERS2-BRCA1-16x9-1.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/SISTERS2-BRCA1-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/SISTERS2-BRCA1-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em><sub>(Sisters left to right: Chris Swatfager, Cindy Larson, Carrie Patnode and Amy Scheid. Photo is courtesy of Chris Swatfager.)</sub></em><br></figcaption></figure>



<p>Sisters often share certain genetic traits, such as hair color and facial features. But for three sisters from Minnesota, they discovered a much deeper connection — a shared genetic mutation known to dramatically increase their risk for <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/ovarian-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20375941" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ovarian cancer</a>.</p>



<p>Their BRCA1 variants came to light through a <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine</a> DNA sequencing study. The study highlights the importance of genetic screening and the potential for hereditary health concerns. The diagnoses have prompted each of the sisters to take preventative actions for themselves, and their families. </p>



<p>"Having this knowledge is lifesaving and life changing," says Chris Swatfager, the middle sister from Minnesota who was the first to undergo the DNA testing and receive the difficult diagnosis.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>BRCA1 is an inherited condition that significantly increases the likelihood of developing breast and ovarian cancer during a person's lifetime. According to the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/genetics/brca-fact-sheet#:~:text=Breast%20cancer%3A%20About%2013%25%20of,age%20(2%E2%80%934)." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Institutes of Health</a>, the breast cancer risk is 55%-72%, compared to approximately 13% for the general population. The risk for ovarian cancer ranges from 30%-60%, compared to approximately 1% for the general population. A parent with a BRCA1 mutation has a 50% chance of passing it down to their child. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Genetic screening reveals hidden health risks</h3>



<p>Given Chris's medical history of breast lumps, and her sister Carrie's breast cancer battle 16 years earlier, she says a clear picture suddenly came into focus. However, her original motivation to participate in the DNA sequencing study was driven by the heartbreaking death of her youngest sister, Amy, who had a heart attack in 2020. It marked the second heart attack-related death in the family. Chris believed there must be a hereditary link to heart disease.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Chris had learned that the Mayo Clinic study was screening for three actionable hereditary conditions, including a high cholesterol disorder called&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/familial-hypercholesterolemia/symptoms-causes/syc-20353755" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">familial hypercholesterolemia</a>, which raises the risk for a heart attack.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The other conditions in the study were related to BRCA1, as well as BRCA2, which is associated with breast, ovarian, pancreatic, and prostate cancers. Additionally,&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lynch-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20374714" target="_blank">Lynch Syndrome</a>&nbsp;was being assessed, which raises the risk of colorectal cancer.</p>



<p>Though none of these other conditions had crossed her mind.&nbsp;</p>



<p>To her surprise, Chris's results ruled out a genetic susceptibility to familial hypercholesterolemia, revealing instead a BRCA1 mutation.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>After undergoing comprehensive genetic counseling and receiving guidance from her physician, Chris opted for a double mastectomy and hysterectomy to mitigate her cancer risks. She also shared her diagnosis with her sisters, who, in turn, pursued genetic testing and received their own BRCA1 diagnoses.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>For Carrie Patnode, who had already battled breast cancer at the age of 48, the diagnosis has brought assurance that she can stay ahead of any new cancer developments with increased screenings and scans.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>"I think I may have done things differently if the BRCA test would have been provided when I was first diagnosed with breast cancer," Carrie says. "Now, after everything I've been through, I figure I'm going in every six months and getting mammograms every year and doing MRIs every year, and I'm confident they're going to find anything that reappears."&nbsp;</p>



<p>Cindy Larson, the oldest among the sisters and a retired letter carrier, developed bladder cancer shortly after receiving her genetic test results. She has chosen to hold off on any preventative procedures related to her BRCA1 variant, guided by the advice of her Mayo Clinic physician,<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/pruthi-sandhya-m-d/bio-00083681">&nbsp;Sandhya Pruthi, M.D.</a></p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">A new frontier in predicting disease risk</h3>



<p>Dr. Pruthi specializes in breast cancer prevention, and she’s working to pinpoint Cindy's genetic risk estimation related to her breast and ovarian cancer syndrome.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Pruthi says new and sophisticated genome sequencing technologies are opening the door to less invasive alternatives with the advancement of polygenic risk scores. The complex scores, compiled from a combination of data from thousands of a person's DNA variants, have the potential to offer precise insights into how patients should respond to a genetic mutation diagnosis associated with a cancer syndrome.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Polygenic risk scores allow us to potentially determine a patient's 5-year, 10-year and lifetime cancer risk," Dr. Pruthi says. "It may help us determine if and when a patient should undergo preventative procedures now or opt for surveillance over the next decade." &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>In the meantime, Dr. Pruthi says the power of genetic testing lies in its ability to help identify patients at high risk for cancer, enabling earlier screening and mitigating the risk of metastatic cancer and premature deaths — something she sees all too often.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Quest to bring genetic screening into everyday healthcare</h3>



<p>Mayo Clinic is advancing the idea of bringing genetic screening to routine patient care.</p>



<p>“We’re also studying the health utilization needs of those patients affected. This knowledge will transform the delivery of care in the coming decade,” says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine/about/director-insights">Konstantinos Lazaridis, M.D.</a>, the Carlson and Nelson Endowed Executive Director for Mayo Clinic's Center for Individualized Medicine.</p>



<p>Dr. Lazaridis says the immense impact of population-scale genetic screening reaches far beyond the benefits to individual people. It is also about the biological family members of those affected.</p>



<p>“It provides a collective wisdom that can shape public health strategies, increase disease prevention, and advance individualized medicine. It empowers people to be proactive about their own healthcare and prevention.” Dr. Lazaridis says.</p>



<p>For Chris, Carrie and Cindy, equally important to their own diagnoses is sharing the hereditary condition with their children and other blood relatives so they too can receive early disease detection.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"This affects generations of families and I hope genetic testing will soon become available for everyone," Chris says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This article first appeared on the <a href="https://individualizedmedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/10/31/mayo-clinics-dna-study-reveals-brca1-mutations-in-3-sisters-prompts-life-changing-decisions/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">blog of the Center for Individualized Medicine</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-dna-study-reveals-brca1-mutations-in-3-sisters-prompts-life-changing-decisions/">Mayo Clinic&#8217;s DNA study reveals BRCA1 mutations in 3 sisters, prompts life-changing decisions</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/SISTERS2-BRCA1-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/SISTERS2-BRCA1-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Amy Scheid]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[BRCA1]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Carrie Patnode]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Chris Swatfager]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cindy Larson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Sandhya Pruthi]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>