<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Research - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research-2/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research-2/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 14:31:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>A silent tumor, precancerous polyps and the power of genetic screening</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-silent-tumor-precancerous-polyps-and-the-power-of-genetic-screening/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Christina Wu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Konstantinos Lazaridis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Niloy Jewel Samadder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lynch Syndrome]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tammy LeDoux]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381552</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Tammy LeDoux could never have imagined she had a tumor the size of a pineapple growing on her left ovary. Or that precancerous polyps were lurking in her stomach and colon.&#160; "I never had any cramping. I never had any pain. I never felt anything hard or lumpy in my abdomen or down in my [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-silent-tumor-precancerous-polyps-and-the-power-of-genetic-screening/">A silent tumor, precancerous polyps and the power of genetic screening</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/TAMMY9-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381550" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/TAMMY9-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/TAMMY9-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/TAMMY9-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/TAMMY9-16x9-1.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Tammy LeDoux could never have imagined she had a tumor the size of a pineapple growing on her left ovary. Or that precancerous polyps were lurking in her stomach and colon.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"I never had any cramping. I never had any pain. I never felt anything hard or lumpy in my abdomen or down in my pelvic area. I never knew anything was there," says Tammy, an information technology analyst who lives in Wisconsin.</p>



<p>The surprising discoveries came after Tammy underwent genetic screening via the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine</a>, which revealed she has <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lynch-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20374714" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lynch syndrome.</a> The disorder is associated with an 80% risk of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353669" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colorectal cancer</a> and 50% risk of uterine and endometrial cancer.</p>



<p>"I honestly feel like knowing these genetic results has saved my life," Tammy says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Tammy's experience mirrors that of many other patients who, prior to participating in the Center’s DNA sequencing research study, called Tapestry, were unaware of their disease risk.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Overall, nearly 1.3 million Mayo Clinic patients like Tammy were invited to join Tapestry, which screened for three hereditary conditions: familial hypercholesterolemia (hereditary high cholesterol), hereditary breast and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/ovarian-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20375941" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ovarian cancer</a> (BRCA1 and BRCA2), and Lynch syndrome. Of those, roughly 100,000 chose to participate.</p>



<p>Based on existing literature, the study anticipated nearly 2% of participants would receive a positive result.</p>



<p>"What keeps me up at night is the fact that 1.2 million patients chose <em>not</em> to participate in the study, and this means around 20,000 of them likely have an undiagnosed hereditary risk or condition when considering the 2 percent rate of a positive result," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine/about/director-insights" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Konstantinos Lazaridis,</a> the Carlson and Nelson Endowed Executive Director for Mayo Clinic's Center for Individualized Medicine.</p>



<p>"We need to do better job of educating people about the value of genetic screening for rare but preventable conditions," he says.</p>



<p>Dr. Lazaridis says Mayo Clinic is advancing the idea of bringing genetic screening to routine patient care to help identify patients at high risk for cancer and other diseases, enabling earlier screening and mitigating the risk of cancer, the need to use expensive and limited therapies for advanced disease, and reducing premature deaths.</p>



<p>Beyond disease prevention, Mayo Clinic researchers are investigating volumes of Tapestry data to drive forward medical discoveries that enhance novel diagnostics and treatments.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Launching the Mayo Clinic Early Onset and Hereditary GI Cancers Program</strong></h2>



<p>In tandem with these efforts, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/samadder-niloy-jewel-m-d/bio-20396993">Dr. Niloy Jewel Samadder</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/wu-christina-s-m-b-b-ch-m-d/bio-20529971" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Christina Wu,</a> physician scientists in the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>, launched a new program in February 2024 to address the significant rise of colorectal and other gastrointestinal cancers in young people.</p>



<p>The Mayo Clinic Early Onset and Hereditary Gastrointestinal Cancers Program is dedicated to patients under the age of 55 who are diagnosed with colorectal, gastric, esophageal, liver, bile duct or pancreatic cancer.</p>



<p>This patient-centric program creates an integrated network of services involving gastroenterology, gynecology, oncology, colorectal surgery, infertility, pathology, genetics and adolescent and young adult specialists.</p>



<p>In 2022, Mayo Clinic's three campuses in Arizona, Florida and Minnesota reported over 2,000 newly diagnosed cases of gastrointestinal cancers among people under the age of 55. The marked rise in young-onset colorectal and other gastrointestinal cancers underscores a pressing health issue. The new program aims to provide accelerated access to top-tier care.</p>



<p>Dr. Samadder emphasizes that encircling patients with a multidisciplinary team of specialists will help provide the best possible outcomes.</p>



<p>"Our goal is to put the patient at the center of a collaborative framework of experts from diverse fields working seamlessly together," says Dr. Samadder, a Mayo Clinic gastroenterologist and cancer geneticist.</p>



<p>"The program also incorporates translational discoveries such as immunology and cancer evolution, as well as a clinical trial menu, research initiatives and a multi-omics approach that connects to a patient's unique biological datasets,” Dr. Samadder says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Tammy’s journey to the Tapestry study</strong></h2>



<p>Tammy’s initial motivation to participate in the Tapestry DNA research study was her curiosity about her ancestral heritage — another aspect of the study.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Upon receiving her genetic screening results, Tammy's team of genetic counselors and physicians moved quickly to educate her on Lynch Syndrome and help her schedule various screenings, including a colonoscopy, urine biopsy and ultrasound.&nbsp;</p>



<p>These screenings uncovered 10 polyps in her colon and stomach, some with precancerous characteristics, and two concerning moles on her skin. Soon after, Tammy made the proactive decision to undergo a hysterectomy to reduce her cancer risk. It was during this procedure that surgeons discovered and removed the sizable benign tumor.</p>



<p>"I couldn’t believe it. I’m beyond grateful," Tammy says. "I've been through the ringer, but now I have peace of mind knowing I've reduced my risks for cancer, and I can go in every couple years to check for any new polyps."</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is dedicated to shaping a future where cancers and other diseases can be prevented altogether, or identified at earlier stages, allowing for more precise treatment by a collaborative team of specialists.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-silent-tumor-precancerous-polyps-and-the-power-of-genetic-screening/">A silent tumor, precancerous polyps and the power of genetic screening</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/TAMMY9_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/TAMMY9-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Christina Wu]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Konstantinos Lazaridis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Niloy Jewel Samadder]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Lynch Syndrome]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Tammy LeDoux]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Diversity science researcher  achieving goal of making difference in people&#8217;s lives</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/diversity-science-researcher-achieving-goal-of-making-difference-in-peoples-lives/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2024 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Gladys Asiedu]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381496</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>From the time she was a young woman, Gladys Asiedu, Ph.D., knew she wanted to help people. Her path to achieving that goal began in Ghana. Learn about her journey and the difference she is making as a diversity science researcher. Gladys Asiedu, Ph.D., always knew she wanted to make a difference in people's lives. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/diversity-science-researcher-achieving-goal-of-making-difference-in-peoples-lives/">Diversity science researcher  achieving goal of making difference in people&#8217;s lives</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="533" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Asiedu_2016_Kern_faculty_16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381487" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Asiedu_2016_Kern_faculty_16x9.jpg 533w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Asiedu_2016_Kern_faculty_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 533px) 100vw, 533px" /></figure>



<h5 class="wp-block-heading has-text-align-center"><strong>From the time she was a young woman, Gladys Asiedu, Ph.D., knew she wanted to help people. Her path to achieving that goal began in Ghana. Learn about her journey and the difference she is making as a diversity science researcher.</strong></h5>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/asiedu-gladys-b-ph-d/bio-20528987" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gladys Asiedu, Ph.D.</a>, always knew she wanted to make a difference in people's lives. A steady focus on that altruistic goal would ultimately lead her to Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>As a child in Ghana in West Africa, she didn't know what that would mean, or how she would get there.</p>



<p>She received her undergraduate degree in English and religious studies from the University of Cape Coast in Ghana. In 2004, she and her family landed in Manhattan, Kansas, where she pursued graduate education at Kansas State University, receiving a master's in family studies and human services, a Ph.D. in family studies, and a graduate certificate in women's studies.</p>



<p>Her research career in Kansas began with a question: What happens when you or someone you love is diagnosed with HIV or AIDS? What are the mental and social impacts on patients and their families? And how do those impacts affect treatment?</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A passion for equity in the pursuit of health and wellness</strong></h2>



<p>Dr. Asiedu's experience in international and community health programs before coming to the U.S. gave her firsthand knowledge of the devastating effects of such a diagnosis on underprivileged and underserved populations.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="225" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Asiedu_3-225x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381491" style="width:225px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Asiedu_3-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Asiedu_3-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Asiedu_3-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Asiedu_3-1536x2048.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Gladys Asiedu sitting in her office in 2002, during which the time she was working with the Regional AIDS project and the Ghana Tourism Authority.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>In both her <a href="https://krex.k-state.edu/handle/2097/325" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">master's thesis</a> and Ph.D. dissertation, Dr. Asiedu argued that HIV/AIDS-related stigma and discrimination is not something that affects just one person or one family. It is a systemic issue that affects the health and well-being of a whole community, as well as healthcare providers and care systems.</p>



<p>Dr. Asiedu observed that this stigma was fueled by misinformation and limited understanding of science, and she proposed that education was the first step to averting fears related to the disease.</p>



<p>"An aspect of our human survival mechanism is to fear the unknown and to stigmatize it," says Dr. Asiedu. "Some of the findings of the research illuminate the misconceptions, misinformation and limited knowledge of HIV that fueled the stigmatization of those diagnosed with the disease." &nbsp;</p>



<p>Her <a href="https://krex.k-state.edu/handle/2097/6698" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dissertation</a> expanded on this finding and illustrated that community-based, participatory research — <a href="https://www.nimhd.nih.gov/programs/extramural/community-based-participatory.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">a newly emerging concept at the time</a> — was an effective way to identify potential interventions.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A continuing focus on community</strong></h2>



<p>In 2010, Dr. Asiedu moved to Rochester, where she hoped to help build a world where people would have equitable experiences and opportunities to live their healthiest and happiest lives.</p>



<p>Mayo didn't initially seem like a promising place to pursue her passion, with sparse ongoing social science research at the time.</p>



<p>"But there is always a first time, and in the first year, I worked with <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/pruthi-sandhya-m-d/bio-00083681" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Sandhya Pruthi</a> in Women's Health, who was crafting cancer screening interventions tailored to the culture and beliefs of low-income women in the Southeastern communities to increase rates of breast cancer screening," Dr. Asiedu says.</p>



<p>"Then I did a postdoc in health services research with Dr. Carmen Radecki Breitkopf, looking at disparities in common cancer screenings, preventive and therapeutic care," she says.</p>



<p>That's when she began to think Mayo might hold opportunities for the kind of work she wanted to pursue.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Diversity science</strong></h2>



<p>Today, Dr. Asiedu is a leading researcher in the new <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/research-activities/diversity-science" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Diversity Science Program</a> of the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</a>.</p>



<p>Program Director <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/blocker-renaldo-c-ph-d/bio-20121385" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Renaldo Blocker, Ph.D.</a>, Dr. Asiedu and other colleagues defined diversity science at Mayo. They started by thinking about the biases and inequities in the U.S.</p>



<p>"We were initially moved by our own experiences and the experiences of our colleagues, and were passionate about effecting change in our workplace and community," says Dr. Asiedu. "We became passionate about addressing this for our own institution and wanted to do good in the workforce space. &nbsp;But after the murder of George Floyd, it grew beyond the initial vision."</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic pledged $100 million to eliminate racism, advance equity and inclusion within Mayo Clinic, and improve health equity for people everywhere.</p>



<p>"This pledge from Mayo signifies the investment that the organization has in advancing equity, and that meant so much for what we wanted to do," says Dr. Asiedu. "So it was incumbent on us to define our tasks within the commitment that Mayo made and to reimagine how we approach diversity at Mayo."</p>



<p>That meant revisiting how to design diversity, equity and inclusion efforts, and health equity studies in a more scientific and rigorous manner, and ensuring that diversity, equity and inclusion research and discoveries by Mayo happen in a systematic, scientifically sound manner.</p>



<p>"We created the Diversity Science Program to be a hub for scientists and practitioners who wanted to work in this space but needed the guidance, consults and strategies that could potentially accelerate progress toward inclusivity through research," Dr. Asiedu says.</p>



<p>The team knew their work had to be more than just internal to Mayo. They needed to address the needs of the workforce, patients and community. They had to investigate and build interventions for sustainable transformation inside Mayo and across the global community.</p>



<p>"The fact that this program came into existence signifies our recognition of inequities and inequalities in our world, oppressions and disparities that come from systems of power," Dr. Asiedu says. "Systemic structures and cultural norms that have allowed dominant groups to undermine the value and dignity of members of minority groups.</p>



<p>"Launching the Diversity Science Program showed a renewed commitment by Mayo to conduct the rigorous research that underlies transformation and to share the knowledge gained through investigation and implementation of interventions," says Dr. Asiedu. "It's about time we change the science of characterizing inequities and disparities and move toward impactful science that implements interventions and programs resulting in equity and meaningful outcomes for all groups of people."</p>



<p>For Dr. Asiedu, the birth of the Diversity Science Program also expanded her ability to pursue health equity from myriad perspectives.</p>



<p>Dr. Asiedu invests her research expertise in investigations across all the program focus areas because she feels strongly about holistically examining health and healthcare delivery within larger contexts and identifying ways to improve outcomes and satisfaction among those who experience the most significant disparities.</p>



<p>She derives much satisfaction from her work, which feeds her passion. Her personal life provides more evidence of her commitment to improving the lives of others.</p>



<p>Between the demands of being an "Uber driver" for her school-aged kids, she volunteers for community-building activities in her church. Dr. Asiedu is surrounded by her community of friends and family who inspire and expand on her ideas to make a difference for people in the U.S., her home country, and perhaps the world.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Seeking a new perspective on clinical trial participation among underrepresented minority patients</strong></h2>



<p>Together with <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/price-katharine-a-m-d/bio-20521904" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Katharine Price, M.D.</a>, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/warsame-rahma-m-d/bio-20207073" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Rahma Warsame, M.D.</a>, and others, Dr. Asiedu explored the experiences, motivations, and decision-making of underrepresented minority patients successfully treated in a cancer clinical trial. After reviewing existing literature, they deliberately chose a mixed-methods approach, considering the question from an entirely new angle.</p>



<p>This positive approach acknowledges the existing strengths and everyday experiences of these patients.</p>



<p>"We wanted to gain some idea of barriers and facilitators to clinical trial enrollment through an appreciative inquiry," Dr. Asiedu says.</p>



<p>That meant approaching patients already in a clinical trial and asking, "What are your motivations for participating in this clinical trial?"</p>



<p>The team used surveys and the photo-elicitation interview technique — a visual research method — to explore and understand the motivations and facilitators of trial participation.</p>



<p>"PEI (photo-elicitation interview) is a powerful method for illuminating human experience and surfacing information, which may otherwise remain invisible using conventional approaches," says Dr. Asiedu. "This approach has the potential to alter clinical trial recruitment efforts that include patient-generated visuals of clinical trial experiences that could enhance culturally tailored educational programming."</p>



<p>The authors found that altruism appears to be a significant motivator to enroll in a cancer clinical trial. This message could be incorporated into recruitment strategies to improve the recruitment of diverse patients.</p>



<p>To gain a more comprehensive picture, the study included perspectives from physicians, study coordinators, clinical trial investigators, recruitment personnel and other staff involved in clinical trials to provide important insight into the complex issue of inclusive accrual.</p>



<p>Ultimately, Dr. Asiedu and the team's most critical observation was that clinical trial participation requires a relational approach. It is more than a simple two-party contractual agreement.</p>



<p>"It's not just you, the patient, making the decision. It is a decision for you and your family and friends and together with doctors," she says.</p>



<p>The team expects their study results to be published soon.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Effectively engaging the community to reach vulnerable populations during a public health crisis</strong></h2>



<p>Early in the COVID pandemic, Dr. Asiedu worked with two research teams to develop and evaluate a community-engaged bidirectional crisis and emergency-risk communications framework to assist in reaching immigrant communities as well as African Americans in Southeast Minnesota. The researchers knew they needed to work with the communities to identify the paths likely to lead to receptiveness. They needed to refine the messaging in ways that were both palatable and encouraged action while reducing fear and uncertainty.</p>



<p>The two research teams, <a href="https://rochesterhealthy.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Rochester Healthy Community Partnership</a> led by <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/sia-irene-g-m-d/bio-00085447" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Irene Sia, M.D.</a>, and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/wieland-mark-l-m-d-m-p-h/bio-00093813" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mark Wieland, M.D.</a>, and <a href="https://faith4heart.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">FAITH!</a> led by <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/brewer-laprincess-c-m-d-m-p-h/bio-20249241" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">LaPrincess Brewer, M.D.</a>, developed a bidirectional communication approach using the Crisis and Emergency Risk Communication model from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention to address COVID-19 prevention, testing, and socioeconomic impacts with immigrant, refugee and African American groups in Southeast Minnesota. This communication framework was culturally tailored and adapted to the needs of the immigrant and African American population in Southeast Minnesota.</p>



<p>This communication intervention reached over 40,000 community members in seven different language groups across Olmsted County. Framework implementation also led to systems and policy changes to meet the needs of immigrant, refugee and African American populations.</p>



<p>"The project helped reduce COVID-19 disparities through shared creation and dissemination of public health messages, enhanced connection to existing resources, and incorporation of community perspectives in regional pandemic mitigation policies," says Dr. Asiedu. "The framework has been adapted for use in other communities to encourage participation in healthful health communication to diverse populations."</p>



<p><strong>Read more about the framework:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33301390/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Emergency Preparedness and Risk Communication Among African American Churches: Leveraging a Community-Based Participatory Research Partnership COVID-19 Initiative</a>.</li>



<li><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33942018/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Leveraging community-engaged research partnerships for crisis and emergency risk communication to vulnerable populations in the COVID-19 pandemic</a>.</li>



<li><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37830352/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Perspectives of African American Church Leaders in Response to COVID-19 Emergency Preparedness and Risk Communication Efforts Within a Community Engaged Research Partnership: COVID-19 Emergency Risk Communication</a>.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Getting big-city care to the bedsides of the tiniest rural patients</strong></h2>



<p>Dr. Asiedu worked with <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/fang-jennifer-l-m-d/bio-00027602" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jennifer Fang, M.D.</a>, and her team to determine the best way to incorporate remote neonatology consultative support in hospitals without local access to this specialty.</p>



<p>It seemed simple: Add video telemedicine for newborn resuscitation care, thereby lessening rural health disparities and improving the odds of safer deliveries and healthier babies.</p>



<p>The team quickly realized this, too, was about relationships. Local doctors needed to be brought into conversations where they would learn the value of technology in helping them provide the best possible care for their patients. They needed to understand how the process would work, how the neonatologist would integrate with their local team, and how this intervention would improve outcomes. The research turned toward developing an effective outreach and education program that felt empowering for the rural care providers.</p>



<p>Today, Mayo's <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/teleneonatology-program" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Teleneonatology Program</a> is available across <a href="https://www.mayoclinichealthsystem.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Health System</a> and also supports non-Mayo medical facilities.</p>



<p><strong>Read more about the program:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30809596/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Health Care Professionals' Perspectives on Teleneonatology Through the Lens of Normalization Process Theory</a>.</li>



<li><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29420138/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">A Mixed-Methods Study on the Barriers and Facilitators of Telemedicine for Newborn Resuscitation</a>.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Improving care for men with prostate cancer who are also immigrants from sub-Saharan Africa</strong></p>



<p>Most recently, Dr. Asiedu has been working with colleagues at <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> to customize another framework — one for understanding the social determinants of migrant health. They hope their work leads to improved care and survivorship experiences for Black men with prostate cancer.</p>



<p>The current investigation is a <a href="https://iccare4blackmen.org/pilotproject4/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pilot study among sub-Saharan African immigrants</a>, identifying factors contributing to health-seeking behavior. Their findings advance knowledge in the <a href="https://iccare4blackmen.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">iCCaRE Consortium</a>, a shortened name for the Inclusive Cancer Care Research Equity for Black Men Consortium.</p>



<p>The team expects to expand the pilot to phase 2 in early 2024, involving other African and Caribbean immigrant communities and expanding collaborations to the University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center.</p>



<p><a href="https://aacrjournals.org/cebp/article/32/1_Supplement/B050/712121/Abstract-B050-The-iCCARE-consortium-for-prostate" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Read more about this collaboration</a> in Cancer Epidemiology, Biomarkers &amp; Prevention.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p>The <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/about/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</a> collaborates with clinical areas across Mayo to create and evaluate data-driven solutions to transform the experience of health and healthcare for patients, staff, and communities. It drives continuous improvement of Mayo Clinic as a learning health system, enabling always safe, evidence-based, high-quality care.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/diversity-science-researcher-achieving-goal-of-making-difference-in-peoples-lives/">Diversity science researcher  achieving goal of making difference in people&#8217;s lives</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Asiedu_2016_Kern_faculty_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Asiedu_2016_Kern_faculty_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[diversity science]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Gladys Asiedu]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Aspiring innovators aim to transform medicine with the next big idea</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/aspiring-innovators-aim-to-transform-medicine-with-the-next-big-idea/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kate Ledger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 14:31:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Alfredo Quinones-Hinojosa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kaisorn Chaichana]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maarten Rotman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mary Hedges]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381571</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Residents and students at Mayo Clinic learning the craft of their careers are also adopting a mindset to transform healthcare. Programs at Mayo are helping these enterprising inventors ask the right questions and take the steps to bring their innovative ideas to market.     </p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/aspiring-innovators-aim-to-transform-medicine-with-the-next-big-idea/">Aspiring innovators aim to transform medicine with the next big idea</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Formatted-Lightbulb.jpg" alt="Image of a lightbulb with sparks" class="wp-image-381572" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Formatted-Lightbulb.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Formatted-Lightbulb-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></figure></div>


<p>As a resident in internal medicine, Ramez Barsoom, M.D., is often considering ways to improve healthcare, but inspiration struck one day as he was doing an ordinary household chore. While using tools to mount a TV on the wall, he got an idea for a new medical device to simplify the detection of pneumonia in patients' lungs.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="640" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Barsoom_Ramez_A._Ramez_Barsoom_30268052_20230410.jpg" alt="Image of Ramez Barsoom, M.D." class="wp-image-381574" style="width:175px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Barsoom_Ramez_A._Ramez_Barsoom_30268052_20230410.jpg 640w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Barsoom_Ramez_A._Ramez_Barsoom_30268052_20230410-240x300.jpg 240w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Ramez Barsoom, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Dr. Barsoom, who came to <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/residencies-and-fellowships/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic School of Graduate Medical Education</a> last year as an M.D. with a master's degree in engineering, began noodling about developing the device. "I typically keep an innovation journal where I jot down all the different ideas that come to me, " he says. "Periodically, I set aside time to review each idea individually and assess whether the clinical need warrants a solution and hasn't been addressed before."</p>



<p>As a creative problem-solver who’s eager to explore new ideas, Dr. Barsoom is not alone. He is among many trainees at Mayo Clinic who, while learning the craft of their careers, are also strategizing about ways to transform healthcare. Several programs at Mayo are helping these enterprising inventors ask the right questions and take the steps to bring their innovative ideas to market.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Innovating step by step</strong></h2>



<p>Dr. Barsoom quickly realized his idea addressed an important medical need. Pneumonia remains a significant health issue worldwide, and diagnosing it often involves X-rays, which may be too costly for communities with few resources.</p>



<p>One of the first challenges he faced was engineering a version of his device. (Dr. Barsoom and other Mayo innovators can't share too many details about their inventions, which are still in development.) He was able to learn the steps involved in device development from the <a href="https://innovationexchange.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Innovation Exchange</a>, a resource that connects inventors with experts from healthcare, engineering and business. Drawing on his engineering background, he worked out a basic design and conducted an initial series of experiments to test the concept.&nbsp;</p>



<p>According to<a> </a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/hedges-mary-s-m-d/bio-20055284" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mary Hedges, M.D.</a>, program director for internal medicine residency in Florida, innovation is an essential focus in the training of new physicians. The residency program is among the first in the nation to add a formal innovation curriculum to physician training. "This is the future of medicine," she says. "Our residency aims to provide trainees with exposure to innovation, whether it's just an introduction or more in-depth opportunities for those who intend to make it part of their careers."&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Taking the stage to pitch the idea</strong></h2>



<p>As Dr. Barsoom's concept moved forward, he applied to pitch it at a competition hosted by the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-clinical-translational-science/offices/office-of-entrepreneurship/resources" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Office of Entrepreneurship</a>: the Alligator Tank in Florida, one of Mayo's healthcare innovation-launching events that occur on each campus. (Inventors on the Rochester campus participate in the <a href="https://www.walleyetank.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Walleye Tank</a>; those in Arizona join the <a href="https://mayoclinicasualliance.org/event/2023-scorpion-tank-healthcare-pitch-competition/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Scorpion Tank</a>.)</p>



<p>The format of the events is similar to the TV show Shark Tank, in which inventors describe new products in under two minutes to a panel of judges. The panel — in this case, a team of Mayo clinicians and innovation experts — asks questions and then votes on a winner.</p>



<p>"Some of the winning ideas from previous years are now products on the market or are in clinical trials," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/bruce-charles-j-m-b-ch-b/bio-00086002" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Charles Bruce, M.B., Ch.B.</a>, chief innovation officer in Florida.</p>



<p>Ultimately, Dr. Barsoom's presentation was among several that impressed the judges. He won a cash prize of $2,500. His project also earned a grant from the Mayo Clinic Innovation Exchange, which paired him with an external engineering firm to further develop the device.</p>



<p>"The next steps involve transforming my preliminary bench-tested solution into a minimum viable prototype and ultimately developing clinical trials that are necessary to test it," he says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Creating tools to make physicians' lives easier</strong></h2>



<p>Francis Shue was excited when she realized she might be onto a big idea that could potentially be the basis of a startup company. &nbsp;As a Ph.D. student at <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a>, Shue studies Alzheimer's disease in the lab of neuroscientist <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/kanekiyo-takahisa-m-d-ph-d/bio-00055074" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Takahisa Kanekiyo, M.D., Ph.D.</a> Alongside her bench research, her curiosity was piqued by artificial intelligence.</p>



<p>Working with the lab's collaborators at Carnegie Mellon, she began to explore a side project, using AI to organize patients' X-rays and other imaging tests. "My idea started out completely in the research sphere," she says. "We wanted to create something to make physicians' lives easier."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="350" height="404" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/FrancisShue2.jpg" alt="Image of Francis Shue" class="wp-image-381575" style="width:175px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/FrancisShue2.jpg 350w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/FrancisShue2-260x300.jpg 260w" sizes="(max-width: 350px) 100vw, 350px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Francis Shue</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>As she explored further, the idea seemed to have potential as a business. To learn how to take her idea to the next level, she signed up for a series of classes offered by the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-clinical-translational-science/offices/office-of-entrepreneurship" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Office of Entrepreneurship</a>. The classes introduced her to market and customer research and helped her identify a target audience for the product. The office also helped connect her to executives in industry, whom she interviewed to continue developing her product.</p>



<p>Though she didn't win a prize for her pitch at the Alligator Tank, she is emphatic about the value of the experience and how much she learned along the way. "I was able to get a lot of insider knowledge, hone my business skills and make many wonderful connections," says Shue. She now aims to have a career that involves discovery, innovation and business.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="640" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Lee_Hiva_30223512_20230627.jpg" alt="Image of Hiva Lee, M.D." class="wp-image-381577" style="width:175px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Lee_Hiva_30223512_20230627.jpg 640w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Lee_Hiva_30223512_20230627-240x300.jpg 240w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Hiva Lee, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"The Tank events can help fast-track the innovation and the inventor," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-clinical-translational-science/offices/office-of-entrepreneurship/leadership" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Maarten Rotman, Ph.D.</a>, Entrepreneurial Education Manager of the Office of Entrepreneurship, who hosts the event and helps participants prepare their pitches. "Most importantly, the students take on a new mindset as they conceive of their approach to developing a product and how to present it."</p>



<p>Internal medicine resident Hiva Lee, M.D., agrees. Opportunities like the Alligator Tank enabled him to develop the idea for a device that aims to reduce in-hospital infections.</p>



<p>"There are inevitably bumps along the road when developing a product," he says. "I’m in the middle of one now, as I’m trying to navigate the many paths to funding, research and development—so stay tuned!"</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A new device to study cancer</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="667" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Bechtle_Alexandra_R._20127570_202107070124.jpg" alt="Image of Alex Bechtle" class="wp-image-381576" style="width:175px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Bechtle_Alexandra_R._20127570_202107070124.jpg 667w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Bechtle_Alexandra_R._20127570_202107070124-250x300.jpg 250w" sizes="(max-width: 667px) 100vw, 667px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Alex Bechtle</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Alex Bechtle was able to jump right in as an inventor thanks to opportunities at Mayo. A few years ago, while still an undergraduate majoring in biomedical engineering, she spent a few summers studying brain cancer in the labs of neurosurgeons <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/quinones-hinojosa-alfredo-m-d/bio-20247553" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alfredo Quinones-Hinojosa, M.D.</a> and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/chaichana-kaisorn-l-m-d/bio-20428510" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kaisorn Chaichana, M.D.</a> The research teams became interested in using a 3-D printer to develop a new tool to visualize the unique attributes of metastasizing brain cancer cells. Using concepts from her undergraduate classes, Bechtle designed and developed the prototype, which the researchers immediately put to use.</p>



<p>Now a third-year student at <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/mayo-clinic-alix-school-of-medicine/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Alix School of Medicine</a>, Bechtle found additional opportunities to develop the skills inventors need. She fine-tuned a presentation about the 3-D printed device and first pitched it at the Alligator Tank in 2019. With new developments, she pitched it again in 2020, winning the crowd favorite award from the audience. Amid her medical school classes, she also took part in a week-long biomedical innovation "selective," one of the medical school's unique training courses on a specialized topic.</p>



<p>Though she is exploring making the code for the 3-D printed device freely available to researchers, Bechtle says the opportunities to learn about innovation throughout her training have made her even more alert to new ideas. "I do have the perspective of how can we improve a system or how can we improve a tool — and also that it’s essential to connect with others to discuss ideas and find ways to innovate," she says.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/aspiring-innovators-aim-to-transform-medicine-with-the-next-big-idea/">Aspiring innovators aim to transform medicine with the next big idea</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/11-lightbulb.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Formatted-Lightbulb.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Alfredo Quinones-Hinojosa]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Kaisorn Chaichana]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Maarten Rotman]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mary Hedges]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mcthumb >https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Formatted-Lightbulb-150x150.jpg</mayoclinic:mcthumb >	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Genetic testing pinpoints cardiovascular risk in patients with aortic disorders</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/genetic-testing-pinpoints-cardiovascular-risk-in-patients-with-aortic-disorders/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Vincent Jacobbi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2024 14:30:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[M. Hassan Murad]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mohammed Firwana]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science of Health Care Delivery]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381403</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A new Mayo Clinic systematic review has shed light on genetically inherited aortic disorders in patients, highlighting the importance of early diagnosis and treatment for those with inherited cardiovascular risk.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/genetic-testing-pinpoints-cardiovascular-risk-in-patients-with-aortic-disorders/">Genetic testing pinpoints cardiovascular risk in patients with aortic disorders</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/AI-heart.jpg" alt="Digital heart" class="wp-image-381420" style="width:830px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/AI-heart.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/AI-heart-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></figure></div>


<p>A new Mayo Clinic systematic <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S074152142301306X?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">review</a> has shed light on genetically inherited aortic disorders, highlighting the importance of early diagnosis and treatment for those who have inherited cardiovascular risk.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The researchers identified that a procedure known as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/thoracic-aortic-aneurysm/multimedia/endovascular-repair-for-thoracic-aortic-aneurysm/img-20123853#:~:text=In%20endovascular%20thoracic%20aortic%20aneurysm,with%20small%20hooks%20or%20pins." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Thoracic Endovascular Aortic Repair (TEVAR)</a> provided a high survival rate for young adult patients with type B <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/aortic-dissection/symptoms-causes/syc-20369496" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">aortic dissections</a>. Type B aortic dissections consist of a tear in the descending part of the aorta that may extend into the abdominal aorta.</p>



<p>"We studied type B aortic dissections and aortic aneurysms and their management, especially in people born with genetic complications or syndromes," says Mohammed M. Firwana, M.B.B.S., research fellow and lead author of the study.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Firwana_Mohammed_21674922_202003050932-250x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381417" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Firwana_Mohammed_21674922_202003050932-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Firwana_Mohammed_21674922_202003050932.jpg 667w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mohammed M. Firwana, M.B.B.S., research fellow and lead author of the study.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Notably, in over one-third of patients, genetic testing identified new aortic events within 15&nbsp;years. Patients with genetic risk factors exhibited a 62% rate of recurring aortic events, compared with 11% in patients without genetic risk factors, signifying the potential for more severe complications in the presence of such disorders.</p>



<p>Dr. Firwana adds that some of the findings varied by race, underlining the critical need for awareness and early treatment across all demographics.</p>



<p>"One of the more interesting findings was that Black patients with genetic risk factors had lower mortality than White patients, and that's mostly explained by how they presented at a younger age and their condition was likely managed earlier," says Dr. Firwana.<br><br>Researchers underscore that aortic aneurysms, dissections, and ruptures are thought to be the cause of 43,000 to 47,000 fatalities in the U.S. each year and that approximately 20% of thoracic aortic aneurysms are related to the genetic condition, also known as heritable thoracic aortic disease. These conditions are often silent but can lead to aortic dissection or rupture with often fatal outcomes.</p>



<p>Dr. Firwana emphasizes that identifying certain genetic mutations provides important knowledge and understanding of genetically inherited aortic disorders in patients.</p>



<p>He adds that there are multiple risk factors that can lead to a higher likelihood of aortic disorders, for example, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/marfan-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20350782" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Marfan syndrome</a>, a connective tissue disease, that affects one in 5,000 people in the U.S.</p>



<p>Dr. Firwana notes that another condition that can leave people prone to aortic issues is hypertension.</p>



<p>"Hypertension stands out as an important risk factor," says Dr. Firwana.</p>



<p>"It contributes to the weakening of the walls of the aorta over time, making them more susceptible to tearing or dissection."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/WF516862_0012-1-200x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381418" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/WF516862_0012-1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/WF516862_0012-1.jpg 533w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">M. Hassan Murad, M.D., senior author of the study</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Researchers note that the systematic review is being used to help support guideline development&nbsp;when managing genetically inherited aortic disorders in patients and that more research is needed to identify the role of Thoracic Endovascular Aortic Repair in patients with&nbsp;connective tissue disease.</p>



<p>Dr. Firwana emphasizes that quitting smoking, managing hypertension, and addressing diabetes are crucial preventive strategies for those with these genetic predispositions.</p>



<p>"A panel of experts from the Society for Vascular Surgery will use this systematic review to develop a clinical practice guideline that aims to help patients make decisions about their care," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/murad-m-hassan-m-d/bio-00094157" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">M. Hassan Murad, M.D.,</a> senior author of the study. "Further research on this topic can guide tailored interventions for improved patient outcomes."</p>



<p>The <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/education-training" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</a> supported this research. Review the <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S074152142301306X?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/genetic-testing-pinpoints-cardiovascular-risk-in-patients-with-aortic-disorders/">Genetic testing pinpoints cardiovascular risk in patients with aortic disorders</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/AI-heart-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/AI-heart.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[M. Hassan Murad]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mohammed Firwana]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Science of Health Care Delivery]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>World Cancer Day: Making a commitment to close the cancer care gap</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/world-cancer-day-making-a-commitment-to-close-the-cancer-care-gap/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2024 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer care gap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Rick Bold]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381393</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Union for International Cancer Control (UICC) recognizes&#160;World Cancer Day&#160;annually on February 4. The UICC's 2024 theme for World Cancer Day is "Close the Care Gap." The care gap is the gap between people who can obtain healthcare related to the prevention, early detection, diagnosis and treatment of cancer and those who cannot. The factors [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/world-cancer-day-making-a-commitment-to-close-the-cancer-care-gap/">World Cancer Day: Making a commitment to close the cancer care gap</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1017" height="572" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381396" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_16x9.jpg 1017w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1017px) 100vw, 1017px" /></figure>



<p>The Union for International Cancer Control (UICC) recognizes&nbsp;<a href="https://www.worldcancerday.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">World Cancer Day</a>&nbsp;annually on February 4. The UICC's 2024 theme for World Cancer Day is "Close the Care Gap." The care gap is the gap between people who can obtain healthcare related to the prevention, early detection, diagnosis and treatment of cancer and those who cannot.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Bold-Rick-J._30304260_20231002-819x1024-1-240x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381394" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Bold-Rick-J._30304260_20231002-819x1024-1-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Bold-Rick-J._30304260_20231002-819x1024-1-768x960.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Bold-Rick-J._30304260_20231002-819x1024-1.jpg 819w" sizes="(max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /></figure></div>


<p>The factors that create this gap include income, education and geographical location barriers. Discrimination based on ethnicity, race, gender, sexual orientation, age, disability and lifestyle can also be a barrier. Some people are also more likely to be exposed to factors that increase cancer risk, such as environmental hazards, unhealthy diet and tobacco.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic joins the UICC in breaking down barriers that stand in the way of cancer care. In this Q&amp;A,&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/richard-bold-m-d-named-site-director-mayo-clinic-comprehensive-cancer-center-in-arizona/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Rick Bold, M.D.</a>, site deputy director for&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;in Arizona, discusses Mayo Clinic's commitment to closing the cancer care gap:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What does World Cancer Day mean to Mayo Clinic?</h2>



<p>It means understanding the gaps in our cancer care and our cancer outcomes. It means recognizing those gaps by intentionally trying to close and eliminate them. There are different ways to define the gap; it may be related to the incidence of cancer, it may be related to the outcomes of cancer, and it may be related to access to cancer care. Each of these is a different gap that affects how people cope with cancer, how people survive cancer, and how people are diagnosed with cancer. We should strive to close and eliminate each of these gaps.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What is Mayo Clinic doing to help close the cancer care gap?</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20370588" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cancer</a> is not just one disease. For example, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a> is different for each person. Understanding why breast cancer developed at an individualized level — personalized or precision medicine — helps us determine the proper treatment for that patient and leads to better outcomes. Maybe a woman's genes caused cancer to develop. Perhaps it's where she lived — her environmental history or what she ate. We're doing <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials/search-results?studySiteStatusesGrouped=Open/Status%20Unknown&amp;pocId=CON-20167633" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">studies</a> reaching out to women across different communities, ethnic backgrounds and age groups to understand how <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/breast-cancer-risk-assessment/about/pac-20393195" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer risk</a> is determined. If every person is different, we need to understand that their cancer is different based on who they are. That's one effort that's helping to close the cancer care gap.</p>



<p>Another effort to close the gap is improving access to screening. Cancer screening is one of the most effective tools to reduce the burden of cancer in our communities. However, only some people have access to screening. Mayo Clinic is asking: How can we help everyone get access? How can we make screening easier? For example, can we detect&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353669" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colon cancer</a>&nbsp;with a blood test instead of a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/colonoscopy/about/pac-20393569" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colonoscopy</a>? Can we detect it&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/fecal-occult-blood-test/multimedia/fecal-occult-blood-test-kit/img-20007541" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">with a stool sample</a>&nbsp;collected in a person's home without time away from work or family or disrupting intestinal function by drinking a solution to cleanse the colon for a colonoscopy? Mayo Clinic is researching cancer screening tools that can be made available to more people conveniently at a lower cost. These efforts can help us close the gap by detecting more cancers at their earliest stage, which is when cures happen.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is also using technology to close the gap. One example of this is&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/sections/overview/ovc-20185491" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">proton beam therapy</a>&nbsp;for radiation. Mayo Clinic has two proton therapy units, one in Scottsdale, Arizona, and one in Rochester, Minnesota. We've studied how to deliver proton beam therapy in a way that improves patient outcomes. Some people can't take the time to get radiation, which may last weeks or months. Using proton beam therapy, we can shorten treatment time, broadening access by making it more convenient for people to get treatment in a minimally disruptive way.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What is Mayo Clinic doing to reach out to underserved and rural communities facing cancer care barriers?</h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic is developing cancer screening techniques that can be implemented internationally while recognizing that even in the U.S., not everybody has a hospital or a cancer center nearby. Many people are geographically isolated from healthcare or may lack insurance that pays for screening. We're trying to identify methods that could detect a variety of cancers early in a patient-friendly fashion, no matter what environment a person is living in and no matter what resources they have.</p>



<p>All Mayo Clinic locations see themselves as serving the community around them. We are developing strategic partnerships and relationships to elevate access to care in those communities and share our clinical expertise. This moves our care beyond the walls of our hospitals and clinics. Moving cancer care into patients' homes is becoming a national concept. We're starting to delve into that model of care. This will expand our ability to serve a broader population, not just in our local communities but nationally or internationally.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What is Mayo Clinic's goal for the future of cancer care?</h2>



<p>The ideal goal would be to eliminate cancer or turn cancer into a disease nobody needs to worry about. That's a long-term goal, and maybe we will get there.</p>



<p>In the shorter term, the goal is to achieve equitable cancer care that provides the best outcomes in a way that doesn't significantly disrupt the lives of patients and their families while respecting their individuality and their role in decision-making. We want to put all those things together and then always keep working on improving outcomes.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is committed to eliminating care gaps so every patient, regardless of where they live or who they are, receives the same cancer care and experiences the same positive outcomes. Mayo Clinic is here to serve patients. That's our primary mission.</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/02/01/world-cancer-day-making-a-commitment-to-close-the-cancer-care-gap/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center Blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/world-cancer-day-making-a-commitment-to-close-the-cancer-care-gap/">World Cancer Day: Making a commitment to close the cancer care gap</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer care gap]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Rick Bold]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New 4D imaging may detect poor pumping in deadly heart disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-4d-imaging-may-detect-poor-pumping-in-deadly-heart-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lynda De Widt]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. DeLisa Fairweather]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[myocarditis]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=380837</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Researchers at Mayo Clinic in Florida have found that a newer imaging technique may find subtle changes in heart dysfunction during acute stages of myocarditis and also heart functional differences by sex.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-4d-imaging-may-detect-poor-pumping-in-deadly-heart-disease/">New 4D imaging may detect poor pumping in deadly heart disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="366" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Echocardiogram_2_1505832_3734178_0046-16x9-1.jpg" alt="An image of a technician performing an echocardiogram on the heart" class="wp-image-380847" style="aspect-ratio:16/9;object-fit:cover;width:814px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Echocardiogram_2_1505832_3734178_0046-16x9-1.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Echocardiogram_2_1505832_3734178_0046-16x9-1-300x200.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></figure></div>


<p>In a new study, Mayo Clinic researchers found that a novel 4D echo imaging method that measures cardiac strain may detect subtle changes in the heart's dysfunction during acute <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/myocarditis/symptoms-causes/syc-20352539" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">myocarditis</a>, a deadly heart disease. In addition, they were able to describe heart functional differences by sex using the technology in a preclinical model. Currently, there are no disease-specific therapies to treat myocarditis.</p>



<p>The research is published in <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2589004223025701" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">iScience</a>.</p>



<p>An <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/echocardiogram/about/pac-20393856" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">echocardiogram</a> is one of the most common methods of measuring heart function and allows physicians to screen for heart issues, as well as monitor patients with existing heart conditions, such as myocarditis, or inflammation of the heart muscle often caused by viral infections. The test shows how blood moves through the heart's chambers and valves. Cardiac strain is a measurement that shows how well the heart muscle can move. When the muscle is inflamed, it can stiffen. It is particularly important to know the function of the left ventricle, which is the most muscular and hard-working chamber of the heart.</p>



<p>Myocarditis occurs most frequently in men under the age of 50 (especially ages 16-30). Women are at the greatest risk of developing the condition after the age of 50, or when they are postmenopausal, according to the researchers.</p>



<p>In this study, the researchers used a model of viral myocarditis to compare sex differences in male and female mice with myocarditis to a control group of mice after day 10 of infection. The researchers discovered that sex differences existed in cardiac strain during myocarditis, which they say was not known previously, and that worse cardiac strain in male mice with myocarditis correlated with more cardiac inflammation than in female mice with the condition. The data suggested that worse cardiac function may correlate to the severity of cardiac inflammation.</p>



<p>That data allowed the researchers to predict which mice were most likely to suffer from heart failure, which also occurs more often in men.</p>



<p>Researchers analyzed different echocardiography imaging techniques to measure heart function and found that the more traditional ones had limits and only showed a small portion of the total picture of how the heart changes during the disease process.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-right-align-caption">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="814" height="543" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/image.png" alt="Image of DeLisa Fairweather, Ph.D." class="wp-image-380839" style="width:294px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/image.png 814w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/image-300x200.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/image-768x512.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 814px) 100vw, 814px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">DeLisa Fairweather, Ph.D., is director of translational research for the Department of Cardiovascular Medicine at Mayo Clinic in Florida.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Until<strong> </strong>now, we have not had access to technology that can precisely describe small changes in cardiac function during acute myocarditis," says the study's senior author, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/fairweather-delisa-ph-d/bio-20320752" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">DeLisa Fairweather, Ph.D.</a>, vice-chair of translational research for the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/cardiovascular-medicine/home/orc-20121930" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Cardiovascular Medicine</a> at Mayo Clinic in Florida, where she also leads a <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/translational-cardiovascular-disease-research/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Translational Cardiovascular Disease Research Laboratory</a>. "Using a novel 4D echocardiography imaging technique in mice, we more precisely described functional changes in cardiac strain that occur during myocarditis by sex. Knowing how our model functionally relates to human disease allows us to draw clearer conclusions as to the efficacy of novel treatments moving forward that can save patients' lives."</p>



<p>The researchers say their findings demonstrate the importance of using cardiac strain to assess cardiac function in patients with suspected myocarditis, and especially focusing on sex differences, which are associated with clinical outcomes.</p>



<p>"Our discoveries will help us investigate how effective new treatments and drugs may be for human disease and how they may improve cardiac function using our preclinical model," says Dr. Fairweather. "This can make the process of assessing new drugs for treatment faster and more accurate."</p>



<p>"Cardiac strain also can be used to assess patients for changes in heart function during earlier stages of disease, which means doctors can treat them earlier to mitigate long-term, irreversible heart damage," she added.</p>



<p>Dr. Fairweather's body of research on myocarditis also includes a recently published paper in <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/smll.202303317" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">the journal Small</a> that found that extracellular vesicles isolated from the platelets of healthy people used in a mouse model of viral myocarditis decreased inflammation and improved cardiac function. Dr. Fairweather says this preclinical research will pave the way for future clinical trials in humans. The research team says their work on cardiac strain demonstrates key differences in cardiac function between male and female mice with myocarditis and matches what is found clinically in patients.</p>



<p>The next step in the team's research is to use these techniques when testing new treatments for myocarditis in their preclinical animal model.</p>



<p>This research was supported by the National Institutes of Health (NIH) under grant award R01 HL164520, American Heart Association and Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about/about-regenerative-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</a>. For a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding, see the <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2589004223025701" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">paper</a>.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-4d-imaging-may-detect-poor-pumping-in-deadly-heart-disease/">New 4D imaging may detect poor pumping in deadly heart disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Echocardiogram_2_1505832_3734178_0046-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Echocardiogram_2_1505832_3734178_0046-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. DeLisa Fairweather]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[myocarditis]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Growing mini-organs to find new treatments for complex disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/growing-mini-organs-to-find-new-treatments-for-complex-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Buckles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Brooke Druliner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Charles Howe]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. William Faubion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Organoids]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381038</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic investigators are growing three-dimensional human intestines in a dish to track disease and find new cures for complex conditions such as inflammatory bowel disease. These mini organs function like human intestines with the ability to process metabolites that convert food into energy on a cellular level and secrete mucus that protects against bacteria. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/growing-mini-organs-to-find-new-treatments-for-complex-disease/">Growing mini-organs to find new treatments for complex disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid2-16x9-1-1024x577.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381047" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid2-16x9-1-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid2-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid2-16x9-1-768x433.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid2-16x9-1.jpg 1155w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Microscopic view of an intestinal organoid</figcaption></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> investigators are growing three-dimensional human intestines in a dish to track disease and find new cures for complex conditions such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/inflammatory-bowel-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353315" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">inflammatory bowel disease</a>. These mini organs function like human intestines with the ability to process metabolites that convert food into energy on a cellular level and secrete mucus that protects against bacteria. These 3D mini intestines in a dish, known as "organoids," provide a unique platform for studying the intricacies of the human gut.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Brooke-Druliner-300x200.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381053" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Brooke-Druliner-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Brooke-Druliner-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Brooke-Druliner-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Brooke-Druliner-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Brooke-Druliner.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Brooke Druliner, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Cells that cluster into the 3D intestinal organoids are grown from a small amount of human intestinal tissue containing epithelial stem cells, taken from a person via a biopsy or surgery. Epithelial cells provide a protective barrier on skin, glands and internal organs and have shown potential for healing and regeneration. <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/druliner-brooke-r-ph-d/bio-20520602" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Brooke Druliner, Ph.D.</a>, leads this team science research.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/howe-charles-l-ph-d/bio-00083834" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Charles Howe, Ph.D.</a>, directs the Office of Core Shared Services and is working with Dr. Druliner and others across the Mayo Clinic to build the infrastructure in support of organoid-based research and translation.</p>



<p>"Thanks to these advancements, we are closer than ever to being able to create a "patient-in-a-dish" platform," he says. "Intestines in a dish are an example of how this new research tool will help us better understand inflammatory reactions in gastrointestinal-tract diseases. Our hope is this could lead to new drug targets and treatments."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A growing health problem</h2>



<p>Inflammatory bowel disease is a growing worldwide health problem that affects approximately 3 million people in the U.S., according to the <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/ibd/features/IBD-more-chronic-diseases.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Centers for Disease Control</a>. It encompasses a group of inflammatory conditions that affect the digestive system such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/crohns-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353304" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Crohn's disease</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/ulcerative-colitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20353326" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ulcerative colitis</a>. Symptoms of inflammatory bowel disease include abdominal pain and diarrhea but vary widely from one person to the next, posing a challenge in finding successful treatments. Immunotherapies are commonly prescribed but are effective only 40% of the time, and few patients experience lasting relief.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="574" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid1-16x9-1-1024x574.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381039" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid1-16x9-1-1024x574.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid1-16x9-1-300x168.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid1-16x9-1-768x431.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid1-16x9-1.jpg 1186w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Microscopic view of an intestinal organoid</figcaption></figure>



<p>Intestinal organoids provide a new, humanlike tool for tracking inflammatory bowel disease.</p>



<p>"A combination of animal and human models is more effective for our research. Intestinal organoids have the potential to allow us to screen drugs for toxicity and monitor effectiveness before the drug is tested in a clinical trial," says Dr. Druliner.</p>



<p>A Mayo Clinic research team including Dr. Druliner and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/faubion-william-a-jr-m-d/bio-00027222" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">William Faubion, Jr., M.D.</a>, a gastroenterologist-researcher and medical director for <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic's Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics,</a> is using these intestinal organoids to recreate features of inflammatory bowel disease.</p>



<p>Their robust research with intestinal organoids is bolstered in part by the more than 4,000 patients that come to Mayo Clinic every year with inflammatory bowel disease. Consenting patients donate tissue to a specialized biobank, and that tissue is matched with immune cells from the same patient. Those tissues and cells are used to create individualized 3D mini-intestines, with the goal of using these models for testing therapies tailored to the specific patient's individual disease.</p>



<p>"Our goal is to use our models to identify inflammatory bowel disease subtypes with predictable outcomes, including response to therapy or risk of disease progression," says Dr. Druliner.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Revolutionizing research</strong></h2>



<p>The broader vision is to one day expand 3D organoids from a variety of organs, preserve them and use them to track disease and screen drugs for a wide range of conditions including cancer, epilepsy, heart disease and dementia.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Charles-Howe-300x200.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381052" style="width:294px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Charles-Howe-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Charles-Howe-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Charles-Howe-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Charles-Howe-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Charles-Howe.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Charles Howe, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We think this has the potential to revolutionize the way we approach disease research. We hope to save time and resources and avoid development of therapies that fail upon translation into patients," says Dr. Howe. "Understanding which treatments show potential for success in human organoids could dramatically accelerate the rate of new therapies for patients with unmet needs."</p>



<p>A long-term goal would be to not only use the intestinal organoids for drug identification but also as a source of tissue regeneration to heal disease.</p>



<p>The researchers have partnered with the Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics to discuss the potential for biomanufacturing these mini organs in the future and how to establish quality control, reproducibility and scalability.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Challenges to overcome</strong></h2>



<p>The organoid research team already has overcome many challenges, including understanding ways to identify and collect fresh tissue to grow the organoids, and how to test if they accurately mimic the function of their original organ. Researchers are currently trying to address issues of quality control and validation to ensure the mini organs are accurate representations of a patient's individual disease. Another goal is to include more diverse cells such as immune cells, neurons or vasculature cells in these mini organs.</p>



<p>This research was initially made possible by Mayo Clinic's Cells2Cures initiative and Mayo Clinic’s Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics. It is now funded in part by an Organoid Biomanufacturing for Transforming Healthcare grant from the <a href="https://www.minnesotapartnership.info/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Minnesota Partnership for Biotechnology and Medical Genomics</a>, which is working towards establishing a joint Mayo Clinic – University of Minnesota Organoid Center. Learn more about this grant and the principal investigators from the University of Minnesota on the <a href="https://www.minnesotapartnership.info/2023/12/21/minnesota-partnership-awards-five-collaborative-research-grants-for-2023/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Minnesota Partnership website</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Related resources:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-mini-brain-study-reveals-possible-key-link-to-autism-spectrum-disorder/">Mayo Clinic ‘mini-brain’ study reveals possible key link to autism spectrum disorder</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/minnesota-partnership-awards-five-collaborative-research-grants-for-2023/">Minnesota Partnership awards five collaborative research grants for 2023</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/growing-mini-organs-to-find-new-treatments-for-complex-disease/">Growing mini-organs to find new treatments for complex disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid2-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid2-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Brooke Druliner]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Charles Howe]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. William Faubion]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Organoids]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Mayo Clinic stem cell research to take flight into space</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-stem-cell-research-to-take-flight-into-space/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lynda De Widt]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 14:28:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bone Loss]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Abba Zubair]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stem Cells]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stem cells in space]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=380364</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Update 1-30-24: According to NASA, a successful launch occurred at 12:07 EST. The spacecraft is scheduled to link with the International Space Station during the early morning hours of Feb.1. Update 1-29-24: NASA has moved the launch of this mission to Tuesday, Jan. 30, subject to weather conditions and other factors. You can watch for [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-stem-cell-research-to-take-flight-into-space/">New Mayo Clinic stem cell research to take flight into space</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/MVI_1410_1-1024x576.jpg" alt="SpaceX CRS-10 mission blast off from NASA's Kennedy Space Center with Dr. Zubair's stem cell research" class="wp-image-113641" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/MVI_1410_1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/MVI_1410_1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/MVI_1410_1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/MVI_1410_1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Update 1-30-24:</strong> According to NASA, a successful launch occurred at 12:07 EST.  The spacecraft is scheduled to link with the International Space Station during the early morning hours of Feb.1.</p>



<p></p>



<p><strong>Update 1-29-24: </strong> NASA has moved the launch of this mission to Tuesday, Jan. 30, subject to weather conditions and other factors.  You can watch for updates by following <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/event/nasas-northrop-grumman-crs-20-mission/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">NASA's launch schedule</a>.  Video assets with Dr. Zubair have been added below.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p></p>



<p>A Mayo Clinic research experiment will be part of a payload that launches into space from NASA's <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/kennedy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kennedy Space Center</a> in Cape Canaveral, Florida, on Jan. 29, subject to weather conditions and other factors. The research team from the lab of <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/zubair-abba-c-m-d-ph-d/bio-00092417" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Abba Zubair</a> is preparing <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bone-marrow-transplant/in-depth/stem-cells/art-20048117" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stem cells</a> for the flight to test how the absence of gravity plays a role in bone loss.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr._Zubair_in_lab_2017_1504453_3696200_0018R-200x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-380366" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr._Zubair_in_lab_2017_1504453_3696200_0018R-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr._Zubair_in_lab_2017_1504453_3696200_0018R.jpg 534w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Abba Zubair</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We've known for some time that astronauts lose bone density on long-duration space flights," says Dr. Zubair, a laboratory medicine and pathology specialist at Mayo Clinic in Florida. "We want to understand how this occurs so we can work on solutions that prevent bone loss not only in astronauts while they're in space, but also in patients here on Earth."</p>



<p>The research project will examine the effect of gravity on a type of stem cells derived from bone marrow known as mesenchymal stem cells, or adult stem cells with growth factors and healing potential. They play a key role in tissue repair and regeneration. Dr. Zubair's team will look at how the stem cells function while in space. Dr. Zubair says the experiment could have implications for future space flights that include taking humans to Mars.</p>



<p>This early research also could affect human clinical trials down the road, perhaps a decade away, according to Dr. Zubair.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeDcmT7xhSdUg"  title="New Mayo Clinic stem cell research to take flight into space" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/DcmT7xhSdUg?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: B-ROLL and Broadcast-quality sound bites with Dr. Zubair are available in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Name super/CG: Abba Zubair, M.D., Ph.D./Laboratory Medicine and Pathology&nbsp;/Mayo Clinic.</strong></p>



<p>"We will use what we learn from this project to advance our research on the road to clinical trials, with the ultimate goal of testing therapeutic agents that can prevent or treat bone loss that comes with osteoporosis, as well as bone loss that occurs in patients who are bedridden for long periods of time," he says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="219" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Stem_cells_cultivated_with_red_growth_medium_GettyImages-1140201087-300x219.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-380368" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Stem_cells_cultivated_with_red_growth_medium_GettyImages-1140201087-300x219.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Stem_cells_cultivated_with_red_growth_medium_GettyImages-1140201087-768x560.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Stem_cells_cultivated_with_red_growth_medium_GettyImages-1140201087.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Stem cells cultivated with red growth medium</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>The research will be conducted during two space flights. The first space flight will evaluate the impact of microgravity on bone-forming stem cells. The second space flight is tentatively planned for the end of the year and will analyze the effect of microgravity on other cell types that participate in bone formation or loss. A compound will be tested that can be used to treat bone loss in space and potentially on Earth.</p>



<p>The <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/blast-off-stem-cells-from-mayo-clinic-physicians-lab-launch-into-space/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">first foray into space</a> for Dr. Zubair's research was in 2017, when a payload of several samples of donated stem cells blasted off from Kennedy Space Center in a test to determine if they could hold up in space and be more quickly mass-produced in microgravity for use in stroke treatment. A subsequent research experiment in space found that <a href="https://regenerativemedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2020/06/18/stem-cells-in-space-interstellar-research-to-improve-regenerative-therapies/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stem cells grown in weightlessness</a> are safe and feasible for applications to human disease.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is collaborating with <a href="https://www.colorado.edu/center/bioserve/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bioserve Space Technologies</a> in Boulder, Colorado, which is providing the space flight hardware for the research project.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-stem-cell-research-to-take-flight-into-space/">New Mayo Clinic stem cell research to take flight into space</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/03/Launch1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/MVI_1410_2.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Bone Loss]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Abba Zubair]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Stem Cells]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[stem cells in space]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Save the date! RegenBio Summit: Transforming Next-Gen Biotherapeutics</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/save-the-date-regenbio-summit-transforming-next-gen-biotherapeutics/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Buckles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 13:00:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#biomanufacturing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#biomedical research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#biotherapeutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Dr. Julie Allickson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Dr. Saranya Wyles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Mayo Clinic RegeBio Summit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Regenerative medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=380970</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The need for lifesaving options for diseases with no treatment or cure is great, and Mayo Clinic is addressing that challenge in part with a new conference focused on advancing first-of-their kind regenerative biotherapies. RegenBio Summit: Transforming Next-Gen Biotherapeutics will be held Dec. 9 to 11 at the Ponte Vedra Inn &#38; Club in Ponte [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/save-the-date-regenbio-summit-transforming-next-gen-biotherapeutics/">Save the date! RegenBio Summit: Transforming Next-Gen Biotherapeutics</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="463" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Resize-WF1385852_0143.jpg" alt="A Mayo Clinic researcher studies biotherapeutics.
" class="wp-image-380978" style="aspect-ratio:16/9;object-fit:cover;width:839px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Resize-WF1385852_0143.jpg 463w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Resize-WF1385852_0143-300x200.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 463px) 100vw, 463px" /></figure>



<p>The need for lifesaving options for diseases with no treatment or cure is great, and Mayo Clinic is addressing that challenge in part with a new conference focused on advancing first-of-their kind regenerative biotherapies.</p>



<p><a href="https://ce.mayo.edu/content/regenbio-summit-transforming-next-gen-biotherapeutics#group-tabs-node-course-default1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">RegenBio Summit: Transforming Next-Gen Biotherapeutics</a> will be held Dec. 9 to 11 at the Ponte Vedra Inn &amp; Club in Ponte Vedra Beach, Florida. Save the date for an event that will bring together the best minds in medicine, biotechnology and entrepreneurship to discuss how to best bring a new class of medicines known as biotherapies to all patients. Regenerative biotherapies are made from human sources such as blood, cells and tissue and have shown potential for targeted healing with few side effects.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Wyles2-300x200.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381163" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Wyles2-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Wyles2-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Wyles2.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Saranya Wyles, M.D., Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We are living longer, but those extra years are often burdened with chronic disease," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/wyles-saranya-p-m-d-ph-d/bio-20476857" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Saranya Wyles, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, a dermatologist and associate director for education in Mayo Clinic's <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</a>. "Regenerative biotherapeutics offer hope of increasing health longevity by focusing on restoring health and function."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Collaborations to advance biotherapeutics</h2>



<p>The summit is an opportunity to build collaborations between academia, regulatory agencies and industry. Because this field of medicine is rapidly progressing, a cell or gene therapy may face different regulatory standards in the U.S. than it would in&nbsp; Europe or Asia. That can raise questions that slow or stall approvals of a new drug. A key topic of discussion will be setting global guidelines for new regenerative biotherapies to advance them from research into standard of care.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic will also highlight ways its unique biomanufacturing structure is designed to accelerate new discoveries from the lab to early-stage clinical trials. Mayo Clinic's advanced biomanufacturing operations are based on industry best practices and driven by patient need. The operations coordinate process development, quality control and quality assurance to ensure an emerging therapy meets standards for commercial grade biotherapies.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Allickson_WF782604_0002-300x200.jpg" alt="Julie Allickson, Ph.D." class="wp-image-378671" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Allickson_WF782604_0002-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Allickson_WF782604_0002-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Allickson_WF782604_0002.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Julie Allickson, Ph.D</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We're planning to share Mayo Clinic's blueprint of how to develop and disseminate new biotherapies in the most trusted way for patient care," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/allickson-julie-g-ph-d/bio-20523656" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Julie Allickson, Ph.D.</a>, the Michael S. and Mary Sue Shannon Director of the Mayo Clinic Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics. "Our biomanufacturing model is designed to troubleshoot and address problems early, so a new regenerative intervention can be seamlessly transferred to an industry collaborator, creating the bridge for safe and effective biotherapies to improve patients' lives worldwide."</p>



<p>Dr. Allickson is also the Otto Bremer Trust Director, Biomanufacturing and Product Development, <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advancing-patient-care-with-biologics-4-ways-mayo-clinics-biomanufacturing-strategy-is-making-a-difference/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics.</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Exploring the future of healthcare</h2>



<p>Regenerative biotherapeutics are projected to make up 10% of all health care interventions in the coming years. The summit will explore a possible future with tissue engineering, 3D bioprinting, cell therapies, gene and viral therapies, and cell-free interventions and how they might apply to medical practice areas such as orthopedics, cancer, cardiology, neurology and transplant. In addition, there will be sessions on training the future workforce to deliver these promising therapies to patients. The summit will bring together a global community of peers, thought leaders and organizations invested in regenerative therapies.</p>



<p>Registration for RegenBio Summit: Transforming Next-Gen Biotherapeutics will open in the coming weeks. Watch the <a href="https://ce.mayo.edu/content/regenbio-summit-transforming-next-gen-biotherapeutics#group-tabs-node-course-default1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">summit website</a> for announcements on keynote speakers, plenaries and fireside chats.</p>



<p>Attendees can earn continuing medical education credits.</p>



<p>###</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/save-the-date-regenbio-summit-transforming-next-gen-biotherapeutics/">Save the date! RegenBio Summit: Transforming Next-Gen Biotherapeutics</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/biotherapeutics-WF1385852_0143_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/biotherapeutics-WF1385852_0143_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#biomanufacturing]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#biomedical research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#biotherapeutics]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Dr. Julie Allickson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Dr. Saranya Wyles]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Mayo Clinic RegeBio Summit]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Regenerative medicine]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mcthumb >https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Resize-WF1385852_0143-150x150.jpg</mayoclinic:mcthumb >	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: How precise diagnosis of lymphoma offers patients best treatment options</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-precise-diagnosis-of-lymphoma-offers-patients-best-treatment-options/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Lisa Rimsza]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lymphoma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=379901</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Dr. Lisa Rimsza&#160;is a pathologist, director of the&#160;Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory&#160;and researcher with the&#160;Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center. Her research specializes in&#160;lymphoma,&#160;with a focus on developing tests for accurate patient diagnoses and assessing disease aggressiveness. Dr. Rimsza has made significant advances in this field of research.&#160;She says having a precise diagnosis allows physicians to [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-precise-diagnosis-of-lymphoma-offers-patients-best-treatment-options/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How precise diagnosis of lymphoma offers patients best treatment options</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/rimsza-lisa-m-m-d/bio-20185498?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Lisa Rimsza</a>&nbsp;is a pathologist, director of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/laboratory-medicine-pathology/overview/specialty-groups/laboratory-genetics/molecular-genetics-laboratory?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory</a>&nbsp;and researcher with the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>. Her research specializes in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lymphoma/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352642" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymphoma,</a>&nbsp;with a focus on developing tests for accurate patient diagnoses and assessing disease aggressiveness.</p>



<p>Dr. Rimsza has made significant advances in this field of research.&nbsp;She says having a precise diagnosis allows physicians to provide patients with the best possible treatment.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/M6ARKpwlWYU" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeM6ARKpwlWYU"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Why precision diagnosis is crucial for patients" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/M6ARKpwlWYU?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:05) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: “Mayo Clinic News Network.” Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Script-MCM-Precision-diagnosis.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"My lab focuses on&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-what-is-lymphoma/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymphoma</a>, which is a group of diseases and cancers that arise from the lymphatic systems," says Dr. Rimsza.<br><br>"We specialize in developing new tests to make sure we can get the most accurate diagnosis for the patient, and also figure out whether their disease is likely to be more or less aggressive," she says.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Lisa Rimsza, M.D., in the Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory" class="wp-image-380355" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Lisa Rimsza, M.D., in the Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory</figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>"We've been working with an interesting platform, or technology platform, which actually is able to use the tissue that is most commonly available from patient biopsies when a biopsy is taken out. It's put in formaldehyde and then in paraffin wax," she says. "We've been using a technology that actually is able to work with that tissue and get good information about genes and expression."</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Lisa Rimsza, M.D., and team in the Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory. Front row, from left: Charlie Kern, Colleen Ramsower and Dr. Rimsza. Back row, from left: Lindsey Armitage, Lee Wisner, Jon Ocal, Katie Zellner." class="wp-image-380360" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Lisa Rimsza, M.D., and team in the Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory. Front row, from left: Charlie Kern, Colleen Ramsower and Dr. Rimsza. Back row, from left: Lindsey Armitage, Lee Wisner, Jon Ocal, Katie Zellner.</figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>"It's absolutely important that the patient has the most accurate diagnosis as possible. And what we're doing is going through the most common types of lymphomas, and trying to build a series of assays that will answer several different diagnostic questions," says Dr. Rimsza.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Learn more about Dr. Rimsza's work:</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f4yhqxCY7mk" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Lisa Rimsza - 2023 Arizona Bioscience Research of the Year</a></li>



<li><a href="https://news.mayocliniclabs.com/2023/11/14/rna-test-identifies-large-b-cell-lymphoma-subtypes-lisa-rimsza-m-d/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">RNA test identifies large B-cell lymphoma subtypes</a></li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-understanding-treating-lymphoma/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Understanding, treating lymphoma</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-treating-leukemia-and-lymphoma/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Consumer Health: Treating leukemia and lymphoma</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-precise-diagnosis-of-lymphoma-offers-patients-best-treatment-options/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How precise diagnosis of lymphoma offers patients best treatment options</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-researcher-lab-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-microscope-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Lisa Rimsza]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[lymphoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss><!-- Static page delivered by HubScale -->