<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Research - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 14:01:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic&amp;#8217;s largest-ever exome study offers blueprint for biomedical breakthroughs&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-largest-ever-exome-study-offers-blueprint-for-biomedical-breakthroughs/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individualized Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=393581</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic's Center for Individualized Medicine has achieved a significant milestone with its Tapestry study, generating the clinic's largest-ever collection of exome data, which include genes that code for proteins — key to understanding health and disease.&amp;#160;&amp;#160; Led by Konstantinos Lazaridis, M.D., the study analyzed DNA from over 100,000 participants from diverse [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-largest-ever-exome-study-offers-blueprint-for-biomedical-breakthroughs/">Mayo Clinic&amp;#8217;s largest-ever exome study offers blueprint for biomedical breakthroughs&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/16x9-Tapestry-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-393916" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/16x9-Tapestry-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/16x9-Tapestry-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/16x9-Tapestry-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/16x9-Tapestry-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/16x9-Tapestry.png 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic's Center for Individualized Medicine</a> has achieved a significant milestone with its Tapestry study, generating the clinic's largest-ever collection of exome data, which include genes that code for proteins — key to understanding health and disease.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Led by <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine/about/director-insights" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Konstantinos Lazaridis, M.D.</a>, the <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/article/S0025-6196(24)00405-1/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> analyzed DNA from over 100,000 participants from diverse backgrounds, providing important insights into certain genetic predispositions to support personalized and proactive medical guidance.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The study focused on pathogenic (disease-causing) and likely pathogenic genetic variants linked to three specific conditions: hereditary breast and ovarian cancer syndrome, Lynch syndrome and familial hypercholesterolemia. Findings revealed that 1.9% of participants — nearly 2,000 people — carried at least one genetic variant that could increase their risk for these diseases. Notably, about 65% of those with a detected variant had no known prior personal or family history of the conditions.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>For many participants found to carry a genetic variant, the information has been life changing. Some have taken proactive steps, such as undergoing early screenings or preventive surgeries, which in some cases led to early cancer detection or reduced their risk of heart disease.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"The implications of the Tapestry study are monumental," says Dr. Lazaridis, the Carlson and Nelson Endowed Executive Director for the Center for Individualized Medicine. "As this study continues to inform and transform the practice of personalized medicine, it also sets a new standard for how large-scale medical research can be conducted in an increasingly digital and decentralized world."&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A monumental, decentralized effort&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</h2>



<p>Almost as significant as the study's outcome is how it was accomplished. The Tapestry study has been Mayo Clinic's largest decentralized trial, meaning it was conducted remotely through electronic contact, education and consent, with sample collection materials delivered to the participant’s home.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Launched in early 2020 during the COVID-19 pandemic, the project overcame unprecedented challenges, including securing consent from over 100,000 of the 1.3 million people invited to participate and mobilizing vast resources.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"It was a tremendous effort," Dr. Lazaridis recalls. "The engagement of such a number of participants in a relatively short time and during a pandemic showcased the trust and the dedication not only of our team but also of our patients."&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"We have also learned valuable lessons about some patients' decisions not to participate in Tapestry, which will be the focus of future publications," he added.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Participants' saliva samples from all three of Mayo Clinic's campuses — in Minnesota, Arizona and Florida — were used to extract DNA for exome sequencing. Exome sequencing analyzes nearly 20,000 genes that provide instructions for making proteins, which play many critical roles in the body. This is where most known disease-causing pathogenic or likely pathogenic genetic variants occur.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>This genetic exploration focused on hereditary conditions such as the BRCA1 and BRCA2 genes. According to the <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/breast-ovarian-cancer-hereditary/causes/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Centers for Disease Control</a>, women with these pathogenic genetic variants have a higher likelihood of developing breast and ovarian cancer, while men with BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutations face an increased risk of breast cancer and a potentially elevated risk of prostate cancer. The study also examined <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/colorectal-cancer-hereditary/about/about-lynch-syndrome.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lynch syndrome</a>, which raises the risk of colorectal and uterine cancers, and <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/colorectal-cancer-hereditary/about/lynch-syndrome.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">familial hypercholesterolemia</a>, known for its impact on early-onset heart disease, heart attacks and stroke.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>In addition to targeting these well-known conditions, the center’s experts are applying advanced analytics to the Tapestry data in collaboration with investigators across the enterprise. This work aims to explore lesser-known genetic variants that may contribute to a range of other health issues and diseases.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">From data to actionable insights</h2>



<p>These actionable insights are being integrated into participants' health records to guide future medical decisions, such as personalized interventions and regular health screenings to potentially improve patient outcomes.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Genetic counselors have played a crucial role in educating both patients and providers about the implications of their genetic data.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"Receiving genetic information can be difficult, but it also empowers patients to take proactive steps for their health," says Jennifer Kemppainen, CGC, supervisor of the Mayo Clinic Genetic Testing and Counseling unit and part of the Tapestry study team. "We help patients understand their results and educate them about screening and management options, so they feel prepared to meet with specialists and make informed decisions about their care."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A repository for tomorrow's cures</h2>



<p>Along with its impact on participants' healthcare, one of the most significant outcomes of the Tapestry study is the creation of a comprehensive genetic data repository. This extensive database has become a valuable resource for Mayo's scientific community, with 118 research requests submitted, that have resulted in the distribution of over 1.1 million exome datasets to interested investigators.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The data repository supports ongoing individual projects and fosters a collaborative environment where researchers can exchange ideas and findings to increase the potential for breakthroughs across different fields of medicine.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"What we've accomplished with the Tapestry study is a blueprint for future endeavors in medical science," Dr. Lazaridis says. "It demonstrates that through innovation, determination and collaboration, we can deeply advance our understanding of DNA function and eventually other bio-molecules like RNA, proteins and metabolites, turning them into novel diagnostic tools to improve health, prevent illness and even treat disease."&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Review the <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/article/S0025-6196(24)00405-1/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>###&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;amp;utm_medium=l&amp;amp;utm_content=content&amp;amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;amp;geo=national&amp;amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;amp;invsrc=other&amp;amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and to providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;amp;utm_medium=l&amp;amp;utm_content=content&amp;amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;amp;geo=national&amp;amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;amp;invsrc=other&amp;amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong>&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Susan Murphy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinics-largest-ever-exome-study-offers-blueprint-for-biomedical-breakthroughs/">Mayo Clinic&amp;#8217;s largest-ever exome study offers blueprint for biomedical breakthroughs&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/DNA_1x1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/16x9-Tapestry.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Mayo Clinic collaboration studies engineered stem cells for liver disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-mayo-clinic-collaboration-studies-engineered-stem-cells-for-liver-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Buckles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biotherapeutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[alcoholic hepatitis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Julie Allickson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HepaTx]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[liver cells]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Liver Disease]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=397189</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic's Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics is collaborating with the biotech firm HepaTx on an experimental therapy to regenerate tissue in patients with late-stage liver disease. This new technology takes mesenchymal stem cells from adipose (fat) tissue and coaxes them to function like hepatocyte (liver) cells. The purpose of the collaboration is to move this [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-mayo-clinic-collaboration-studies-engineered-stem-cells-for-liver-disease/">A Mayo Clinic collaboration studies engineered stem cells for liver disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/HepaTx-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-397254" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/HepaTx-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/HepaTx-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/HepaTx-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/HepaTx-16x9-1.jpg 1512w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic's <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</a> is collaborating with the biotech firm <a href="https://hepatx.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">HepaTx</a> on an experimental therapy to regenerate tissue in patients with late-stage liver disease. This new technology takes mesenchymal stem cells from adipose (fat) tissue and coaxes them to function like hepatocyte (liver) cells. The purpose of the collaboration is to move this technology to early clinical trials and study its effect on people with liver damage from alcohol-related hepatitis.</p>



<p>Mesenchymal stem cells are adult stem cells that have been well studied and have been shown to be safe in humans.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic brings to the collaboration expertise in regulatory affairs, clinical trials, product development and biomanufacturing. HepaTx brings a new cell technology directed toward a disease with few therapeutic options. Together they will work to advance the engineered liver cells to first-in-human safety studies.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Allickson-WF782604_0002-300x200.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-397191" style="width:300px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Allickson-WF782604_0002-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Allickson-WF782604_0002-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Allickson-WF782604_0002.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Julie Allickson, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Our goal in working with industry is to quickly bring a pipeline of cell-based therapeutics to patients with unmet needs," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/allickson-julie-g-ph-d/bio-20523656" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Julie Allickson, Ph.D.</a>, chief technology officer at Mayo Clinic's Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics. "This is a very exciting opportunity to pair Mayo Clinic's know-how with a new discovery aimed at improving the health, lives and therapeutic outcomes for patients."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A new cell-based therapy for liver disease</strong></h2>



<p>Excessive alcohol use damages and eventually destroys liver cells, causing inflammation that can lead to abdominal pain, scarring and liver failure. Alcoholic hepatitis is one type of chronic liver disease that affects 20-40% of heavy drinkers.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="179" height="179" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Hepatx-Liver-Tech-2024_1x1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-397320" style="width:277px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Hepatx-Liver-Tech-2024_1x1.jpg 179w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Hepatx-Liver-Tech-2024_1x1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 179px) 100vw, 179px" /></figure></div>


<p>In the early stage of liver disease, treatment is aimed at managing the symptoms through a combination of small molecule drugs and quitting drinking. However, in later stages, cell and tissue damage are often irreversible. People with end-stage liver disease may need an organ transplant to survive.</p>



<p>The engineered liver cell technology from HepaTx is so new that it has never been manufactured on a large scale for patients. That's where the Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics process development experts come in. They develop standard operating procedures —a blueprint of sorts — for biomanufacturing in Mayo Clinic's state-of-the-art current Good Manufacturing Practice (cGMP) facilities. CGMP refers to a set of practices that ensures a new therapy meets strict quality control and quality assurance standards for medicines made from living sources such as cells.</p>



<p>"We engage with investigators at proof of concept. We guide the technology through process development to identify any gaps in safety that could delay regulatory approval for a clinical trial," says Dr. Allickson. "Our biomanufacturing infrastructure is based on industry best practices, which positions us well to work with outside collaborators to advance a new therapy toward market approval for patients."</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic will lead the early clinical trials in which patients with alcohol-related hepatitis will be infused with the engineered liver cells. The research will focus on safety and effectiveness of this cell replacement therapy in repairing late stage disease.</p>



<p>Working with industry collaborators that are aligned with Mayo Clinic values is a strategic priority for the Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic has a financial interest in the technology referenced in this article. Mayo Clinic will use any revenue it receives to support its not-for-profit mission in patient care, education and research.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p>Related stories:</p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-secures-arpa-h-award-to-build-a-living-pharmacy-within-the-body-for-inflammatory-disease/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic secures ARPA-H award to build a living pharmacy within the body for inflammatory disease</a></p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/innovation-centers-spur-new-biotherapeutics-for-patients/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Innovation centers spur new biotherapeutics for patients</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-mayo-clinic-collaboration-studies-engineered-stem-cells-for-liver-disease/">A Mayo Clinic collaboration studies engineered stem cells for liver disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/HepaTx-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/HepaTx-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[alcoholic hepatitis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Julie Allickson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[HepaTx]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[liver cells]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Liver Disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Thanksgiving is the perfect time to share family health history&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/why-thanksgiving-is-the-perfect-time-to-share-family-health-history/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 16:37:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individualized Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. John Presutti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Joseph Murray]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Niloy Jewel Samadder]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=396916</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>As you gather around the table this Thanksgiving to share meals, stories and traditions, consider taking a moment to talk about something that could save lives: your family's health history.&amp;#160;&amp;#160; Thanksgiving Day is recognized as Family Health History Day, a national call to raise awareness of inherited health risks. Mayo Clinic experts are encouraging families [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/why-thanksgiving-is-the-perfect-time-to-share-family-health-history/">Why Thanksgiving is the perfect time to share family health history&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DNA7-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-396933" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DNA7-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DNA7-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DNA7-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DNA7-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DNA7.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>As you gather around the table this Thanksgiving to share meals, stories and traditions, consider taking a moment to talk about something that could save lives: your family's health history.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Thanksgiving Day is recognized as <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/family-health-history/about/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Family Health History Day</a>, a national call to raise awareness of inherited health risks. Mayo Clinic experts are encouraging families to use the holiday to identify these risks and take proactive steps toward prevention.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"Hereditary conditions range from autoimmune disorders like celiac disease to cancers tied to genetic mutations," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/murray-joseph-a-m-d/bio-20053816" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Joseph Murray, M.D.</a>, a gastroenterologist at Mayo Clinic with over 30 years of expertise in treating complex digestive diseases. "Thanksgiving provides a unique opportunity to notice these patterns in your family's health and start conversations that could benefit generations to come."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Hereditary links to digestive conditions</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/digestive-system2-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-397056" style="width:373px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/digestive-system2-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/digestive-system2-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/digestive-system2-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/digestive-system2-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/digestive-system2-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p>Two conditions Dr. Murray highlights, celiac disease and eosinophilic esophagitis, can have hereditary components but are not always linked to family history.</p>



<p>"Food is central to Thanksgiving, so it's a perfect time to notice who's avoiding certain dishes," Dr. Murray says. "If someone skips bread or mentions swallowing difficulties, it could point to something hereditary."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/celiac-disease/care-at-mayo-clinic/mac-20352230?customer_id=199-030-3372&amp;amp;mc_id=google&amp;amp;campaign=16975831874&amp;amp;geo=9019562&amp;amp;kw=celiac%20disease%20mayo%20clinic&amp;amp;ad=593694771501&amp;amp;network=g&amp;amp;sitetarget=&amp;amp;adgroup=135482631493&amp;amp;extension=&amp;amp;target=kwd-346724094689&amp;amp;matchtype=e&amp;amp;device=c&amp;amp;account=1990303372&amp;amp;invsrc=consult&amp;amp;placementsite=minnesota&amp;amp;gclid=Cj0KCQiA6Ou5BhCrARIsAPoTxrCZKg3OkoT2wsT0T2_zMoR3Z8CC_g4emqPt3PljXSLedwpdaLHIbDYaAlrCEALw_wcB" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Celiac disease</a>, an autoimmune condition triggered by gluten, can cause symptoms like diarrhea, abdominal pain, bloating, weight loss, anemia, fatigue, skin rashes, mouth ulcers and joint pain. It can be diagnosed at any age and presents in over 300 ways, making testing crucial — especially for those with close relatives at higher risk.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"For siblings, the risk is as high as 20%," Dr. Murray says. "Accurate diagnosis is key, because eliminating gluten without testing can mask other health issues, such as irritable bowel syndrome or lactose intolerance, and delay treatment."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Murray says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/eosinophilic-esophagitis/care-at-mayo-clinic/mac-20372209?customer_id=199-030-3372&amp;amp;mc_id=google&amp;amp;campaign=12364095989&amp;amp;geo=9019562&amp;amp;kw=eosinophilic%20esophagitis%20mayo%20clinic&amp;amp;ad=499362077185&amp;amp;network=g&amp;amp;sitetarget=&amp;amp;adgroup=123190878452&amp;amp;extension=&amp;amp;target=kwd-838282939870&amp;amp;matchtype=e&amp;amp;device=c&amp;amp;account=1990303372&amp;amp;invsrc=consult&amp;amp;placementsite=minnesota&amp;amp;gclid=Cj0KCQiA6Ou5BhCrARIsAPoTxrAfoV1y7F9smeY6Bfw7FKwjjSi8juZXfAwfHlzPuIjmq1UxhYMvOv8aAo5aEALw_wcB" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">eosinophilic esophagitis</a> is another condition to be aware of. It involves inflammation of the esophagus that leads to difficulty swallowing or food impaction. In children, symptoms can include vomiting, avoiding certain foods or difficulty gaining weight. In adults, it typically presents as difficulty swallowing or the sensation of food getting stuck, which can sometimes require emergency medical attention. Available treatment options include anti-inflammatory medications and immune-targeted therapies.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Turning genomics into action</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/genomics10-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-397057" style="width:380px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/genomics10-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/genomics10-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/genomics10-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/genomics10-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/genomics10-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p>Family health history also plays a vital role in cancer and heart disease prevention, says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/presutti-r-john-d-o-faafp/bio-20053922?mc_id=us&amp;amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;amp;utm_medium=l&amp;amp;utm_content=content&amp;amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;amp;geo=national&amp;amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;amp;invsrc=other&amp;amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">John Presutti, D.O.</a>, a family medicine physician and the Cecilia and Dan Carmichael Family Associate Director for the Center for Individualized Medicine at Mayo Clinic in Florida. In his dual role, Dr. Presutti combines his expertise in primary care with advances in genomics to help patients uncover hereditary risks and take proactive steps.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Presutti also leads Mayo Clinic's pilot program integrating genomic data into clinical care. This initiative offers genomic screening for actionable genetic markers associated with hereditary breast and ovarian cancer syndrome, Lynch syndrome and familial hypercholesterolemia. These markers can inform preemptive interventions and allow for personalized care.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"Approximately 10% of cancers are inherited," Dr. Presutti says. "Uncovering hidden genetic mutations through family discussions allows us to screen patients earlier and potentially save lives."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Hereditary breast and ovarian cancer syndrome is linked to mutations in the BRCA1 and BRCA2 genes. Mutations in BRCA1 can lead to a 60% lifetime risk of developing breast cancer and a 40% risk of having ovarian cancer, among other cancers. BRCA2 mutations increase the risk of developing breast cancer to 50% and ovarian cancer to 20%, with additional risks for prostate and pancreatic cancers in males.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Lynch syndrome is associated with an 80% lifetime risk of developing <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353669" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colorectal cancer</a> and 50% risk of uterine/endometrial cancer. Familial hypercholesterolemia, a genetic disorder that causes dangerously high cholesterol levels, significantly increases the risk of early heart disease and stroke if left untreated.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>&amp;nbsp;Dr. Presutti encourages families to ask questions such as:&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Have any family members had cancer or heart disease?&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>At what age were they diagnosed?&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Are there patterns of chronic illnesses or early deaths in the family?&amp;nbsp;</li>



<li></li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Detecting early-onset GI cancers</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="573" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/colorectal-cancer3-1024x573.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-397058" style="width:408px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/colorectal-cancer3-1024x573.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/colorectal-cancer3-300x168.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/colorectal-cancer3-768x429.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/colorectal-cancer3-1536x859.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/colorectal-cancer3-2048x1145.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p>For younger people, family health history can be especially important as rates of gastrointestinal (GI) cancers are on the rise among people under age 55. Mayo Clinic's Early Onset and Hereditary Gastrointestinal Cancers Program aims to address this growing concern, says Niloy Jewel Samadder, M.D., a Mayo Clinic gastroenterologist and cancer geneticist.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"The rise in young-onset gastrointestinal cancers is a pressing health issue," Dr. Samadder says. "Our goal is to put patients at the center of a collaborative framework of experts working seamlessly together."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Launched in 2024, the program integrates gastroenterology, oncology, surgery, pathology and genetics to provide comprehensive, patient-centered care. Translational discoveries, such as immunology studies and a multi-omics approach, are also part of the program, helping to tailor treatments to a patient's unique biological profile.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"This multidisciplinary approach doesn't just address cancer — it uncovers hereditary risks that can guide care for families," Dr. Samadder explains. "It's about creating a roadmap for prevention and better outcomes."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A tradition that saves lives</strong>&amp;nbsp;</h2>



<p>If you discover something significant about your family health history this Thanksgiving, take action:&amp;nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Talk to your primary care provider about screening or preventive measures.&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Encourage family members to discuss shared health risks with their doctors.&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Learn about lifestyle changes or early interventions that could lower your risk.&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Stay proactive by keeping your health records updated and sharing them with relatives.&amp;nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>"Don't just talk about your family health history," Dr. Presutti says. "Act on it. It could save your life."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>For more information, visit <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/family-health-history/about/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CDC Family Health History.</a>&amp;nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/why-thanksgiving-is-the-perfect-time-to-share-family-health-history/">Why Thanksgiving is the perfect time to share family health history&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/1x1-DNA.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DNA7.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. John Presutti]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Joseph Murray]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Niloy Jewel Samadder]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers develop new AI tools to reveal seizure hotspots, improve patient care</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-new-ai-tools-to-reveal-seizure-hotspots-improve-patient-care/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Colette Gallagher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AI and Digital Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nuri Ince]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=397013</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have developed new artificial intelligence (AI)-based tools to pinpoint specific regions of the brain with seizure hotspots more quickly and accurately in patients with drug-resistant epilepsy. Their study, published in Nature Communications Medicine, highlights the potential of AI to revolutionize epilepsy treatment by interpreting brain waves during electrode implantation surgery. This transformative [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-new-ai-tools-to-reveal-seizure-hotspots-improve-patient-care/">Mayo Clinic researchers develop new AI tools to reveal seizure hotspots, improve patient care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/BrainWaves-Getty16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Illustration of brain waves. Getty Images" class="wp-image-397015" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/BrainWaves-Getty16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/BrainWaves-Getty16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/BrainWaves-Getty16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/BrainWaves-Getty16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/BrainWaves-Getty16x9.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Getty Images</figcaption></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have developed new artificial intelligence (AI)-based tools to pinpoint specific regions of the brain with seizure hotspots more quickly and accurately in patients with drug-resistant epilepsy. Their <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s43856-024-00654-0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>, published in Nature Communications Medicine, highlights the potential of AI to revolutionize epilepsy treatment by interpreting brain waves during electrode implantation surgery. This transformative approach could significantly reduce the time patients spend in the hospital, accelerating the identification and removal of seizure-generating brain regions.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="640" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Ince-Nuri-F._30246090_20230814.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-397019" style="width:189px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Ince-Nuri-F._30246090_20230814.jpg 640w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Ince-Nuri-F._30246090_20230814-240x300.jpg 240w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Nuri Ince, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"This innovative approach could enable more rapid and accurate identification of seizure-generating areas during stereo-electroencephalography (EEG) implantation surgery, potentially reducing the cost and risks of prolonged monitoring," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/ince-nuri-f-ph-d/bio-20562159" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nuri Ince, Ph.D.</a>, senior author of the study and a consultant in the Mayo Clinic Department of Neurologic Surgery.</p>



<p>Drug-resistant epilepsy often requires surgical removal of the seizure-causing brain tissue. A first step in that treatment is typically a surgery that involves implanting electrodes in the brain and monitoring neural activity for several days or weeks to identify the location of the seizures.</p>



<p>While physicians can detect high-frequency brain waves immediately after electrode implantation, doing so is challenging due to their short duration and low amplitude, as well as environmental noise mimicking pathological events. To detect high-frequency brain waves, they rely on a manual data analysis process that includes visual inspection and artifact rejection to remove unwanted or corrupted data points. This process is labor-intensive and susceptible to error.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Faster, more accurate diagnosis</strong></h2>



<p>The researchers developed an AI algorithm that helps pinpoint seizure hotspots, allowing clinicians to make quicker, more accurate decisions about how to proceed.</p>



<p>"We created an AI tool that automatically analyzes EEG recordings during brain surgeries and accurately identifies true high-frequency brain waves associated with the areas of the brain thought to be the source of seizures while eliminating fake high brain waves caused by artifacts," explains Dr. Ince.</p>



<p>Accurately identifying these patterns in EEG recordings helps the healthcare team rapidly find the area of the brain where the seizure originates, enabling the next step: surgery for targeted tissue removal, which is critical for achieving seizure freedom. A faster identification process also reduces the need for prolonged monitoring after electrode implantation. This is essential for minimizing risks, such as infections, which are five times more likely to occur in children than in adults during prolonged stays in epilepsy monitoring units.</p>



<p>The group's future work will focus on transforming the framework into a fully online, real-time system that can interpret the brain waves during electrode implantation surgery and provide feedback to the clinical team regarding the location of the epileptic brain tissue.</p>



<p>"This research could potentially lead to a future where surgical interventions are tailored to individual patients based on their unique brain wave patterns," says Dr. Ince.</p>



<p>&amp;nbsp;Review the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s43856-024-00654-0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p><a id="_msocom_1"></a></p>



<p><a id="_msocom_2"></a></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-new-ai-tools-to-reveal-seizure-hotspots-improve-patient-care/">Mayo Clinic researchers develop new AI tools to reveal seizure hotspots, improve patient care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/BrainWaves-Getty1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/BrainWaves-Getty16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nuri Ince]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo researchers develop AI-enhanced strategy to personalize medication alerts</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-researchers-develop-ai-enhanced-strategy-to-personalize-medication-alerts/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individualized Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Arjun Athreya]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=396797</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Electronic health records are increasingly including technology-aided predictions of how patients may respond to specific medications, known as pharmacogenomic alerts. Two Mayo Clinic Ph.D. candidates are exploring how artificial intelligence (AI) can be used to make these alerts more actionable and less intrusive for clinicians, who can suffer from alert overload. In a new study, [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-researchers-develop-ai-enhanced-strategy-to-personalize-medication-alerts/">Mayo researchers develop AI-enhanced strategy to personalize medication alerts</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-PGX-RESEARCH3-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-396799" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-PGX-RESEARCH3-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-PGX-RESEARCH3-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-PGX-RESEARCH3-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-PGX-RESEARCH3-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-PGX-RESEARCH3.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Jean Marrero-Polanco (left ) and Caroline Grant (right) collaborate on concepts for their study. Courtesy of Marrero-Polanco and Grant.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Electronic health records are increasingly including technology-aided predictions of how patients may respond to specific medications, known as pharmacogenomic alerts. Two Mayo Clinic Ph.D. candidates are exploring how artificial intelligence (AI) can be used to make these alerts more actionable and less intrusive for clinicians, who can suffer from alert overload.</p>



<p>In a new <a href="https://ascpt.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cts.70044">study,</a> Ph.D. candidates Caroline Grant and Jean Marrero-Polanco, under the mentorship of lead author <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/athreya-arjun-p-ph-d-m-s/bio-20473903">Arjun Athreya, Ph.D.</a>, found that clinicians generally prefer concise, individualized alerts that use patient-specific genomic data to help personalize their care, rather than more generic or detailed alerts.</p>



<p>Their <a href="https://ascpt.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cts.70044">study</a> is published in Clinical and Translational Science. Both students are doctoral candidates in the Molecular Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics program at the Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences.</p>



<p>"AI has the potential to greatly enhance how we deliver care by providing vital support with enhanced information to clinicians and researchers, but we need to know barriers of technology use and factors that may improve human-technology interaction," says Dr. Athreya, a computer scientist at the Mayo Clinic Department of Molecular Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. "Our goal is to develop digital tools that are technically robust, highly usable and augment clinicians' expertise to ensure patients receive the most effective, personalized care."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Tailoring alerts to clinician experience and specialty</strong></h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DR-ATHREYA-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-396800" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DR-ATHREYA-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DR-ATHREYA-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DR-ATHREYA-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DR-ATHREYA-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-DR-ATHREYA.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Caroline Grant (left), Jean Marrero-Polanco (center), and Dr. Arjun Athreya (right) discuss their pharmacogenomics research. Photo courtesy of Marrero-Polanco and Grant.</figcaption></figure>



<p>For the study — led by Department of Molecular Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics in collaboration with the Department of Psychiatry and Psychology, Internal Medicine and Family Medicine — the team surveyed 305 clinicians from a variety of backgrounds across Mayo Clinic sites in Minnesota, Arizona and Florida, and the Mayo Clinic Health System. Participants hailed from specialty practices including psychiatry, internal medicine and family medicine and included those working in both large urban hospitals and in small rural clinics. This diversity helped the researchers understand how different settings, specialties and experience levels influenced what doctors found most useful.</p>



<p>To analyze clinician preferences, the research team used advanced AI techniques, including natural language processing, which helps computers interpret human language, and machine learning, which allows computers to learn from data. These tools allowed the researchers to efficiently process large volumes of survey data and uncover insights that otherwise would have been difficult to detect.</p>



<p>The study focused on pharmacogenomic alerts in the context of treating major depressive disorder with the antidepressant citalopram. Clinicians were presented with three types of alerts:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Generic alert: Provides standard dosage recommendations without patient-specific data.</li>



<li>Concise, individualized alert: Displays AI-derived predictions of drug efficacy based on a patient’s clinical and genomic markers.</li>



<li>Detailed, individualized alert: Includes in-depth information on the specific genes and markers involved in the AI-derived predictions of drug efficacy.</li>
</ul>



<p>Overall, the clinicians favored the concise, individualized alerts. In contrast, they gave the generic alerts, which resemble current electronic health record alerts for citalopram, failing grades.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Implications for reducing burnout and enhancing care</strong></h2>



<p>The study emphasizes the importance of integrating patient-specific data and offering easy access to detailed information via hyperlinks. The findings also suggest that preferences for alert design varied by clinician specialty and experience. For example, experienced psychiatrists preferred detailed genetic profiles, while early-career internal medicine providers favored more concise alerts.</p>



<p>"Finding the right balance of detail is crucial," says Caroline Grant, first author. "Our study indicates that a one-size-fits-all approach to alerts is not effective. We need to consider who is reading the alert and what they need in that moment."</p>



<p>Grant's research is centered on leveraging AI and large biological data sets to identify biomarkers that predict treatment outcomes. Her long-term goal is to continue developing precision medicine tools that can be applied in both research and clinical settings.</p>



<p>Grant's co-first author, Jean Marrero-Polanco, notes patients will not be the only ones to benefit from the types of improvements suggested in the study.</p>



<p>"By designing drug alerts based on clinician preferences, we're not just supporting personalized medicine for patients — we're potentially enhancing the well-being of clinicians, too," he says, as electronic health record usability has associated with physician burnout.</p>



<p>Born and raised in Puerto Rico, Marrero-Polanco's passion for improving mental health outcomes is deeply personal. He is driven by the need for quality studies on mental health disparities, particularly within underserved communities. His research focuses on developing AI-driven tools that support clinicians in making better decisions, with the long-term goal of leading independent research in academia to advance AI in healthcare.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Next step: Real-world testing</strong></h2>



<p>The next phase of this research will involve testing these refined alerts in actual clinical settings to determine their effect on clinician burnout and patient outcomes. The team plans to develop educational resources to help clinicians understand these AI-derived predictions and use these tools in patient care.</p>



<p>The study was funded by the National Science Foundation. Co-principal investigators include Richard Sharp, Ph.D., director of Mayo Clinic's Biomedical Ethics Research Program; Paul Croarkin, D.O., director of Mayo Clinic’s Children’s Research; Liewei Wang, M.D., Ph.D., director of Mayo Clinic’s Pharmacogenomics Program; Liselotte Dyrbye, M.D., of the Colorado School of Public Health; and William Bobo, M.D., of the Florida State University College of Medicine.</p>



<p>Review the <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC11473792/">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-researchers-develop-ai-enhanced-strategy-to-personalize-medication-alerts/">Mayo researchers develop AI-enhanced strategy to personalize medication alerts</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/1x1-pgx3.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-PGX-RESEARCH3-1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Arjun Athreya]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Innovative blood analysis technique reveals insights into giant cell arteritis&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/innovative-blood-analysis-technique-reveals-insights-into-giant-cell-arteritis/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individualized Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jaeyun Sung]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Kenneth Warrington]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395686</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have identified key protein patterns in the blood that could improve how doctors diagnose and monitor giant cell arteritis, a chronic autoimmune disease that causes inflammation in blood vessels. The condition often affects arteries in the head and can lead to vision loss or stroke if untreated. The new research, led by [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/innovative-blood-analysis-technique-reveals-insights-into-giant-cell-arteritis/">Innovative blood analysis technique reveals insights into giant cell arteritis&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/16x9-blood3-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-395692" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/16x9-blood3-1024x576.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/16x9-blood3-300x169.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/16x9-blood3-768x432.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/16x9-blood3-1536x864.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/16x9-blood3.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have identified key protein patterns in the blood that could improve how doctors diagnose and monitor <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/giant-cell-arteritis/symptoms-causes/syc-20372758">giant cell arteritis</a>, a chronic autoimmune disease that causes inflammation in blood vessels. The condition often affects arteries in the head and can lead to vision loss or stroke if untreated.</p>



<p>The new research, led by <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/sung-jaeyun-ph-d/bio-20320110" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jaeyun Sung, Ph.D.</a>, and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/warrington-kenneth-j-m-d/bio-00027302" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kenneth Warrington, M.D.</a>, lays the groundwork for more accurate diagnosis and personalized treatment approaches.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>In the <a href="https://ard.bmj.com/content/early/2024/08/16/ard-2024-225868.info" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>, published in Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases, researchers analyzed more than 7,000 proteins from blood samples collected from patients with giant cell arteritis and healthy people. This large-scale analysis, known as proteomics, allows scientists to study the full range of proteins in a sample and identify distinct patterns associated with disease activity. The researchers used these patterns to develop machine learning models that helped them distinguish between active and remission states with over 95% accuracy.&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="534" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/WF4998388_0352-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396792" style="width:356px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/WF4998388_0352-1.jpg 534w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/WF4998388_0352-1-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 534px) 100vw, 534px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Jaeyun Sung, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"In our study, we used high-throughput proteomics to help us analyze thousands of proteins simultaneously," says Dr. Sung, a computational biologist at <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine's</a> Microbiomics Program. "We also applied machine learning to help us uncover patterns within these large datasets. This approach has provided us with deeper insights into the biology of giant cell arteritis and brings us closer to developing biomarker panels that could improve diagnosis and treatment."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Sung specializes in developing computational models that connect biological processes to health outcomes. His expertise lies in multi-omics, which integrates data from proteins, genes and other biological markers to uncover patterns in chronic diseases. He is dedicated to turning these discoveries into practical tools that clinicians can use to improve patient care. He recently developed a computational tool to help specialists <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-researchers-develop-tool-that-measures-health-of-a-persons-gut-microbiome/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">analyze the gut microbiome</a> to provide insights into overall well-being.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Precision through proteomics</strong></h2>



<p>Symptoms of giant cell arteritis, such as headaches, jaw pain and fatigue, overlap with many other conditions, making an accurate diagnosis challenging. The disease primarily affects older adults and can lead to serious complications if not treated promptly. Doctors typically rely on common inflammation tests, but they lack the specific information to confirm a diagnosis of giant cell arteritis. As a result, many patients experience delays in receiving treatment.&amp;nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="667" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Warrington-Kenneth-J._12405400_202105030323-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396793" style="width:339px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Warrington-Kenneth-J._12405400_202105030323-1.jpg 667w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Warrington-Kenneth-J._12405400_202105030323-1-250x300.jpg 250w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 667px) 100vw, 667px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Kenneth Warrington, M.D.,</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Using proteomics, the researchers gained crucial insights into when the disease is active and when it’s in remission. This knowledge helps doctors not only determine when to begin treatment but also when it may be safe to pause medication.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"This precision enables us to refine treatment decisions," says Dr. Warrington, a rheumatologist and Director of the Vasculitis Clinic in the Division of Rheumatology in the Department of Internal Medicine. "Recognizing when a patient's disease is in remission allows us to reduce reliance on certain medications, which can minimize side effects and improve overall patient care."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Warrington's research focuses on identifying diagnostic biomarkers and understanding the molecular mechanisms behind vasculitis conditions. With extensive experience in clinical trials, he is dedicated to translating his findings into therapies that improve patient outcomes.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Next steps in research</strong></h2>



<p>The researchers plan to next test these protein markers in larger, more diverse patient groups to ensure the findings are reliable. They also aim to compare the results with other inflammatory diseases to confirm the markers' specificity to giant cell arteritis. Future research will explore other biological data, such as gene expression activity, to further enhance our understanding of the disease.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Review the <a href="https://ard.bmj.com/content/early/2024/08/16/ard-2024-225868.info" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&amp;nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/innovative-blood-analysis-technique-reveals-insights-into-giant-cell-arteritis/">Innovative blood analysis technique reveals insights into giant cell arteritis&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/1x1-blood11-template.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9blood11-template.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jaeyun Sung]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Kenneth Warrington]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>(VIDEO) Focus on hope: Brescia&amp;#8217;s Story</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-focus-on-hope-brescias-story/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 17:48:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer survivor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health &amp; Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Healthcare Delivery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#cancersupportgroup]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[American Cancer Society]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cancer cures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lymphoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=396442</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>At 20 years old, Brescia Dover was ready to take on the world. She was on her way to achieving her dream of being a professional photographer. Everything was going according to plan when her dream came to a halt. Brescia was diagnosed with cancer. With her plans for her future pushed aside, Brescia's focus [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-focus-on-hope-brescias-story/">(VIDEO) Focus on hope: Brescia&amp;#8217;s Story</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-in-Italy-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396534" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-in-Italy-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-in-Italy-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-in-Italy-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-in-Italy-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-in-Italy-16x9-1-2048x1153.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Brescia Dover studying abroad in Italy </strong><br><strong>Photo courtesy: Brescia Dover</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>At 20 years old, Brescia Dover was ready to take on the world. </p>



<p>She was on her way to achieving her dream of being a professional photographer.</p>



<p>Everything was going according to plan when her dream came to a halt. Brescia was diagnosed with cancer. With her plans for her future pushed aside, Brescia's focus was now on her health and hope.</p>



<p>It's an unexpected chapter facing an increasing number of adolescents and young adults diagnosed with cancer.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K2wUmw6h0wQ" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Focus on hope: Brescia's Story</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeK2wUmw6h0wQ"  title="Focus on hope: Brescia&amp;#039;s Story" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/K2wUmw6h0wQ?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (2:31) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the </strong><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/FOCUS-ON-HOPE-BRESCIAS-STORY-FINAL-VIDEO-SCRIPT.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>script.</strong></a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Brescia's dream</strong></h2>



<p>At 4 years old, it was clear Brescia Dover had a flare for creativity. She readily admits she was never one to miss an opportunity to play dress-up, draw pictures, or tell a story.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-center-align-caption">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-as-a-little-girl-768x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396517" style="width:570px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-as-a-little-girl-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-as-a-little-girl-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-as-a-little-girl-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-as-a-little-girl-1536x2048.jpg 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">           <strong>Brescia at 4 years old                 </strong><br><strong>Photo courtesy: Brescia Dover</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Being creative has always been at the core of what I do," she says. Early on she developed a love for photography and videography. Brescia's dream was to pursue a career that allowed her to put her creative energy to work.</p>



<p>After high school Brescia's passion led her to college to study film and media production. She even traveled to Italy to study abroad. After her Italian adventure, Brescia returned to the U.S. to finish college. First, she went to her doctor for her annual checkup.</p>



<p>"I lived a really healthy, balanced lifestyle," says Brescia. "My doctor found swelling on the side of my neck. I hadn't noticed the swelling and didn't have any symptoms." Brescia was sent for an ultrasound followed by a surgical biopsy.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="903" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-headshot-with-lump-1024x903.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396519" style="width:600px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-headshot-with-lump-1024x903.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-headshot-with-lump-300x265.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-headshot-with-lump-768x678.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-headshot-with-lump-1536x1355.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-headshot-with-lump.jpg 1682w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Looking back at this photo taken before her cancer diagnosis, Brescia says she can see the swelling on the left side of her neck <br>Photo courtesy: Brescia Dover</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The diagnosis - cancer</strong></h2>



<p>The surgical biopsy revealed Brescia had <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-what-is-lymphoma/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hodgkin lymphoma</a>, a rare type of <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-new-blood-cancer-treatment-options-with-chimeric-antigen-receptor-t-cell-therapy/">blood cancer</a>. "Being diagnosed with cancer at 20 years old was so scary and I wouldn't wish that on any 20-year-old," says Brescia. "I think about the young version of me who just found out she had cancer, and I just wish I could give her a hug."</p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-understanding-treating-lymphoma/">Hodgkin lymphoma</a> is a type of cancer that begins in the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-to-maintain-a-healthy-immune-system/">lymphatic system</a>, which is part of the immune system. Brescia says the news came as a shock because she felt healthy and had no family history of cancer. "It felt like there was something I could have done to prevent it, but I learned that there's nothing I could have done," says Brescia.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Being a young adult with cancer</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-post-op-biopsy-768x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396443" style="width:293px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-post-op-biopsy-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-post-op-biopsy-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-post-op-biopsy-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-post-op-biopsy-1536x2048.jpg 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Brescia at Mayo Clinic <br>Photo courtesy: Brescia Dover</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p></p>



<p>"When I was going through college and diagnosed with cancer it was not what I was expecting," says Brescia. "Being a young adult with cancer was very hard and challenging. It is scary and can be very frightening."</p>



<p>At 20 years old, Brescia falls into a group of patients referred to as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/adolescent-young-adult-cancer-program/sections/overview/ovc-20564751" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">adolescents and young adults with cancer</a>. AYA patients are between the ages of 15 and 39. Experts says AYA patients face a distinct set of challenges.</p>



<p>"One of the reasons this age group is so important is based on their life stage; the things they uniquely face, like body image, disruption in school and work, financial challenges, feeling isolation," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/rosenthal-allison-c-d-o/bio-20178616" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Allison Rosenthal</a>, with the Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Doctor and cancer survivor</strong></h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="938" height="527" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Dr-Rosenthal-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-393253" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Dr-Rosenthal-16x9-1.jpg 938w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Dr-Rosenthal-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/08/Dr-Rosenthal-16x9-1-768x431.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 938px) 100vw, 938px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Dr. Allison Rosenthal is medical director of Mayo Clinic's Adolescent and Young Adult Cancer Program</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>Dr. Rosenthal knows firsthand the challenges AYA patients face. She was diagnosed with <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/car-t-cell-therapy-restores-hope-for-leukemia-patient/">leukemia</a> during medical school. "I had leukemia in medical school. There were a lot of missed opportunities in my care to recognize the issues that I might face as a 24-year-old woman," explains Dr. Rosenthal.</p>



<p>Putting her experience into action, Dr. Rosenthal championed <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/adolescent-young-adult-cancer-program/sections/overview/ovc-20564751" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic's Adolescent and Young Adults with Cancer program</a>. The program is tailored to meet the unique needs of AYA patients to include medical care, fertility concerns, social and relationship issues, school and work concerns, and the personal and emotional impact of cancer in this age group.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p><strong>"I want the patients I care for to feel like they are comprehensively care for and that somebody understands that this is different."</strong></p><cite>-Dr. Allison Rosenthal, director, Mayo Clinic Adolescent and Young Adult Cancer Program</cite></blockquote></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="863" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-and-Dr.-Rosenthal-1-1024x863.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396524" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-and-Dr.-Rosenthal-1-1024x863.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-and-Dr.-Rosenthal-1-300x253.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-and-Dr.-Rosenthal-1-768x647.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-and-Dr.-Rosenthal-1-1536x1294.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-and-Dr.-Rosenthal-1-2048x1726.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Brescia and her doctor, Allison Rosenthal <br>Photo courtesy: Brescia Dover</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>Brescia underwent about four months of chemotherapy treatment under the care of Dr. Rosenthal. "She did a beautiful job of explaining to me what the process was going to look like and what my treatment plan was going to look like. Because I'm so young, she walked me through the whole process," says Brescia. </p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Cancer-free and focused on the future</strong></h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="946" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-celebrates-five-year-cancer-free-1024x946.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396530" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-celebrates-five-year-cancer-free-1024x946.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-celebrates-five-year-cancer-free-300x277.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-celebrates-five-year-cancer-free-768x709.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-celebrates-five-year-cancer-free-1536x1419.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-celebrates-five-year-cancer-free-2048x1892.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Photo courtesy: Brescia Dover</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>After her cancer treatments, Brescia returned to college and got her degree. She the started her own marketing agency providing social media management, videography, photography, and brand development with her personal creative touch. She also celebrated her five-year anniversary of being cancer-free.</p>



<p>"I also have a podcast called the Checkered Jaguar where I get to have incredible conversations with people, share their stories and connect people who may be going through similar challenges that I went through," says Brescia. "We're all in this journey together and just being open and vulnerable with my journey, as challenging as it may be, I feel like it connects me to people all around the world."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="861" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Checkered-jaguar-861x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396515" style="width:608px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Checkered-jaguar-861x1024.jpg 861w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Checkered-jaguar-252x300.jpg 252w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Checkered-jaguar-768x914.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Checkered-jaguar.jpg 1024w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 861px) 100vw, 861px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Brescia is five years cancer-free and owns her own marketing agency<br>Photo courtesy: Brescia Dover</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p>"<strong>To anyone in their 20s diagnosed with cancer, know that you are never alone. There is light at the end of the tunnel and there is hope</strong>."</p><cite>-Brescia dover, cancer survivor</cite></blockquote></figure>



<p><strong><em>If you are someone you know would like to learn more about the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/adolescent-young-adult-cancer-program/sections/overview/ovc-20564751">Mayo Clinic Adolescent and Young Adults with Cancer Program please click this link</a> or email us at arzayacancerprg@mayo.edu. You can also reach us at 480-574-1341.</em></strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Related articles</strong>:</h2>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/cancer/news/mayo-clinic-cancer-center-launches-program-for-adolescents-and-young-adults/mac-20523513" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Mayo Clinic Cancer Center launches program for adolescents and young adults</strong></a></li>



<li><a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2022/01/06/meeting-the-unique-needs-of-adolescents-and-young-adults-with-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Meeting the unique needs of adolescents and young adults with cancer</strong></a></li>



<li><a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/adolescent-young-adult-aya-cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Adolescent &amp;amp; Young Adult (AYA) Cancer Support Group</strong></a><div class="ch-group-privacy" style="align-items: center;font-family: MayoClinicSerif;font-size: 16px"></div></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/all-star-pitcher-liam-hendriks-shares-how-he-closed-out-cancer-at-mayo-clinic-in-arizona/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>All-Star pitcher Liam Hendriks shares how he closed out cancer at Mayo Clinic in Arizona</strong></a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/cancer-is-tough-evelyn-owens-is-tougher/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Cancer is tough. Evelyn Owens is tougher</strong></a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/videoharnessing-the-power-of-innovation-and-a-patients-will-to-survive/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>(VIDEO) Harnessing the power of innovation and a patient’s will to survive</strong></a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-jessies-journey/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Jessie’s Journey</strong></a></li>
</ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-focus-on-hope-brescias-story/">(VIDEO) Focus on hope: Brescia&amp;#8217;s Story</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-headshot-with-lump.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Brescia-seated-holding-camera-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#cancersupportgroup]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[American Cancer Society]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cancer cures]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[lymphoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mcthumb >https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Crop-of-Dr.-R-and-Brescia-150x150.jpg</mayoclinic:mcthumb >	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo researchers study stool to unlock microbiome&amp;#8217;s role in cancer treatment&nbsp;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-researchers-study-stool-to-unlock-microbiomes-role-in-cancer-treatment/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 12:30:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individualized Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Purna Kashyap]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=394082</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>At Mayo Clinic’s Center for Individualized Medicine, scientists are investigating stool samples to uncover new insights into cancer treatment. Often seen as waste, stool may provide valuable information about the microbiome — a complex ecosystem of microorganisms, including bacteria, fungi and viruses in the gut. Growing evidence shows the microbiome plays a significant role in [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-researchers-study-stool-to-unlock-microbiomes-role-in-cancer-treatment/">Mayo researchers study stool to unlock microbiome&amp;#8217;s role in cancer treatment&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-video"><video autoplay controls loop muted poster="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1498719393_SD_Small_-_WEB_MBL_H264_900-1.mp4" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1498719393_SD_Small_-_WEB_MBL_H264_900.mp4"></video></figure>



<p>At <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic’s Center for Individualized Medicine</a>, scientists are investigating stool samples to uncover new insights into cancer treatment. Often seen as waste, stool may provide valuable information about the microbiome — a complex ecosystem of microorganisms, including bacteria, fungi and viruses in the gut. </p>



<p>Growing evidence shows the microbiome plays a significant role in health, including how the body responds to diseases like cancer and how it influences treatment outcomes.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A new frontier in cancer research</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="534" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/KASHYAP-5.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396251" style="width:238px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/KASHYAP-5.jpg 534w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/KASHYAP-5-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 534px) 100vw, 534px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Purna Kashyap, M.B.B.S., the Bernard and Edith Waterman Director of the Mayo Clinic Microbiomics Program.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>A key part of the team's research is the Oncobiome Project, an initiative within the center’s Microbiomics Program. The project includes a large collection of stool samples from cancer patients across Mayo Clinic campuses in Minnesota, Arizona and Florida. These samples, collected before patients began treatment, are helping researchers identify microbial patterns that predict how well a patient will respond to treatments, and potentially pave the way for more personalized cancer care strategies.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>What sets the Oncobiome project apart is its strategic design, which bridges research and clinical practice. This approach makes it easier to translate scientific discoveries into personalized treatments for cancer patients.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"Ultimately, we hope to individualize treatment plans that provide the right drug at the right time based on a person’s unique microbiome and genetics," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/kashyap-purna-c-m-b-b-s/bio-00092735" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Purna Kashyap, M.B.B.S.</a>, the Bernard and Edith Waterman Director of the Mayo Clinic Microbiomics Program.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Decoding microbiome's cancer link through stool analysis</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="534" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microbiome-Dr.-Mars2.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396189" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microbiome-Dr.-Mars2.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microbiome-Dr.-Mars2-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microbiome-Dr.-Mars2-768x513.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Helen Xiao, Ph.D., (front) and Ruben Mars, Ph.D., work in an anaerobic chamber workstation, used to create an oxygen-free environment, in the Microbiomics Program laboratory at Mayo Clinic's Center for Individualized Medicine, October 9, 2024.</figcaption></figure>



<p>At the heart of the project is the collection and analysis of more than 2,000 stool samples. This extensive biobank allows Dr. Kashyap and his team to examine whether the microbiome composition correlates with specific types of cancer. They also are investigating whether the microbiome can predict the likelihood of event-free survival for patients with cancers such as lymphoma who are undergoing various treatments.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Additionally, the project explores whether enzymes and metabolites produced by the gut microbiome can offer insights into how patients will respond to cancer immunotherapies and help identify potential adverse reactions.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="534" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/WF4998388_0214.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396260" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/WF4998388_0214.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/WF4998388_0214-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/WF4998388_0214-768x513.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Research fellow, Prabhjot Sekhon Ph.D., works with a microbiology testing and identification system in the Microbiomics Program laboratory at Mayo Clinic's Center for Individualized Medicine, October 9, 2024.</figcaption></figure>



<p>"We included a diverse group of patients at various stages of different cancers and undergoing various treatments. This allows us to identify microbial patterns that forecast optimal cancer outcomes, independent of the underlying cancer," Dr. Kashyap says.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>Beyond personalizing cancer care, the team is integrating additional "omics" to gain deeper insights into patients' genetics, environment and immune status. This includes genomics (the study of genes), proteomics (proteins), exposomics (environmental exposures), metabolomics (metabolic processes) and transcriptomics (RNA transcripts).&amp;nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1688" height="1125" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/MICROBIOME-DR.MARS3_.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396269" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/MICROBIOME-DR.MARS3_.jpg 1688w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/MICROBIOME-DR.MARS3_-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/MICROBIOME-DR.MARS3_-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/MICROBIOME-DR.MARS3_-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/MICROBIOME-DR.MARS3_-1536x1024.jpg 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1688px) 100vw, 1688px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Ruben Mars, Ph.D., works within an anaerobic chamber in the Microbiomics Program laboratory at Mayo Clinic's Center for Individualized Medicine.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Ruben Mars, Ph.D., a research scientist at the Center for Individualized Medicine, is playing a key role in spearheading several studies within the Oncobiome project to understand the impact of microbes on cancer risk, treatment efficacy and the underlying mechanisms of any treatment side effects.&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>"Although a diverse and balanced gut microbiome is widely recognized as beneficial for our health, pinpointing specific microbial changes that enhance treatment outcomes remains challenging," Dr. Mars says. "Through the Oncobiome project, we're optimistic about developing innovative methods to manipulate the microbiome and ultimately improve cancer care for patients."&amp;nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="534" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microbiomics-17.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396198" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microbiomics-17.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microbiomics-17-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microbiomics-17-768x513.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Tijs Louwies, Ph.D., a research technologist, works with an ussing chamber system, to study how substances pass through cell layers, in the Microbiomics Program laboratory at Mayo Clinic's Center for Individualized Medicine, October 9, 2024.</figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Connecting the microbiome to health outcomes</h2>



<p>This research is part of a broader series of the team's investigations into the microbiome. Their recent published studies focus on the microbiome's role in <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38922780/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gut-brain disorders</a>, including how bacteria affect intestinal functions like motility. Other published work examines <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34453142/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">C. difficile infections</a>, exploring how the bacteria persist in the intestine. </p>



<p>Mayo's microbiome scientists are also studying the impact of the gut microbiome on the <a href="https://genomemedicine.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13073-021-00957-0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">progression of rheumatoid arthritis</a> and patients' response to treatment. In another <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/microbiology/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2021.674835/full" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study,</a> the team linked a specific microbe, Porphyromonas somerae, to endometrial cancer, finding its intracellular activity may play a pathogenic role in the disease.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-researchers-study-stool-to-unlock-microbiomes-role-in-cancer-treatment/">Mayo researchers study stool to unlock microbiome&amp;#8217;s role in cancer treatment&nbsp;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/1x1-microbiome23.png</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/16x9-microbiome1.png</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Purna Kashyap]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Discovery reveals how to prevent organ damage in pancreatitis</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/discovery-reveals-how-to-prevent-organ-damage-in-pancreatitis/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[mbroadfoot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 21:02:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Vijay Singh]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=396300</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Researchers at Mayo Clinic have discovered how high levels of triglycerides, a type of fat found in the bloodstream, can rapidly damage organs during acute pancreatitis. They discovered in pancreatitis that circulating triglycerides swiftly break down into smaller building blocks known as fatty acids that can damage organs such as the lung and kidneys. Blocking [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/discovery-reveals-how-to-prevent-organ-damage-in-pancreatitis/">Discovery reveals how to prevent organ damage in pancreatitis</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Researchers at Mayo Clinic have discovered how high levels of triglycerides, a type of fat found in the bloodstream, can rapidly damage organs during acute pancreatitis. They discovered in pancreatitis that circulating triglycerides swiftly break down into smaller building blocks known as fatty acids that can damage organs such as the lung and kidneys. Blocking this breakdown prevented such damage from occurring.</p>



<p>The findings, published in the <a href="https://www.jci.org/articles/view/184785" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Journal of Clinical Investigation</a>, open a new therapeutic avenue for treating pancreatitis by halting the breakdown of triglycerides.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="600" height="720" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Vijay-Singh.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396303" style="width:251px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Vijay-Singh.jpg 600w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Vijay-Singh-250x300.jpg 250w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Vijay Singh, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"This discovery not only provides a deeper understanding of the mechanisms behind triglyceride-induced organ damage in pancreatitis but also offers a promising strategy to improve patient outcomes," says senior author <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/singh-vijay-p-m-b-b-s-m-d/bio-20111292" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Vijay Singh, M.D.</a>, a gastroenterologist at&nbsp;Mayo Clinic's campus in Scottsdale, Arizona.</p>



<p>Acute <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pancreatitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20360227" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pancreatitis</a> is a common gastrointestinal disorder that leads to approximately 275,000 hospital admissions annually in the U.S. alone. &nbsp;An estimated 30% of patients with acute pancreatitis have a form of the disease marked by high levels of triglycerides.</p>



<p>Patients with hypertriglyceridemia-associated acute pancreatitis have a higher risk of <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;amp;db=pubmed&amp;amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;amp;list_uids=37461868&amp;amp;query_hl=11&amp;amp;itool=pubmed_docsum" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">persistent organ failure and severe pancreatitis</a>, which often requires life support, prolongs hospitalization and increases mortality rates. Despite these severe outcomes, the <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36599412/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">mechanisms</a> driving this form of acute pancreatitis have remained unclear until now.</p>



<p>In this study, the researchers analyzed triglyceride and fatty acid levels in blood samples from 269 patients with acute pancreatitis. They found that patients with very high triglycerides had more severe disease and higher levels of fatty acids.</p>



<p>In addition, they did experiments in preclinical models to see how metabolizing triglycerides into fatty acids affected organ health. In animals, this process led to organ failure, which could be prevented by blocking an enzyme called <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31917686/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lipase</a>, which plays a crucial role in triglyceride metabolism.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="837" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/graphical-abstract-837x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396305" style="width:365px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/graphical-abstract-837x1024.jpg 837w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/graphical-abstract-245x300.jpg 245w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/graphical-abstract-768x939.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/graphical-abstract-1256x1536.jpg 1256w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/graphical-abstract-1675x2048.jpg 1675w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 837px) 100vw, 837px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">In pancreatitis, circulating triglycerides swiftly break down into smaller building blocks known as fatty acids that can damage organs such as the lung and kidneys. Illustration: Renee Cannon</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>The finding could inform new ways to manage triglyceride elevation during pancreatitis. Current treatments, such as the use of the blood thinner heparin to reduce triglycerides, have shown minimal benefit in reducing organ damage or the severity of pancreatitis. Heparin works by breaking down triglycerides, but this process does not significantly improve patient outcomes.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers, led by Dr. Singh, are currently developing alternative therapies for acute pancreatitis that block the breakdown of triglycerides.</p>



<p>The recent study also sheds light on the implications of using heparin and other treatments that release the enzyme lipase. It found that the worst outcomes were observed in pancreatitis patients receiving nutrition via IV, as intravenous formulations containing triglycerides can be broken down to potentially harmful fatty acids by circulating lipases. &amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>The research team is now investigating the relevance of this finding in patients with elevated lipase levels due to other diseases, such as intestinal, heart and lung conditions. These diseases may silently damage the pancreas, causing it to leak lipase and create a vicious cycle of worsening organ damage.</p>



<p>"Preliminary studies suggest that patients with elevated triglycerides and lipase levels require more frequent admissions to the intensive care unit," says Dr. Singh. "If confirmed, these findings could point to new ways to prevent the progression of these diseases."</p>



<p>Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.jci.org/articles/view/184785" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">paper</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/discovery-reveals-how-to-prevent-organ-damage-in-pancreatitis/">Discovery reveals how to prevent organ damage in pancreatitis</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/graphical-abstract-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/graphical-abstract-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Vijay Singh]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hourglass-shaped stent could ease severe chest pain from microvascular disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/hourglass-shaped-stent-could-ease-severe-chest-pain-from-microvascular-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Terri Malloy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2024 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Clinical Trials]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[angina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[angina treatment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[coronary angiogram]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Amir Lerman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[small vessel disease]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=396180</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A study at Mayo Clinic suggests that an hourglass-shaped stent could improve blood flow and ease severe and reoccurring chest pain in people with microvascular disease. Of 30 participants in a phase 2 clinical trial, 76% saw improvement in their day-to-day life. For example, some participants who reported not being able to [&amp;#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/hourglass-shaped-stent-could-ease-severe-chest-pain-from-microvascular-disease/">Hourglass-shaped stent could ease severe chest pain from microvascular disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="684" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microvascular-disease_1293229_EC1294075-001-1-1024x684.jpg" alt="View of a heart with coronary artery disease or coronary microvascular disease. An inset highlights the clogging and narrowing of the arteries." class="wp-image-396227" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microvascular-disease_1293229_EC1294075-001-1-1024x684.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microvascular-disease_1293229_EC1294075-001-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microvascular-disease_1293229_EC1294075-001-1-768x513.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microvascular-disease_1293229_EC1294075-001-1.jpg 1464w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A study at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> suggests that an hourglass-shaped stent could improve blood flow and ease severe and reoccurring chest pain in people with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/small-vessel-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20352117" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">microvascular disease</a>. Of 30 participants in a phase 2 clinical trial, 76% saw improvement in their day-to-day life. For example, some participants who reported not being able to walk around the block or up a flight of stairs without chest pain were able to do these ordinary physical activities at the end of a 120-day period. Clinical measures of blood flow related to the microvasculature of the heart significantly improved during follow-up, according to findings published in the <a href="https://authors.elsevier.com/a/1k39I6uPJvuWBq" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Journal of the American College of Cardiology: Cardiovascular Interventions</a>.</p>



<p>Microvascular disease is a condition in which tiny blood vessels in the heart are not working properly, resulting in reduced blood flow to the heart. The resulting chest pains, or <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/angina/symptoms-causes/syc-20369373" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">angina</a>, can be debilitating, limiting a person's ability to exercise, do household chores or even walk to the mailbox. About 40% of patients receiving a diagnostic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/coronary-angiogram/about/pac-20384904" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">coronary angiogram</a> for chest pain do not have blocked arteries that also can cause angina. However, up to 66% of these patients do have coronary microvascular disease, which is more common in women overall and found in people with conditions such as diabetes, high blood pressure and obesity.</p>



<p>For decades, there have been few viable treatment options to improve blood flow through the tiny vessels of the heart. At most, doctors have treated symptoms of angina with several medications and cardiovascular disease prevention methods, including healthy eating, weight loss and regular exercise. The use of a stent could target the issue behind the chest pain — the severe reduction in blood flow affecting the heart muscle.</p>



<p>Unlike tube-shaped stents used to open clogged arteries, the hourglass-shaped stent narrows in the middle. The different design is thought to increase back pressure, redistributing blood flow more fully through small vessels in the heart that were not working at capacity.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Amir_Lerman_1539878_3777595_0001-300x200.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396220" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Amir_Lerman_1539878_3777595_0001-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Amir_Lerman_1539878_3777595_0001-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Amir_Lerman_1539878_3777595_0001-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Amir_Lerman_1539878_3777595_0001-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Amir_Lerman_1539878_3777595_0001.jpg 1688w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><sup>Amir Lerman, M.D.</sup></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"The patients with heart-related microvascular dysfunction in this study had little ability to control their chronic angina, which severely limited their day-to-day activities," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/lerman-amir-m-d/bio-00078051" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Amir Lerman, M.D.</a>, a cardiologist at Mayo Clinic and senior author of the study. "Beyond reductions in chest pain and being able to comfortably handle more physical activity, the majority of patients in the study also showed a connection between the changes in their coronary flow reserve, which is a measure of maximum blood flow, and changes in their quality-of-life responses on the survey. This points to the link between the physiological measurement and angina symptoms."</p>



<p>Dr. Lerman notes that more studies are needed to better understand how the reducer stent works and its long-term effects on blood flow. The stent did not improve chest pain symptoms in 20%-30% of the participants, so future research studies will need to better identify which patients respond best to this therapy. &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> <br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/hourglass-shaped-stent-could-ease-severe-chest-pain-from-microvascular-disease/">Hourglass-shaped stent could ease severe chest pain from microvascular disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microvascular-disease_510085_EC1294075-001-0_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/microvascular-disease_1293229_EC1294075-001_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[angina]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[angina treatment]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cardiology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[coronary angiogram]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Amir Lerman]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Heart Disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[small vessel disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss> 