<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Research - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research-2/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research-2/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2023 15:07:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>A decade of data describes nationwide youth mental health crisis</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-decade-of-data-describes-nationwide-youth-mental-health-crisis/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Alastair McKean]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Tanner Bommersbach]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[youth mental health]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374693</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>When Tanner Bommersbach, M.D., and a team of Mayo Clinic researchers analyzed national records of pediatric emergency department visits, they provided essential data to describe the growing national crisis in pediatric mental health. Their study found that from 2011 to 2020, youth visits to emergency departments for mental health reasons&#160;doubled, while the proportion of visits [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-decade-of-data-describes-nationwide-youth-mental-health-crisis/">A decade of data describes nationwide youth mental health crisis</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" width="500" height="282" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/depressed-man-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374695" style="aspect-ratio:16/9;object-fit:cover" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/depressed-man-16x9-1.jpg 500w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/depressed-man-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></figure>



<p>When Tanner Bommersbach, M.D., and a team of Mayo Clinic researchers analyzed national records of pediatric emergency department visits, they provided essential data to describe the growing national crisis in pediatric mental health.</p>



<p>Their study found that from 2011 to 2020, youth visits to emergency departments for mental health reasons&nbsp;<em>doubled</em>, while the proportion of visits for suicide-related symptoms increased&nbsp;<em>fivefold</em>.</p>



<p>The team's findings were recently published in the&nbsp;<a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2804326" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Journal of the American Medical Association</a>. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Bommersbach, a child and adolescent psychiatry fellow, hopes the study's results will be useful in national conversations about youth mental health.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Taking on a serious problem</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Bommersbach-Tanner-J._15901441_20220701-240x300-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374697" style="width:265px;height:331px" width="265" height="331" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Tanner Bommersbach, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Dr. Bommersbach has had a longstanding interest in children's mental health. During high school and college, he worked in a North Dakota group home for children with developmental disabilities where he observed their interactions with their psychiatrists. The experience prompted him to pursue a career as a physician. He attended&nbsp;<a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/mayo-clinic-alix-school-of-medicine/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Alix School of Medicine</a>&nbsp;where he found a mentor in psychiatrist&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/bostwick-j-michael-m-d-mfa/bio-00027634" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">J. Michael Bostwick, M.D</a>. Working with Dr. Bostwick during medical school, Dr. Bommersbach became interested in research and took part in studies investigating how people with suicidal symptoms interact with the healthcare system.</p>



<p></p>



<p>After pursuing a master's in public health to learn more about research methodology and completing his residency, Dr. Bommersbach returned to Mayo for fellowship training, where he has continued to conduct research on suicide prevention and epidemiology in pediatric mental health. He was recently first author on&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/article/S0025-6196(23)00071-X/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">another study</a>&nbsp;about rising rates of suicidal behaviors and unmet treatment needs among U.S. adults who experience a major depressive episode.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Rising rates of illness</strong></h2>



<p>Dr. Bommersbach says the study of pediatric emergency room visits expanded upon other studies that have shown rising rates of youth mental health concerns — but the magnitude of the rise in pediatric mental health visits, especially those that were suicide-related, took him by surprise.</p>



<p>The study used data from 2011 to 2020 from the National Hospital Ambulatory Medical Care Survey, an annual cross-sectional national probability sample survey of emergency departments. The research team examined mental health-related visits for patients aged 6 to 24 years. Data showed a significant rise in visits across all age groups, sexes, races and ethnicities. But the greatest increase was for patients aged 10 to 14 years.</p>



<p>Even though data were not yet available from 2021 or 2022, the findings did include some data from early in the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>



<p></p>



<div class="wp-block-media-text is-stacked-on-mobile" style="grid-template-columns:29% auto"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img decoding="async" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/McKean-Alastair-J.-MD_15241271_201406250921-250x300-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374698 size-full" /></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p>"Over the last few decades, we've seen an increase in youth mental health issues. COVID likely accelerated and exacerbated these concerns," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mckean-alastair-j-m-d/bio-20149218" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alastair McKean, M.D.</a>, a co-author of the JAMA study.</p>
</div></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Prompting change</strong></h2>



<p>The findings of the study do not identify why children's mental health visits increased so dramatically, but the authors point to several potential contributing factors, including increased awareness of mental health concerns among youth, improved and increased referrals from doctors, greater willingness among young people to seek help and reduced access to other mental health services in the community.</p>



<p>Of particular concern is the increase in suicide-related symptoms in young people, which increased in all age groups, across sex, race and ethnicity, insurance type and geographic region. The authors point out that suicide-related visits among adolescents accounted for 6.6% of all ED visits in 2019-2020.</p>



<p>The numbers are a call to action, they say.</p>



<p>"The first part of prompting change is having real data, and this study shows that this is a growing national crisis," says Dr. McKean.</p>



<p>"One area that needs to be addressed in a national conversation is increasing access to non-hospital services that can treat mental health issues. Emergency departments frequently act as safety nets for individuals with unmet health needs, especially for uninsured and undocumented children," says Dr. Bommersbach. "My goal is to continue research that will illuminate these national gaps so that we can move toward a national commitment to mental healthcare and expanded community-based services for young people."</p>



<p>This article originally published on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/09/18/youth-mental-health/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-decade-of-data-describes-nationwide-youth-mental-health-crisis/">A decade of data describes nationwide youth mental health crisis</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/depressed-man-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/depressed-man-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Alastair McKean]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Tanner Bommersbach]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[youth mental health]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Mayo Clinic individualized medicine leader on a quest to bring cutting-edge medicine to all</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-individualized-medicine-leader-on-a-quest-to-bring-cutting-edge-medicine-to-all/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 23 Sep 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Victor Ortega]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[individualized medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374444</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>As a pulmonologist and genomic scientist,&#160;Victor Ortega, M.D., Ph.D., is leading a charge to breathe new life into precision medicine advancements. His mission is rooted in a deep commitment to health equities and inspired by his grandmother.&#160; "My grandmother died of asthma, and that should not have happened. She was Puerto Rican like me, and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-individualized-medicine-leader-on-a-quest-to-bring-cutting-edge-medicine-to-all/">New Mayo Clinic individualized medicine leader on a quest to bring cutting-edge medicine to all</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/precision-medicine2-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374447" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/precision-medicine2-16x9-1.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/precision-medicine2-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/precision-medicine2-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>As a pulmonologist and genomic scientist,&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/ortega-victor-e-m-d-ph-d/bio-20520652" target="_blank">Victor Ortega, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, is leading a charge to breathe new life into precision medicine advancements. His mission is rooted in a deep commitment to health equities and inspired by his grandmother.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"My grandmother died of asthma, and that should not have happened. She was Puerto Rican like me, and Puerto Ricans have the highest severity and frequency of asthma of any ethnic group in the world," Dr. Ortega says. "They also represent less than 1% of people in genetic studies. So, I've made it a life mission to develop cures and diagnostics for people like my grandma, and for all people."&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Predicting disease risks: Polygenic Risk Scores</strong></h3>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Ortega-Victor-E._14023334_202109070736-250x300-1.jpg" alt="Victor Ortega, M.D., Ph.D." class="wp-image-374446" style="width:193px;height:231px" width="193" height="231" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em><sub>Victor Ortega, M.D., Ph.D.</sub></em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>In his new role as the associate director for the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine</a>&nbsp;in Arizona, Dr. Ortega is guiding his team toward a transformative future of healthcare, where each person's unique DNA profile may serve as a personalized guide to their health and well-being.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Imagine knowing your genetic predisposition for having a heart attack in your 50s, or if you're in the top 5% of the population for the risk of cancer or diabetes. With this knowledge, you could make informed lifestyle choices and receive screenings to mitigate that risk," Dr. Ortega says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Previously inconceivable, he says personalized health forecasts, derived from so-called polygenic risk scores, are possible because of new and sophisticated genome sequencing technologies. The complex scores are compiled from a combination of data from thousands of a person's DNA variants. The data has the potential to predict disease risks, such as heart disease, diabetes, asthma, and specific cancers. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Ortega says getting to the point where all people know their polygenic risk scores will require a solid foundation of "omics" research and datasets, cutting-edge technologies and further discoveries of gene-disease links — all of which are within his team's expertise and capabilities.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Omics is an emerging multidisciplinary field of biological sciences that encompasses genomics, proteomics, epigenomics, transcriptomics, metabolomics and more. &nbsp;</p>



<p>"It's going to take considerable work and planning, but it really is the way of the future,"&nbsp;he says.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Advancing omics beyond research labs</strong></h3>



<p>In the shorter term, Dr. Ortega plans to transition more omics discoveries from research labs to the clinic. Omics data can help identify the molecular culprits driving a person's disease, as well as biomarkers that can lead to the development of targeted treatments and diagnostics.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Recent omics discoveries at Mayo Clinic's Center for Individualized Medicine have enabled scientists to predict&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://docs.google.com/document/u/0/d/1uPkwEmVIX5wmqGyf2sj0Wkm4_PnbDuAZRpVrywJURD8/edit" target="_blank">antidepressant response</a>&nbsp;in people with depression and discover a potential&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://individualizedmedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2022/10/04/mayo-study-lays-foundation-to-predict-antidepressant-response-in-people-with-suicide-attempts/" target="_blank">therapeutic strategy</a>&nbsp;for bone marrow cancer. Scientists have also used omics to pinpoint&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://individualizedmedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2022/07/25/mayo-clinic-researchers-pinpoint-genetic-variations-that-might-sway-course-of-covid-19/" target="_blank">genetic variations</a>&nbsp;that potentially increase the risk for severe COVID-19, uncover&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://individualizedmedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2022/10/25/research-provides-critical-information-about-the-size-and-growth-speed-of-gliomas/" target="_blank">potential clues</a>&nbsp;for preventing and treating gliomas and unravel the genetic mystery of a&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://individualizedmedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2022/06/21/scientists-unravel-genetic-mystery-of-rare-neurodevelopmental-disorder-provide-definitive-diagnoses-to-21-families-worldwide/" target="_blank">rare neurodevelopmental disorder</a>.  &nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Expanding genomic testing across diseases</strong></h3>



<p>Drawing from his years of extensive clinical experience in treating patients with severe respiratory illnesses, Dr. Ortega is also working to expand genomic testing to a broader set of diseases. He highlights the center's collaborative Program for Rare and Undiagnosed Diseases as an effective model that he hopes to amplify. &nbsp;</p>



<p>The Program for Rare and Undiagnosed Diseases proactively engages healthcare teams across Mayo's clinical practice to conduct&nbsp;targeted genomic testing for patients with a suspected rare genetic disease. He says expanding this strategy to more diseases will help build collaborations across Mayo and educate more clinicians on genomics. It may also ensure the most effective genomic sequencing tests are given to patients, ultimately improving patient care and outcomes.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>He points to cystic fibrosis, a genetic respiratory disorder, as an example of how genetic misconceptions and wrong testing strategies can negatively affect diverse populations. &nbsp;</p>



<p>"Clinicians might overlook genetic tests for cystic fibrosis in minority groups because of a misconception that cystic fibrosis is most prevalent in people of European white ancestry," he says. "However, the disease can affect various ethnic populations with distinct variants, so they also may order the wrong test." &nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Clearing the path to cutting-edge medicine for all</strong></h3>



<p>Dr. Ortega emphasizes the importance of collaborations and data sharing to accelerate medical discoveries and improve health equity. His dedication to collaborations extends beyond the walls of Mayo Clinic to other consortiums that share profound commitments to enhancing diversity.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"The future of healthcare is happening right now," Dr. Ortega says. "But it's much bigger than genomics advancements and innovations. It's about making sure cutting-edge medicine is accessible to every person." </p>



<p>This article first appeared on the <a href="https://individualizedmedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/09/12/new-mayo-clinic-individualized-medicine-leader-on-a-quest-to-bring-cutting-edge-medicine-to-all/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">blog of the Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-individualized-medicine-leader-on-a-quest-to-bring-cutting-edge-medicine-to-all/">New Mayo Clinic individualized medicine leader on a quest to bring cutting-edge medicine to all</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/precision-medicine2-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/precision-medicine2-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Victor Ortega]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[individualized medicine]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New gene markers detect Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer, Mayo Clinic study</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-gene-markers-detect-lynch-syndrome-associated-colorectal-cancer-mayo-clinic-study/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelley Luckstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 16:22:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[colorectal cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jewel Samadder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[genetic markers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genetic Testing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lynch Syndrome]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374770</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Researchers from Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center and Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine have discovered new genetic markers to identify Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer with high accuracy. Studies are underway to determine if these genetic markers are in stool samples and, if so, how this could lead to a non-invasive screening [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-gene-markers-detect-lynch-syndrome-associated-colorectal-cancer-mayo-clinic-study/">New gene markers detect Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer, Mayo Clinic study</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="689" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610-1024x689.jpg" alt="a close-up view of a deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) sequencing test illuminated in green, blue, and purple" class="wp-image-362241" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610-1024x689.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610-300x202.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610-768x517.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610-1536x1034.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-661498610.jpg 1671w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Researchers from <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine/education/gerstner-family-career-development-awards" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine</a> have discovered new genetic markers to identify Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer with high accuracy. Studies are underway to determine if these genetic markers are in stool samples and, if so, how this could lead to a non-invasive screening option for patients with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lynch-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20374714?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lynch syndrome.</a> Their research was published in <a href="https://aacrjournals.org/cancerpreventionresearch/article/doi/10.1158/1940-6207.CAPR-23-0107/729134/Methylated-DNA-Markers-for-Sporadic-Colorectal-and" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cancer Prevention Research</a>, a journal of the American Association for Cancer Research.</p>



<p>"This is an exciting finding that brings us closer to the reality that clinicians may soon be able to offer a non-invasive cancer screening option to patients with the highest risk of getting cancer," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/samadder-niloy-jewel-jewel-j-m-d/bio-20415667?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jewel Samadder, M.D.</a>, co-lead author of the paper and gastroenterologist at Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center. "I look forward to the day when I no longer have to remind patients with Lynch Syndrome to schedule their annual colonoscopy and complete the prep, when they will instead be able to provide a stool sample to screen for cancer."</p>



<p>Lynch syndrome is an inherited genetic condition that significantly increases the risk of multiple cancers, most notably colorectal and uterine cancers. Approximately 1 in 300 people have Lynch syndrome, many of whom are unaware of it. Patients with Lynch syndrome undergo <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/colonoscopy/about/pac-20393569?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colonoscopies</a> annually to detect and remove pre-cancerous lesions that can form colorectal cancer, in addition to undergoing invasive tests or prophylactic surgery to prevent uterine cancer.</p>



<p>For this study, the researchers evaluated a panel of methylated DNA markers (MDM) for sporadic colorectal and endometrial cancers in people with Lynch syndrome (LS). Sporadic cancer is cancer that occurs randomly in people with no family history or known predisposing risk factors. The researchers also included control groups with no cancer. For colorectal cancer, there were 23 LS cases, 48 sporadic cases, 32 LS controls, and 48 sporadic controls. For endometrial cancer, there were 30 LS cases, 48 sporadic cases, 29 LS controls and 37 sporadic controls.</p>



<p>"We found that a marker panel composed of three biomarkers (LASS4, LRRC4, PPP2R5C) could effectively differentiate Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer from Lynch syndrome controls, with 92% accuracy. This three-marker panel also performed similarly in distinguishing sporadic colorectal cancer cases from controls," says Dr. Samadder. This three-marker panel is being tested in a multi-site clinical trial in patients with Lynch syndrome as a non-invasive screening option.</p>



<p>"Our findings support the feasibility of cancer detection in stool and lower gynecologic genital tract samples in the setting of Lynch syndrome and warrant further testing," says Dr. Samadder.</p>



<p>The research was funded by the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine</a> and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine/education/gerstner-family-career-development-awards#:~:text=The%20Gerstner%20Family%20Career%20Development,research%20using%20individualized%20medicine%20approaches." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gerstner Family Career Development Award</a>. For a full list of funding, authors and conflicts of interest, see the <a href="https://aacrjournals.org/cancerpreventionresearch/article/doi/10.1158/1940-6207.CAPR-23-0107/729134/Methylated-DNA-Markers-for-Sporadic-Colorectal-and" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">paper</a>.  </p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive&nbsp;Cancer Center </strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;is defining new boundaries in possibility, focusing on patient-centered care, developing novel treatments, training future generations of cancer experts, and bringing cancer research to communities. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs that are changing approaches to cancer prevention, screening, and treatment and improving the lives of cancer survivors.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-gene-markers-detect-lynch-syndrome-associated-colorectal-cancer-mayo-clinic-study/">New gene markers detect Lynch syndrome-associated colorectal cancer, Mayo Clinic study</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/a-close-up-view-of-a-deoxyribonucleic-acid-DNA-sequencing-test-illuminated-in-green-blue-and-purple-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/03/a-close-up-view-of-a-deoxyribonucleic-acid-DNA-sequencing-test-illuminated-in-green-blue-and-purple-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[colorectal cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jewel Samadder]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[genetic markers]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Genetic Testing]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Lynch Syndrome]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic advances research on mysterious blood vessel disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-advances-research-on-mysterious-blood-vessel-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[asatake]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Sep 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Cornelia Weyand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Giant Cell Arteritis]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374416</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Giant cell arteritis&#160;(GCA), formerly known as temporal arteritis, was first described by Mayo doctors and classified as an inflammatory condition of the blood vessels in the early to mid-20th century. The condition causes bulging blood vessels at the temples, which, left untreated, may lead to blindness, stroke or even an aortic aneurysm. The cause of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-advances-research-on-mysterious-blood-vessel-disease/">Mayo Clinic advances research on mysterious blood vessel disease</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Weyand-gca-feature-image-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374418" style="aspect-ratio:16/9;object-fit:cover;width:839px" width="839" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Weyand-gca-feature-image-16x9-1.jpg 500w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Weyand-gca-feature-image-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Immunofluorescent image of highly activated immune cells in giant cell arteritis (GCA). This inflammatory blood vessel condition is an autoimmune disease that affects about 200,000 people in the U.S.  <br></figcaption></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/giant-cell-arteritis/symptoms-causes/syc-20372758" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Giant cell arteritis</a>&nbsp;(GCA), formerly known as temporal arteritis, was first described by Mayo doctors and classified as an inflammatory condition of the blood vessels in the early to mid-20th century. The condition causes bulging blood vessels at the temples, which, left untreated, may lead to blindness, stroke or even an aortic aneurysm. The cause of GCA is unknown.</p>



<p>Nearly 200,000 people in the U.S. are affected. Most are over the age of 50. The disease is more common in Rochester, Minnesota, than other locations due to the area's large resident populations of Northern European or Scandinavian descent, which may be genetically predisposed to GCA.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Weyand-Cornelia-WF535495_0009-300x200-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374420" style="width:253px;height:168px" width="253" height="168" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Cornelia M. Weyand, M.D., Ph.D., Senior Associate Consultant in Rheumatology and Immunology, and Professor of Immunology and Medicine, in her research lab.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Over the last three decades, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/weyand-cornelia-m-m-d-ph-d/bio-20527870" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cornelia Weyand, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, a Mayo rheumatologist and clinician-scientist, has been building on the work of her predecessors to investigate the source of the disease. Her work has illuminated the immune system's role in the inflammatory process and paved the way for potential new therapies. These insights may also lead to immune therapies that treat more common diseases, including cancer.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Surprising from the start</strong></h2>



<p>Bayard Horton, M.D., Thomas Magath, M.D., Ph.D., and George Brown, M.D., first observed the symptoms of GCA — including bulging arteries at the temples — in two different patients and were among the first in the world to perform temporal artery biopsies,&nbsp;<a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamainternalmedicine/article-abstract/539500" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">publishing their findings in 1934</a>. They also were among the first to classify the condition as a&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-vasculitis-affects-the-body/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">vasculitis</a>, but they didn’t have an explanation for how the disease worked.</p>



<p>A physician in England, J. R. Gilmour, M.B., C.M., renamed the disease giant cell arteritis due to the enlarged cells he observed in 1941. But a significant breakthrough did not come until a decade later when in 1950, Mayo Clinic physicians&nbsp;<a href="https://libraryguides.mayo.edu/historicalunit/cortisone#:~:text=In%201950%2C%20Mayo%20Clinic%20doctors,of%20cortisone%20to%20rheumatoid%20arthritis." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Edward Kendall, Ph.D., and Philip Hench, M.D.</a>, received the Nobel Prize for the discovery of cortisone. Because cortisone suppresses inflammation, it became one of the primary treatments for GCA. However, the treatment doesn't get to the source of the condition.</p>



<p>From early on, scientists were surprised to find that GCA involves the immune system. Blood vessels, critical to the body's function, tend to evade the inflammatory and damaging processes of immune cells, a characteristic that researchers refer to as "immune privilege." However, GCA targets the blood vessels, including the aorta, the largest artery in the body.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Taking a closer look</strong></h2>



<p>Nearly a decade passed before another Mayo physician looked at the disease more closely. "When I started, no one was interested in giant cell arteritis," says Gene Hunder, M.D., a rheumatologist and emeritus physician at Mayo.</p>



<p>He says GCA was not on physicians' radar simply because the disease had not been well defined. "If you know about something, you see it in a patient and make a note of it. If you aren't aware of it, you let it go by. I think that was what was happening with giant cell arteritis for many years," Dr. Hunder says.</p>



<p>He recalls seeing a patient at Mayo in the mid-1960s who presented with a barely palpable pulse and was diagnosed with inflammation of the aorta. He and a resident examined the case in detail. Then, they delved into the medical files to find records of several patients with low pulses in their arms or neck but no further diagnoses. They conducted an epidemiologic study, which provided evidence that patients with GCA frequently also had inflamed aortas.</p>



<p>The finding attracted the attention of the medical world. "I think the fact that the aorta was involved struck the doctors harder because that's a big blood vessel and could have disastrous side effects," Dr. Hunder says.</p>



<p>It's known that GCA is more prevalent in women than men, but no one can predict who will get it. The frontline treatment — the corticosteroid prednisone — is the same approach as half a century ago but relieves symptoms only temporarily. "In vasculitis, it's not unusual for some symptoms to go away, but the inflammation in the arteries will go on. The activity of the disease declines with the corticosteroid therapy, but there is still inflammation in the blood vessel," Dr. Hunder says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Picking up the thread</strong></h2>



<p>In 1990, Dr. Weyand joined Mayo Clinic and soon saw the scientific opportunity to diagnose and treat many patients with GCA in Minnesota and to study the disease.</p>



<p>A few years ago, she and her colleagues identified a problem with a protein that seemed to cause the immune system to go haywire in patients with GCA. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>A typical immune system responds to antigens, or toxins, that cause infection or are derived from cancerous cells. While immune protection against infection and cancer is a high priority, the immune system also needs built-in brakes, or immune checkpoints, that tell the immune system to stop and prevent it from over-responding. Dr. Weyand and colleagues, including&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/goronzy-jorg-m-d-ph-d/bio-20527076" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jörg J Goronzy, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, found that the protein PD-L1 is weakly expressed in patients with GCA, preventing the delivery of a stop signal to T cells. This finding led the team to conclude that patients with GCA have a broken immune checkpoint, which explains an overabundance of inflammation.</p>



<p>"That became a landmark <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28115719/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">paper</a> because it was the first report of human autoimmune disease linked to a nonfunctional [immune] checkpoint," she says.</p>



<p>Recently, her research team made another discovery, furthering the understanding of an immune system gone awry. They found a second immune checkpoint that is not working in GCA. They saw that a specific ligand, a molecule that binds to and activates a receptor on immune cells, gets trapped and can't make it to the surface of the immune cell to signal the immune system to stop. When the ligand, called CD155, gets trapped, it triggers the unrestricted proliferation of T cells. The T cells invade and accumulate in blood vessel walls. There, they secrete the cytokine interleukin-9, which further attacks and damages the blood vessel.</p>



<p>"We now have seen a second checkpoint that is not working. So, this seems to be the reason why these patients are driving inflammatory responses in the aorta where they are not supposed to be," Dr. Weyand says.</p>



<p>That&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cell.com/cell-reports-medicine/pdfExtended/S2666-3791(23)00122-2">study showed</a>&nbsp;the immune cells lacking the CD155 ligands also can be detected in blood and GCA lesions and therefore are new biomarkers of the disease that may help improve diagnosis.</p>



<p>What's more, the researchers have shown in another <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37672564/">recent paper</a> that the structure of the blood vessel tissues itself shelters and fosters the disease-inducing immune cells in GCA. This provides even more information for potential GCA therapies.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Research-Weyand-Timeline-septv1-01-1024x683-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374421" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Research-Weyand-Timeline-septv1-01-1024x683-1.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Research-Weyand-Timeline-septv1-01-1024x683-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Research-Weyand-Timeline-septv1-01-1024x683-1-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Advancing immunology has relevance to cancer too</strong></h2>



<p>These advances in the immunology of GCA have relevance to cancer, too, Dr. Weyand points out. Increasingly, immune therapies that enhance a person's own immune response are being used to treat various forms of cancer.</p>



<p>Patients with cancer are on the opposite end of the spectrum from patients with vasculitis in that their immune checkpoints, or brakes, work too well to stop immune response, and tumors take advantage of that. As a result, oncologists prescribe immune checkpoint inhibitors to unleash patients' immune systems to fight cancer cells and tumors.</p>



<p>Ultimately, knowing how to target faulty immune checkpoints opens the opportunity to identify new GCA treatments. Dr. Weyand's team has developed a preclinical model outfitted with human arteries and a human immune system called an immune avatar. The model system enables researchers to study GCA more closely, monitor inflammation and test immunotherapies to suppress inflammation.</p>



<p>"That immune avatar has been a dimensional step forward for us," she says. "This research changes our fundamental understanding of the pathogenesis of giant cell arteritis and paves the way for an entirely new approach for treatment."</p>



<p>Dr. Weyand's research has received support from the National Institutes of Health, Stanford University and Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>This post originally appeared on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/09/13/mayo-clinic-advances-research-on-mysterious-blood-vessel-disease/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-advances-research-on-mysterious-blood-vessel-disease/">Mayo Clinic advances research on mysterious blood vessel disease</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Weyand-gca-feature-image-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Weyand-gca-feature-image-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Cornelia Weyand]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Giant Cell Arteritis]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic and GE HealthCare enter strategic collaboration to advance innovation in medical imaging and theranostics</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-and-ge-healthcare-enter-strategic-collaboration-to-advance-innovation-in-medical-imaging-and-theranostics/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jcaban]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 13:36:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GE HealthCare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medical innovation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374361</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Combining the world-class clinical and research expertise of Mayo Clinic with the deep research, engineering, and product development expertise of GE HealthCare, this new collaboration aims to forge an integrated innovation engine to advance the practice of radiology and care to patients worldwide. ROCHESTER, Minn. ― Today, Mayo Clinic and GE HealthCare announce a strategic [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-and-ge-healthcare-enter-strategic-collaboration-to-advance-innovation-in-medical-imaging-and-theranostics/">Mayo Clinic and GE HealthCare enter strategic collaboration to advance innovation in medical imaging and theranostics</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="577" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/RochesterMeeting-16x9-1-1024x577.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374365" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/RochesterMeeting-16x9-1-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/RochesterMeeting-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/RochesterMeeting-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/RochesterMeeting-16x9-1-1536x865.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/RochesterMeeting-16x9-1.jpg 1948w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><em>Combining the world-class clinical and research expertise of Mayo Clinic with the deep research, engineering, and product development expertise of GE HealthCare, this new collaboration aims to forge an integrated innovation engine to advance the practice of radiology and care to patients worldwide.</em></p>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. ― Today, Mayo Clinic and GE HealthCare announce a strategic healthcare collaboration for research and product development programs aimed to transform the experience of patients and clinicians in the practice of radiology and the delivery of novel therapies.</p>



<p>The Strategic Collaboration for Innovation in Medical Imaging and Theranostics comprises Mayo Clinic and GE HealthCare scientists, technology developers, clinicians and other healthcare providers. The collaboration seeks to better equip clinicians with technology to precisely diagnose and treat medical conditions and personalize the patient experience at each step of their care journey through the clinical translation of novel technologies and approaches to medical imaging and theranostics.</p>



<p>“We are at a critical time in healthcare – technology is rapidly evolving, and we have a responsibility to drive healthcare capabilities through clinical translation and adoption of advanced technologies,” says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/callstrom-matthew-r-m-d-ph-d/bio-20054437?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Matthew Callstrom, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, chair of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/radiology/sections/overview/ovc-20469630?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Radiology</a> at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota. “This collaboration brings our research and clinical teams’ expertise and feedback closer to product development and commercialization of innovation, ultimately accelerating the rate of translation of our research to patient care and offering greater opportunity for global impact.”</p>



<p>Building upon a long history of research collaborations between the two organizations, the alliance will deepen the collaborative efforts by focusing on four core areas:</p>



<ol type="1" start="1">
<li>Rapidly accelerating the development and clinical translation of <strong>advanced Magnetic Resonance (MR) technologies and techniques</strong>, transforming patient care through artificial intelligence (AI) enabled exams from order to report.</li>



<li>Transforming cancer care through precise imaging and dosimetry of highly targeted <strong>theranostic agents </strong>and enabling broader access through more efficient radioisotope production.</li>



<li>Making <strong>diagnostic and interventional ultrasound</strong> easier and faster to use and read, while advancing automation and quantification to improve patient access, consistency of care and clinician experience.</li>



<li>Improving the patient imaging experience across the care continuum by leveraging <strong>multi-modal data, AI and digital health platforms</strong> that together streamline clinical operations and support more personalized diagnosis and therapy.</li>
</ol>



<p>“Mayo Clinic is globally acknowledged to be among the best in healthcare and care innovation. By collaborating with their scientists, inventors and healthcare providers, we will accelerate innovation and increase the clinical impact of our technologies beyond what either of our organizations could achieve independently,” says Jan Makela, president and CEO of Imaging, GE HealthCare.</p>



<p>The multi-focal collaboration brings together clinical research, product development, application of new clinical uses and techniques, and increased access for patients. It features close alignment between research teams and the medical departments that depend on radiological data, spanning multiple radiological disciplines, cardiology, oncology, radiation oncology, vascular, neurology, nuclear medicine and urology. Collaboration activities and research will take place at Mayo Clinic’s campus in Rochester, Minnesota.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>About GE HealthCare Technologies Inc.</strong><br>GE HealthCare is a leading global medical technology, pharmaceutical diagnostics, and digital solutions innovator, dedicated to providing integrated solutions, services, and data analytics to make hospitals more efficient, clinicians more effective, therapies more precise, and patients healthier and happier. Serving patients and providers for more than 100 years, GE HealthCare is advancing personalized, connected, and compassionate care, while simplifying the patient’s journey across the care pathway. Together our Imaging, Ultrasound, Patient Care Solutions, and Pharmaceutical Diagnostics businesses help improve patient care from diagnosis, to therapy, to monitoring. We are an $18.3 billion business with 50,000 employees working to create a world where healthcare has no limits.</p>



<p>Follow us on&nbsp;<a href="https://www.facebook.com/GEHealthCare/">Facebook</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/gehealthcare/mycompany/">LinkedIn</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://twitter.com/GEHealthcare">Twitter</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.instagram.com/gehealthcare/">Instagram</a>, and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gehealthcare.com/insights?showPopup=false">Insights</a>&nbsp;for the latest news, or visit our website&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gehealthcare.com/">https://www.gehealthcare.com/</a>&nbsp;for more information.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>GE HealthCare Media Contact</strong>                                                                                                                           Caitlin Lamey                                                                                                                                                              M +1 951 249 1401                                                                                                                          <a href="mailto:Caitlin.Lamey@ge.com">Caitlin.Lamey@ge.com</a></p>



<p><strong>Mayo Clinic Media Contact</strong>                                                                                                                             Jeanette Caban – Business Development                                                                                <a href="mailto:Caban.Jeanette@mayo.edu">Caban.Jeanette@mayo.edu</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-and-ge-healthcare-enter-strategic-collaboration-to-advance-innovation-in-medical-imaging-and-theranostics/">Mayo Clinic and GE HealthCare enter strategic collaboration to advance innovation in medical imaging and theranostics</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/RochesterMeeting-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/RochesterMeeting-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[GE HealthCare]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[medical innovation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Study identifies risk factors for long-haul COVID disease in adults</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/study-identifies-risk-factors-for-long-haul-covid-disease-in-adults/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lynda De Widt]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Sep 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[COVID-19]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Bala Munipalli]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[long-haul COVID-19]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374021</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have identified risk factors that can cause adult COVID-19 patients to suffer symptoms that linger for months or years. The condition is often referred to as long-haul COVID. The findings are reported in the Journal of Investigative Medicine. Researchers surveyed more than 3,000 adults over the age of 18 who were treated [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/study-identifies-risk-factors-for-long-haul-covid-disease-in-adults/">Study identifies risk factors for long-haul COVID disease in adults</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="712" height="400" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Digitally-generated_molecule_of_SARS-CoV-2_virus_GettyImages-1357650209_1_16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374243" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Digitally-generated_molecule_of_SARS-CoV-2_virus_GettyImages-1357650209_1_16x9.jpg 712w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Digitally-generated_molecule_of_SARS-CoV-2_virus_GettyImages-1357650209_1_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 712px) 100vw, 712px" /></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have identified risk factors that can cause adult <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/coronavirus/symptoms-causes/syc-20479963" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">COVID-19</a> patients to suffer symptoms that linger for months or years. The condition is often referred to as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/coronavirus/in-depth/coronavirus-long-term-effects/art-20490351" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">long-haul COVID</a>. The findings are reported in the <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/10815589231190560" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Journal of Investigative Medicine</a>.</p>



<p>Researchers surveyed more than 3,000 adults over the age of 18 who were treated via Mayo Clinic's virtual COVID-19 clinics in Florida, Arizona and Minnesota between March 2020 and March 2021. They reviewed the patients' symptoms, the incidence of long-haul COVID in the group and how many were hospitalized due to COVID-19. The patients were also asked to rate their perception of the severity of their symptoms, whether they received a diagnosis of long-haul COVID, how long it took for them to resume their usual activities, and how much time they missed from work.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Study Findings</h2>



<p>"We found that patients with severe COVID-19 symptoms were more likely to have long-haul COVID than those who had mild symptoms," says Bala Munipalli, M.D., an internist at Mayo Clinic in Florida and co-senior author of the study. "A majority of these were women who had been hospitalized, suffered from psychological impacts from COVID-19 such as anxiety and depression, and required more than one month to return to their normal activities after the illness."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Munipalli_Bala_21559457_201911070239.jpg" alt="Dr. Bala Munipalli" class="wp-image-374245" style="width:301px;height:361px" width="301" height="361" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Munipalli_Bala_21559457_201911070239.jpg 667w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Munipalli_Bala_21559457_201911070239-250x300.jpg 250w" sizes="(max-width: 301px) 100vw, 301px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Bala Munipalli</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>The average age of the respondents in the study was 54 and most were women, including 57% of the patients surveyed who reported severe symptoms; 60% with mild symptoms; and 65% with moderate symptoms. Most patients (92%) with mild symptoms were able to resume their usual schedules within four weeks after COVID-19 infection, but 23% of these patients with mild acute infection developed long-haul COVID. Significantly more (37.4%) patients with severe symptoms were hospitalized than those with mild (0.9%) or moderate symptoms (4.8%). Hospitalized patients also reported having persistent symptoms of long-haul COVID (67%), needing a month or more to resume their usual activities, missing work for at least three weeks, and having negative psychological side effects.</p>



<p>Most respondents in the study reported long-haul COVID symptoms that lasted three to six months, with those symptoms ranging in severity. The most common symptoms in the study group were fatigue, loss of smell, altered taste, shortness of breath and poor sleep.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">More to learn</h2>



<p>"The inability to resume normal activities within one month after acute COVID-19 may be a predictive factor for long-haul COVID. As we continue to study this disease, we hope to gain a better understanding of who is susceptible to it, the symptoms that remain persistent, and how to best manage these patients in the early course of their illness," says Dr. Munipalli. "Additional studies may help guide the standardization of future assessment tools to evaluate impairment and also provide valuable information to employers, educators, policymakers and patients."</p>



<p>The researchers note that a multidisciplinary approach to long-haul COVID is needed and that healthcare personnel should recognize key symptoms, obtain a careful medical history and physical examination, as well as pay close attention to comorbid medical conditions in patients with persistent symptoms.</p>



<p>Dr. Munipalli says her team plans additional research focusing on treatments for long-haul COVID.</p>



<p>Other Mayo Clinic researchers on this paper include <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/abu-dabrh-abd-moain-moain-m-b-b-ch-m-s/bio-10031859" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Abd Moain Abu Dabrh, M.B., B.Ch., M.S.</a>; <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/knight-dacre-m-d/bio-20529283" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dacre Knight, M.D.</a>; Ilana Logvinov, M.D.; Stefan Paul; Troy Delaney, Yaohua Ma; Zhuo Li; and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/ganesh-ravindra-m-b-b-s-m-d/bio-20308859" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ravindra Ganesh, M.B.B.S., M.D.</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/study-identifies-risk-factors-for-long-haul-covid-disease-in-adults/">Study identifies risk factors for long-haul COVID disease in adults</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Digitally-generated_molecule_of_SARS-CoV-2_virus_GettyImages-1357650209_1_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Digitally-generated_molecule_of_SARS-CoV-2_virus_GettyImages-1357650209_1_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Bala Munipalli]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[long-haul COVID-19]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic in Florida opens downtown Jacksonville site focused on education, research</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-in-florida-opens-downtown-jacksonville-site-focused-on-education-research/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tia R. Ford]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 15:50:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[clinical trials]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[community engagement]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Downtown]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Alfredo Quinones Hinojosa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Folakemi Odedina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Kent Thielen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[equity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jacksonville]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=373879</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. ― Mayo Clinic in Florida has opened its Community Health Collaborative in downtown Jacksonville. The office aims to understand the healthcare needs of Mayo Clinic's neighbors and share health education and biomedical research that supports their needs. "Expanding Mayo Clinic’s footprint into downtown Jacksonville with a dedicated space for community engagement and Mayo [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-in-florida-opens-downtown-jacksonville-site-focused-on-education-research/">Mayo Clinic in Florida opens downtown Jacksonville site focused on education, research</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Jax-health-collaborative-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374199" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Jax-health-collaborative-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Jax-health-collaborative-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Jax-health-collaborative-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Jax-health-collaborative-16x9-1-1536x865.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Jax-health-collaborative-16x9-1-2048x1153.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. ― <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a> has opened its Community Health Collaborative in downtown Jacksonville. The office aims to understand the healthcare needs of Mayo Clinic's neighbors and share health education and biomedical research that supports their needs.</p>



<p>"Expanding Mayo Clinic’s footprint into downtown Jacksonville with a dedicated space for community engagement and Mayo Clinic research teams, allows us to fully explore innovative solutions that address the communities' most pressing health issues," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/thielen-kent-r-m-d/bio-20054148?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kent Thielen, M.D.</a>, CEO of Mayo Clinic in Florida. "This is truly an exciting time for our teams, and we look forward to reaching more of our community."</p>



<p>The site, in the Edward Ball Building near City Hall, is nearly 3,100 square feet of office space and dedicated areas for community health education, clinical trial participation, outreach and more. Mayo Clinic will not provide medical care at this location.</p>



<p>"The Community Health Collaborative is a positive step toward addressing health disparities and building health equity in our community," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/odedina-folakemi-t-ph-d/bio-20516377" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Folakemi Odedina, Ph.D.</a>, enterprise co-director, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-for-health-equity-community-engagement-research/community-engagement" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Health Equity and Community Engagement Research</a>. "Using an approach that meets people where they are, the downtown site will serve as a 'hub' where we’ll work with community organizations and others throughout the city for the health of the people."</p>



<p>"We’re excited to bring our local community in downtown Jacksonville expanded access to everything Mayo Clinic research offers to help improve health outcomes," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/quinones-hinojosa-alfredo-m-d/bio-20247553" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alfredo Quiñones-Hinojosa, M.D.</a>, dean of research at Mayo Clinic in Florida. "We’re working with our neighbors to collaborate on research studies that directly address the needs of the community and help us discover more possible treatments and cures. Our researchers also will gain valuable insight from the people we serve so we may continue our commitment to address healthcare issues important to populations in the areas we serve."</p>



<p>The Mayo Clinic Community Health Collaborative will offer the following:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Mayo Clinic Community Engagement (CE) Studios</h2>



<p>The <a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/blog/health-equity-research/tab/researcher/#Community%20Engagement%20Studios" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CE Studios</a> program helps researchers work directly with community members. Community experts sign up to participate and meet virtually with Mayo Clinic researchers to provide consultation, guidance and advice on reaching community members. The benefits of this process are mutual, as researchers gain specific insights, and community members learn firsthand about research that may affect them and others with similar experiences.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Mayo Clinic Community Research Registry</h2>



<p>The registry is a database of diverse people who have consented to be contacted for biomedical research opportunities including clinical trials and biospecimen research. The goal of the registry is to reduce the disproportionate effect of disease in racially and ethnically diverse communities. About 250 members of the Jacksonville community are currently enrolled in the registry.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Community Scientist Program</h2>



<p>This program is made up of "community scientists," or community members who collaborate with medical researchers to improve the health of those in their communities. Members participate in activities such as providing input on study designs, reviewing study recruitment materials for cultural appropriateness and giving community presentations to advocate for research. The program supports biomedical research advocates in local neighborhoods and helps them build trust between Mayo Clinic and their neighbors.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Community-Engaged Research Advisory Boards</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-clinical-translational-science/community/community-engaged-research-program/resources/advisory-boards" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Community Advisory Boards</a> are groups of community members who volunteer to consult with researchers. Board members are from a variety of backgrounds, meet regularly, and have broad scientific and local cultural knowledge. Board members also may work with community partners to develop activities to address community health needs.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Kevin Punsky, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-in-florida-opens-downtown-jacksonville-site-focused-on-education-research/">Mayo Clinic in Florida opens downtown Jacksonville site focused on education, research</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/JAX-health-collaborative1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Jax-health-collaborative-16x9-2.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[clinical trials]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[community engagement]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Downtown]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Alfredo Quinones Hinojosa]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Folakemi Odedina]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Kent Thielen]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[equity]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[health]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Jacksonville]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Finding the balance: Opioids and pain control after surgery</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/finding-the-balance-opioids-and-pain-control-after-surgery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Vincent Jacobbi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2023 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Cornelius Thiels]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Hallbera Gudmundsdottir]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[opioids]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=373922</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In a recent Mayo Clinic&#160;study, researchers found that most patients prescribed fewer opioids after surgery were able to maintain satisfactory comfort levels without requiring more prescription refills later. Under new evidence-based guidelines, patients undergoing various surgeries received fewer opioid pills, and 88% reported feeling "very" or "somewhat" satisfied with their pain management. Researchers worked with [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/finding-the-balance-opioids-and-pain-control-after-surgery/">Finding the balance: Opioids and pain control after surgery</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/10/several-prescription-medicine-oxycodone-opioids-bottles-on-a-table-with-spilled-tablets-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="several prescription medicine (oxycodone - opioids) bottles on a table with spilled tablets" class="wp-image-284726" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/10/several-prescription-medicine-oxycodone-opioids-bottles-on-a-table-with-spilled-tablets-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/10/several-prescription-medicine-oxycodone-opioids-bottles-on-a-table-with-spilled-tablets-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/10/several-prescription-medicine-oxycodone-opioids-bottles-on-a-table-with-spilled-tablets-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/10/several-prescription-medicine-oxycodone-opioids-bottles-on-a-table-with-spilled-tablets-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/10/several-prescription-medicine-oxycodone-opioids-bottles-on-a-table-with-spilled-tablets-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>In a recent Mayo Clinic&nbsp;<a href="https://journals.lww.com/annalsofsurgery/Fulltext/2023/08000/Finding_the_Balance_Between_Reduced_Opioid.10.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>, researchers found that most patients prescribed fewer opioids after surgery were able to maintain satisfactory comfort levels without requiring more prescription refills later.</p>



<p>Under new evidence-based guidelines, patients undergoing various surgeries received fewer opioid pills, and 88% reported feeling "very" or "somewhat" satisfied with their pain management.</p>



<p>Researchers worked with the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/core-resources/survey-research-center/about/project-types" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Survey Research Center</a>&nbsp;to survey patients undergoing a range of elective surgeries. The survey investigated their post-surgery experiences, overall pain management approach and opioid use.</p>



<p>The study’s results were used to understand the connection between reducing opioid prescriptions and patient satisfaction with pain relief.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Guideline development</strong></h2>



<p>The&nbsp;<a href="https://journals.lww.com/annalsofsurgery/Fulltext/2023/08000/Finding_the_Balance_Between_Reduced_Opioid.10.aspx#:~:text=Prior%20Guideline%20Development" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">guidelines were developed</a>&nbsp;through research that examined the amount of opioid medication used by patients, the number of pills left over and the frequency of refills. The results were then applied to create recommendations for prescribing opioids after surgery.</p>



<p>"We wanted to better understand how many pills each patient needed and how many were left over, which set the foundation for publishing guidelines to say how much people need to be prescribed," says senior author of the study&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/thiels-cornelius-a-d-o-m-b-a/bio-20452389" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cornelius A. Thiels, D.O.</a>, a surgical oncologist at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>The guidelines recommend either low, standard or high dosing for each procedure based on specific patient factors associated with variations in opioid requirements.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Dr.Thiels_Image.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374013" style="width:247px;height:370px" width="247" height="370" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Dr.Thiels_Image.jpg 533w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Dr.Thiels_Image-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 247px) 100vw, 247px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Cornelius A. Thiels, D.O.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We implemented these evidence-based guidelines into practice and developed educational content for pharmacists, surgeons, nurse practitioners, physician’s assistants and residents, and saw excellent compliance with the guidelines," says Dr. Thiels.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Impact on pain control</strong></h2>



<p>The study showed that while most patients experienced reasonable pain control with reduced opioid prescribing guidelines, a small group of patients did not find their needs met. That group may benefit from further tailoring and individualizing the opioid prescribing guidelines, the study concluded.</p>



<p>While the patient-focused survey supported managing pain with fewer opioids, it also underscored the need for accurate prescribing from the start. The researchers noticed that despite education efforts encouraging patients to dispose of unused opioids properly, many still had leftover pills, which could lead to misuse.</p>



<p>Misuse of prescription opioids remains an important contributor to the opioid epidemic in the U.S., with the study noting that in 2020 alone, 2.3 million people were reported to have a prescription opioid use disorder. That same year, over 16,000 people died from an overdose of prescription opioids.</p>



<p>Dr. Thiels says the findings underscore the need to balance managing pain and opioid use and the importance of educating patients and prescribing the right amount of medication in the first place.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="222" height="295" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Hallbera-Gudmundsdottir-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374014" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Hallbera Gudmundsdottir, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/research-activities/surgical-outcomes-program/fellows/hallbera-gudmundsdottir" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hallbera Gudmundsdottir, M.D.,</a>&nbsp;first author of the study, adds that the research "is an important first step toward not only safer but also better pain management for every patient after surgery."</p>



<p>Dr. Thiels and Dr. Gudmundsdottir note that future research will focus on using artificial intelligence to help achieve optimal pain control for every patient after discharge.</p>



<p>The&nbsp;Mayo Clinic&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</a>&nbsp;supported this research. Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://journals.lww.com/annalsofsurgery/Fulltext/2023/08000/Finding_the_Balance_Between_Reduced_Opioid.10.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This article originally appeared on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/09/07/finding-the-balance-opioids-and-pain-control-after-surgery/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/finding-the-balance-opioids-and-pain-control-after-surgery/">Finding the balance: Opioids and pain control after surgery</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/10/several-prescription-medicine-oxycodone-opioids-bottles-on-a-table-with-spilled-tablets-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/10/several-prescription-medicine-oxycodone-opioids-bottles-on-a-table-with-spilled-tablets-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Cornelius Thiels]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Hallbera Gudmundsdottir]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[opioids]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic study reveals proton beam therapy may shorten breast cancer treatment</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-study-reveals-proton-beam-therapy-may-shorten-breast-cancer-treatment/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lynda De Widt]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 22:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Robert Mutter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Proton Beam Therapy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=373735</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — In a randomized trial, published in The Lancet Oncology, Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center researchers uncover evidence supporting a shorter treatment time for breast cancer patients. The study compared two separate dosing schedules of pencil-beam scanning proton therapy, the most advanced type of proton therapy known for its precision in targeting cancer [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-study-reveals-proton-beam-therapy-may-shorten-breast-cancer-treatment/">Mayo Clinic study reveals proton beam therapy may shorten breast cancer treatment</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="800" height="450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Proton_beam_therapy_2_WF1518956_0008_16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-373771" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Proton_beam_therapy_2_WF1518956_0008_16x9.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Proton_beam_therapy_2_WF1518956_0008_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Proton_beam_therapy_2_WF1518956_0008_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — In a randomized trial, published in <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanonc/article/PIIS1470-2045(23)00388-1/fulltext">The Lancet Oncology</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a> researchers uncover evidence supporting a shorter treatment time for breast cancer patients. The study compared two separate dosing schedules of pencil-beam scanning proton therapy, the most advanced type of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/proton-therapy/about/pac-20384758?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">proton therapy</a> known for its precision in targeting cancer cells while preserving healthy tissue to reduce the risk of side effects.</p>



<p>Survival rates for <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a> continue to improve due to advances in diagnosis and treatment, leading to increasing emphasis on reducing the long-term toxicity of cancer treatment, including <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/radiation-therapy-for-breast-cancer/about/pac-20384940?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">radiotherapy</a>.</p>



<p>Prior to this study, all patients treated with proton postmastectomy radiotherapy (PMRT) had received a conventional 25- to 30-day course delivered five days per week over five to six weeks. The researchers hoped to demonstrate that condensing the course of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/home/orc-20185488?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">proton beam therapy</a>, a form of particle therapy that could spare the heart and lungs from radiation damage, may result in a similar side effect profile.</p>



<p>Eighty-two patients with indications for PMRT, many of whom had prior breast reconstruction, were randomized to either conventional fractionation (fractions of radiation dose) administered in 25 days, or a condensed 15-day hypofractionated schedule. With hypofractionation, a larger dose of radiotherapy is delivered with each treatment, allowing all radiotherapy to be completed in just three weeks. The investigators found that both conventional and hypofractionated proton therapy resulted in excellent control of the cancer while sparing surrounding normal tissue. Further, complication rates were comparable between the two study groups.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="800" height="533" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Mutter_at_proton_therapy_center_in_Rochester_1629227_3883636_0007no-brand-name.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-373773" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Mutter_at_proton_therapy_center_in_Rochester_1629227_3883636_0007no-brand-name.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Mutter_at_proton_therapy_center_in_Rochester_1629227_3883636_0007no-brand-name-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Mutter_at_proton_therapy_center_in_Rochester_1629227_3883636_0007no-brand-name-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> Robert Mutter, M.D.</figcaption></figure>



<p>"The study provides the first prospective data supporting the use of shorter-course proton PMRT, including in patients with immediate breast reconstruction, and the first mature results of a randomized trial in the field of breast particle therapy," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/mutter-robert-w-m-d/bio-20343551" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Robert Mutter, M.D.</a>, a radiation oncologist and physician-scientist at Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center. "We can now consider the option of 15 days of therapy with patients based on the similar treatment outcomes observed as the longer conventional course. Of note, the short course actually resulted in reduced skin side effects during and after treatment."</p>



<p>Importantly, the researchers noted that the new schedule spares patients additional inconvenience, cost, and other burdens associated with the longer regimen. As there are a limited number of proton therapy facilities in the United States and the world, Dr. Mutter adds that demonstrating the safety and feasibility of the shorter treatment course could result in greater access to proton beam technology for difficult-to-treat breast cancer cases.</p>



<p>The researchers say additional investigation into the optimal PMRT dose and fractionation is warranted. The team plans additional research, investigating the delivery of PMRT in as few as five days.</p>



<p>"Ultimately, our goal is to personalize radiotherapy based on tumor biology," Dr. Mutter says. "We want to identify the best possible radiotherapy schedules or drug-radiotherapy combinations to eliminate cancer while minimizing side effects."</p>



<p>The research was funded by a grant from the National Cancer Institute, Mayo Clinic, and&nbsp;a gift from&nbsp;Lawrence and Marilyn Matteson. For a full list of funding, authors, and conflicts of interest, see the <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanonc/article/PIIS1470-2045(23)00388-1/fulltext">paper</a>.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is expanding its proton beam therapy services in Rochester, Minnesota, with a $200 million&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-announces-plans-to-expand-proton-beam-therapy-services-in-minnesota/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">facility expansion project</a>&nbsp;expected to open in 2027. Mayo Clinic opened its first Minnesota proton facility in 2015. In 2016, Mayo Clinic opened the Southwest’s first proton therapy facility at its Arizona site. Now, construction is underway on a new, 200,000-square-foot integrated oncology building on&nbsp;Mayo Clinic’s campus in Florida where proton beam therapy will be delivered to patients when available in 2026. The facility also will allow Mayo Clinic researchers to study <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-hitachi-to-build-first-next-generation-carbon-ion-therapy-treatment-facility-in-north-america/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">carbon ion therapy</a> in clinical trials as a potential treatment.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Comprehensive&nbsp;Cancer Center</strong><br>Designated as a comprehensive cancer center by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Cancer Institute</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;is defining new boundaries in possibility, focusing on patient-centered care, developing novel treatments, training future generations of cancer experts, and bringing cancer research to communities. At Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center, a culture of innovation and collaboration is driving research breakthroughs that are changing approaches to cancer prevention, screening, and treatment and improving the lives of cancer survivors.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Kelley Luckstein, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-study-reveals-proton-beam-therapy-may-shorten-breast-cancer-treatment/">Mayo Clinic study reveals proton beam therapy may shorten breast cancer treatment</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Proton_beam_therapy_2_WF1518956_0008_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Proton_beam_therapy_2_WF1518956_0008_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Robert Mutter]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Proton Beam Therapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Stress test abnormalities reveal more than just cardiovascular risks, Mayo Clinic study finds</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/stress-test-abnormalities-reveal-more-than-just-cardiovascular-risks-mayo-clinic-study-finds/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jay Furst]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2023 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cardiovascular disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Thomas Allison]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[exercise test]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hypertension]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Proceedings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stress Test]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=373776</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. —&#160;The treadmill exercise test with electrocardiogram (ECG), also known as an exercise stress test, is one of the most familiar tests in medicine. While exercise testing typically is focused on diagnosing coronary artery disease, a recent study from Mayo Clinic finds that exercise test abnormalities, such as low functional aerobic capacity, predicted non-cardiovascular [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/stress-test-abnormalities-reveal-more-than-just-cardiovascular-risks-mayo-clinic-study-finds/">Stress test abnormalities reveal more than just cardiovascular risks, Mayo Clinic study finds</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="682" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Cardiac-stress-test-original-1024x682.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-373782" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Cardiac-stress-test-original-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Cardiac-stress-test-original-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Cardiac-stress-test-original-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Cardiac-stress-test-original-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Cardiac-stress-test-original.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. —&nbsp;The treadmill <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/stress-test/about/pac-20385234?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">exercise test</a> with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ekg/about/pac-20384983?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">electrocardiogram (ECG)</a>, also known as an exercise stress test, is one of the most familiar tests in medicine. While exercise testing typically is focused on diagnosing coronary artery disease, a recent study from Mayo Clinic finds that exercise test abnormalities, such as low functional aerobic capacity, predicted non-cardiovascular causes of death such as cancer in addition to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/cardiovascular-medicine/home/orc-20121930?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cardiovascular</a>-related deaths. These new findings are published in <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/article/S0025-6196(23)00284-7/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a>.</p>



<p>The exercise stress test is noninvasive, easily available and provides important diagnostic information. In addition to the ECG itself, the test produces data on functional aerobic capacity, heart rate recovery and <a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/discussion/chronotropic-incompetence/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chronotropic index</a>, the standardized measure of heart rate during exercise that reflects age, resting heart rate and fitness.</p>



<p>"In our exercise testing cohort, non-cardiovascular deaths were more frequently observed than cardiovascular deaths," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/allison-thomas-g-ph-d-m-p-h/bio-20053049?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Thomas Allison, Ph.D., M.P.H.</a>, director of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/integrative-medicine-health/sections/tests-procedures/orc-20464680?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic's Integrated Stress Testing Center</a> and the study's senior author. "Though this was a cardiac stress test, we found that cancer was the leading cause of death, at 38%, whereas only 19% of deaths were cardiovascular.&nbsp;Exercise test results including low exercise capacity, low peak heart rate, and a slow recovery of the heart rate after exercise test were associated with increased mortality."</p>



<p>The study looked at 13,382 patients who had no baseline cardiovascular issues or other serious diseases and who had completed exercise tests at Mayo Clinic between 1993 and 2010, then were followed closely for a median period of 12.7 years.</p>



<p>The findings suggest that clinicians should focus not only on ECG results but on data in the exercise test results such as low functional aerobic capacity, low chronotropic index and abnormal heart rate recovery. Patients should be encouraged to increase their <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/fitness/in-depth/aerobic-exercise/art-20045541?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">physical activity</a> if these results are atypical, even if the ECG results show no significant cardiovascular-related risk, Dr. Allison says.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Proceedings</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a> is a monthly peer-reviewed journal that publishes original articles and reviews on clinical and laboratory medicine, clinical research, basic science research, and clinical epidemiology. The journal, sponsored by Mayo Foundation for Medical Education and Research as part of its commitment to physician education, has been published for 97 years and has a circulation of 127,000.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and to providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Jay Furst, Mayo Clinic Education Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/stress-test-abnormalities-reveal-more-than-just-cardiovascular-risks-mayo-clinic-study-finds/">Stress test abnormalities reveal more than just cardiovascular risks, Mayo Clinic study finds</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Cardiac-stress-test-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/Cardiac-stress-test-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cardiovascular disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Thomas Allison]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[exercise test]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Hypertension]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Proceedings]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Stress Test]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>