<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Research - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research-2/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research-2/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2024 14:30:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Genetic testing pinpoints cardiovascular risk in patients with aortic disorders</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/genetic-testing-pinpoints-cardiovascular-risk-in-patients-with-aortic-disorders/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Vincent Jacobbi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2024 14:30:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[M. Hassan Murad]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mohammed Firwana]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science of Health Care Delivery]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381403</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A new Mayo Clinic systematic review has shed light on genetically inherited aortic disorders in patients, highlighting the importance of early diagnosis and treatment for those with inherited cardiovascular risk.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/genetic-testing-pinpoints-cardiovascular-risk-in-patients-with-aortic-disorders/">Genetic testing pinpoints cardiovascular risk in patients with aortic disorders</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/AI-heart.jpg" alt="Digital heart" class="wp-image-381420" style="width:830px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/AI-heart.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/AI-heart-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></figure></div>


<p>A new Mayo Clinic systematic <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S074152142301306X?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">review</a> has shed light on genetically inherited aortic disorders, highlighting the importance of early diagnosis and treatment for those who have inherited cardiovascular risk.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The researchers identified that a procedure known as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/thoracic-aortic-aneurysm/multimedia/endovascular-repair-for-thoracic-aortic-aneurysm/img-20123853#:~:text=In%20endovascular%20thoracic%20aortic%20aneurysm,with%20small%20hooks%20or%20pins." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Thoracic Endovascular Aortic Repair (TEVAR)</a> provided a high survival rate for young adult patients with type B <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/aortic-dissection/symptoms-causes/syc-20369496" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">aortic dissections</a>. Type B aortic dissections consist of a tear in the descending part of the aorta that may extend into the abdominal aorta.</p>



<p>"We studied type B aortic dissections and aortic aneurysms and their management, especially in people born with genetic complications or syndromes," says Mohammed M. Firwana, M.B.B.S., research fellow and lead author of the study.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img decoding="async" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Firwana_Mohammed_21674922_202003050932-250x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381417" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Firwana_Mohammed_21674922_202003050932-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Firwana_Mohammed_21674922_202003050932.jpg 667w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mohammed M. Firwana, M.B.B.S., research fellow and lead author of the study.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Notably, in over one-third of patients, genetic testing identified new aortic events within 15&nbsp;years. Patients with genetic risk factors exhibited a 62% rate of recurring aortic events, compared with 11% in patients without genetic risk factors, signifying the potential for more severe complications in the presence of such disorders.</p>



<p>Dr. Firwana adds that some of the findings varied by race, underlining the critical need for awareness and early treatment across all demographics.</p>



<p>"One of the more interesting findings was that Black patients with genetic risk factors had lower mortality than White patients, and that's mostly explained by how they presented at a younger age and their condition was likely managed earlier," says Dr. Firwana.<br><br>Researchers underscore that aortic aneurysms, dissections, and ruptures are thought to be the cause of 43,000 to 47,000 fatalities in the U.S. each year and that approximately 20% of thoracic aortic aneurysms are related to the genetic condition, also known as heritable thoracic aortic disease. These conditions are often silent but can lead to aortic dissection or rupture with often fatal outcomes.</p>



<p>Dr. Firwana emphasizes that identifying certain genetic mutations provides important knowledge and understanding of genetically inherited aortic disorders in patients.</p>



<p>He adds that there are multiple risk factors that can lead to a higher likelihood of aortic disorders, for example, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/marfan-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20350782" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Marfan syndrome</a>, a connective tissue disease, that affects one in 5,000 people in the U.S.</p>



<p>Dr. Firwana notes that another condition that can leave people prone to aortic issues is hypertension.</p>



<p>"Hypertension stands out as an important risk factor," says Dr. Firwana.</p>



<p>"It contributes to the weakening of the walls of the aorta over time, making them more susceptible to tearing or dissection."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/WF516862_0012-1-200x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381418" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/WF516862_0012-1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/WF516862_0012-1.jpg 533w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">M. Hassan Murad, M.D., senior author of the study</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Researchers note that the systematic review is being used to help support guideline development&nbsp;when managing genetically inherited aortic disorders in patients and that more research is needed to identify the role of Thoracic Endovascular Aortic Repair in patients with&nbsp;connective tissue disease.</p>



<p>Dr. Firwana emphasizes that quitting smoking, managing hypertension, and addressing diabetes are crucial preventive strategies for those with these genetic predispositions.</p>



<p>"A panel of experts from the Society for Vascular Surgery will use this systematic review to develop a clinical practice guideline that aims to help patients make decisions about their care," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/murad-m-hassan-m-d/bio-00094157" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">M. Hassan Murad, M.D.,</a> senior author of the study. "Further research on this topic can guide tailored interventions for improved patient outcomes."</p>



<p>The <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/education-training" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</a> supported this research. Review the <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S074152142301306X?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/genetic-testing-pinpoints-cardiovascular-risk-in-patients-with-aortic-disorders/">Genetic testing pinpoints cardiovascular risk in patients with aortic disorders</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/AI-heart-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/AI-heart.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[M. Hassan Murad]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mohammed Firwana]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Science of Health Care Delivery]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>World Cancer Day: Making a commitment to close the cancer care gap</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/world-cancer-day-making-a-commitment-to-close-the-cancer-care-gap/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2024 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer care gap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Rick Bold]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381393</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Union for International Cancer Control (UICC) recognizes&#160;World Cancer Day&#160;annually on February 4. The UICC's 2024 theme for World Cancer Day is "Close the Care Gap." The care gap is the gap between people who can obtain healthcare related to the prevention, early detection, diagnosis and treatment of cancer and those who cannot. The factors [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/world-cancer-day-making-a-commitment-to-close-the-cancer-care-gap/">World Cancer Day: Making a commitment to close the cancer care gap</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1017" height="572" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381396" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_16x9.jpg 1017w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1017px) 100vw, 1017px" /></figure>



<p>The Union for International Cancer Control (UICC) recognizes&nbsp;<a href="https://www.worldcancerday.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">World Cancer Day</a>&nbsp;annually on February 4. The UICC's 2024 theme for World Cancer Day is "Close the Care Gap." The care gap is the gap between people who can obtain healthcare related to the prevention, early detection, diagnosis and treatment of cancer and those who cannot.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Bold-Rick-J._30304260_20231002-819x1024-1-240x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381394" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Bold-Rick-J._30304260_20231002-819x1024-1-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Bold-Rick-J._30304260_20231002-819x1024-1-768x960.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Bold-Rick-J._30304260_20231002-819x1024-1.jpg 819w" sizes="(max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /></figure></div>


<p>The factors that create this gap include income, education and geographical location barriers. Discrimination based on ethnicity, race, gender, sexual orientation, age, disability and lifestyle can also be a barrier. Some people are also more likely to be exposed to factors that increase cancer risk, such as environmental hazards, unhealthy diet and tobacco.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic joins the UICC in breaking down barriers that stand in the way of cancer care. In this Q&amp;A,&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/richard-bold-m-d-named-site-director-mayo-clinic-comprehensive-cancer-center-in-arizona/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Rick Bold, M.D.</a>, site deputy director for&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>&nbsp;in Arizona, discusses Mayo Clinic's commitment to closing the cancer care gap:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What does World Cancer Day mean to Mayo Clinic?</h2>



<p>It means understanding the gaps in our cancer care and our cancer outcomes. It means recognizing those gaps by intentionally trying to close and eliminate them. There are different ways to define the gap; it may be related to the incidence of cancer, it may be related to the outcomes of cancer, and it may be related to access to cancer care. Each of these is a different gap that affects how people cope with cancer, how people survive cancer, and how people are diagnosed with cancer. We should strive to close and eliminate each of these gaps.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What is Mayo Clinic doing to help close the cancer care gap?</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20370588" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cancer</a> is not just one disease. For example, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a> is different for each person. Understanding why breast cancer developed at an individualized level — personalized or precision medicine — helps us determine the proper treatment for that patient and leads to better outcomes. Maybe a woman's genes caused cancer to develop. Perhaps it's where she lived — her environmental history or what she ate. We're doing <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials/search-results?studySiteStatusesGrouped=Open/Status%20Unknown&amp;pocId=CON-20167633" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">studies</a> reaching out to women across different communities, ethnic backgrounds and age groups to understand how <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/breast-cancer-risk-assessment/about/pac-20393195" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer risk</a> is determined. If every person is different, we need to understand that their cancer is different based on who they are. That's one effort that's helping to close the cancer care gap.</p>



<p>Another effort to close the gap is improving access to screening. Cancer screening is one of the most effective tools to reduce the burden of cancer in our communities. However, only some people have access to screening. Mayo Clinic is asking: How can we help everyone get access? How can we make screening easier? For example, can we detect&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/colon-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353669" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colon cancer</a>&nbsp;with a blood test instead of a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/colonoscopy/about/pac-20393569" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">colonoscopy</a>? Can we detect it&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/fecal-occult-blood-test/multimedia/fecal-occult-blood-test-kit/img-20007541" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">with a stool sample</a>&nbsp;collected in a person's home without time away from work or family or disrupting intestinal function by drinking a solution to cleanse the colon for a colonoscopy? Mayo Clinic is researching cancer screening tools that can be made available to more people conveniently at a lower cost. These efforts can help us close the gap by detecting more cancers at their earliest stage, which is when cures happen.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is also using technology to close the gap. One example of this is&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/proton-beam-therapy-program/sections/overview/ovc-20185491" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">proton beam therapy</a>&nbsp;for radiation. Mayo Clinic has two proton therapy units, one in Scottsdale, Arizona, and one in Rochester, Minnesota. We've studied how to deliver proton beam therapy in a way that improves patient outcomes. Some people can't take the time to get radiation, which may last weeks or months. Using proton beam therapy, we can shorten treatment time, broadening access by making it more convenient for people to get treatment in a minimally disruptive way.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What is Mayo Clinic doing to reach out to underserved and rural communities facing cancer care barriers?</h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic is developing cancer screening techniques that can be implemented internationally while recognizing that even in the U.S., not everybody has a hospital or a cancer center nearby. Many people are geographically isolated from healthcare or may lack insurance that pays for screening. We're trying to identify methods that could detect a variety of cancers early in a patient-friendly fashion, no matter what environment a person is living in and no matter what resources they have.</p>



<p>All Mayo Clinic locations see themselves as serving the community around them. We are developing strategic partnerships and relationships to elevate access to care in those communities and share our clinical expertise. This moves our care beyond the walls of our hospitals and clinics. Moving cancer care into patients' homes is becoming a national concept. We're starting to delve into that model of care. This will expand our ability to serve a broader population, not just in our local communities but nationally or internationally.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What is Mayo Clinic's goal for the future of cancer care?</h2>



<p>The ideal goal would be to eliminate cancer or turn cancer into a disease nobody needs to worry about. That's a long-term goal, and maybe we will get there.</p>



<p>In the shorter term, the goal is to achieve equitable cancer care that provides the best outcomes in a way that doesn't significantly disrupt the lives of patients and their families while respecting their individuality and their role in decision-making. We want to put all those things together and then always keep working on improving outcomes.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is committed to eliminating care gaps so every patient, regardless of where they live or who they are, receives the same cancer care and experiences the same positive outcomes. Mayo Clinic is here to serve patients. That's our primary mission.</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/02/01/world-cancer-day-making-a-commitment-to-close-the-cancer-care-gap/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center Blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/world-cancer-day-making-a-commitment-to-close-the-cancer-care-gap/">World Cancer Day: Making a commitment to close the cancer care gap</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/shutterstock_583329955-1024x682_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer care gap]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Rick Bold]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New 4D imaging may detect poor pumping in deadly heart disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-4d-imaging-may-detect-poor-pumping-in-deadly-heart-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lynda De Widt]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. DeLisa Fairweather]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[myocarditis]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=380837</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Researchers at Mayo Clinic in Florida have found that a newer imaging technique may find subtle changes in heart dysfunction during acute stages of myocarditis and also heart functional differences by sex.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-4d-imaging-may-detect-poor-pumping-in-deadly-heart-disease/">New 4D imaging may detect poor pumping in deadly heart disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="366" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Echocardiogram_2_1505832_3734178_0046-16x9-1.jpg" alt="An image of a technician performing an echocardiogram on the heart" class="wp-image-380847" style="aspect-ratio:16/9;object-fit:cover;width:814px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Echocardiogram_2_1505832_3734178_0046-16x9-1.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Echocardiogram_2_1505832_3734178_0046-16x9-1-300x200.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></figure></div>


<p>In a new study, Mayo Clinic researchers found that a novel 4D echo imaging method that measures cardiac strain may detect subtle changes in the heart's dysfunction during acute <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/myocarditis/symptoms-causes/syc-20352539" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">myocarditis</a>, a deadly heart disease. In addition, they were able to describe heart functional differences by sex using the technology in a preclinical model. Currently, there are no disease-specific therapies to treat myocarditis.</p>



<p>The research is published in <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2589004223025701" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">iScience</a>.</p>



<p>An <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/echocardiogram/about/pac-20393856" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">echocardiogram</a> is one of the most common methods of measuring heart function and allows physicians to screen for heart issues, as well as monitor patients with existing heart conditions, such as myocarditis, or inflammation of the heart muscle often caused by viral infections. The test shows how blood moves through the heart's chambers and valves. Cardiac strain is a measurement that shows how well the heart muscle can move. When the muscle is inflamed, it can stiffen. It is particularly important to know the function of the left ventricle, which is the most muscular and hard-working chamber of the heart.</p>



<p>Myocarditis occurs most frequently in men under the age of 50 (especially ages 16-30). Women are at the greatest risk of developing the condition after the age of 50, or when they are postmenopausal, according to the researchers.</p>



<p>In this study, the researchers used a model of viral myocarditis to compare sex differences in male and female mice with myocarditis to a control group of mice after day 10 of infection. The researchers discovered that sex differences existed in cardiac strain during myocarditis, which they say was not known previously, and that worse cardiac strain in male mice with myocarditis correlated with more cardiac inflammation than in female mice with the condition. The data suggested that worse cardiac function may correlate to the severity of cardiac inflammation.</p>



<p>That data allowed the researchers to predict which mice were most likely to suffer from heart failure, which also occurs more often in men.</p>



<p>Researchers analyzed different echocardiography imaging techniques to measure heart function and found that the more traditional ones had limits and only showed a small portion of the total picture of how the heart changes during the disease process.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-right-align-caption">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="814" height="543" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/image.png" alt="Image of DeLisa Fairweather, Ph.D." class="wp-image-380839" style="width:294px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/image.png 814w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/image-300x200.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/image-768x512.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 814px) 100vw, 814px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">DeLisa Fairweather, Ph.D., is director of translational research for the Department of Cardiovascular Medicine at Mayo Clinic in Florida.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Until<strong> </strong>now, we have not had access to technology that can precisely describe small changes in cardiac function during acute myocarditis," says the study's senior author, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/fairweather-delisa-ph-d/bio-20320752" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">DeLisa Fairweather, Ph.D.</a>, vice-chair of translational research for the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/cardiovascular-medicine/home/orc-20121930" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Cardiovascular Medicine</a> at Mayo Clinic in Florida, where she also leads a <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/translational-cardiovascular-disease-research/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Translational Cardiovascular Disease Research Laboratory</a>. "Using a novel 4D echocardiography imaging technique in mice, we more precisely described functional changes in cardiac strain that occur during myocarditis by sex. Knowing how our model functionally relates to human disease allows us to draw clearer conclusions as to the efficacy of novel treatments moving forward that can save patients' lives."</p>



<p>The researchers say their findings demonstrate the importance of using cardiac strain to assess cardiac function in patients with suspected myocarditis, and especially focusing on sex differences, which are associated with clinical outcomes.</p>



<p>"Our discoveries will help us investigate how effective new treatments and drugs may be for human disease and how they may improve cardiac function using our preclinical model," says Dr. Fairweather. "This can make the process of assessing new drugs for treatment faster and more accurate."</p>



<p>"Cardiac strain also can be used to assess patients for changes in heart function during earlier stages of disease, which means doctors can treat them earlier to mitigate long-term, irreversible heart damage," she added.</p>



<p>Dr. Fairweather's body of research on myocarditis also includes a recently published paper in <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/smll.202303317" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">the journal Small</a> that found that extracellular vesicles isolated from the platelets of healthy people used in a mouse model of viral myocarditis decreased inflammation and improved cardiac function. Dr. Fairweather says this preclinical research will pave the way for future clinical trials in humans. The research team says their work on cardiac strain demonstrates key differences in cardiac function between male and female mice with myocarditis and matches what is found clinically in patients.</p>



<p>The next step in the team's research is to use these techniques when testing new treatments for myocarditis in their preclinical animal model.</p>



<p>This research was supported by the National Institutes of Health (NIH) under grant award R01 HL164520, American Heart Association and Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about/about-regenerative-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</a>. For a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding, see the <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2589004223025701" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">paper</a>.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-4d-imaging-may-detect-poor-pumping-in-deadly-heart-disease/">New 4D imaging may detect poor pumping in deadly heart disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Echocardiogram_2_1505832_3734178_0046-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Echocardiogram_2_1505832_3734178_0046-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. DeLisa Fairweather]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[myocarditis]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Growing mini-organs to find new treatments for complex disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/growing-mini-organs-to-find-new-treatments-for-complex-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Buckles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Brooke Druliner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Charles Howe]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. William Faubion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Organoids]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381038</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic investigators are growing three-dimensional human intestines in a dish to track disease and find new cures for complex conditions such as inflammatory bowel disease. These mini organs function like human intestines with the ability to process metabolites that convert food into energy on a cellular level and secrete mucus that protects against bacteria. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/growing-mini-organs-to-find-new-treatments-for-complex-disease/">Growing mini-organs to find new treatments for complex disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid2-16x9-1-1024x577.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381047" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid2-16x9-1-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid2-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid2-16x9-1-768x433.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid2-16x9-1.jpg 1155w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Microscopic view of an intestinal organoid</figcaption></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> investigators are growing three-dimensional human intestines in a dish to track disease and find new cures for complex conditions such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/inflammatory-bowel-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353315" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">inflammatory bowel disease</a>. These mini organs function like human intestines with the ability to process metabolites that convert food into energy on a cellular level and secrete mucus that protects against bacteria. These 3D mini intestines in a dish, known as "organoids," provide a unique platform for studying the intricacies of the human gut.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Brooke-Druliner-300x200.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381053" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Brooke-Druliner-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Brooke-Druliner-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Brooke-Druliner-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Brooke-Druliner-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Brooke-Druliner.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Brooke Druliner, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Cells that cluster into the 3D intestinal organoids are grown from a small amount of human intestinal tissue containing epithelial stem cells, taken from a person via a biopsy or surgery. Epithelial cells provide a protective barrier on skin, glands and internal organs and have shown potential for healing and regeneration. <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/druliner-brooke-r-ph-d/bio-20520602" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Brooke Druliner, Ph.D.</a>, leads this team science research.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/howe-charles-l-ph-d/bio-00083834" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Charles Howe, Ph.D.</a>, directs the Office of Core Shared Services and is working with Dr. Druliner and others across the Mayo Clinic to build the infrastructure in support of organoid-based research and translation.</p>



<p>"Thanks to these advancements, we are closer than ever to being able to create a "patient-in-a-dish" platform," he says. "Intestines in a dish are an example of how this new research tool will help us better understand inflammatory reactions in gastrointestinal-tract diseases. Our hope is this could lead to new drug targets and treatments."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A growing health problem</h2>



<p>Inflammatory bowel disease is a growing worldwide health problem that affects approximately 3 million people in the U.S., according to the <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/ibd/features/IBD-more-chronic-diseases.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Centers for Disease Control</a>. It encompasses a group of inflammatory conditions that affect the digestive system such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/crohns-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353304" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Crohn's disease</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/ulcerative-colitis/symptoms-causes/syc-20353326" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ulcerative colitis</a>. Symptoms of inflammatory bowel disease include abdominal pain and diarrhea but vary widely from one person to the next, posing a challenge in finding successful treatments. Immunotherapies are commonly prescribed but are effective only 40% of the time, and few patients experience lasting relief.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="574" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid1-16x9-1-1024x574.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381039" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid1-16x9-1-1024x574.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid1-16x9-1-300x168.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid1-16x9-1-768x431.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid1-16x9-1.jpg 1186w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Microscopic view of an intestinal organoid</figcaption></figure>



<p>Intestinal organoids provide a new, humanlike tool for tracking inflammatory bowel disease.</p>



<p>"A combination of animal and human models is more effective for our research. Intestinal organoids have the potential to allow us to screen drugs for toxicity and monitor effectiveness before the drug is tested in a clinical trial," says Dr. Druliner.</p>



<p>A Mayo Clinic research team including Dr. Druliner and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/faubion-william-a-jr-m-d/bio-00027222" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">William Faubion, Jr., M.D.</a>, a gastroenterologist-researcher and medical director for <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic's Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics,</a> is using these intestinal organoids to recreate features of inflammatory bowel disease.</p>



<p>Their robust research with intestinal organoids is bolstered in part by the more than 4,000 patients that come to Mayo Clinic every year with inflammatory bowel disease. Consenting patients donate tissue to a specialized biobank, and that tissue is matched with immune cells from the same patient. Those tissues and cells are used to create individualized 3D mini-intestines, with the goal of using these models for testing therapies tailored to the specific patient's individual disease.</p>



<p>"Our goal is to use our models to identify inflammatory bowel disease subtypes with predictable outcomes, including response to therapy or risk of disease progression," says Dr. Druliner.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Revolutionizing research</strong></h2>



<p>The broader vision is to one day expand 3D organoids from a variety of organs, preserve them and use them to track disease and screen drugs for a wide range of conditions including cancer, epilepsy, heart disease and dementia.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Charles-Howe-300x200.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381052" style="width:294px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Charles-Howe-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Charles-Howe-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Charles-Howe-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Charles-Howe-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Charles-Howe.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Charles Howe, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We think this has the potential to revolutionize the way we approach disease research. We hope to save time and resources and avoid development of therapies that fail upon translation into patients," says Dr. Howe. "Understanding which treatments show potential for success in human organoids could dramatically accelerate the rate of new therapies for patients with unmet needs."</p>



<p>A long-term goal would be to not only use the intestinal organoids for drug identification but also as a source of tissue regeneration to heal disease.</p>



<p>The researchers have partnered with the Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics to discuss the potential for biomanufacturing these mini organs in the future and how to establish quality control, reproducibility and scalability.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Challenges to overcome</strong></h2>



<p>The organoid research team already has overcome many challenges, including understanding ways to identify and collect fresh tissue to grow the organoids, and how to test if they accurately mimic the function of their original organ. Researchers are currently trying to address issues of quality control and validation to ensure the mini organs are accurate representations of a patient's individual disease. Another goal is to include more diverse cells such as immune cells, neurons or vasculature cells in these mini organs.</p>



<p>This research was initially made possible by Mayo Clinic's Cells2Cures initiative and Mayo Clinic’s Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics. It is now funded in part by an Organoid Biomanufacturing for Transforming Healthcare grant from the <a href="https://www.minnesotapartnership.info/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Minnesota Partnership for Biotechnology and Medical Genomics</a>, which is working towards establishing a joint Mayo Clinic – University of Minnesota Organoid Center. Learn more about this grant and the principal investigators from the University of Minnesota on the <a href="https://www.minnesotapartnership.info/2023/12/21/minnesota-partnership-awards-five-collaborative-research-grants-for-2023/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Minnesota Partnership website</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Related resources:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-mini-brain-study-reveals-possible-key-link-to-autism-spectrum-disorder/">Mayo Clinic ‘mini-brain’ study reveals possible key link to autism spectrum disorder</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/minnesota-partnership-awards-five-collaborative-research-grants-for-2023/">Minnesota Partnership awards five collaborative research grants for 2023</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/growing-mini-organs-to-find-new-treatments-for-complex-disease/">Growing mini-organs to find new treatments for complex disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid2-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Organoid2-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Brooke Druliner]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Charles Howe]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. William Faubion]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Organoids]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Mayo Clinic stem cell research to take flight into space</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-stem-cell-research-to-take-flight-into-space/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lynda De Widt]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 14:28:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bone Loss]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Abba Zubair]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stem Cells]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stem cells in space]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=380364</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Update 1-30-24: According to NASA, a successful launch occurred at 12:07 EST. The spacecraft is scheduled to link with the International Space Station during the early morning hours of Feb.1. Update 1-29-24: NASA has moved the launch of this mission to Tuesday, Jan. 30, subject to weather conditions and other factors. You can watch for [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-stem-cell-research-to-take-flight-into-space/">New Mayo Clinic stem cell research to take flight into space</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/MVI_1410_1-1024x576.jpg" alt="SpaceX CRS-10 mission blast off from NASA's Kennedy Space Center with Dr. Zubair's stem cell research" class="wp-image-113641" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/MVI_1410_1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/MVI_1410_1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/MVI_1410_1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/MVI_1410_1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Update 1-30-24:</strong> According to NASA, a successful launch occurred at 12:07 EST.  The spacecraft is scheduled to link with the International Space Station during the early morning hours of Feb.1.</p>



<p></p>



<p><strong>Update 1-29-24: </strong> NASA has moved the launch of this mission to Tuesday, Jan. 30, subject to weather conditions and other factors.  You can watch for updates by following <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/event/nasas-northrop-grumman-crs-20-mission/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">NASA's launch schedule</a>.  Video assets with Dr. Zubair have been added below.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p></p>



<p>A Mayo Clinic research experiment will be part of a payload that launches into space from NASA's <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/kennedy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kennedy Space Center</a> in Cape Canaveral, Florida, on Jan. 29, subject to weather conditions and other factors. The research team from the lab of <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/zubair-abba-c-m-d-ph-d/bio-00092417" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Abba Zubair</a> is preparing <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bone-marrow-transplant/in-depth/stem-cells/art-20048117" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stem cells</a> for the flight to test how the absence of gravity plays a role in bone loss.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr._Zubair_in_lab_2017_1504453_3696200_0018R-200x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-380366" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr._Zubair_in_lab_2017_1504453_3696200_0018R-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr._Zubair_in_lab_2017_1504453_3696200_0018R.jpg 534w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr. Abba Zubair</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We've known for some time that astronauts lose bone density on long-duration space flights," says Dr. Zubair, a laboratory medicine and pathology specialist at Mayo Clinic in Florida. "We want to understand how this occurs so we can work on solutions that prevent bone loss not only in astronauts while they're in space, but also in patients here on Earth."</p>



<p>The research project will examine the effect of gravity on a type of stem cells derived from bone marrow known as mesenchymal stem cells, or adult stem cells with growth factors and healing potential. They play a key role in tissue repair and regeneration. Dr. Zubair's team will look at how the stem cells function while in space. Dr. Zubair says the experiment could have implications for future space flights that include taking humans to Mars.</p>



<p>This early research also could affect human clinical trials down the road, perhaps a decade away, according to Dr. Zubair.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeDcmT7xhSdUg"  title="New Mayo Clinic stem cell research to take flight into space" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/DcmT7xhSdUg?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: B-ROLL and Broadcast-quality sound bites with Dr. Zubair are available in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Name super/CG: Abba Zubair, M.D., Ph.D./Laboratory Medicine and Pathology&nbsp;/Mayo Clinic.</strong></p>



<p>"We will use what we learn from this project to advance our research on the road to clinical trials, with the ultimate goal of testing therapeutic agents that can prevent or treat bone loss that comes with osteoporosis, as well as bone loss that occurs in patients who are bedridden for long periods of time," he says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="219" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Stem_cells_cultivated_with_red_growth_medium_GettyImages-1140201087-300x219.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-380368" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Stem_cells_cultivated_with_red_growth_medium_GettyImages-1140201087-300x219.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Stem_cells_cultivated_with_red_growth_medium_GettyImages-1140201087-768x560.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Stem_cells_cultivated_with_red_growth_medium_GettyImages-1140201087.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Stem cells cultivated with red growth medium</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>The research will be conducted during two space flights. The first space flight will evaluate the impact of microgravity on bone-forming stem cells. The second space flight is tentatively planned for the end of the year and will analyze the effect of microgravity on other cell types that participate in bone formation or loss. A compound will be tested that can be used to treat bone loss in space and potentially on Earth.</p>



<p>The <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/blast-off-stem-cells-from-mayo-clinic-physicians-lab-launch-into-space/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">first foray into space</a> for Dr. Zubair's research was in 2017, when a payload of several samples of donated stem cells blasted off from Kennedy Space Center in a test to determine if they could hold up in space and be more quickly mass-produced in microgravity for use in stroke treatment. A subsequent research experiment in space found that <a href="https://regenerativemedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2020/06/18/stem-cells-in-space-interstellar-research-to-improve-regenerative-therapies/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stem cells grown in weightlessness</a> are safe and feasible for applications to human disease.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is collaborating with <a href="https://www.colorado.edu/center/bioserve/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bioserve Space Technologies</a> in Boulder, Colorado, which is providing the space flight hardware for the research project.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-mayo-clinic-stem-cell-research-to-take-flight-into-space/">New Mayo Clinic stem cell research to take flight into space</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/03/Launch1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/02/MVI_1410_2.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Bone Loss]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Abba Zubair]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Stem Cells]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[stem cells in space]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Save the date! RegenBio Summit: Transforming Next-Gen Biotherapeutics</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/save-the-date-regenbio-summit-transforming-next-gen-biotherapeutics/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Buckles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 13:00:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#biomanufacturing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#biomedical research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#biotherapeutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Dr. Julie Allickson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Dr. Saranya Wyles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Mayo Clinic RegeBio Summit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Regenerative medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=380970</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The need for lifesaving options for diseases with no treatment or cure is great, and Mayo Clinic is addressing that challenge in part with a new conference focused on advancing first-of-their kind regenerative biotherapies. RegenBio Summit: Transforming Next-Gen Biotherapeutics will be held Dec. 9 to 11 at the Ponte Vedra Inn &#38; Club in Ponte [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/save-the-date-regenbio-summit-transforming-next-gen-biotherapeutics/">Save the date! RegenBio Summit: Transforming Next-Gen Biotherapeutics</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="463" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Resize-WF1385852_0143.jpg" alt="A Mayo Clinic researcher studies biotherapeutics.
" class="wp-image-380978" style="aspect-ratio:16/9;object-fit:cover;width:839px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Resize-WF1385852_0143.jpg 463w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Resize-WF1385852_0143-300x200.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 463px) 100vw, 463px" /></figure>



<p>The need for lifesaving options for diseases with no treatment or cure is great, and Mayo Clinic is addressing that challenge in part with a new conference focused on advancing first-of-their kind regenerative biotherapies.</p>



<p><a href="https://ce.mayo.edu/content/regenbio-summit-transforming-next-gen-biotherapeutics#group-tabs-node-course-default1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">RegenBio Summit: Transforming Next-Gen Biotherapeutics</a> will be held Dec. 9 to 11 at the Ponte Vedra Inn &amp; Club in Ponte Vedra Beach, Florida. Save the date for an event that will bring together the best minds in medicine, biotechnology and entrepreneurship to discuss how to best bring a new class of medicines known as biotherapies to all patients. Regenerative biotherapies are made from human sources such as blood, cells and tissue and have shown potential for targeted healing with few side effects.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Wyles2-300x200.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381163" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Wyles2-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Wyles2-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Wyles2.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Saranya Wyles, M.D., Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We are living longer, but those extra years are often burdened with chronic disease," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/wyles-saranya-p-m-d-ph-d/bio-20476857" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Saranya Wyles, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, a dermatologist and associate director for education in Mayo Clinic's <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</a>. "Regenerative biotherapeutics offer hope of increasing health longevity by focusing on restoring health and function."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Collaborations to advance biotherapeutics</h2>



<p>The summit is an opportunity to build collaborations between academia, regulatory agencies and industry. Because this field of medicine is rapidly progressing, a cell or gene therapy may face different regulatory standards in the U.S. than it would in&nbsp; Europe or Asia. That can raise questions that slow or stall approvals of a new drug. A key topic of discussion will be setting global guidelines for new regenerative biotherapies to advance them from research into standard of care.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic will also highlight ways its unique biomanufacturing structure is designed to accelerate new discoveries from the lab to early-stage clinical trials. Mayo Clinic's advanced biomanufacturing operations are based on industry best practices and driven by patient need. The operations coordinate process development, quality control and quality assurance to ensure an emerging therapy meets standards for commercial grade biotherapies.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Allickson_WF782604_0002-300x200.jpg" alt="Julie Allickson, Ph.D." class="wp-image-378671" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Allickson_WF782604_0002-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Allickson_WF782604_0002-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Allickson_WF782604_0002.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Julie Allickson, Ph.D</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We're planning to share Mayo Clinic's blueprint of how to develop and disseminate new biotherapies in the most trusted way for patient care," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/allickson-julie-g-ph-d/bio-20523656" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Julie Allickson, Ph.D.</a>, the Michael S. and Mary Sue Shannon Director of the Mayo Clinic Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics. "Our biomanufacturing model is designed to troubleshoot and address problems early, so a new regenerative intervention can be seamlessly transferred to an industry collaborator, creating the bridge for safe and effective biotherapies to improve patients' lives worldwide."</p>



<p>Dr. Allickson is also the Otto Bremer Trust Director, Biomanufacturing and Product Development, <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advancing-patient-care-with-biologics-4-ways-mayo-clinics-biomanufacturing-strategy-is-making-a-difference/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics.</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Exploring the future of healthcare</h2>



<p>Regenerative biotherapeutics are projected to make up 10% of all health care interventions in the coming years. The summit will explore a possible future with tissue engineering, 3D bioprinting, cell therapies, gene and viral therapies, and cell-free interventions and how they might apply to medical practice areas such as orthopedics, cancer, cardiology, neurology and transplant. In addition, there will be sessions on training the future workforce to deliver these promising therapies to patients. The summit will bring together a global community of peers, thought leaders and organizations invested in regenerative therapies.</p>



<p>Registration for RegenBio Summit: Transforming Next-Gen Biotherapeutics will open in the coming weeks. Watch the <a href="https://ce.mayo.edu/content/regenbio-summit-transforming-next-gen-biotherapeutics#group-tabs-node-course-default1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">summit website</a> for announcements on keynote speakers, plenaries and fireside chats.</p>



<p>Attendees can earn continuing medical education credits.</p>



<p>###</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/save-the-date-regenbio-summit-transforming-next-gen-biotherapeutics/">Save the date! RegenBio Summit: Transforming Next-Gen Biotherapeutics</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/biotherapeutics-WF1385852_0143_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/biotherapeutics-WF1385852_0143_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#biomanufacturing]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#biomedical research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#biotherapeutics]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Dr. Julie Allickson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Dr. Saranya Wyles]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Mayo Clinic RegeBio Summit]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Regenerative medicine]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mcthumb >https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Resize-WF1385852_0143-150x150.jpg</mayoclinic:mcthumb >	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: How precise diagnosis of lymphoma offers patients best treatment options</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-precise-diagnosis-of-lymphoma-offers-patients-best-treatment-options/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Lisa Rimsza]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lymphoma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=379901</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Dr. Lisa Rimsza&#160;is a pathologist, director of the&#160;Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory&#160;and researcher with the&#160;Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center. Her research specializes in&#160;lymphoma,&#160;with a focus on developing tests for accurate patient diagnoses and assessing disease aggressiveness. Dr. Rimsza has made significant advances in this field of research.&#160;She says having a precise diagnosis allows physicians to [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-precise-diagnosis-of-lymphoma-offers-patients-best-treatment-options/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How precise diagnosis of lymphoma offers patients best treatment options</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/rimsza-lisa-m-m-d/bio-20185498?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Lisa Rimsza</a>&nbsp;is a pathologist, director of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/laboratory-medicine-pathology/overview/specialty-groups/laboratory-genetics/molecular-genetics-laboratory?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory</a>&nbsp;and researcher with the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>. Her research specializes in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/lymphoma/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20352642" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymphoma,</a>&nbsp;with a focus on developing tests for accurate patient diagnoses and assessing disease aggressiveness.</p>



<p>Dr. Rimsza has made significant advances in this field of research.&nbsp;She says having a precise diagnosis allows physicians to provide patients with the best possible treatment.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/M6ARKpwlWYU" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeM6ARKpwlWYU"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Why precision diagnosis is crucial for patients" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/M6ARKpwlWYU?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:05) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: “Mayo Clinic News Network.” Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Script-MCM-Precision-diagnosis.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"My lab focuses on&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-what-is-lymphoma/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lymphoma</a>, which is a group of diseases and cancers that arise from the lymphatic systems," says Dr. Rimsza.<br><br>"We specialize in developing new tests to make sure we can get the most accurate diagnosis for the patient, and also figure out whether their disease is likely to be more or less aggressive," she says.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="Lisa Rimsza, M.D., in the Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory" class="wp-image-380355" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Rimsza-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Lisa Rimsza, M.D., in the Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory</figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>"We've been working with an interesting platform, or technology platform, which actually is able to use the tissue that is most commonly available from patient biopsies when a biopsy is taken out. It's put in formaldehyde and then in paraffin wax," she says. "We've been using a technology that actually is able to work with that tissue and get good information about genes and expression."</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Lisa Rimsza, M.D., and team in the Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory. Front row, from left: Charlie Kern, Colleen Ramsower and Dr. Rimsza. Back row, from left: Lindsey Armitage, Lee Wisner, Jon Ocal, Katie Zellner." class="wp-image-380360" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-and-Team-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Lisa Rimsza, M.D., and team in the Mayo Clinic Molecular Diagnostic Laboratory. Front row, from left: Charlie Kern, Colleen Ramsower and Dr. Rimsza. Back row, from left: Lindsey Armitage, Lee Wisner, Jon Ocal, Katie Zellner.</figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>"It's absolutely important that the patient has the most accurate diagnosis as possible. And what we're doing is going through the most common types of lymphomas, and trying to build a series of assays that will answer several different diagnostic questions," says Dr. Rimsza.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Learn more about Dr. Rimsza's work:</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f4yhqxCY7mk" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Lisa Rimsza - 2023 Arizona Bioscience Research of the Year</a></li>



<li><a href="https://news.mayocliniclabs.com/2023/11/14/rna-test-identifies-large-b-cell-lymphoma-subtypes-lisa-rimsza-m-d/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">RNA test identifies large B-cell lymphoma subtypes</a></li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-understanding-treating-lymphoma/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Understanding, treating lymphoma</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/consumer-health-treating-leukemia-and-lymphoma/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Consumer Health: Treating leukemia and lymphoma</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-precise-diagnosis-of-lymphoma-offers-patients-best-treatment-options/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How precise diagnosis of lymphoma offers patients best treatment options</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-researcher-lab-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr.-Lisa-Rimsza-microscope-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Lisa Rimsza]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[lymphoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Graves&#8217; disease &#8211; when the thyroid is overactive</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-graves-disease-when-the-thyroid-is-overactive/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 15:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Marius Stan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Graves' Disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thyroid]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=379586</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Graves' disease is an autoimmune disorder that triggers the thyroid gland to produce more thyroid hormones than the body needs. It's the most common cause of&#160;hyperthyroidism, or an overactive thyroid. Dr. Marius Stan, a Mayo Clinic endocrinologist, has more on this&#160;thyroid disorder.&#160; Editor's note: January is National Thyroid Disease Awareness Month. Watch: The Mayo Clinic [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-graves-disease-when-the-thyroid-is-overactive/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Graves&#8217; disease &#8211; when the thyroid is overactive</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/graves-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20356240?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Graves' disease</a> is an autoimmune disorder that triggers the thyroid gland to produce more thyroid hormones than the body needs. It's the most common cause of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hyperthyroidism/symptoms-causes/syc-20373659?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hyperthyroidism</a>, or an overactive thyroid.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/stan-marius-n-m-d/bio-20055065?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Marius Stan</a>, a Mayo Clinic endocrinologist, has more on this&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/graves-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20356240?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">thyroid disorder</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Editor's note: January is National Thyroid Disease Awareness Month.</h4>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/mhYeuD_Z3Po" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubemhYeuDZ3Po"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Thyroid overdrive – understanding Graves&#039; disease" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mhYeuD_Z3Po?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:05) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/SCRIPT-MCM-Graves-disease-MNS-edits9292.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"Thyroid, and mainly thyroid hormones, are the gas pedal, if you will, for the body," says Dr. Stan.</p>



<p>"And as we're pushing that gas pedal, metabolism accelerates, our heart rate beats faster, we feel hot, we can't rest, we can't sleep," he says.</p>



<p>Other symptoms of Graves' disease may include&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hyperthyroidism/expert-answers/thyroid-disease/faq-20058228?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">anxiety</a>, weight loss, heat sensitivity and bulging eyes.</p>



<p>"It's a situation of an overactive thyroid that is caused by antibodies that we unfortunately produce that end up really whipping the thyroid into an overactive state," he says.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-media-text is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="303" height="303" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/08/a-medical-illustration-of-the-thyroid-gland-1X1.jpg" alt="a medical illustration of the thyroid gland. Graves' disease triggers the thyroid gland to produce more thyroid hormones than the body needs. " class="wp-image-245984 size-full" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/08/a-medical-illustration-of-the-thyroid-gland-1X1.jpg 303w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/08/a-medical-illustration-of-the-thyroid-gland-1X1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/08/a-medical-illustration-of-the-thyroid-gland-1X1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 303px) 100vw, 303px" /></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p>The thyroid gland is located at the base of the neck, just below the Adam's apple.</p>
</div></div>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Medications are often the first line of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/graves-disease/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20356245?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">treatment</a>. When that doesn't work,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/thyroidectomy/about/pac-20385195?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">surgery</a>&nbsp;or radioactive iodine to destroy the thyroid tissue may be an option.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr. Stan is leading several clinical&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/stan-marius-n-m-d/bio-00028124" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">research</a>&nbsp;trials targeting the disorder.</p>



<p>"I'm quite optimistic, looking at some of the early results of our trials, that there will be major benefits for patients in the coming years," he says.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">When to see a doctor</h3>



<p>Graves' disease, the most common cause of hyperthyroidism, is more common among women and in people younger than age 40.</p>



<p>If you experience unintentional weight loss, a rapid heartbeat, unusual sweating, swelling at the base of your neck, or other signs of hyperthyroidism, schedule an appointment with your healthcare professional. Make sure to communicate all observed symptoms, including minor ones, during your appointment.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/sharing-mayo-clinic-an-eye-on-the-future/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sharing Mayo Clinic: An eye on the future</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-women-and-thyroid-disease-2/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Women and thyroid disease</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treating-thyroid-nodules-without-surgery/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Treating thyroid nodules without surgery</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-graves-disease-when-the-thyroid-is-overactive/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Graves&#8217; disease &#8211; when the thyroid is overactive</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/closeup-of-young-white-or-perhaps-Asian-woman-touching-her-neck-near-her-throat-maybe-a-goiter-thyroid-disease-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/closeup-of-young-white-or-perhaps-Asian-woman-touching-her-neck-near-her-throat-maybe-a-goiter-thyroid-disease-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Marius Stan]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Graves' Disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Thyroid]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research fuels advances in bile duct cancer care</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/research-fuels-advances-in-bile-duct-cancer-care/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2024 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bile duct cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sumera Ilyas]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=380174</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Bile duct cancer, also known as cholangiocarcinoma, forms in the thin tubes that carry bile from your liver to your gallbladder and small intestine. Though relatively rare, cholangiocarcinoma is often diagnosed in later stages, making it more difficult to treat, and cases in the U.S. are increasing. In a&#160;review article&#160;published in Nature Reviews Clinical Oncology [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/research-fuels-advances-in-bile-duct-cancer-care/">Research fuels advances in bile duct cancer care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/05/multi-pipette-research-of-cancer-stem-cells-_shutterstock_261331172_16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="multi pipette research of cancer stem cells" class="wp-image-238754" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/05/multi-pipette-research-of-cancer-stem-cells-_shutterstock_261331172_16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/05/multi-pipette-research-of-cancer-stem-cells-_shutterstock_261331172_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/05/multi-pipette-research-of-cancer-stem-cells-_shutterstock_261331172_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Bile duct cancer, also known as cholangiocarcinoma, forms in the thin tubes that carry bile from your liver to your gallbladder and small intestine. Though relatively rare, cholangiocarcinoma is often diagnosed in later stages, making it more difficult to treat, and cases in the U.S. are increasing.</p>



<p>In a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41571-023-00770-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">review article</a>&nbsp;published in Nature Reviews Clinical Oncology in 2023, lead author&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/ilyas-sumera-i-m-b-b-s/bio-20258409" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sumera I. Ilyas, M.B.B.S.</a>, and co-authors share advances in diagnosing, staging and treating bile duct cancer. Dr. Ilyas is a Mayo Clinic physician-scientist and a transplant hepatologist whose&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/ilyas-sumera-i-m-b-b-s/bio-10031656" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">research</a>&nbsp;focuses on the immunobiology of liver cancer. Here is a summary of their review:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The immune microenvironment of bile duct tumors promotes their growth.</h2>



<p>Dr. Ilyas says bile duct cancers have distinct tumor immune microenvironments (TIMEs). Researchers have begun to understand the complexity of these TIMEs and their relationship with the three different types of cholangiocarcinoma —&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cholangiocarcinoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20352408" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">intrahepatic, hilar and distal</a>. The TIMEs of bile duct cancer have fewer cytotoxic cells — immune cells that help kill mutated and cancerous cells— and more cells that suppress the immune system. TIMEs may affect how the disease progresses and whether it can be treated with immunotherapy.</p>



<p>The genetic profile of different segments of bile duct tumors can also vary, known as heterogeneity. This makes it more challenging to target characteristics of the tumor for treatment.</p>



<p>Researchers are trying to understand how TIMEs help bile duct cancer grow and progress, evade the immune system and resist chemotherapy. Altering the TIME could make treatments more effective, &nbsp;including&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy/checkpoint-inhibitors" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">immune checkpoint inhibitors</a>&nbsp;and other&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">immunotherapy</a>&nbsp;treatments.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Blood and bile samples may help diagnose bile duct cancer earlier.</h2>



<p>Diagnosing bile duct cancer early, when it's easier to treat, is a challenge. This is partly because cancer experts don't yet have the right tests and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/def/biomarker" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">biomarkers</a>&nbsp;to detect cholangiocarcinoma. "Efforts to identify better biomarkers to help diagnose the disease at an early stage and help gauge response to treatment are important," explains Dr. Ilyas. "Currently, there is a great deal of ongoing research focused on the use of tumor DNA in diagnosing and monitoring cholangiocarcinoma in patients receiving treatment."</p>



<p>Dr. Ilyas says research has identified potential biomarkers for cholangiocarcinoma. Researchers are now studying how biomarkers obtained through blood and bile samples from patients can help improve cholangiocarcinoma diagnosis. They are also looking for ways to detect and monitor tumors using&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/def/liquid-biopsy" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">liquid biopsies</a>, which use DNA that breaks away from the tumor to circulate in bodily fluids like blood or bile. "Although we anticipate that liquid biopsy may enhance early detection of cholangiocarcinoma, larger scale studies are needed to confirm its effectiveness," she says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Bile duct cancer treatments are improving.</h2>



<p>"Systemic treatment options for cholangiocarcinoma were once quite limited and not very effective," says Dr. Ilyas. Systemic therapies are drugs used to treat cancer, such as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/chemotherapy/about/pac-20385033" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chemotherapy</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">targeted therapy</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">immunotherapy</a>.</p>



<p>Targeted therapies are drugs targeting mutations that control how cancer cells grow, divide and spread. With a better understanding of the different genetic profiles of bile duct cancer subtypes, cancer experts are developing new treatments tailored to specific types of cholangiocarcinoma. The Food and Drug Administration has approved several new drugs that target specific genetic mutations associated with bile duct tumor growth. "The emergence of targeted therapies has broadened treatment options and, in doing so, given much more hope to our patients," says Dr. Ilyas.</p>



<p>Immunotherapy uses the body's immune system to attack cancer. While immunotherapy has not yet proven effective for treating cholangiocarcinoma, Dr. Ilyas says ongoing research to identify biomarkers and to understand why bile duct cancer doesn't respond to immunotherapy may improve outcomes.</p>



<p>Researchers are also studying liver transplants as a treatment option for cholangiocarcinoma in select patients with certain tumor types. However, Dr. Ilyas says this form of treatment needs further research.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Learn more</h2>



<p>Learn about&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cholangiocarcinoma/symptoms-causes/syc-20352408" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cholangiocarcinoma</a>&nbsp;and find a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials/search-results?keyword=cholangiocarcinoma&amp;studySiteStatusesGrouped=Open/Status%20Unknown" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">clinical trial</a>&nbsp;at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>Join the&nbsp;<a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/group/cancer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cancer Support Group</a>&nbsp;on Mayo Clinic Connect, an online community for patients and caregivers.</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://cancerblog.mayoclinic.org/2024/01/10/research-fuels-advances-in-bile-duct-cancer-care/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/research-fuels-advances-in-bile-duct-cancer-care/">Research fuels advances in bile duct cancer care</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/05/multi-pipette-research-of-cancer-stem-cells-_shutterstock_261331172_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/05/multi-pipette-research-of-cancer-stem-cells-_shutterstock_261331172_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[bile duct cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Sumera Ilyas]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Unlocking the mechanisms of HIV in preclinical research</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/unlocking-the-mechanisms-of-hiv-in-preclinical-research/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Buckles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Andrew Badley]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HIV]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=379964</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have unraveled the molecular mechanisms that affect which&#160; cells infected with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) die and which survive, a discovery heralded as a step toward eliminating all HIV-infected cells from the body. This pioneering research goes beyond two common approaches to treating HIV infections. The first approach is to block HIV [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/unlocking-the-mechanisms-of-hiv-in-preclinical-research/">Unlocking the mechanisms of HIV in preclinical research</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="575" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/GettyImages-1445701859-Red-Ribbon-16x9-2-1024x575.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-379969" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/GettyImages-1445701859-Red-Ribbon-16x9-2-1024x575.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/GettyImages-1445701859-Red-Ribbon-16x9-2-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/GettyImages-1445701859-Red-Ribbon-16x9-2-768x431.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/GettyImages-1445701859-Red-Ribbon-16x9-2-1536x863.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/GettyImages-1445701859-Red-Ribbon-16x9-2-2048x1150.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have unraveled the molecular mechanisms that affect which&nbsp; cells infected with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hiv-aids/symptoms-causes/syc-20373524" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)</a> die and which survive, a discovery heralded as a step toward eliminating all HIV-infected cells from the body.</p>



<p>This pioneering research goes beyond two common approaches to treating HIV infections. The first approach is to block HIV proteins, thereby preventing HIV cell replication. The second is to prevent HIV from reaching cells. However, neither treatment reduces the number of cells in the body that contain HIV, and these cells, also known as the HIV reservoir, are resistant to all current therapies. &nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="225" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr-Badley3x4-225x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-379965" style="width:132px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr-Badley3x4-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/Dr-Badley3x4.jpg 396w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Andrew Badley, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"This research takes a new approach to eliminate HIV-infected cells. Our premise was that if we could understand how some HIV infected cells die following acute HIV infection, then we could design medical interventions which cause most HIV infected cells to die," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/badley-andrew-d-m-d/bio-00026694" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Andrew Badley, M.D.</a>, senior author of the study.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The findings of this decade long Mayo Clinic research are published in the <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36448802/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Journal of Virology</a>.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Research to understand HIV proteins</strong></h2>



<p>The key to unlocking the mystery of what causes HIV-infected cells to die or survive is understanding how HIV proteins bind with other proteins inside the cell. When a cell is infected with HIV, that cell produces a protein called Casp8p41. Previously the Mayo research team discovered that Casp8p41 causes the HIV-infected cell to die. However not all HIV-infected cells die because Casp8p41 can bind to a human protein called Bcl2, which neutralizes Casp8p41. The team discovered if Casp8p41 binds to Bcl2, then the HIV-infected cells survive. However, if Casp8p41 does not bind to Bcl2 then the infected cell dies, and the number of HIV-infected cells diminish.</p>



<p>"Our team found that what determines whether or not a cell lives or die is how much of those two proteins they have," says Dr. Badley.</p>



<p>Researchers applied this discovery to probe whether a Bcl2 inhibitor could eliminate HIV-infected cells in mouse models by blocking Bcl2 from binding to Casp8p41. Bcl2 inhibitors have shown similar properties against blood cancers.</p>



<p>This research demonstrated that the Bcl2 inhibitor has potential for killing infected cells, including "sleeper" cells that harbor HIV and reducing the HIV reservoir.</p>



<p>The Mayo Clinic team is one of the first, if not the first, to move this research into mice implanted with human immune systems and infected with HIV. Dr. Badley's team compared the cells of mice receiving the Bcl2 inhibitor to cells from a control group of mice without the inhibitor.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A disease with no cure</strong></h2>



<p>HIV causes <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hiv-aids/symptoms-causes/syc-20373524" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS)</a>, a chronic, potentially life-threatening condition that destroys cells that coordinate the immune system, weakening it. HIV can be suppressed with combination of drugs, known as antiretroviral therapy, that reduces replication of HIV-infected cells. Antiretroviral therapy does not kill infected cells or reduce the size of the HIV reservoir, which could become active at any time, producing new HIV.</p>



<p>"Data in our study confirm meaningful anti-HIV effects of the Bcl2 inhibitor during HIV infection in humanized mouse models. Our hope is that this research will contribute to an eventual cure for HIV," says Dr. Badley.</p>



<p>More study is needed to confirm these findings.</p>



<p>Review <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36448802/">the study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p>###</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/unlocking-the-mechanisms-of-hiv-in-preclinical-research/">Unlocking the mechanisms of HIV in preclinical research</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/GettyImages-1445701859-Red-Ribbon-1x1-2.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/01/GettyImages-1445701859-Red-Ribbon-16x9-2.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Andrew Badley]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[HIV]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>