<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Research - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research-2/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research-2/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 11:33:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Beyond BRCA1/2: Pinpointing the risk of inherited breast cancer genes</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/beyond-brca1-2-pinpointing-the-risk-of-inherited-breast-cancer-genes/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Fergus Couch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Goetz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Siddhartha Yadav]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[genetics]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376407</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Risk can be a complicated and confounding concept, particularly when it comes to life-or-death situations like cancer. The discovery of the BRCA1 and BRCA2 genes in the 1990s enabled many women to learn they are at high risk of developing breast cancer. More than a dozen other breast cancer genes have been identified since, but [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/beyond-brca1-2-pinpointing-the-risk-of-inherited-breast-cancer-genes/">Beyond BRCA1/2: Pinpointing the risk of inherited breast cancer genes</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" width="1000" height="563" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/01/Immunohistochemistry-for-HER2-shows-positive-cell-membrane-staining-in-this-infiltrating-ductal-carcinoma_shutterstock_392445517_16x9.jpg" alt="Immunohistochemistry for HER2 shows positive cell membrane staining in this infiltrating ductal carcinoma" class="wp-image-181530" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/01/Immunohistochemistry-for-HER2-shows-positive-cell-membrane-staining-in-this-infiltrating-ductal-carcinoma_shutterstock_392445517_16x9.jpg 1000w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/01/Immunohistochemistry-for-HER2-shows-positive-cell-membrane-staining-in-this-infiltrating-ductal-carcinoma_shutterstock_392445517_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/01/Immunohistochemistry-for-HER2-shows-positive-cell-membrane-staining-in-this-infiltrating-ductal-carcinoma_shutterstock_392445517_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Immunohistochemistry for HER2 shows positive membrane staining in this infiltrating ductal carcinoma. At the molecular level, breast cancer is typically broken down into four major subtypes — triple-negative, HER2-positive, luminal A and luminal B — each with different degrees of aggressiveness and responses to treatment.<br></figcaption></figure>



<p>Risk can be a complicated and confounding concept, particularly when it comes to life-or-death situations like cancer. The discovery of the BRCA1 and BRCA2 genes in the 1990s enabled many women to learn they are at high risk of developing breast cancer. More than a dozen other <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20352470" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">breast cancer</a> genes have been identified since, but the risks associated with them have been far less certain. Research from Mayo Clinic has filled critical gaps in the understanding of how these genes predispose women to disease, in ways that directly influence patient care.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full"><img decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Siddartha-Yadav-200x300-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376410" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Siddhartha Yadav, M.D.<br></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"This is truly bench to bedside research," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/yadav-siddhartha-m-b-b-s-m-d/bio-20489847" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Siddhartha Yadav, M.D.</a>, a medical oncologist and breast cancer researcher. "Just finding out you have one of these genetic alterations is not good enough — we need to know the risk so we can mitigate that risk."</p>



<p>Dr. Yadav has been working with cancer geneticist&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/couch-fergus-j-ph-d/bio-00027515" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Fergus Couch, Ph.D.</a>, for the last six years to define the risks that come with inheriting various genetic variants. In 2021, they and nearly 60 other researchers&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33471974/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">published a seminal study</a>&nbsp;in the New England Journal of Medicine that provided more accurate risk estimates for 28 different breast cancer genes.</p>



<p>"We’ve known about these genes for quite some time," says Dr. Couch. "But nobody ever had enough information or enough data to really say anything about the risks associated with them."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Aggregating Data to Estimate Risk</strong>s</h2>



<p>In 2016, Dr. Couch and his colleagues built a large, population-based study drawing from 17 established epidemiology studies such as the Harvard Nurses’ Health Study and the American Cancer Society’s Cancer Prevention Studies. The result was the Cancer Risk Estimates Related to Susceptibility (CARRIERS) consortium, which amassed a collection of samples from approximately 35, 000 women with breast cancer and another 35,000 women without breast cancer.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/1299536_3506340_0027-200x300-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376409" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Fergus Couch, Ph.D., is the Zbigniew and Anna M. Scheller Professor of Medical Research.<br></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Analyzing these samples revealed that the risks associated with mutations for women in the general population were lower than previous estimates, which had been based on high-risk populations with a personal or family history of breast cancer. The analysis, published in the&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33471974/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">seminal NEJM study</a>, indicated that 16 of the 28 genes previously thought to play a role in breast cancer did not increase a woman’s risk of disease.</p>



<p>"There was a lot of false information out there about what genes may or may not increase risk," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/goetz-matthew-p-m-d/bio-00027285" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Matthew Goetz, M.D.</a>, breast cancer oncologist and director of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/research-programs/womens-cancer-program/breast-cancer-spore/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic’s Breast Cancer&nbsp;SPORE</a>, which has funded research in this area since its creation in 2005. The&nbsp;<a href="https://trp.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">SPORE</a>, or Specialized Program of Research Excellence, is a cornerstone of the&nbsp;National Cancer Institute's efforts to promote collaborative, interdisciplinary translational cancer research.</p>



<p>"Dr. Couch’s work brought clarity, and led to the National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) taking at least one gene off their list of genes to test for," says Dr. Goetz.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/1173095_3367870_0012-200x300-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376408" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Matthew Goetz, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Updating Guidelines, Understanding Outcome</strong>s</h2>



<p>The NCCN is one of several organizations, including the American Society of Clinical Oncology and the American Society of Breast Surgeons, that have set guidelines for screening for inherited breast cancer gene changes, known as germline genetic testing. "Deciding who needs testing is one of the biggest controversies in the field," says Dr. Yadav. "Some have suggested all women get tested; others have recommended testing only women of a certain age."</p>



<p>Dr. Yadav and his colleagues evaluated these criteria, applying them to a large patient registry that included nearly 4,000 women treated for breast cancer at Mayo Clinic. They found that the NCCN guidelines missed 35-50% of patients with disease-causing genetic mutations. The findings, published in 2020 in the&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32125938/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Journal of Clinical Oncology</a>, led NCCN and other organizations to expand their guidelines on germline genetic testing.</p>



<p>Another area where the Mayo team has made a significant impact is in linking breast cancer genes to clinical outcomes. According to Dr. Yadav, women newly diagnosed with cancer in one breast often want to know the chances that the disease will spread to the other breast or to other parts of the body. "For BRCA1 and BRCA2 carriers, we knew that their risks were high," he says. "But for these other genes that cause breast cancer, what happens to those women? There were no answers to that."</p>



<p>Using data from the CARRIERS consortium, the researchers&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36623243/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">determined the risks</a>&nbsp;that women carrying different germline genetic mutations had of developing cancer in both breasts, known as contralateral breast cancer. For example, they found that carriers of ATM mutations did not have a significantly elevated risk of contralateral breast cancer, whereas those with BRCA1, BRCA2 and CHEK2 mutations had double the risk. The researchers believe the findings make genetic information more actionable, as different breast cancer genes appear to create tumors that behave quite differently.</p>



<p>At the molecular level, breast cancer is typically broken down into&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/in-depth/breast-cancer/art-20045654" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">four major subtypes</a>&nbsp;— triple-negative, HER2-positive, luminal A and luminal B — each with different degrees of aggressiveness and responses to treatment. Through an industry collaboration with a genetic testing company, the Mayo team analyzed testing results from nearly 55,000 breast cancer patients and found that&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32091585/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">different breast cancer genes</a>&nbsp;appear to drive each of the different subtypes.</p>



<p>"Those insights into tumor biology are critically important for treatment and prevention," says Dr. Goetz. "There are some drugs, for example, that work fairly well to reduce the risk of developing luminal A breast cancer, but they don’t do anything to reduce the risk of triple-negative breast cancer."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Examining Variants of Uncertain Significance</strong></h2>



<p>BRCA1, BRCA2 and most of the other genes associated with breast cancer are normally involved in repairing damage to DNA. When these genes are defective, DNA damage can accumulate, allowing cells to grow out of control and turn cancerous. Researchers have identified hundreds of genetic alterations that are known to cause breast cancer, but they have also uncovered thousands more that could either cause disease or be benign. These variants of uncertain significance (VUS), as they are called, are a big problem for clinicians and patients alike.</p>



<p>"There’s 30,000 women, probably more, in the United States carrying these types of variants and we don’t know what to do with them," says Dr. Couch. "We’re supposed to just ignore those results, but the psychological impact is already there. We hear stories about women getting prophylactic surgeries on the basis of VUS results just because they’re so worried about them."</p>



<p>Dr. Couch has led&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35736817/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">extensive efforts</a>&nbsp;to reclassify the VUS lurking in breast cancer genes, methodically reproducing one variant after another in the lab and assessing their effect on DNA repair. "Our approach has proved invaluable in improving our understanding of these different variants, but it has been slow-going," he says. "In 15 years, we’ve done about 500 variants of BRCA2." Recently, his team ramped up its research by using high-throughput, CRISPR-based gene editing technology to generate each variant, which will enable them to create a catalog of every possible VUS and their impacts.</p>



<p>In the future, the researchers plan to continue probing the connections between genes and breast cancer, examining how cancers with different genetic mutations respond to therapy and even searching for previously undiscovered breast cancer genes.</p>



<p>"This is not just some esoteric research that stays in the lab or an academic publication," says Dr. Couch. "These findings get rapidly integrated into the clinical workflow, informing patients about the risks they face and how to manage them."</p>



<p>This article first appeared on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/10/09/beyond-brca1-2-pinpointing-the-risk-of-inherited-breast-cancer-genes/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/beyond-brca1-2-pinpointing-the-risk-of-inherited-breast-cancer-genes/">Beyond BRCA1/2: Pinpointing the risk of inherited breast cancer genes</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/01/Immunohistochemistry-for-HER2-shows-positive-cell-membrane-staining-in-this-infiltrating-ductal-carcinoma_shutterstock_392445517_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/01/Immunohistochemistry-for-HER2-shows-positive-cell-membrane-staining-in-this-infiltrating-ductal-carcinoma_shutterstock_392445517_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Fergus Couch]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Goetz]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Siddhartha Yadav]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[genetics]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic expert explains why a change is needed when talking about dementia</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-expert-explains-why-a-change-is-needed-when-talking-about-dementia/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[DeeDee Stiepan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neurosciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dementia terminology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Ronald Petersen]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376188</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>One of the challenges in addressing Alzheimer's disease, dementia, cognitive impairment and aging is not related to the conditions themselves but rather the terminology. That’s according to Dr. Ronald Petersen, director of the Mayo Clinic Alzheimer's Disease Research Center, who suggests a new framework for dementia nomenclature is needed. Inconsistent use of terms such as [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-expert-explains-why-a-change-is-needed-when-talking-about-dementia/">Mayo Clinic expert explains why a change is needed when talking about dementia</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/3d-graphic-image-of-a-brain-with-blue-and-orange-colors-depicting-portions-of-the-brain-affected-by-Alzheimers-Disease-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="3d graphic image of a brain with blue and orange colors depicting portions of the brain affected by Alzheimer's Disease" class="wp-image-274531" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/3d-graphic-image-of-a-brain-with-blue-and-orange-colors-depicting-portions-of-the-brain-affected-by-Alzheimers-Disease-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/3d-graphic-image-of-a-brain-with-blue-and-orange-colors-depicting-portions-of-the-brain-affected-by-Alzheimers-Disease-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/3d-graphic-image-of-a-brain-with-blue-and-orange-colors-depicting-portions-of-the-brain-affected-by-Alzheimers-Disease-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/3d-graphic-image-of-a-brain-with-blue-and-orange-colors-depicting-portions-of-the-brain-affected-by-Alzheimers-Disease-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/3d-graphic-image-of-a-brain-with-blue-and-orange-colors-depicting-portions-of-the-brain-affected-by-Alzheimers-Disease-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>One of the challenges in addressing Alzheimer's disease, dementia, cognitive impairment and aging is not related to the conditions themselves but rather the terminology. That’s according to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/petersen-ronald-c-m-d-ph-d/bio-20054548">Dr. R</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/petersen-ronald-c-m-d-ph-d/bio-20054548" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">o</a><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/petersen-ronald-c-m-d-ph-d/bio-20054548">nald Petersen</a>, director of the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/alzheimers-disease-research-center/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Alzheimer's Disease Research Center</a>, who suggests a new framework for dementia nomenclature is needed. Inconsistent use of terms such as Alzheimer's disease and dementia has compromised progress in clinical care, research and development of therapeutics. Dementia-associated stigma further contributes to inconsistent and imprecise language.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/9fxF5dS5kcQ" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Petersen discusses why a change is needed when talking about dementia</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutube9fxF5dS5kcQ"  title="Mayo Clinic expert explains why a change is needed when talking about dementia" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/9fxF5dS5kcQ?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video is available in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy</strong>:<strong>&nbsp;Mayo Clinic News Network. Name super/CG: Ronald Petersen, M.D., Ph.D./Alzheimer's Disease Research Center/Mayo Clinic.</strong></p>



<p>"We sometimes use these terms inconsistently. That confuses us as scientists, and clinicians. It confuses our patients and our families. So we decided to take a look at that whole issue and see if we could understand the problem, and then make some recommendations," says Dr. Petersen.</p>



<p>In a recently published <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaneurology/fullarticle/2810313" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">paper</a> authored by Dr. Petersen, the Advisory Council on Alzheimer's Research, Care, and Services of the National Plan to Address Alzheimer's Disease authorized a committee to help bring consistency to the use of the terms.</p>



<p>What's the difference between Alzheimer's disease and dementia?</p>



<p>"Dementia is a clinical syndrome, which means that it has a set of clinical features of the disease. Alzheimer's disease, though, implies that there's an underlying biological cause of the dementia. Often we get these two terms confused," says Dr. Petersen.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Clearing up the confusion</h2>



<p>The initiative is organized into three groups: researchers and scientists, clinicians and public stakeholders. Focus groups, which included people from underrepresented groups, also were asked to look at the various cultural issues surrounding this language.</p>



<p>"How the term dementia is used in one group might be quite different from how it's used in another group. We put all of these inputs together and came up with a framework that we hope is going to help sort out how these terms should be used so that everybody is using them consistently."</p>



<p>Dr. Petersen says the goal is not to change any definitions of any disease, but rather to clarify how different expert groups are defining the diseases.</p>



<p>"Is it clinically? Is it biologically? Or is it a combination of clinical and biologic features? So the framework is meant to characterize those distinctions," says Dr. Petersen.</p>



<p>"We hope by clarifying how people are using these terms, we'll be better able to communicate with patients and families when we discuss a disease like Alzheimer's disease."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The next steps</h2>



<p>Dr. Petersen says the next step is going to be a beta test of the new framework.</p>



<p>"In the next phase of this exercise, we're going to ask clinicians, primary care physicians, and specialty clinicians to actually use this framework to see if it helps them explain the underlying diseases to the patients and to the families. We're going to ask patients and families, 'What did you understand going in? What do you understand going out?' Same thing with the clinicians themselves," says Dr. Petersen.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-expert-explains-why-a-change-is-needed-when-talking-about-dementia/">Mayo Clinic expert explains why a change is needed when talking about dementia</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/3d-graphic-image-of-a-brain-with-blue-and-orange-colors-depicting-portions-of-the-brain-affected-by-Alzheimers-Disease-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/06/3d-graphic-image-of-a-brain-with-blue-and-orange-colors-depicting-portions-of-the-brain-affected-by-Alzheimers-Disease-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[dementia terminology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Ronald Petersen]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Treating thyroid nodules without surgery</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treating-thyroid-nodules-without-surgery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2023 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Marius Stan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[endocrinology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thyroid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[thyroid cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thyroid Nodules]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=375394</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Most lumps or&#160;nodules&#160;in the thyroid, which is a gland in your neck, are not harmful and don't need treatment. But sometimes, they can grow bigger and cause problems like trouble swallowing. In those cases, doctors might need to do surgery to remove them.&#160; There's also a treatment called&#160;radiofrequency ablation&#160;(RFA), which uses heat to make the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treating-thyroid-nodules-without-surgery/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Treating thyroid nodules without surgery</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Most lumps or&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-understanding-thyroid-nodules/">nodules</a>&nbsp;in the thyroid, which is a gland in your neck, are not harmful and don't need treatment. But sometimes, they can grow bigger and cause problems like trouble swallowing. In those cases, doctors might need to do surgery to remove them.&nbsp;</p>



<p>There's also a treatment called&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/endocrinology/news/radiofrequency-ablation-therapy-for-large-benign-thyroid-nodules/mac-20439239">radiofrequency ablation</a>&nbsp;(RFA), which uses heat to make the nodules smaller.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/stan-marius-n-m-d/bio-20055065" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Marius Stan</a>, a Mayo Clinic endocrinologist, says this nonsurgical treatment for shrinking thyroid nodules offers patients a safe and highly successful procedure. He says Mayo Clinic also is researching how RFA may be used to treat&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/thyroid-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20354161" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">thyroid cancer</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/n5L7sGMTWwk" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutuben5L7sGMTWwk"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Treating thyroid nodules without surgery" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/n5L7sGMTWwk?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:10) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/SCRIPT-MCM-Thyroid-Nodules.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>"Radiofrequency ablation, which many people might simply call an RFA, is a way of targeting a specific part of the thyroid, an abnormal part, by delivering high energy into that specific area of the thyroid and destroying it," says Dr. Stan.</p>



<p>He says patients with enlarged, benign thyroid nodules are good candidates for RFA.</p>



<p>"Patients will have an inch and a half to two inches thyroid nodules in diameter that we think are reaching the point where a problem is present or is likely going to be present," Dr. Stan says.</p>



<p></p>



<div class="wp-block-media-text is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="976" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Radiofrequency-ablation-thyroid-16x9-1-1024x976.png" alt="Radiofrequency ablation thyroid medical illustration (RFA)" class="wp-image-375404 size-full" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Radiofrequency-ablation-thyroid-16x9-1-1024x976.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Radiofrequency-ablation-thyroid-16x9-1-300x286.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Radiofrequency-ablation-thyroid-16x9-1-768x732.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Radiofrequency-ablation-thyroid-16x9-1.png 1180w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p>Radiofrequency ablation (RFA) works by works by using heat to shrink or destroy benign thyroid nodules.</p>
</div></div>



<p>Along with retaining thyroid function, there are other advantages.</p>



<p>"The benefit is that we can do it in the outpatient setting, without the scar on the neck," he says.</p>



<p>Treating thyroid nodules is one application for RFA. Mayo Clinic is one of the leading U.S. institutions to research using RFA for thyroid cancer treatment.</p>



<p>"We hope that this will also be able to destroy a thyroid cancer very specifically, as opposed to a surgical approach that would eliminate part of the thyroid," says Dr. Stan.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-understanding-thyroid-nodules/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Understanding thyroid nodules</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/thyroid-disease-diminishes-quality-of-life/">Thyroid Disease Can Diminish Quality of Life</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-treating-thyroid-nodules-without-surgery/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Treating thyroid nodules without surgery</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/closeup-of-young-white-or-perhaps-Asian-woman-touching-her-neck-near-her-throat-maybe-a-goiter-thyroid-disease-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/08/closeup-of-young-white-or-perhaps-Asian-woman-touching-her-neck-near-her-throat-maybe-a-goiter-thyroid-disease-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Marius Stan]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[endocrinology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Thyroid]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[thyroid cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Thyroid Nodules]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New study suggests ECG-AI can detect cardiovascular disease risks sooner</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-study-suggests-ecg-ai-can-detect-cardiovascular-disease-risks-sooner/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Terri Malloy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2023 14:37:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[atherosclerosis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cardiovascular disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Coronary Artery Disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Francisco López Jiménez]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ECG]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Electrocardiogram]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[heart attack]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pooled cohort equation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stroke]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376435</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Artificial intelligence (AI) from patient electrocardiograms (ECGs) may be an innovative solution to enhance heart disease risk assessment. Atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease — arteries narrowed or blocked by the accumulation of fatty plaques — is the leading global cause of death and is often driven by coronary artery disease. New study data published [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-study-suggests-ecg-ai-can-detect-cardiovascular-disease-risks-sooner/">New study suggests ECG-AI can detect cardiovascular disease risks sooner</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-futuristic-3D-graphic-image-of-a-heart-EKG-perhaps-representing-AI-artificial-intelligenceHeartEKG_141652744-1024x576-1.jpg" alt="a futuristic 3D graphic image of a heart EKG, perhaps representing AI artificial intelligence" class="wp-image-309665" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-futuristic-3D-graphic-image-of-a-heart-EKG-perhaps-representing-AI-artificial-intelligenceHeartEKG_141652744-1024x576-1.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-futuristic-3D-graphic-image-of-a-heart-EKG-perhaps-representing-AI-artificial-intelligenceHeartEKG_141652744-1024x576-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-futuristic-3D-graphic-image-of-a-heart-EKG-perhaps-representing-AI-artificial-intelligenceHeartEKG_141652744-1024x576-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Artificial intelligence (AI) from patient electrocardiograms (ECGs) may be an innovative solution to enhance heart disease risk assessment. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/arteriosclerosis-atherosclerosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20350569?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Atherosclerotic</a> cardiovascular disease — arteries narrowed or blocked by the accumulation of fatty plaques — is the leading global cause of death and is often driven by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/coronary-artery-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350613?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">coronary artery disease</a>. New <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/eclinm/article/PIIS2589-5370(23)00436-4/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study data published in eClinicalMedicine</a> suggest that ECG-AI can flag some risks years sooner than current risk calculator equations by identifying signs of coronary artery disease, such as calcification and blockages, as well as evidence of a prior heart attack.</p>



<p>Many people may have coronary artery disease and not be aware of it. Unfortunately, the first sign of the disease could be sudden death or a major heart attack. Clinician tools, such as the pooled cohort equation, help determine a patient's 10-year risk for heart attacks and strokes. The tools guide shared decisions about the timing of therapies, but these tools have limitations.</p>



<p>ECG is a widely available test that measures the heart's electrical activity, and AI can be trained to identify and detect hidden patterns of disease from those electrical signals.</p>



<p>The ECG-AI to predict coronary artery disease was developed at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> and <a href="https://anumana.ai/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Anumana</a> using the retrospective analysis of electronic health data of over 7 million patients across the U.S. Three separate ECG-AI models were trained, one each to detect coronary artery calcium, coronary artery blockage and segments of the heart's left ventricle not moving well — a sign of a prior heart attack.</p>



<p>"Used together, the three independent ECG-AI models predicted which patients had a high risk of hidden coronary artery disease, and therefore a high risk of having a heart attack. This is important information to guide our conversations with patients at the point of care, especially since the AI was useful in calculating these risks for as short as three years," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/lopez-jimenez-francisco-m-d-m-s/bio-00028001" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Francisco Lopez-Jimenez, M.D.</a>, a cardiologist at Mayo Clinic and senior author of the paper. "Used alone, the pooled cohort equation estimates the 10-year risk of developing cardiovascular disease. The addition of ECG-AI to see hidden risks sooner has the potential to save more lives. This model may also help identify people who do not know they have coronary disease who may benefit from lifesaving therapies."</p>



<p>The study was funded by Anumana, a spinoff company of nference and Mayo Clinic. Mayo Clinic has licensed this technology to Anumana. Mayo Clinic and authors of this study may benefit financially in the future if this technology is commercialized.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/new-study-suggests-ecg-ai-can-detect-cardiovascular-disease-risks-sooner/">New study suggests ECG-AI can detect cardiovascular disease risks sooner</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-futuristic-3D-graphic-image-of-a-heart-EKG-perhaps-representing-AI-artificial-intelligence-1x1-HeartEKG_141652744-1024x576-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2021/06/a-futuristic-3D-graphic-image-of-a-heart-EKG-perhaps-representing-AI-artificial-intelligenceHeartEKG_141652744-1024x576-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[atherosclerosis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cardiovascular disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Coronary Artery Disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Francisco López Jiménez]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[ECG]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Electrocardiogram]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[heart attack]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Heart Disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[pooled cohort equation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Stroke]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>A closer look at heart health: Research shows social factors at play</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-closer-look-at-heart-health-research-shows-social-factors-at-play/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Vincent Jacobbi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Samuel Savitz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Failure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376278</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A recent Mayo Clinic&#160;study&#160;of residents living in a mostly rural, 11‐county region of southeast Minnesota found that patients with heart failure and multiple social risk factors were more likely than other heart failure patients to experience adverse outcomes such as emergency department visits, hospitalization, delayed recovery and reduced quality of life. Researchers investigated the effect [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-closer-look-at-heart-health-research-shows-social-factors-at-play/">A closer look at heart health: Research shows social factors at play</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/05/a-graphic-of-a-heart-and-an-electrocardiogram-reading-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="a graphic of a heart and an electrocardiogram reading" class="wp-image-133653" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/05/a-graphic-of-a-heart-and-an-electrocardiogram-reading-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/05/a-graphic-of-a-heart-and-an-electrocardiogram-reading-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/05/a-graphic-of-a-heart-and-an-electrocardiogram-reading-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>A recent Mayo Clinic<a>&nbsp;</a><a href="https://www.ahajournals.org/doi/10.1161/JAHA.122.028734" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;of residents living in a mostly rural, 11‐county region of southeast Minnesota found that patients with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-failure/symptoms-causes/syc-20373142" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart failure</a> and multiple social risk factors were more likely than other heart failure patients to experience adverse outcomes such as emergency department visits, hospitalization, delayed recovery and reduced quality of life.</p>



<p>Researchers investigated the effect of social factors, including education, isolation and "community deprivation" — a lack of community resources and opportunities measured at the community level.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="667" height="800" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Savitz-Samuel-T._20498616_202009010234.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376284" style="aspect-ratio:0.83375;width:224px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Savitz-Samuel-T._20498616_202009010234.jpg 667w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Savitz-Samuel-T._20498616_202009010234-250x300.jpg 250w" sizes="(max-width: 667px) 100vw, 667px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Samuel Savitz, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"The findings suggest that it is possible to identify a small but meaningful subset of patients with heart failure who have multiple, co-occurring social risk factors and may be at greater risk for poor health outcomes," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/savitz-samuel-sam-t-ph-d/bio-20503199" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Samuel Savitz, Ph.D.,</a>&nbsp;a Mayo Clinic health services researcher and lead author of the study.</p>



<p>Researchers used a statistical method to categorize 3,142 patients with heart failure. They all were living in an 11‐county region of southeast Minnesota and were 18 years or older with a first‐ever diagnosis of heart failure. The average age was 73.4, with 45.2% of the patients being women.</p>



<p>Researchers divided them into four groups based on living environments and other social risk factors.</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Group 1</strong>&nbsp;had 1,093 patients living in urban areas with moderate social risk factors.</li>



<li><strong>Group 2</strong>&nbsp;had 531 patients living in rural areas with similar risk factors.</li>



<li><strong>Group 3</strong>&nbsp;had 185 patients and was considered moderately rural with multiple social risk factors.</li>



<li><strong>Group 4</strong>, the reference group, had 1,333 patients and consisted of mostly urban areas with higher education levels and fewer social risk challenges.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Key findings</strong></h2>



<p>According to the study, patients in Group 3 — living in a moderately rural area and facing the most social risk factors — used more healthcare services than those in Group 4, who had higher education levels and more access to community resources.</p>



<p>Patients in Group 1 — living in urban areas — had better outcomes than those in the "mostly urban" Group 4, despite having more social risk factors. The researchers suggest this was likely due to better access to care within their urban community.</p>



<p>The research also revealed that approximately 18.2% of patients within the study experienced moderate social isolation, while 5.7% experienced high social isolation, indicating a lack of social connections or support.</p>



<p>"This study provides further evidence that health systems and policymakers should devote resources and develop interventions to address the effects of social risk factors on patient outcomes," says&nbsp;Dr. Savitz.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Taking a Patient-Centered Approach</strong></h2>



<p>Dr. Savitz said the study also shows that heart failure cannot be treated in isolation but should be viewed through a broader lens of the patient’s life circumstances. Future interventions, he says, could use a patient-centered approach to address social risk factors.</p>



<p>He notes that it is crucial to evaluate whether these findings extend to other regions of the country, particularly those with greater racial and ethnic diversity.</p>



<p>The&nbsp;Mayo Clinic&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</a>&nbsp;supported this research. Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ahajournals.org/doi/10.1161/JAHA.122.028734" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This article original published on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/10/23/a-closer-look-at-heart-health-research-shows-social-factors-at-play/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-closer-look-at-heart-health-research-shows-social-factors-at-play/">A closer look at heart health: Research shows social factors at play</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/05/a-graphic-of-a-heart-and-an-electrocardiogram-reading-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/05/a-graphic-of-a-heart-and-an-electrocardiogram-reading-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Samuel Savitz]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Heart Failure]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>17-gene signature linked to remission after triple-negative breast cancer treatment </title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/17-gene-signature-linked-to-remission-after-triple-negative-breast-cancer-treatment/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Judy Boughey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Krishna Rani Kalari]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Goetz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[genetics]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376121</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have discovered a distinctive pattern in a specific set of 17 genes that may be associated with remission after treatment for&#160;triple-negative breast cancer. The multi-omics study,&#160;published in Breast Cancer Research, highlights the potential for further investigating this signature as a target for individualized medicine.&#160; Approximately 10-15% of breast cancers fall into the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/17-gene-signature-linked-to-remission-after-triple-negative-breast-cancer-treatment/">17-gene signature linked to remission after triple-negative breast cancer treatment </a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/breast-cancer5-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376124" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/breast-cancer5-16x9-1.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/breast-cancer5-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/breast-cancer5-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have discovered a distinctive pattern in a specific set of 17 genes that may be associated with remission after treatment for&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/in-depth/breast-cancer/art-20045654" target="_blank">triple-negative breast cancer</a>. The multi-omics study,&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://breast-cancer-research.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13058-023-01656-x" target="_blank">published in Breast Cancer Research</a>, highlights the potential for further investigating this signature as a target for individualized medicine.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Approximately 10-15% of breast cancers fall into the category of "triple-negative," indicating that their growth is not driven through the hormone receptors for estrogen or progesterone, nor by the human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2). In contrast, other breast cancers have at least one of these receptors, allowing for treatments that can target or block them to inhibit the cancer's progression.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Triple-negative breast cancer is known for its resistance to targeted therapies, leaving chemotherapy as the primary treatment option. While most patients initially respond well to the standard neoadjuvant chemotherapy, nearly 20% of patients will experience recurrence after treatment.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"It's crucial that we create tools that assist clinicians in making informed treatment decisions," says&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/kalari-krishna-r-ph-d/bio-00095546" target="_blank">Krishna Rani Kalari, Ph.D.</a>, a lead author of the study and an associate professor of biomedical informatics at the Center for Individualized Medicine. "This 17-gene signature is one of the candidate tools that shows potential. However, for this signature to have clinical utility, there will need to be studies evaluating whether alternative drugs/drug combinations may work in this group of patients."&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Decoding pattern in 17 genes</h3>



<p>In their study, the researchers investigated tumor samples before and after treatment of patients with triple-negative breast cancer who failed to respond to neoadjuvant chemotherapy. Using multi-omics analysis and machine learning technologies, they examined changes in gene expression to understand the molecular underpinnings driving tumor recurrence.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Multi-omics is an emerging multidisciplinary field of biological sciences that encompasses genomics, proteomics, epigenomics, transcriptomics, metabolomics and more.  &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The team identified 17 genes associated with relapse-free survival and found that many of the genes may play a role in triggering inflammation to initiate an immune system response. Dr. Kalari says failure to initiate immune response prevents the clearance of weakened tumor cells, thereby permitting the development of treatment resistance and disease re-occurrence.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Quest for individualized medicine</h3>



<p>The study is an extension of Mayo Clinic's clinical prospective breast cancer study known as Breast Cancer Genome-Guided Therapy Study (<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine/research/clinical-studies/beauty2" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">BEAUTY</a>). The goal of the study is to determine why some patient’s tumors respond to chemotherapy while others don't, and to use that knowledge as a catalyst to develop personalized medicine therapies.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Next, the team plans to further investigate the gene signature and test therapeutic strategies.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Co-lead authors of the study are Mayo Clinic researchers&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/kalari-krishna-r-ph-d/bio-00095546" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Krishna Rani Kalari, Ph.D.</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/boughey-judy-c-m-d/bio-00027350">Judy Boughey, M.D</a>., and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/goetz-matthew-p-m-d/bio-00027285">Matthew Goetz, M.D.</a>&nbsp;Additional authors include Xiaojia Tang, Ph.D. and Kevin Thompson, Ph.D. A comprehensive list of the authors, disclosures, and funding are available in the <a href="https://breast-cancer-research.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13058-023-01656-x" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://individualizedmedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/10/18/17-gene-signature-linked-to-remission-after-triple-negative-breast-cancer-treatment/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">blog of the Center for Individualized Medicine</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/17-gene-signature-linked-to-remission-after-triple-negative-breast-cancer-treatment/">17-gene signature linked to remission after triple-negative breast cancer treatment </a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/breast-cancer5-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/breast-cancer5-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Judy Boughey]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Krishna Rani Kalari]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Goetz]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[genetics]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic selects Owen Garrick, M.D., as dean of Clinical Trials</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-selects-owen-garrick-m-d-as-dean-of-clinical-trials/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Julie Vera]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2023 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dean of Clinical Trials]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Gregory Gores]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Owen Garrick]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Karen Hartman]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376149</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic Research leaders are excited to announce the arrival of Owen Garrick, M.D., as the dean of Clinical Trials. Dr. Garrick will start in his new position on Oct. 30. The dean of Clinical Trials is tasked with strengthening Mayo Clinic's standing as a national leader of innovative, demand-generating clinical trials for patients everywhere. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-selects-owen-garrick-m-d-as-dean-of-clinical-trials/">Mayo Clinic selects Owen Garrick, M.D., as dean of Clinical Trials</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="900" height="506" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/OwenGarrick-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376151" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/OwenGarrick-16x9-1.jpg 900w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/OwenGarrick-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/OwenGarrick-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 900px) 100vw, 900px" /></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research">Research </a>leaders are excited to announce the arrival of Owen Garrick, M.D., as the dean of <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials/about-clinical-studies">Clinical Trials</a>. Dr. Garrick will start in his new position on Oct. 30.</p>



<p>The dean of Clinical Trials is tasked with strengthening Mayo Clinic's standing as a national leader of innovative, demand-generating clinical trials for patients everywhere. Dr. Garrick will lead the transformation of Mayo Clinic’s clinical trials, including developing digital capabilities, accelerating the volume of remote clinical trials and enhancing national awareness of clinical trials at Mayo Clinic. In this role, Dr. Garrick will serve as a member of the Research Executive Management Team, report to <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/gores-gregory-j-m-d/bio-00078325" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gregory Gores, M.D.</a>, Kinney Executive Dean of Research, Mayo Clinic, and partner with Karen Hartman, vice chair, Research Administration, Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>"We're thrilled to welcome Dr. Garrick into this role that focuses on advancing our clinical trials strategy and operations," says Dr. Gores. "He brings broad and deep experience in clinical trials leadership, business development and participation in external organizations that will be invaluable in ensuring clinical trials are fully integrated with the future of Mayo Clinic's Cure, Connect and Transform strategy."</p>



<p>Dr. Garrick comes to Mayo most recently from CVS Health, where he was chief medical officer for Clinical Trial Services. He also has worked on and lectured and published extensively about diversity and equity for patients and in the healthcare workforce pipeline.</p>



<p>"Dr. Garrick's business acumen is critical to the future of clinical trials as Mayo continues bringing its Category-of-One research, treatments and cures to more patients than ever," says Hartman. "His breadth of experience will challenge us to think differently about clinical trials transformation." &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>A wealth of expertise</strong></p>



<p>In his three-decade career, Dr. Garrick has demonstrated a commitment to improving health outcomes, including in drug development, research, ethics, regulatory science and health system management particularly for underserved populations. Under his leadership as chief medical officer for Clinical Trial Services, CVS Health enrolled more than 36,000 participants into U.S. clinical trials, representing 5% of all study participants in the country. Dr. Garrick executed medical strategy for Trial Delivery, Recruitment and Real-World Evidence business lines, ensuring compliance, clinical insights and clinical innovation.</p>



<p>He oversaw the development of machine-learning models for patient identification and outreach, leveraging in-home, digital and retail pharmacy care delivery for research and evidence generation. Dr. Garrick also served as vice president and head of Clinical Trial Development and Delivery for CVS Health, where he launched a large and diverse decentralized clinical trials network and launched a Clinical Trial Diversity solution to improve recruitment of diverse populations into clinical trials.</p>



<p>Dr. Garrick has held leadership positions at several other healthcare organizations, including McKesson, Novartis and Merck. He also has worked on the health insurance side at MetLife, and on the finance side at Goldman Sachs.</p>



<p>Dr. Garrick earned an A.B. (bachelor of arts) in psychology from Princeton University; his M.D. from Yale School of Medicine; and an MBA from The Wharton School, University of Pennsylvania. He's served on several boards including the American Medical Association; the American Psychiatric Association Foundation; Sutter Health; and as a committee member on the Health and Human Services Secretary’s Advisory Council on Human Research Protections.</p>



<p>"I am truly looking forward to this opportunity. I can't wait to get to work helping transform clinical trials at Mayo Clinic," says Dr. Garrick. "The reputation of Mayo Clinic, and the tremendous work the team already has done to expand access to trials for everyone, means Mayo Clinic is positioned to be a clear leader in this space. I'm honored to join the effort."</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-selects-owen-garrick-m-d-as-dean-of-clinical-trials/">Mayo Clinic selects Owen Garrick, M.D., as dean of Clinical Trials</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/OwenGarrick-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/OwenGarrick-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dean of Clinical Trials]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Gregory Gores]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Owen Garrick]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Karen Hartman]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Proceedings, Kidney International publish consensus statement on new approach to identifying kidney disorder</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-proceedings-kidney-international-publish-consensus-statement-on-new-approach-to-identifying-kidney-disorder/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jay Furst]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2023 16:52:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Karl Nath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Vesna Garovic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[edema]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kidney disorder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kidney International]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Proceedings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[membranous nephropathy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nephrotic syndrome]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[proteinuria]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=375899</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Forty-eight international experts on membranous nephropathy have co-authored a consensus report that calls for a new method of classifying diagnoses of the syndrome. They say the change would result in greater accuracy in diagnoses, which would open the door to improved patient care and targeted treatment. To call attention to the report, Mayo Clinic Proceedings [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-proceedings-kidney-international-publish-consensus-statement-on-new-approach-to-identifying-kidney-disorder/">Mayo Clinic Proceedings, Kidney International publish consensus statement on new approach to identifying kidney disorder</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidneys16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-363122" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidneys16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidneys16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidneys16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidneys16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidneys16x9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Forty-eight international experts on <a href="https://www.kidney-international.org/article/S0085-2538(23)00490-8/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">membranous nephropathy</a> have co-authored a <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/article/S0025-6196(23)00372-5/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">consensus report</a> that calls for a new method of classifying diagnoses of the syndrome. They say the change would result in greater accuracy in diagnoses, which would open the door to improved patient care and targeted treatment. To call attention to the report, <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a> and <a href="https://www.kidney-international.org/article/S0085-2538(23)00490-8/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kidney International</a> have published the report simultaneously.</p>



<p>Membranous nephropathy is a kidney disorder that involves immunologic attack on structures inside the kidney that help filter wastes and fluids, and it's a relatively common cause of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/nephrotic-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20375608">nephrotic syndrome</a> in adults. Nephrotic syndrome is a kidney disorder that causes the body to leak relatively large amounts of protein into the urine. It causes swelling, particularly in the feet and ankles, and increases the risk of other health problems.</p>



<p>With current diagnostic processes, in approximately 70% of cases involving membranous nephropathy, it's classified as the primary cause of disease. In the remaining cases, it's classified as secondary to another recognized disease or cause. "Recent discoveries have rendered the primary-secondary classification of membranous nephropathy anachronistic," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/nath-karl-a-m-d/bio-00027413" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Karl Nath, M.B., Ch.B</a>, a co-author of the report and editor-in-chief of Mayo Clinic Proceedings. "In its place, the Mayo Clinic Consensus Report on Membranous Nephropathy proposes a new two-step classification that incorporates recent discoveries, is clinically based and pragmatic."</p>



<p>The consensus report is the result of a Mayo Clinic-sponsored meeting in Rochester, Minnesota, on Oct. 29, 2022, and was made possible by discoveries at Mayo Clinic. The article in Mayo Clinic Proceedings and Kidney International<em>, </em>the journal of the <a href="https://www.theisn.org/">International Society of Nephrology</a>, outlines a diagnostic classification process that incorporates recent discoveries and emerging research. <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/fervenza-fernando-fernando-c-c-m-d-ph-d/bio-00027412">Fernando Fervenza, M.D., Ph.D.,</a> director of Mayo Clinic's <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/mayo-nephrology-collaborative-group/about">Nephrology Collaborative Group</a>, is senior author. First author is <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/sethi-sanjeev-m-d-ph-d/bio-20513111">Sanjeev Sethi, M.D., Ph.D.,</a> a Mayo Clinic pathologist who specializes in kidney diseases.</p>



<p>In <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/article/S0025-6196(23)00403-2/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">a commentary</a> that accompanies the consensus statement in Mayo Clinic Proceedings, Dr. Nath and co-authors <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/erickson-lori-a-m-d/bio-00084505" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lori A. Erickson, M.D.</a>, and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/garovic-vesna-d-m-d-ph-d/bio-00027747" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Vesna Garovic, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, write that the consensus report makes clear the need for a new approach to diagnostic classification. "This new classification assimilates new knowledge as it emerges and provides a foundation for further discoveries in membranous nephropathy," says Dr. Nath.</p>



<p>Dr. Nath and Dr. Garovic are nephrologists in the Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/nephrology-hypertension/sections/overview/ovc-20464571" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Division of Nephrology and Hypertension</a>, Department of Medicine, and Dr. Erickson is in the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/laboratory-medicine-pathology/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathology</a>.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Proceedings</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a> is a monthly peer-reviewed journal that publishes original articles and reviews on clinical and laboratory medicine, clinical research, basic science research and clinical epidemiology. The journal, sponsored by Mayo Foundation for Medical Education and Research as part of its commitment to physician education, has been published for 97 years and has a circulation of 127,000.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and to providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Jay Furst, Research and Education Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-proceedings-kidney-international-publish-consensus-statement-on-new-approach-to-identifying-kidney-disorder/">Mayo Clinic Proceedings, Kidney International publish consensus statement on new approach to identifying kidney disorder</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidneys1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidneys16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Karl Nath]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Vesna Garovic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[edema]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[kidney disorder]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Kidney International]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Proceedings]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[membranous nephropathy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[nephrotic syndrome]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[proteinuria]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Zooming in on rare bone cells that drive osteoporosis</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/zooming-in-on-rare-bone-cells-that-drive-osteoporosis/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Caitlin Doran]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Madison Doolittle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sundeep Khosla]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[osteoporosis]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=375682</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have developed a new high-resolution, analytical technique to identify the rare senescent bone cells that are known to drive osteoporosis. Senescent cells are malfunctioning cells that build up as people age or as the result of chronic diseases. Once these cells form, they can contribute to developing diseases and consequences of aging. This [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/zooming-in-on-rare-bone-cells-that-drive-osteoporosis/">Zooming in on rare bone cells that drive osteoporosis</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle_NCOMM_Art1-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375683" style="width:840px;height:473px" width="840" height="473" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle_NCOMM_Art1-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle_NCOMM_Art1-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle_NCOMM_Art1-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle_NCOMM_Art1-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle_NCOMM_Art1-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 840px) 100vw, 840px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">High-resolution image showing senescent cells in bone that drive osteoporosis.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have developed a new high-resolution, analytical technique to identify the rare senescent bone cells that are known to drive <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/osteoporosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20351968" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">osteoporosis</a>. Senescent cells are malfunctioning cells that build up as people age or as the result of chronic diseases. Once these cells form, they can contribute to developing diseases and consequences of aging. This new method, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37524694/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">detailed in a paper published in Nature Communications</a>, will enable scientists to better target experimental anti-aging drugs at the cellular level, advancing efforts to find treatments for osteoporosis and other aging-related diseases.</p>



<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle-Madison-L._21598983_202001200201-250x300-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375685" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Madison Doolittle, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-left">"Senescent cells are notoriously challenging to identify. With this work, we are overcoming a barrier that has hindered past research," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/osteoporosis-and-bone-biology/faculty-staff" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Madison Doolittle, Ph.D.,</a> a Mayo Clinic endocrinology researcher and first author of the paper. "We expect this technique will enhance our ability to study these cells in a precise manner, understand the mechanisms of diseases and develop more focused targets for treatment."</p>



<p>This research will inform clinical trials at Mayo Clinic and around the world that are testing experimental treatments for osteoporosis, Alzheimer’s disease, chronic kidney disease and other aging-related diseases. The new technique is already being used to map senescent cells through the National Institutes of Health's&nbsp;<a href="https://commonfund.nih.gov/senescence" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cellular Senescence Network</a>.</p>



<p>The new technique involves mass cytometry, a method scientists employ to analyze the differences among many types of cells and to identify specific cells by the types of proteins displayed on their surfaces or interiors. To pinpoint senescent cells, the researchers looked for the presence of p16, p21, BCL-2, and CD24 proteins, which control the development and survival of senescent cells.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Khosla-Sundeep_10803408_20221205-240x300-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375686" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Sundeep Khosla, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p></p>



<p>"The novel, single-cell approach that Dr. Doolittle developed opens up new ways to identify these rare senescent cells not only in bone but also broadly across tissues," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/khosla-sundeep-m-d/bio-00078126" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sundeep Khosla, M.D.,</a>&nbsp;a Mayo Clinic endocrinologist and senior author of the paper. "From a translational and clinical perspective, this would help in potentially quantifying the burden of senescent cells in patients and their response to interventions that kill or disable these harmful cells."</p>



<p>Dr. Khosla anticipates that future research will focus on applying this technique to identify strategies to improve bone healing and regeneration after skeletal injury.</p>



<p>Dr. Khosla is the Dr. Francis Chucker and Nathan Landow Professor of Research at Mayo Clinic College of Medicine and Science.</p>



<p>For the full list of disclosures and research funding, please see the paper.</p>



<p>This article first published on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/10/05/zooming-in-on-rare-bone-cells-that-drive-osteoporosis/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/zooming-in-on-rare-bone-cells-that-drive-osteoporosis/">Zooming in on rare bone cells that drive osteoporosis</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle_NCOMM_Art1-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle_NCOMM_Art1-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Madison Doolittle]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Sundeep Khosla]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[osteoporosis]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Advancing ultrasound microvessel imaging and AI to improve cancer detection</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advancing-ultrasound-microvessel-imaging-and-ai-to-improve-cancer-detection/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[asatake]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 13:01:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[artificial intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Azra Alizad]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Mostafa Fatemi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ultrasound]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=375666</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Ultrasound&#160;— a technology that uses sound waves to produce an image — is commonly used to monitor the development of a baby as it grows inside its mother. But ultrasound imaging also can be used to investigate suspicious masses of tissue and nodules that may be cancerous. Tumors consist not only of cancer cells but [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advancing-ultrasound-microvessel-imaging-and-ai-to-improve-cancer-detection/">Advancing ultrasound microvessel imaging and AI to improve cancer detection</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Breast-Cancer-ultrasound-AI-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375668" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Breast-Cancer-ultrasound-AI-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Breast-Cancer-ultrasound-AI-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Breast-Cancer-ultrasound-AI-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Breast-Cancer-ultrasound-AI-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Breast-Cancer-ultrasound-AI-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ultrasound/about/pac-20395177" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ultrasound</a>&nbsp;— a technology that uses sound waves to produce an image — is commonly used to monitor the development of a baby as it grows inside its mother. But ultrasound imaging also can be used to investigate suspicious masses of tissue and nodules that may be cancerous.</p>



<p>Tumors consist not only of cancer cells but also a matrix of small blood vessels, or microvessels, that cannot be seen in the images produced by conventional ultrasound machines. To solve this problem, physician-scientist&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/alizad-azra-m-d/bio-00085586" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Azra Alizad, M.D.</a>, and biomedical engineering scientist&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/fatemi-mostafa-ph-d/bio-00086282" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mostafa Fatemi, Ph.D.</a>, teamed up at Mayo Clinic to design and study a tool that may improve the resolution of ultrasound imaging. As demonstrated in&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35486168/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">research findings</a>, they developed high-resolution ultrasound imaging software, compatible with many ultrasound machines, that could exponentially improve both the detail and quality of images.</p>



<p>The investigational software, which they've named quantitative high-definition microvessel imaging (q-HDMI), has been evaluated to capture high-resolution 2D and 3D images of microvessels as small as 150 microns, roughly twice the width of a human hair.</p>



<div class="wp-block-media-text has-media-on-the-right is-stacked-on-mobile" style="grid-template-columns:auto 35%"><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p>"If we can visualize and capture the microvessel in the earliest stages of cancer, we can better diagnose and treat it earlier, which improves the outcome for the patient," says Dr. Alizad, who specializes in ultrasound technology for cancer imaging.</p>
</div><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="925" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Alizad-WF3352118_0032-cut-925x1024-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375671 size-full" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Alizad-WF3352118_0032-cut-925x1024-1.jpg 925w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Alizad-WF3352118_0032-cut-925x1024-1-271x300.jpg 271w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Alizad-WF3352118_0032-cut-925x1024-1-768x850.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 925px) 100vw, 925px" /></figure></div>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Artificial intelligence helps detect what we cannot see</strong></h2>



<p>In addition, the researchers identified a series of biomarkers representing specific characteristics of tiny </p>



<p>vessels, such as shape, pattern, irregularity and complexity, and packaged them into an algorithm that can sort the image data into benign or malignant masses.</p>



<div class="wp-block-media-text is-stacked-on-mobile" style="grid-template-columns:37% auto"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="481" height="532" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Fatemi-WF3352118_0019_vertical.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375670 size-full" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Fatemi-WF3352118_0019_vertical.jpg 481w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Fatemi-WF3352118_0019_vertical-271x300.jpg 271w" sizes="(max-width: 481px) 100vw, 481px" /></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p></p>



<p>"This technology provides a quantitative value that shows the probability of malignancy," Dr. Fatemi says. "It's a tool to extract information in a way that can be useful to clinicians."</p>
</div></div>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Applying it in practice</strong></h2>



<p>In a&nbsp;<a href="https://breast-cancer-research.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13058-022-01583-3" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">clinical study</a>, the researchers showed that their new q-HDMI tool combined with artificial intelligence (AI) was able to detect a very small, 3-millimeter-wide, malignant breast cancer mass comprised of miniscule vessels in a 40-year-old woman. Finding and treating cancer lesions when they are this size before they spread, or metastasize, can be lifesaving.</p>



<p>"The questions in radiology really are: benign or malignant? And if it's suspicious, how concerned should we be?" Dr. Fatemi says.</p>



<p>To help radiologists answer these questions, the researchers applied their software and algorithm to further analyze suspicious breast masses from 521 patients who already had received conventional ultrasound imaging. The results were astounding. The new technology yielded a&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35486168/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">nearly 100% rate of accuracy</a>&nbsp;in determining malignant versus benign masses, regardless of the tumor size.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidqCtLfFbWcEoampt"  title="3D images of benign and malignant breast tissue masses" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qCtLfFbWcEo?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>More recently, the researchers analyzed thyroid nodules from 92 patients. Thyroid nodules are common and it is often hard to differentiate between cancerous and non-cancerous ones through imaging. Yet the prevalence of thyroid cancer has increased over the last few decades.</p>



<p>"With conventional ultrasound images, physicians can diagnose whether a thyroid nodule is benign or malignant with only about 35-75% accuracy," Dr. Alizad says. That's why physicians often opt to perform thyroid biopsies, which enable them to more definitively determine if a thyroid nodule is a cause for concern.</p>



<p>The researchers identified 12 biomarkers that can differentiate benign from malignant thyroid tissues. They programmed the AI-powered algorithm with these biomarkers, which sorted the images and had an 84% rate of accuracy. These results were published in the journal&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36980774/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cancers</a>&nbsp;and highlighted by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nibib.nih.gov/news-events/newsroom/how-combination-advanced-ultrasound-and-ai-could-upgrade-cancer-diagnostics" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Institutes of Health</a>.</p>



<p>"If it is cancer, we definitely want to know that. But if we can determine if a thyroid nodule is benign without even having to do a biopsy, that is even better as it spares the patient from the financial and physical burdens associated with an unnecessary benign biopsy," Dr. Alizad says.</p>



<p>The researchers see that their quantitative tool could be particularly useful in parts of the world where there is limited expertise and resources, such as rural areas and developing countries.</p>



<p>They also are collaborating with oncologists to enable them to use the q-HDMI tool to better monitor the effectiveness of cancer treatments and help them adjust therapies for individual patients in real time.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advancing-ultrasound-microvessel-imaging-and-ai-to-improve-cancer-detection/">Advancing ultrasound microvessel imaging and AI to improve cancer detection</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Breast-Cancer-ultrasound-AI-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Breast-Cancer-ultrasound-AI-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[artificial intelligence]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Azra Alizad]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Mostafa Fatemi]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[ultrasound]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss><!-- Static page delivered by HubScale -->