<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Research - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research-2/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research-2/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2023 12:18:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic names new Research leader</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-names-new-research-leader-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Streed]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2023 21:17:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Vijay Shah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Executive Dean for Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=379310</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic has announced the appointment of Vijay Shah, M.D., as Kinney Executive Dean of Research. He succeeds Gregory Gores, M.D., who has served in the position for 10 years. Dr. Shah, a consultant with joint appointments in Gastroenterology and Hepatology as well as Physiology and Biomedical Engineering, is chair of Internal [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-names-new-research-leader-2/">Mayo Clinic names new Research leader</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="575" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Dr.-Shah-16x9-1-1024x575.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-379313" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Dr.-Shah-16x9-1-1024x575.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Dr.-Shah-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Dr.-Shah-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Dr.-Shah-16x9-1.jpg 1379w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Vijay Shah, M.D.</figcaption></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic has announced the appointment of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/shah-vijay-m-d/bio-20054050" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Vijay Shah, M.D.</a>, as Kinney Executive Dean of Research. He succeeds <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/gores-gregory-j-m-d/bio-20053478" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gregory Gores, M.D.</a>, who has served in the position for 10 years.</p>



<p>Dr. Shah, a consultant with joint appointments in Gastroenterology and Hepatology as well as Physiology and Biomedical Engineering, is chair of Internal Medicine at Mayo Clinic in Rochester and is the Carol M. Gatton Professor of Digestive Diseases Research. In his new position, Dr. Shah's full title will be the Mr. and Mrs. Robert F. Kinney Executive Dean of Research Honoring Ronald F. Kinney, Jr.</p>



<p>"Continued clinical excellence requires research innovation, discovery and translation," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/farrugia-gianrico-m-d/bio-20053394" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gianrico Farrugia, M.D.</a>, president and CEO, Mayo Clinic. "We look forward to Dr. Shah's leadership into a new era of research as we pursue innovations that lead to new cures for our patients. We are also grateful for Dr. Gores' many contributions over the past 10 years, and we are confident that Dr. Shah will bring the committed work done by our Research shield to even greater achievements."</p>



<p>Dr. Shah has maintained National Institutes for Health-funded programs at Mayo Clinic for 25 years related to advanced liver disease that cross basic science, artificial intelligence (AI) and clinical trials. He was named a 2019 Distinguished Mayo Clinic Investigator.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"I'm honored to be able to work with my colleagues in this new position as we pursue innovations that lead to new treatments to help our patients," says Dr. Shah.</p>



<p>Dr. Shah will partner with Heidi Dieter, chair of Research Administration. He will begin his new role on Feb. 1, 2024.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-names-new-research-leader-2/">Mayo Clinic names new Research leader</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Dr.-Shah-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Dr.-Shah-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Vijay Shah]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Executive Dean for Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Shortened telomeres heighten risk of serious lung disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/shortened-telomeres-heighten-risk-of-serious-lung-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cindy Sutherland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Alejandro Ferrer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Eva Carmona Porquera]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Mrinal Patnaik]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pulmonary Fibrosis]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=379084</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In 2017, Cindy Sutherland caught a nasty cold she couldn't shake. After coughing nonstop for weeks, she went to urgent care and got a chest X-ray. When the doctor shared the results with her, he asked, "Have you ever heard of pulmonary fibrosis?" Cindy started to cry because she knew what those words meant. Her [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/shortened-telomeres-heighten-risk-of-serious-lung-disease/">Shortened telomeres heighten risk of serious lung disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="945" height="532" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/telomeres_16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-379086" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/telomeres_16x9.jpg 945w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/telomeres_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/telomeres_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 945px) 100vw, 945px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The 46 human chromosomes are shown in blue, with the telomeres appearing as white pinpoints. The DNA has already been copied, so each chromosome is made up of two identical lengths of DNA, each with its own two telomeres. <em>Credit: Hesed Padilla-Nash and Thomas Ried, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health.</em><br></figcaption></figure>



<p>In 2017, Cindy Sutherland caught a nasty cold she couldn't shake. After coughing nonstop for weeks, she went to urgent care and got a chest X-ray. When the doctor shared the results with her, he asked, "Have you ever heard of pulmonary fibrosis?" Cindy started to cry because she knew what those words meant. Her grandmother had died of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pulmonary-fibrosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20353690" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pulmonary fibrosis</a> at the age of 62. Her mother had died of it at 58, and her sister at 48.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="221" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Cindy_Sutherland-221x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-379088" style="width:183px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Cindy_Sutherland-221x300.jpg 221w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Cindy_Sutherland-755x1024.jpg 755w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Cindy_Sutherland-768x1042.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Cindy_Sutherland-1132x1536.jpg 1132w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Cindy_Sutherland.jpg 1172w" sizes="(max-width: 221px) 100vw, 221px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Cindy Sutherland</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>The progressive lung disease can be traced to a variety of causes — autoimmune conditions, radiation treatments, specific medications or chemotherapeutic agents, toxins like asbestos or coal dust and environmental factors like mold. Recently, researchers have begun to recognize that a <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33935155/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">subset of cases can be attributed to genetics</a>. Some patients with pulmonary fibrosis have shortened telomeres, the caps on the ends of chromosomes that protect cells from aging. Identifying these patients is critical because, in their case, certain treatments like immunosuppressive therapies could be dangerous.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Eva-Carmona-Porquera-200x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-379089" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Eva-Carmona-Porquera-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Eva-Carmona-Porquera.jpg 533w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Eva Carmona Porquera, M.D., Ph.D.<br></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"I think it is way more frequent than we realize," says Sutherland’s pulmonologist, <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/carmona-porquera-eva-m-m-d-ph-d/bio-00027509" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Eva Carmona Porquera, M.D., Ph.D.</a> She is part of a large, multidisciplinary team at Mayo Clinic developing new ways to detect and treat pulmonary fibrosis cases caused by shortened telomeres.</p>



<p>"This is new territory," says Dr. Carmona Porquera. "The good thing is that at Mayo, we can offer genetic testing and telomere testing to our patients to classify, treat and prepare for complications associated with telomere biology disorders."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A rare and complex disorder</strong></h2>



<p>Telomere biology disorders are rare diseases caused by mutations that accelerate telomere shortening. Patients with these disorders are susceptible to a variety of age-related conditions, including pulmonary fibrosis, bone marrow failure, osteoporosis, cancer and liver fibrosis. Many but not all patients show outward signs of premature aging, such as premature graying of hair or brittle nails. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Patnaik_Mrinal_S-250x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-379091" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Patnaik_Mrinal_S-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Patnaik_Mrinal_S.jpg 667w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mrinal Patnaik, M.B.B.S.<br></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Hematologist <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/patnaik-mrinal-s-m-b-b-s/bio-00093620" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mrinal Patnaik, M.B.B.S</a>., first encountered these disorders as a medical resident in the early 2000s. A patient in his thirties with completely gray hair had shown up with a malignant tumor at the head and neck cancer clinic where Dr. Patnaik was training. Doctors there did not realize he had a telomere biology disorder. The patient died a month later from complete bone marrow failure.</p>



<p>"That really hurt me deep down," says Dr. Patnaik. "I felt that there's so many of these patients who are going to be coming into different clinics and if I didn't step up and set up a program for them and educate all my colleagues and set up the infrastructure, we're going to see a lot more patients suffer."&nbsp;</p>



<p>With the help of the Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Individualized Medicine</a>, Dr. Patnaik established the Telomere Biology Disorders Clinic at the Rochester, Minnesota, campus in 2017. The clinic is multidisciplinary in nature, drawing expertise from hematologists, oncologists, pulmonologists, liver specialists, pharmacists, molecular biologists and genetic counselors. To date, the clinic has seen more than 100 patients with shortened telomeres.</p>



<p>"We are among the largest adult telomere biology disorder clinics in the country," says Dr. Patnaik, who plans to open similar clinics in Arizona and Florida.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>No perfect way</strong></h2>



<p>The most frequent manifestation of a telomere biology disorder is pulmonary fibrosis, the scarring of lung tissue that can make it difficult to breathe. As telomeres become shorter and shorter, the chromosomes they are designed to protect can unravel and fray, like a shoelace that has lost its protective cap. Eventually, the telomeres become so short that cells stop dividing — a process known as senescence. Those senescent cells send off a slew of chemicals that act as flares, triggering inflammatory changes that damage and thicken the lungs.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers hope that by diagnosing and treating the disease earlier, they can improve outcomes for patients.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Ferrer_Alejandro-240x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-379090" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Ferrer_Alejandro-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Ferrer_Alejandro.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Alejandro Ferrer, Ph.D.<br></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Telomere biology disorders are <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29976374/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">typically diagnosed</a> by looking for shortened telomeres and testing for genetic mutations. "There are different techniques that have been developed over time to measure telomere length, and each one has pros and cons," says molecular biologist <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/ferrer-alejandro-ph-d/bio-20503546" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alejandro Ferrer, Ph.D.</a> "Basically, there's no perfect way to do this."</p>



<p>One of the most common methods for measuring telomeres involves a technique known as Flow FISH, in which each telomere is labeled with a fluorescent marker and then fed into a machine that quantifies the average amount of fluorescence across all the telomeres on all the chromosomes in the cell. Other techniques involve sequencing to count the repetitive run of bases, TTAGGG, that makes up each telomere, again averaging the result.</p>



<p>"However, it's well-known in the field that it's not that all telomeres get shorter at the same time; it can be just one or two telomeres falling below a certain threshold that can cause disease," says Dr. Ferrer. "If you rely on a technique that uses the average, you could miss those cases."</p>



<p>Dr. Ferrer and collaborators within and outside Mayo Clinic devised a specialized sequencing technique called Telogator to assess the shortest telomere length of each chromosome.</p>



<p>"This test could have diagnostic, prognostic and therapeutic value," says Dr. Patnaik.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Answers, finally</strong></h2>



<p>Even with the limitations of the current tests, the Telomere Biology Clinic is making a <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=29804726&amp;query_hl=11&amp;itool=pubmed_docsum" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">positive impact</a> on patients. Sutherland first visited the clinic in 2020 and learned that, on average, her telomere lengths fell below the first percentile. "Dr. Patnaik said they were the shortest telomeres he had ever seen," she recalls. Genetic testing revealed Sutherland had a mutation in the TERT gene, which codes for a protein called telomerase that is responsible for telomere maintenance.</p>



<p>The Mayo team estimates that they have identified a <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33203829/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">disease-causing variant in a telomere-associated gene</a> in only 40% of patients. In many cases, they have discovered genetic changes that may or may not cause disease — called variants of unknown significance — and have conducted functional studies in the laboratory to categorize the effect of those variants.</p>



<p>Sutherland says she felt relieved when she learned she had a genetic mutation. "You're always looking for a reason, a cause, an explanation for why this happened. Why did my grandmother, my mother and my sister pass of this horrible disease at such a young age?"</p>



<p>But that sense of relief was quickly replaced by one of foreboding for the mother of five. "I was absolutely, positively scared to death for my children."&nbsp;</p>



<p>Telomere biology disorders are subject to a troubling type of genetic inheritance known as genetic anticipation. The disorder tends to become more severe and appear at an earlier age as the mutation — and the shortened telomeres — are passed from one generation to the next. As a result, Sutherland worried not only that she had passed the condition on to her children, but also that they might inherit a form of the disease much worse than what she herself has experienced.</p>



<p>"These findings have repercussions for family members," says Dr. Carmona Porquera. "We can counsel patients: no smoking, no exposures that can cause more injury, be aware of certain symptoms. And we can start treating them earlier with anti-fibrotic drugs, which could slow the progression of the disease."</p>



<p>Sutherland has been taking anti-fibrotic drugs for the last six years. Though she often feels short of breath, at age 65, she still has the energy to babysit her grandchildren.</p>



<p>Recently, genetic testing revealed no inherited mutations in her family tree.</p>



<p>"Maybe this horrible disease will stop with me," she says. "That would be my greatest wish."</p>



<p>This article first published on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/11/28/shortened-telomeres-heighten-risk-of-serious-lung-disease/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/shortened-telomeres-heighten-risk-of-serious-lung-disease/">Shortened telomeres heighten risk of serious lung disease</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/telomeres_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/telomeres_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cindy Sutherland]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Alejandro Ferrer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Eva Carmona Porquera]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Mrinal Patnaik]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Pulmonary Fibrosis]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Researchers make unexpected discovery in how pancreatic cancer spreads</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/researchers-make-unexpected-discovery-in-how-pancreatic-cancer-spreads/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[asatake]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2023 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Gina Razidlo]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Omar Gutierrez]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pancreatic Cancer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=379067</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>How cancer spreads or metastasizes is a big question for cancer researchers and patients. Mayo Clinic researchers studying&#160;pancreatic cancer&#160;— the third deadliest form of cancer in the U.S. — recently made a discovery that advances knowledge of how metastasis unfolds. They identified a cell-signaling protein that drives pancreatic cancer cell growth that could be a [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/researchers-make-unexpected-discovery-in-how-pancreatic-cancer-spreads/">Researchers make unexpected discovery in how pancreatic cancer spreads</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="500" height="282" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Panc0403_DOCK8si_LAMP1-488_6-8-23_1_3x-crop_16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-379068" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Panc0403_DOCK8si_LAMP1-488_6-8-23_1_3x-crop_16x9.jpg 500w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Panc0403_DOCK8si_LAMP1-488_6-8-23_1_3x-crop_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">In this confocal microscopy image, the lysosomal protein called LAMP1 is stained green and surrounds a blue-stained pancreatic cancer cell nucleus.</figcaption></figure>



<p>How cancer spreads or metastasizes is a big question for cancer researchers and patients. Mayo Clinic researchers studying&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pancreatic-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20355421" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pancreatic cancer</a>&nbsp;— the third deadliest form of cancer in the U.S. — recently made a discovery that advances knowledge of how metastasis unfolds. They identified a cell-signaling protein that drives pancreatic cancer cell growth that could be a potential therapeutic target.</p>



<p>"Our ultimate goal is to find the triggers for metastasis and stop it. Combine that with treatments to reduce tumor growth, and we can hopefully improve patient outcomes," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/razidlo-gina-ph-d/bio-00096936" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gina Razidlo, Ph.D.</a>, the senior author of a paper published in <a href="https://www.cell.com/cell-reports/fulltext/S2211-1247(23)01053-7" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cell Reports</a>.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="169" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Gina-Razidlo16x9-300x169.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-379070" style="width:398px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Gina-Razidlo16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Gina-Razidlo16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Gina-Razidlo16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Gina-Razidlo16x9-1536x865.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Gina-Razidlo16x9-2048x1153.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Gina Razidlo, Ph.D.<br></figcaption></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Looking inside the tumor microenvironment</strong></h2>



<p>Tumors grow in nutrient-poor environments, so cancer cells must rewire cellular metabolism to meet their energy needs. One way in which cancer cells hijack metabolic pathways is through lysosomes, which function as the cell's stomach and are filled with digestive enzymes. Lysosomes break down proteins, lipids and nutrients that fuel cells to grow. Previous research has shown that amplified lysosome activity is a hallmark of various forms of cancer.</p>



<p>This knowledge led Dr. Razidlo and lead author Omar Gutierrez Ruiz, Ph.D., to look closely at the characteristics of lysosomes in pancreatic cancer cells driven by mutations in the cancer-producing mutated gene, or oncogene, KRAS. Dr. Gutierrez Ruiz collaborated with the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/core-resources/proteomics-core/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proteomics Core</a> on this project as part of his dissertation, and together, they made an unexpected discovery.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="225" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Omar-Gutierrez-Ruiz-vert_3x4-225x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-379071" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Omar-Gutierrez-Ruiz-vert_3x4-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Omar-Gutierrez-Ruiz-vert_3x4-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Omar-Gutierrez-Ruiz-vert_3x4-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Omar-Gutierrez-Ruiz-vert_3x4-1536x2048.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Omar Gutierrez Ruiz, Ph.D.<br></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>They compared the lysosomes from pancreatic cancer cells expressing oncogenic KRAS with lysosomes from cells with healthy KRAS to find out what was different. Among the 52 proteins they found that had changed on the surface of lysosomes in pancreatic cancer cells, one protein called dedicator of cytokinesis 8 (DOCK8) stood out.</p>



<p>DOCK8 creates invasive protrusions that act like little arms that can worm through and change the structure of a cell and degrade its surroundings. DOCK8 is typically found in healthy immune cells where it helps the cells navigate and squeeze through dense tissue, aiding the response to and fight against infection. Surprisingly, Dr. Razidlo, Dr. Gutierrez Ruiz and their collaborators found DOCK8 on lysosomes in pancreatic cancer cells.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>How does DOCK8 work?</strong></h2>



<p>How cancer cells invade and spread resembles how DOCK8 helps immune cells penetrate tissue. The researchers looked at images and videos of the pancreatic cancer cells, produced in Mayo Clinic's&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-cell-signaling-gastroenterology-c-sig/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Cell Signaling in Gastroenterology</a>. They saw DOCK8 using lysosomes to break down the extracellular environment around the cancer cell — helping it spread.</p>



<p>To confirm that this protein is involved in tumor progression, the team eliminated DOCK8 in pancreatic cancer cells using the gene-editing tool CRISPR. They found in a preclinical model that the DOCK8-depleted lysosomes moved slower, tumor growth slowed and metastasis decreased. Then, they delved further and showed that DOCK8 was present in about 20% of patients with pancreatic cancer whose cells were studied.</p>



<p>"Now that we have found out that DOCK8 is regulating the process of metastasis, it could potentially be a therapeutic target to prevent or stop pancreatic cancer metastasis," says Dr. Gutierrez Ruiz, who graduated from&nbsp;<a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a>&nbsp;in May.</p>



<p>Review the <a href="https://www.cell.com/cell-reports/fulltext/S2211-1247(23)01053-7" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding. </p>



<p>This article first published on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/11/13/researchers-make-unexpected-discovery-in-how-pancreatic-cancer-spreads/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/researchers-make-unexpected-discovery-in-how-pancreatic-cancer-spreads/">Researchers make unexpected discovery in how pancreatic cancer spreads</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Panc0403_DOCK8si_LAMP1-488_6-8-23_1_3x-crop_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Panc0403_DOCK8si_LAMP1-488_6-8-23_1_3x-crop_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Gina Razidlo]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Omar Gutierrez]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Pancreatic Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic opens Anna-Maria and Stephen Kellen Building for research</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-opens-anna-maria-and-stephen-kellen-building-for-research/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Julie Vera]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2023 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Gianrico Farrugia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Greg Gores]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Research]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=378918</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic celebrates the grand opening of the 11-floor Anna-Maria and Stephen Kellen Building. The building will support hiring more scientists to contribute to Mayo's unique capabilities to bring scientific discoveries to patients. It joins other Mayo Clinic research facilities where investigators discover scientific advancements that affect patient care, leading to better [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-opens-anna-maria-and-stephen-kellen-building-for-research/">Mayo Clinic opens Anna-Maria and Stephen Kellen Building for research</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Kellen-Building-Still2-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378939" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Kellen-Building-Still2-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Kellen-Building-Still2-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Kellen-Building-Still2-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Kellen-Building-Still2-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Kellen-Building-Still2-16x9-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Anna-Maria and Stephen Kellen Building</figcaption></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic celebrates the grand opening of the 11-floor <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-marks-construction-milestone-at-new-research-building/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Anna-Maria and Stephen Kellen Building</a>. The building will support hiring more scientists to contribute to Mayo's unique capabilities to bring scientific discoveries to patients. It joins other Mayo Clinic research facilities where investigators discover scientific advancements that affect patient care, leading to better outcomes and improved quality of life in Minnesota and beyond.&nbsp;</p>



<p>At Mayo Clinic, research is the engine that drives advances in medical care, and the building expands the research footprint in the Discovery Square district in downtown Rochester.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/5HfVCMY9Vtk" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Gores talks about the Anna-Maria and Stephen Kellen Building and the impact on medical research</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutube5HfVCMY9Vtk"  title="Mayo Clinic opens Anna-Maria and Stephen Kellen Building for research" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5HfVCMY9Vtk?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites with Dr. Greg Gores, interior tour B-Roll and exterior drone footage are available in the downloads at the end of the post. CG: "Greg Gores, M.D. / Executive Dean of Research/ Mayo Clinic."</strong></p>



<p>Work on the building began in June 2021 with a lead gift from the Anna-Maria and Stephen Kellen Foundation. Contributions from the Kellen Foundation and other generous benefactors have supported the majority of the construction costs for this new research building. It features flexible facilities for basic and translational research to address serious and complex conditions, with a focus on discoveries in neurosciences and cancer research. The research floors include open, collaborative areas and lab space.</p>



<p>"Our journey to disrupt and revolutionize how we discover treatments and cures and how we deliver healthcare and hope to patients is well underway. We have designed the building to adapt to the evolving needs of Mayo Clinic's patients and foster collaboration," says Gregory Gores, M.D., Kinney Executive Dean of Research, Mayo Clinic. "Through team science, researchers will discover scientific breakthroughs via advancements in areas such as artificial intelligence and clinical trials so cures can reach more people outside our walls."</p>



<p>"Mayo Clinic's vision for healthcare transformation demands relentless pursuit of innovations that lead to new cures," says Gianrico Farrugia, M.D., president and CEO of Mayo Clinic. "Through thoughtful team-oriented facilities such as the Kellen Building, our researchers and clinicians will find more ways to detect and eradicate disease earlier, faster and more efficiently."</p>



<p>"We appreciate the vision of the Kellen family and all of our benefactors who made this building possible and who understand the importance of early science. This building will further enable our <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-board-of-trustees-approves-plans-to-transform-healthcare-improve-experience-for-staff-and-patients-redesign-rochester-campus/#:~:text=%22Bold.,greater%20connections%20to%20our%20patients.%22" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bold. Forward. strategic plan</a> and help us engage new collaborators to join us in transforming healthcare," Dr. Gores says.</p>



<p>The Kellen Building features 11 floors, 176,000 square feet and subway connectors to other Mayo Clinic buildings.&nbsp;The new research facility joins other community and industry partners dedicated to improving patient care, health and wellness in downtown Rochester's <a href="https://dmc.mn/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Destination Medical Center Discovery Square district</a>, a research, innovation and development hub.</p>



<p>Watch a <a href="https://app.oxblue.com/open/Knutson/kellenresearchbuilding" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">time-lapse video</a> of the building's construction.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Kellen Building Fast Facts</h2>



<p><strong>Building shell</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>10,000 cubic yards of concrete.</li>



<li>30,000 cubic yards of excavated soil.</li>



<li>1,480,000 linear feet (52 tons of weight) of electrical wire.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Interior</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>16,000-pound steel staircase on the ground floor.</li>



<li>600 5-foot mobile laboratory benches.</li>



<li>53 fume and biosafety hoods.</li>



<li>Designed and constructed to use 30% less energy than comparable buildings.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Exterior</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>The glass exterior consists of 979 panels covering 60,000 square feet of 1-inch insulated glass.</li>



<li>Each panel weighs over 600 pounds and is made of material completely sourced from the U.S.</li>



<li>334 steel outrigger embeds, or support beams, support the scrim structure. Each beam weighs about 160 pounds, bringing the total weight to over 53,000 pounds.</li>



<li>The scrim features a secret shield graphic, representing the three shields of Mayo Clinic: Practice, Research and Education.</li>



<li>The external scrim reduces solar heat gain and contributes to energy reduction.</li>
</ul>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> <br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Heather Carlson Kehren, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>



<p><br>B-roll of the grand opening celebration on Dec. 13 is available. Journalists who would like to access the video can register with the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/request-account/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-opens-anna-maria-and-stephen-kellen-building-for-research/">Mayo Clinic opens Anna-Maria and Stephen Kellen Building for research</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Kellen-Building-Still2-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Kellen-Building-Still2-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Gianrico Farrugia]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Greg Gores]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Medical Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Clinical trial finds cell therapy improves quality of life in advanced heart failure</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/clinical-trial-finds-cell-therapy-improves-quality-of-life-in-advanced-heart-failure/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Buckles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 15:29:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Dr. Andre Terzic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Advanced heart failure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Satsuki Yamada]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stem Cell Therapy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=378894</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Stem cell-based therapy improved quality of life for patients with advanced heart failure, Mayo Clinic researchers and international collaborators discovered in a late-stage multinational clinical trial. In one of the largest studies of cell intervention after a heart attack, patients reported their daily hardship lessened when stem cells optimized for heart repair [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/clinical-trial-finds-cell-therapy-improves-quality-of-life-in-advanced-heart-failure/">Clinical trial finds cell therapy improves quality of life in advanced heart failure</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Sofia-Petta-Setting-Up-Heart-Disease-Research-Samples-Under-The-Direction-Of-Andre-Terzic_WF643269_0015-1024x683.jpg" alt="Sofia Petta Setting Up Heart Disease Research Samples Under The Direction Of Andre Terzic" class="wp-image-378887" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Sofia-Petta-Setting-Up-Heart-Disease-Research-Samples-Under-The-Direction-Of-Andre-Terzic_WF643269_0015-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Sofia-Petta-Setting-Up-Heart-Disease-Research-Samples-Under-The-Direction-Of-Andre-Terzic_WF643269_0015-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Sofia-Petta-Setting-Up-Heart-Disease-Research-Samples-Under-The-Direction-Of-Andre-Terzic_WF643269_0015-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Sofia-Petta-Setting-Up-Heart-Disease-Research-Samples-Under-The-Direction-Of-Andre-Terzic_WF643269_0015-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Sofia-Petta-Setting-Up-Heart-Disease-Research-Samples-Under-The-Direction-Of-Andre-Terzic_WF643269_0015.jpg 1687w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Stem cell-based therapy improved quality of life for patients with advanced <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-failure/symptoms-causes/syc-20373142" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart failure</a>, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> researchers and international collaborators discovered in a late-stage multinational clinical trial. In one of the largest studies of cell intervention after a heart attack, patients reported their daily hardship lessened when stem cells optimized for heart repair supplemented standard of care. This clinical study further documented lower death and hospitalization rates among those treated with cell therapy. This research is published in <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38006196/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stem Cells Translational Medicine</a>.</p>



<p>"In this era of global aging, people live longer, yet are at risk of chronic disease imposing a poor quality of life. Heart failure is an emerging epidemic in need of new healing options," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/terzic-andre-m-d-ph-d/bio-00084640" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Andre Terzic, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic cardiovascular researcher and lead author on the paper. "The stem cell-based approach in the present study demonstrates sustained benefit on physical and emotional health in response to biotherapy." Dr. Terzic is the Marriott Family Director, Comprehensive Cardiac Regenerative Medicine for the Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics.</p>



<p>Approximately 800,000 people in the U.S. suffer <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/heart-attack/symptoms-causes/syc-20373106" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart attacks</a> every year. Damage to cardiac muscle weakens the heart's ability to pump blood through the body, leading to heart failure — a debilitating and life-threatening disease. People with heart failure often suffer a diminished quality of life associated with shortness of breath, fatigue, swollen legs and limited daily activities. Standard of care for heart failure includes a heart-healthy diet and habits, medications, implantable devices, and rehabilitation. However, current regimens do not work for everyone, especially in advanced disease stages.<br><br><strong>The research</strong></p>



<p>The study team recruited 315 patients from 39 hospitals in 10 countries who had advanced heart failure despite receiving standard of care. Patients were randomly divided into groups that would receive stem cell therapy versus those who would not. Patients assigned to cell treatment underwent cardiac catheterization. Then, stem cells taken from their own bone marrow and programmed to heal damaged heart tissue were delivered to the heart. Patients assigned not to receive stem cells had cardiac catheterization without cell delivery — known as the sham treatment.</p>



<p>All participants were asked to complete a 21-question self-assessment at the beginning of the study and then again at 26-, 39- and 52-weeks following treatment. For each question, they rated their physical, behavioral and emotional states on a scale of 0 to 5.</p>



<p>During the one-year follow-up, patients with preexisting left cardiac chamber enlargement consistently reported improved quality of life after cell therapy over those who received the sham treatment. In parallel, lower death and hospitalization rates were recorded among those who received stem cells.</p>



<p>"Data from one of the largest cardiovascular cell therapy trials, testing a regenerative technology discovered at Mayo Clinic, indicate benefit in both quantity and quality of life in advanced heart disease," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/yamada-satsuki-m-d-ph-d/bio-00028010" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Satsuki Yamada, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic cardiovascular researcher and first author on the study. "The benefit of regenerative care has been typically evaluated on the basis of clinician-reported outcomes. What's unique in this study is that it was designed to listen to the patient's experience."</p>



<p>This clinical trial was conducted in a double-blinded fashion, with both participants and their healthcare professionals masked during the study assignment. A double-blind study&nbsp;is designed to reduce the risk of bias when evaluating patient outcomes.</p>



<p>Further independent clinical studies are needed to validate the findings of this research.</p>



<p>The J. Willard and Alice S. Marriott Foundation and National Institutes of Health (R01 HL 134664) provided funding. <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/van-cleve-cardiac-regenerative-medicine-program/about">The Mayo Clinic Van Cleve Cardiac Regenerative Medicine Program</a>, Louis V. Gerstner, Jr. Fund at Vanguard Charitable, Tanoto Foundation, and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about">Mayo Clinic Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</a> provided additional support.</p>



<p>Review <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Facademic.oup.com%2Fstcltm%2Fadvance-article%2Fdoi%2F10.1093%2Fstcltm%2Fszad078%2F7450398&amp;data=05%7C02%7CBuckles.Susan%40mayo.edu%7Ca4e00bdd5cd44d997a2108dbfb4a01a2%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C638380067487331980%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=v87ltjDpjErmSCPR%2FUZSiDyw2RGLTFUKWxzTKBbE%2Bfk%3D&amp;reserved=0">the study</a> for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic's Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</strong><br>Mayo Clinic's Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics seeks to integrate, develop and deploy new regenerative medicine products and services that continually differentiate Mayo's practice to draw patients from around the world for complex care. Learn more on Mayo Clinic's Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">website</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Susan Buckles, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/clinical-trial-finds-cell-therapy-improves-quality-of-life-in-advanced-heart-failure/">Clinical trial finds cell therapy improves quality of life in advanced heart failure</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Sofia-Petta-Setting-Up-Heart-Disease-Research-Samples-Under-The-Direction-Of-Andre-Terzic_WF643269_0015_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Sofia-Petta-Setting-Up-Heart-Disease-Research-Samples-Under-The-Direction-Of-Andre-Terzic_WF643269_0015_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Dr. Andre Terzic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Advanced heart failure]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Satsuki Yamada]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Stem Cell Therapy]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Advancing patient care with biologics: 4 ways Mayo Clinic&#8217;s biomanufacturing strategy is making a difference</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advancing-patient-care-with-biologics-4-ways-mayo-clinics-biomanufacturing-strategy-is-making-a-difference/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Buckles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Cynthia Wilkins]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Julie Allickson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Snigdha Rai]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=378666</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic seeks to harness the power of cells, tissue and genes by delivering first-of-their kind therapeutics for patients in early-stage clinical trials. Mayo Clinic's&#160;Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics&#160;is leading an effort that is at the crossroads of biology, engineering, industry and medicine to expand biomanufacturing for rare and complex disorders. Biomanufacturing is the use of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advancing-patient-care-with-biologics-4-ways-mayo-clinics-biomanufacturing-strategy-is-making-a-difference/">Advancing patient care with biologics: 4 ways Mayo Clinic&#8217;s biomanufacturing strategy is making a difference</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Advanced-Biomanufacturing-WF1385852_0117_16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378675" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Advanced-Biomanufacturing-WF1385852_0117_16x9.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Advanced-Biomanufacturing-WF1385852_0117_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Advanced-Biomanufacturing-WF1385852_0117_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic seeks to harness the power of cells, tissue and genes by delivering first-of-their kind therapeutics for patients in early-stage clinical trials. Mayo Clinic's&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</a>&nbsp;is leading an effort that is at the crossroads of biology, engineering, industry and medicine to expand biomanufacturing for rare and complex disorders. Biomanufacturing is the use of living organisms such as cells in the manufacturing of new medicines.</p>



<p>On-site biomanufacturing helps Mayo Clinic validate new biologics in clinical trials, which aim to benefit patients in at least four ways:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong></strong><strong>Addressing the unmet needs of patients</strong></h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic is driven by the needs of the patient. Innovative new therapies often originate from physician-scientist research teams who are seeking new treatments for complex conditions such as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/diabetes/symptoms-causes/syc-20371444" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">diabetes</a>, kidney failure or cancer.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Allickson_WF782604_0002-300x200.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378671" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Allickson_WF782604_0002-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Allickson_WF782604_0002-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Allickson_WF782604_0002.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Julie Allickson, Ph.D.<br></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"With most of the diseases we are researching, there is no therapy available for the patient, or the care that is available is not effective," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/allickson-julie-g-ph-d/bio-20523656" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Julie Allickson, Ph.D.</a>, the Michael S. and Mary Sue Shannon Director of the Mayo Clinic Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics. "Our goal is to advance cell and gene therapies that go beyond treating symptoms to cure patients. Our hope is to improve&nbsp; quality of life."</p>



<p>Dr. Allickson is also the Otto Bremer Trust Director, Biomanufacturing and Product Development, Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics.</p>



<p>Examples of biologics — medicines from human sources such as blood, cells, genes and tissue — are immunotherapies to kill <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/leukemia/symptoms-causes/syc-20374373" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">blood cancers</a> and an experimental, cell-based vaccine to stop the spread of ovarian cancer.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong></strong><strong>Accelerating the most promising discoveries to patient care</strong></h2>



<p>Biomanufacturing provides a bridge that transitions promising discoveries from the lab to first-in-human clinical trials. The goal is to advance technologies that would have broad clinical use for all patients who need them.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Wilkins_WF2365896_0072-300x200.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378672" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Wilkins_WF2365896_0072-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Wilkins_WF2365896_0072-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Wilkins_WF2365896_0072.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Cynthia Wilkins, Ph.D.<br></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We're manufacturing medicines that we hope will transfer seamlessly to commercial markets," says Cynthia Wilkins, Ph.D., senior director of process development in the Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics. "Working with industry can provide the support needed to move new medicines forward.'"</p>



<p>After validating biotherapeutics in phase 1 or 2 clinical trials, Mayo Clinic wants to license the technology to industry collaborators. From there, those licensees could advance the new drugs to regulatory approval and clinical care for patients around the world.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong></strong><strong>Increasing collaboration and innovation</strong></h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic is expanding its Current Good Manufacturing Practice (CGMP) facilities to manufacture experimental medicines on all its campuses. CGMP facilities are clean rooms where drugs are manufactured in aseptic (free of contamination) environments that meet Food and Drug Administration specifications for safety, identity, strength purity and quality.</p>



<p>With on-site facilities, Mayo's biomanufacturing team can work side by side with researchers to address problems quickly and find innovative solutions. On-site manufacturing capabilities also may enable Mayo to circumvent scheduling backlogs and delays that may occur with external contract manufacturers.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Rai_Snigdha_30267242_20230417-240x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378674" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Rai_Snigdha_30267242_20230417-240x300.jpg 240w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Rai_Snigdha_30267242_20230417.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Snigdha Rai, Ph.D.<br></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"This collaboration gives us immediate feedback on how the biomanufacturing process is progressing. That helps us respond to issues quicker," says Snigdha Rai, Ph.D., senior director of advanced biomanufacturing for the Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics. "If we can troubleshoot quicker and more effectively, then we can get the therapeutic to patients sooner. We want to avoid situations in which we find a problem at the final manufacturing stage and need to start over."</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic has established a robust biomanufacturing structure that includes process development, quality control and quality assurance to ensure a drug has consistent quality once it is scaled up for production.</p>



<p>"On-site collaboration helps ensure we are not deviating from what the investigator wants. If a change is needed in process development, we are able to connect immediately with the investigator," says Dr. Wilkins. "If we're having challenges transferring the discovery to biomanufacturing, we can readily communicate with the investigator and ask, 'What do you know that can help us fix the problem?'"&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Applying a 3-pronged approach to new therapeutics</strong> </h2>



<p>A unique advantage of biomanufacturing at Mayo Clinic is the immediate application it has to patients participating in a wide variety of clinical trials. Physicians work with the biomanufacturing team to help them understand how the process can be shaped to meet the needs of those patients.</p>



<p>"Mayo's approach breaks down the silos. By working directly with physicians, we get to see a variety of medicines for many different types of diseases. That's very exciting. It's different from some other organizations in which the operational side does not interact with the clinical side," says Rai. "That inspires hope we can deliver lifesaving therapies for patients in need of new options."</p>



<p>Education is another critical component that Mayo Clinic integrates into its biomanufacturing strategy.&nbsp;<a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a>&nbsp;is one of the first to offer a doctorate in regenerative sciences with coursework in biomanufacturing for future physicians, scientists and allied health staff.</p>



<p>Biomanufacturing is regulated and complex. The deep collaboration with scientists and physicians across research, education and the practice has uniquely positioned Mayo to advance new biologic therapies for unmet patient needs.</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://regenerativemedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/11/27/advancing-patient-care-with-biologics-4-ways-mayo-clinics-biomanufacturing-strategy-is-making-a-difference/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advancing-patient-care-with-biologics-4-ways-mayo-clinics-biomanufacturing-strategy-is-making-a-difference/">Advancing patient care with biologics: 4 ways Mayo Clinic&#8217;s biomanufacturing strategy is making a difference</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Advanced-Biomanufacturing-WF1385852_0117_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Advanced-Biomanufacturing-WF1385852_0117_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Cynthia Wilkins]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Julie Allickson]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Snigdha Rai]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Use of anticoagulant drug after aortic valve replacement lowers mortality risk, Mayo Clinic study finds</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/use-of-anticoagulant-drug-after-aortic-valve-replacement-lowers-mortality-risk-mayo-clinic-study-finds/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jay Furst]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2023 15:12:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[anticoagulants]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bioprosthetic aortic valve replacement]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Blood Clots]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Proceedings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Warfarin]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=378763</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Patients who received the anticoagulant drug warfarin after bioprosthetic aortic valve replacement had lower incidence of mortality and a decreased risk of blood clots, according to a retrospective study published in Mayo Clinic Proceedings. The use of bioprosthetic aortic valve replacement has increased significantly during the past decade. Among its advantages is [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/use-of-anticoagulant-drug-after-aortic-valve-replacement-lowers-mortality-risk-mayo-clinic-study-finds/">Use of anticoagulant drug after aortic valve replacement lowers mortality risk, Mayo Clinic study finds</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="682" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Dr.-Hartzell-Schaff-showing-patient-image-of-a-heart-on-a-computer-screen_1389923_3585991_0005-1024x682.jpg" alt="Dr. Hartzell Schaff showing patient an image of a heart on a computer screen" class="wp-image-378779" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Dr.-Hartzell-Schaff-showing-patient-image-of-a-heart-on-a-computer-screen_1389923_3585991_0005-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Dr.-Hartzell-Schaff-showing-patient-image-of-a-heart-on-a-computer-screen_1389923_3585991_0005-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Dr.-Hartzell-Schaff-showing-patient-image-of-a-heart-on-a-computer-screen_1389923_3585991_0005-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Dr.-Hartzell-Schaff-showing-patient-image-of-a-heart-on-a-computer-screen_1389923_3585991_0005-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Dr.-Hartzell-Schaff-showing-patient-image-of-a-heart-on-a-computer-screen_1389923_3585991_0005.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Patients who received the anticoagulant drug <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/drugs-supplements/warfarin-oral-route/description/drg-20070945?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">warfarin</a> after <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/aortic-valve-repair-aortic-valve-replacement/about/pac-20385093?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bioprosthetic aortic valve replacement</a> had lower incidence of mortality and a decreased risk of blood clots, according to a retrospective study published in <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/article/S0025-6196(23)00404-4/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a>.</p>



<p>The use of bioprosthetic aortic valve replacement has increased significantly during the past decade. Among its advantages is that most patients can avoid warfarin for anticoagulation treatment. Even so, research has been conflicting on whether patients would benefit from more aggressive early postoperative anticoagulation treatment.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> researchers analyzed nationwide data on more than 10,000 patients who underwent bioprosthetic aortic valve replacement. Warfarin use was associated with a 32% reduction in mortality risk. Patients treated with warfarin early postoperatively also had an increased risk of major bleeding events.</p>



<p>"The findings support early warfarin use in appropriately selected patients, such as patients with low bleeding risk," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/schaff-hartzell-v-m-d/bio-20053174?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hartzell Schaff, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic cardiovascular surgeon who contributed to the study. "There’s often reluctance to prescribe anticoagulant treatment early after surgery due to concerns about bleeding and uncertainty about benefits. Our research finds that the small increased hazard of bleeding (4% versus 2.3%) may be an acceptable risk given the benefits in terms of mortality risk as well as reduced risk of thromboembolism."</p>



<p>The Mayo Clinic study analyzed deidentified patient data from 2007 to 2019 using OptumLabs Data Warehouse, which contains claims data of commercially insured and Medicare Advantage enrollees of all ages and races throughout the U.S. The study was conducted in collaboration with the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/about/overview">Mayo Clinic Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</a>.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Proceedings</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a> is a monthly, peer-reviewed journal that publishes original articles and reviews on clinical and laboratory medicine, clinical research, basic science research and clinical epidemiology. The journal, sponsored by Mayo Foundation for Medical Education and Research as part of its commitment to physician education, has been published for 97 years and has a circulation of 127,000.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic College of Medicine and Science</strong><br><a href="https://college.mayo.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic College of Medicine and Science</a> educates and trains more than 4,000 students, residents, and fellows a year in biomedical education. As part of the nonprofit Mayo Clinic academic medical center, the college is supported by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>'s world-class clinical expertise, a commitment to academic excellence, and unparalleled research capabilities. The college has five schools: <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/mayo-clinic-alix-school-of-medicine/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Alix School of Medicine</a>, <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a>, <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/residencies-and-fellowships/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic School of Graduate Medical Education</a>, <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/health-sciences-education/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic School of Health Sciences</a>, and <a href="https://ce.mayo.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic School of Continuous Professional Development</a>.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Jay Furst, Mayo Clinic Research and Education Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a> </li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/use-of-anticoagulant-drug-after-aortic-valve-replacement-lowers-mortality-risk-mayo-clinic-study-finds/">Use of anticoagulant drug after aortic valve replacement lowers mortality risk, Mayo Clinic study finds</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Dr.-Hartzell-Schaff-showing-patient-image-of-a-heart-on-a-computer-screen_1389923_3585991_0005_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/Dr.-Hartzell-Schaff-showing-patient-image-of-a-heart-on-a-computer-screen_1389923_3585991_0005_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[anticoagulants]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[bioprosthetic aortic valve replacement]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Blood Clots]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Proceedings]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Warfarin]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Identifying new potential in cancer-killing T cells</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/identifying-new-potential-in-cancer-killing-t-cells/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kate Ledger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Joanina Gicobi]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=378084</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>When Joanina Gicobi began her Ph.D. degree five years ago at Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences, she was interested in thinking creatively about ways to improve cancer treatment. In particular, she was curious about the body's natural ability to fight tumors: Could that process be improved? In the laboratory of Haidong Dong, M.D., Ph.D., she [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/identifying-new-potential-in-cancer-killing-t-cells/">Identifying new potential in cancer-killing T cells</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="500" height="282" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Cancer-t-cells-mRNA-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378089" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Cancer-t-cells-mRNA-16x9-1.jpg 500w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Cancer-t-cells-mRNA-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></figure>



<p>When Joanina Gicobi began her Ph.D. degree five years ago at <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/academics/biomedical-research-training/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences</a>, she was interested in thinking creatively about ways to improve <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cancer treatment</a>. In particular, she was curious about the body's natural ability to fight tumors: Could that process be improved? In the laboratory of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/dong-haidong-m-d-ph-d/bio-20055136" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Haidong Dong, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, she joined efforts to learn more about the T cells that are part of an inherent cancer-killing immune response.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Joanina_Gicobi-250x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378091" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Joanina_Gicobi-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Joanina_Gicobi.jpg 667w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Joanina Gicobi, Ph.D.,</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"From the beginning, she was asking impressive questions about an issue that's been a great challenge," says Dr. Dong, whose lab focuses on cancer immunology and immunotherapy.</p>



<p>The inquisitive approach to problem-solving paid off. Dr. Gicobi, who recently completed her Ph.D. thesis, Dr. Dong and a team of Mayo Clinic researchers have provided a new understanding of the body’s cancer-fighting T cells, known as CD8<sup>+</sup>&nbsp;T cells. In&nbsp;<a href="http://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adi2414" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Science Advances</a>, the research team describes a previously unknown type of CD8<sup>+</sup>&nbsp;T cells that can withstand the toxicity of treatments like chemotherapy and radiation therapy. The cells, which they call resilient T cells, remain functional, suggesting there may be additional opportunity after chemotherapy and radiotherapy to target the cancer via the immune system. What's more, the team identified a potential strategy to bolster the cancer-killing capabilities of these hardy cells.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Scrutinizing cells that survive</strong></h2>



<p>One detail that has baffled researchers about CD8<sup>+</sup>&nbsp;T cells is their persistence, particularly in patients who seem to have run out of treatment options.</p>



<p>Some people with advanced cancer undergo what’s known as "salvage therapy" to ease late-stage symptoms. Salvage therapy may include chemotherapy and radiotherapy to shrink tumors that are not responding to immunotherapy or are too large to remove surgically, though the treatments are typically not expected to be a cure. However, researchers had noticed that even after several rounds of therapies that kill off immune cells along with the cancer, some patients sometimes still had cancer-killing CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells circulating in their blood. And those cells, however beaten down, seemed capable of rallying an immune response.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Haidong_Dong-300x200.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378092" style="width:332px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Haidong_Dong-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Haidong_Dong-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Dr._Haidong_Dong.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Haidong Dong, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"But we didn't know the nature of these particular CD8<sup>+</sup>&nbsp;T cells, how to identify them or what might make them unique," Dr. Dong says, adding that the lab hit numerous dead ends as they tried to characterize the cells. "It was not a straightforward route as we searched for answers."</p>



<p>The team monitored a cohort of patients who underwent salvage radiotherapy and then examined those patients' T cells. People who responded better to radiotherapy had T cells that used cellular energy most efficiently and could still kill cancer cells. Somehow the cells were less "exhausted" than other T cells. However, the phenotype didn't fully distinguish what was special about the cells.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Following the data</strong></h2>



<p>In her research, Dr. Gicobi set out to look for molecular markers particular to the T cells that rebound after cancer treatment. Using RNA sequencing, which can provide a map of all potential gene expression in a cell, she came across interesting findings that pointed back to certain genes. Dr. Gicobi noted several genes that were slightly different from those in typical CD8<sup>+</sup>&nbsp;T cells. Among them, she found a gene related to the cells' metabolic pathway, the process by which the cells produce and burn energy. This aligned with the earlier finding, and Dr. Gicobi felt encouraged to delve into the metabolism of the cells as a key differentiator.</p>



<p>"Dr. Dong has told me through my training, 'Always follow the data,'" Dr. Gicobi says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Cancer-T-cells-Dong-mRNA1x1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378090" style="width:214px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Cancer-T-cells-Dong-mRNA1x1.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Cancer-T-cells-Dong-mRNA1x1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">A confocal microscopy image of resilient T cells over-expressing the enzyme ME1.<br></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>As the team members looked further, they found the cells had heightened expression of the enzyme called malic enzyme 1, or ME1. "That was really interesting to us because ME1 is known to deal with molecules called reactive oxygen species, a metabolic byproduct that is important for the functions of immune cells but toxic when in excess. So we were looking at an enzyme that helps reduce the negative effects of metabolic pathways," she says. The finding helped confirm that the resilient T cells in people are a distinct subgroup of CD8<sup>+</sup>&nbsp;T cells.</p>



<p>Then, Dr. Gicobi had the idea that tinkering with ME1 to address the function and energy of immune cells might heighten their response to a tumor.&nbsp;</p>



<p>She engineered the resilient T cells to overproduce ME1. The laboratory experiments found the increase of ME1 revived the cells and made them even better at killing off tumor cells.&nbsp; Importantly, Dr. Gicobi says, "We were able to increase their cancer-killing capacity without the accumulation of reactive oxygen species that induce cellular exhaustion."&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>During her graduate training, Dr. Gicobi presented the findings at the annual meeting of the American Association of Immunologists.</p>



<p>Says Dr. Dong, "The excitement and the questions from attendees were a sign that this work suggests new approaches and more options for improving T cell health, which is an important avenue for the field."</p>



<p>He says further research is necessary to determine how resilient T cells affect patient outcomes and why some people have resilient T cells and others don't. He also hopes to learn more about the mechanisms underlying the function of resilient T cells and to explore the potential development of ME1 as a therapy.</p>



<p>But an important first step has been the understanding that the presence of resilient T cells indicates the perseverance of the body's inherent immune response. "This is one milestone toward new discoveries that can hopefully be translated to help patients," he says.</p>



<p>The study was supported with funding from <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine</a>; <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-biomedical-discovery" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Center for Biomedical Discovery</a>; <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/cancer-research/3-sites-1-comprehensive-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>; and the National Institutes of Health.</p>



<p>This article first published on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/11/15/identifying-new-potential-in-cancer-killing-t-cells/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/identifying-new-potential-in-cancer-killing-t-cells/">Identifying new potential in cancer-killing T cells</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Cancer-T-cells-Dong-mRNA1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Cancer-t-cells-mRNA-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Joanina Gicobi]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health and zombie cells in aging</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/health-and-zombie-cells-in-aging/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Staff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 13:38:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jennifer St. Sauver]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Joao Passos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Nathan LeBrasseur]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Stella Victorelli]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Senesscence]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=378423</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>With age, cells can experience senescence, a state where they stop growing but continue releasing inflammatory and tissue-degrading molecules. When a person is young, the immune system responds and eliminates senescent cells, often referred to as zombie cells. However, zombie cells linger and contribute to various age-related health problems and diseases. Mayo Clinic researchers, in [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/health-and-zombie-cells-in-aging/">Health and zombie cells in aging</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="500" height="282" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/format-Mitochondria-in-senescent-cell-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378424" style="width:785px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/format-Mitochondria-in-senescent-cell-16x9-1.jpg 500w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/format-Mitochondria-in-senescent-cell-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></figure>



<p>With age, cells can experience senescence, a state where they stop growing but continue releasing inflammatory and tissue-degrading molecules. When a person is young, the immune system responds and eliminates senescent cells, often referred to as zombie cells. However, zombie cells linger and contribute to various age-related health problems and diseases. Mayo Clinic researchers, in two studies, shed light on the biology of aging cells.</p>



<p>In a <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/acel.14006" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> published in Aging Cell, Mayo Clinic researchers analyzed zombie cells to explain aging at the cellular level.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Jennifer-St-Sauver-200x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378428" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Jennifer-St-Sauver-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Jennifer-St-Sauver.jpg 533w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Jennifer St. Sauver, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"We know people age at different rates and that a person's chronological age doesn't always match their biological age," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/st-sauver-jennifer-ph-d/bio-00027743" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jennifer St. Sauver, Ph.D.,</a>&nbsp;the lead author of the study and scientific director of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/education-training/population-health-scholars-program" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Population Health Science Scholars Program</a>&nbsp;at&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic's Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</a>. "We found that a group of diverse proteins secreted by zombie cells can serve as biomarkers of senescence and can predict health outcomes in older adults. We also found that measuring these biomarkers in the blood can help predict mortality beyond the combination of a person's chronologic age, sex or presence of a chronic disease."</p>



<p>The study included 1,923 adults aged 65 and older with one health condition or none. The group included 1,066 women and 857 men, with 68% of study participants having no chronic conditions and 32% having one condition.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Nathan-LeBrasseur-200x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378427" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Nathan-LeBrasseur-200x300.jpg 200w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Nathan-LeBrasseur.jpg 533w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Nathan LeBrasseur, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"What's so unique about this study is that even in the absence of disease, biomarkers are highly predictive of bad health outcomes in the future," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/lebrasseur-nathan-k-ph-d-m-s/bio-00055041" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nathan LeBrasseur, Ph.D.</a>, director of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-arlene-kogod-center-aging" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Robert and Arlene Kogod Center on Aging</a>&nbsp;and senior author of the study. Dr. LeBrasseur studies the biological processes that drive aging.</p>



<p>The researchers noted that the most common chronic conditions in the group were arthritis, high cholesterol and a history of cancer.</p>



<p>Researchers found that higher levels of specific senescent biomarkers, such as GDF15, VEGFA, PARC and MMP2, were all associated with an increased risk of death. Some of these biomarkers have been associated with developing chronic diseases. For example, research has shown that people with heart disease and some types of cancers have higher levels of GDF15 and VEGFA. Ongoing studies are investigating how lifestyle factors, including diet, physical activity and medications that appear to help clear senescent cells, influence the circulating levels of the biomarkers.</p>



<p>Dr. LeBrasseur envisions using these biomarkers as tools for clinical practice to find people at risk for health challenges. In addition, research could benefit from identifying subjects who may be most responsive to emerging ways to target senescent cells and gauge their responsiveness to treatment.</p>



<p>Dr. St. Sauver underscores the need to include more diversity in future studies, ensuring various populations are included in ongoing aging research.</p>



<p>"We did see differences in levels of these biomarkers between men and women, and we also know that race and ethnicity influence many biological processes," says Dr. St. Sauver. "For future studies, we must consider these factors in aging research."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Uncovering unknown phenomenon in zombie cells</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Joao-Passos-300x200.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378429" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Joao-Passos-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Joao-Passos-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Joao-Passos.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Joao Passos, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Mayo Clinic researcher&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/passos-joao-ph-d/bio-20454365" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Joao Passos, Ph.D.</a>, who also studies the biology of aging, sees his main purpose as working to enhance the vitality and health span—the period of life free from the consequences of disease and disability—in older people.</p>



<p>In a new study published in&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37821702/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nature</a>, he, along with postdoctoral researcher Stella Victorelli, Ph.D., and a large interdisciplinary team of collaborators, uncovered a previously unknown phenomenon that occurs in zombie cells.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Mitochondria, the tiny powerhouses within a cell, are responsible for producing energy but also play a crucial role when a cell incurs excessive damage. They can initiate a self-destruct mechanism called apoptosis, which leads to a cell's death. Senescent cells, which do not die, are notorious for resisting apoptosis. These two processes, apoptosis and senescence, have often been regarded as opposite cell fates.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>However, Dr. Passos, Dr. Victorelli and the team unexpectedly observed a small group of "rogue" mitochondria attempt to initiate apoptosis in senescent cells. When they do so, these mitochondria release their DNA into the cell's cytosol, the "soup" inside a cell. Mitochondria were once independent bacteria, so the cell perceives the mitochondrial DNA as foreign, which sparks inflammation that can damage tissues and lead to disease.</p>



<p>Furthermore, the researchers found that if they blocked this process in mice equivalent in age to a 70-year-old human, they could reduce tissue inflammation and significantly boost their health, including improving their strength, balance and bone structure.  </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Stella-Victorelli-300x200.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378426" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Stella-Victorelli-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Stella-Victorelli-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Stella-Victorelli.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Stella Victorelli, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>This newfound knowledge of the inner workings of a senescent cell may open doors to new types of therapeutics, beyond senolytics that eliminate senescent cells, to improve peoples' health span.</p>



<p>"Inflammation is one of the main ways we think senescent cells cause detrimental effects in aging-related diseases. So, it's exciting to have found a way to target a pathway that reduces inflammation," Dr. Victorelli explains.  </p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Mapping out the big picture </strong></h2>



<p>Dr. Passos and colleagues, in collaboration with researchers across the U.S., are part of an ambitious project to map senescent cells across different tissues. The project is called the Cellular Senescence Network (<a href="https://sennetconsortium.org/involvement/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">SenNet</a>) and is funded by the National Institutes of Health Common Fund. Its primary objective is to compile a comprehensive atlas of senescent cells within the human body over a lifetime. Dr. Passos recently spearheaded an effort published in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s43587-023-00446-6" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nature Aging</a>&nbsp;to highlight emerging technologies and challenges in&nbsp;<a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2021/11/10/a-zombie-cell-expedition-and-other-senescent-cell-research/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">spatial mapping of cellular senescence</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"By targeting these fundamental mechanisms driving the aging process rather than tackling each disease individually, we have the potential to not only fight one disease of aging but all of them," Dr. Passos says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-d-patricia-e-kern-center-science-health-care-delivery/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Robert D. and Patricia E. Kern Center for the Science of Health Care Delivery</a> supported the Aging Cell&nbsp;<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/acel.14006" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>, and the Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/robert-arlene-kogod-center-aging" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Robert and Arlene Kogod Center on Aging</a> supported the Nature&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37821702/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>. For the full list of disclosures, authors and research funding, please see the studies. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>This story first published on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/11/16/health-and-zombie-cells-in-aging/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/health-and-zombie-cells-in-aging/">Health and zombie cells in aging</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/format-Mitochondria-in-senescent-cell-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/format-Mitochondria-in-senescent-cell-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jennifer St. Sauver]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Joao Passos]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Nathan LeBrasseur]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Stella Victorelli]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Senesscence]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>How can adults with congenital heart disease reduce risks? Study finds lifetime cardiology monitoring is key </title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-can-adults-with-congenital-heart-disease-reduce-risks-study-finds-lifetime-cardiology-monitoring-is-key/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Terri Malloy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2023 16:06:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ACHD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Adult Congenital Heart Disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cardiovascular surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Congenital Heart Disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Luke Burchill]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Failure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[heart surgery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377235</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Heart failure is a potentially urgent health concern for young adults with congenital heart disease (ACHD) that is often overlooked and undertreated, even as hospitalizations for this condition continue to rise. New research from Mayo Clinic shows that young adults in the U.S. living with congenital heart disease are at an increased [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-can-adults-with-congenital-heart-disease-reduce-risks-study-finds-lifetime-cardiology-monitoring-is-key/">How can adults with congenital heart disease reduce risks? Study finds lifetime cardiology monitoring is key </a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/burchill06_16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Dr. Burchill holding a model of a heart" class="wp-image-378356" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/burchill06_16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/burchill06_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/burchill06_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/burchill06_16x9.jpg 1052w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Heart failure is a potentially urgent health concern for young <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/adult-congenital-heart-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20355456?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">adults with congenital heart disease</a> (ACHD) that is often overlooked and undertreated, even as hospitalizations for this condition continue to rise. New research from Mayo Clinic shows that young adults in the U.S. living with congenital heart disease are at an increased risk of death or cardiovascular complications after being hospitalized for heart failure. However, study data published in the <a href="https://www.ahajournals.org/doi/10.1161/JAHA.123.030649" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Journal of the American Heart Association</a> also found that patients who had been receiving recent cardiology care before a heart failure hospitalization were less likely to die.</p>



<p>"More than 85% of children born with congenital heart disease reach adulthood. They are likely to experience complications later, yet 61% of these patients beyond the age of 18 do not see a cardiology specialist," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic/medical-innovation/burchill-congenital-heart-disease?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Luke Burchill, M.B.B.S., Ph.D.</a>, a cardiologist at Mayo Clinic and first author of the study. "These young adult patients have a strong need for individualized care pathways to improve their quality of life and monitor health issues like heart failure."</p>



<p><a href="https://youtu.be/qmiFTmcNyrE" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Watch: Dr. Luke Burchill talks about congenital heart disease</strong></a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeqmiFTmcNyrE"  title="Dr. Luke Burchill - Study on heart failure hospitalizations in adults with congenital heart disease" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qmiFTmcNyrE?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites with Dr. Burchill are available in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Name super/CG: Luke Burchill, M.D./Cardiology/Mayo Clinic</strong>.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.ahajournals.org/doi/full/10.1161/JAHA.118.008775" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Prior research</a> showed that heart failure hospitalizations of U.S. adults with congenital heart disease increased dramatically from 1998 to 2011. To further understand this trend and its effect on patients and hospital resources, Dr. Burchill and colleagues used national data to study a retrospective cohort of adults with congenital heart disease hospitalized in the past decade. The percentage of ACHD heart failure hospitalizations increased significantly, rising from 6.6% in 2010 to 14% in 2020.</p>



<p>In more than 26,000 unique hospital admissions of ACHD patients, 22% had heart failure and 78% did not. Those admitted with heart failure had a higher risk of death and other major heart and brain complications and used more healthcare resources, including rehospitalization and post-acute care services than those admitted without heart failure. However, people who had a cardiology clinic visit within 30 days prior to hospital admission had lower rates of death due to any causes at the 90-day and 1-year mark.</p>



<p>The ACHD patients with heart failure were nearly twice as likely as those without heart failure to be readmitted to a hospital, especially those under age 45, regardless of their type of congenital heart disease. Younger patients also required more medical or supportive care after they left the hospital before they could return home and care for themselves.</p>



<p>"Many of the patients I meet with ACHD and heart failure share a similar story of not having their heart-related symptoms taken seriously, leading to a delayed recognition and treatment of heart failure. The good news is that we can reset the course for most," says Dr. Burchill. "We have new medications to restrengthen the heart, new options for replacing heart valves without opening the chest, and low-risk treatments for returning heart rhythm to normal. Our goal is to shift the focus from heart failure to heart function and patient success in feeling better and living longer."</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>  <br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news. </p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<ul>
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/how-can-adults-with-congenital-heart-disease-reduce-risks-study-finds-lifetime-cardiology-monitoring-is-key/">How can adults with congenital heart disease reduce risks? Study finds lifetime cardiology monitoring is key </a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/burchill06_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/burchill06_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[ACHD]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Adult Congenital Heart Disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cardiology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cardiovascular surgery]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Congenital Heart Disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Luke Burchill]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Heart Failure]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[heart surgery]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>