<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Research - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research-2/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/research-2/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 12:04:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>17-gene signature linked to remission after triple-negative breast cancer treatment </title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/17-gene-signature-linked-to-remission-after-triple-negative-breast-cancer-treatment/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Murphy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Judy Boughey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Krishna Rani Kalari]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Goetz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[genetics]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376121</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have discovered a distinctive pattern in a specific set of 17 genes that may be associated with remission after treatment for&#160;triple-negative breast cancer. The multi-omics study,&#160;published in Breast Cancer Research, highlights the potential for further investigating this signature as a target for individualized medicine.&#160; Approximately 10-15% of breast cancers fall into the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/17-gene-signature-linked-to-remission-after-triple-negative-breast-cancer-treatment/">17-gene signature linked to remission after triple-negative breast cancer treatment </a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/breast-cancer5-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376124" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/breast-cancer5-16x9-1.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/breast-cancer5-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/breast-cancer5-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have discovered a distinctive pattern in a specific set of 17 genes that may be associated with remission after treatment for&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/breast-cancer/in-depth/breast-cancer/art-20045654" target="_blank">triple-negative breast cancer</a>. The multi-omics study,&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://breast-cancer-research.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13058-023-01656-x" target="_blank">published in Breast Cancer Research</a>, highlights the potential for further investigating this signature as a target for individualized medicine.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Approximately 10-15% of breast cancers fall into the category of "triple-negative," indicating that their growth is not driven through the hormone receptors for estrogen or progesterone, nor by the human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2). In contrast, other breast cancers have at least one of these receptors, allowing for treatments that can target or block them to inhibit the cancer's progression.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Triple-negative breast cancer is known for its resistance to targeted therapies, leaving chemotherapy as the primary treatment option. While most patients initially respond well to the standard neoadjuvant chemotherapy, nearly 20% of patients will experience recurrence after treatment.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"It's crucial that we create tools that assist clinicians in making informed treatment decisions," says&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/kalari-krishna-r-ph-d/bio-00095546" target="_blank">Krishna Rani Kalari, Ph.D.</a>, a lead author of the study and an associate professor of biomedical informatics at the Center for Individualized Medicine. "This 17-gene signature is one of the candidate tools that shows potential. However, for this signature to have clinical utility, there will need to be studies evaluating whether alternative drugs/drug combinations may work in this group of patients."&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Decoding pattern in 17 genes</h3>



<p>In their study, the researchers investigated tumor samples before and after treatment of patients with triple-negative breast cancer who failed to respond to neoadjuvant chemotherapy. Using multi-omics analysis and machine learning technologies, they examined changes in gene expression to understand the molecular underpinnings driving tumor recurrence.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Multi-omics is an emerging multidisciplinary field of biological sciences that encompasses genomics, proteomics, epigenomics, transcriptomics, metabolomics and more.  &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The team identified 17 genes associated with relapse-free survival and found that many of the genes may play a role in triggering inflammation to initiate an immune system response. Dr. Kalari says failure to initiate immune response prevents the clearance of weakened tumor cells, thereby permitting the development of treatment resistance and disease re-occurrence.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Quest for individualized medicine</h3>



<p>The study is an extension of Mayo Clinic's clinical prospective breast cancer study known as Breast Cancer Genome-Guided Therapy Study (<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine/research/clinical-studies/beauty2" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">BEAUTY</a>). The goal of the study is to determine why some patient’s tumors respond to chemotherapy while others don't, and to use that knowledge as a catalyst to develop personalized medicine therapies.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Next, the team plans to further investigate the gene signature and test therapeutic strategies.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Co-lead authors of the study are Mayo Clinic researchers&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/kalari-krishna-r-ph-d/bio-00095546" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Krishna Rani Kalari, Ph.D.</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/boughey-judy-c-m-d/bio-00027350">Judy Boughey, M.D</a>., and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/goetz-matthew-p-m-d/bio-00027285">Matthew Goetz, M.D.</a>&nbsp;Additional authors include Xiaojia Tang, Ph.D. and Kevin Thompson, Ph.D. A comprehensive list of the authors, disclosures, and funding are available in the <a href="https://breast-cancer-research.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13058-023-01656-x" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This article first published on the <a href="https://individualizedmedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/10/18/17-gene-signature-linked-to-remission-after-triple-negative-breast-cancer-treatment/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">blog of the Center for Individualized Medicine</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/17-gene-signature-linked-to-remission-after-triple-negative-breast-cancer-treatment/">17-gene signature linked to remission after triple-negative breast cancer treatment </a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/breast-cancer5-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/breast-cancer5-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Breast Cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Judy Boughey]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Krishna Rani Kalari]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Matthew Goetz]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[genetics]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic selects Owen Garrick, M.D., as dean of Clinical Trials</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-selects-owen-garrick-m-d-as-dean-of-clinical-trials/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Julie Vera]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2023 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dean of Clinical Trials]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Gregory Gores]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Owen Garrick]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Karen Hartman]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376149</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic Research leaders are excited to announce the arrival of Owen Garrick, M.D., as the dean of Clinical Trials. Dr. Garrick will start in his new position on Oct. 30. The dean of Clinical Trials is tasked with strengthening Mayo Clinic's standing as a national leader of innovative, demand-generating clinical trials for patients everywhere. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-selects-owen-garrick-m-d-as-dean-of-clinical-trials/">Mayo Clinic selects Owen Garrick, M.D., as dean of Clinical Trials</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="900" height="506" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/OwenGarrick-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376151" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/OwenGarrick-16x9-1.jpg 900w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/OwenGarrick-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/OwenGarrick-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 900px) 100vw, 900px" /></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research">Research </a>leaders are excited to announce the arrival of Owen Garrick, M.D., as the dean of <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials/about-clinical-studies">Clinical Trials</a>. Dr. Garrick will start in his new position on Oct. 30.</p>



<p>The dean of Clinical Trials is tasked with strengthening Mayo Clinic's standing as a national leader of innovative, demand-generating clinical trials for patients everywhere. Dr. Garrick will lead the transformation of Mayo Clinic’s clinical trials, including developing digital capabilities, accelerating the volume of remote clinical trials and enhancing national awareness of clinical trials at Mayo Clinic. In this role, Dr. Garrick will serve as a member of the Research Executive Management Team, report to <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/gores-gregory-j-m-d/bio-00078325" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gregory Gores, M.D.</a>, Kinney Executive Dean of Research, Mayo Clinic, and partner with Karen Hartman, vice chair, Research Administration, Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>"We're thrilled to welcome Dr. Garrick into this role that focuses on advancing our clinical trials strategy and operations," says Dr. Gores. "He brings broad and deep experience in clinical trials leadership, business development and participation in external organizations that will be invaluable in ensuring clinical trials are fully integrated with the future of Mayo Clinic's Cure, Connect and Transform strategy."</p>



<p>Dr. Garrick comes to Mayo most recently from CVS Health, where he was chief medical officer for Clinical Trial Services. He also has worked on and lectured and published extensively about diversity and equity for patients and in the healthcare workforce pipeline.</p>



<p>"Dr. Garrick's business acumen is critical to the future of clinical trials as Mayo continues bringing its Category-of-One research, treatments and cures to more patients than ever," says Hartman. "His breadth of experience will challenge us to think differently about clinical trials transformation." &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>A wealth of expertise</strong></p>



<p>In his three-decade career, Dr. Garrick has demonstrated a commitment to improving health outcomes, including in drug development, research, ethics, regulatory science and health system management particularly for underserved populations. Under his leadership as chief medical officer for Clinical Trial Services, CVS Health enrolled more than 36,000 participants into U.S. clinical trials, representing 5% of all study participants in the country. Dr. Garrick executed medical strategy for Trial Delivery, Recruitment and Real-World Evidence business lines, ensuring compliance, clinical insights and clinical innovation.</p>



<p>He oversaw the development of machine-learning models for patient identification and outreach, leveraging in-home, digital and retail pharmacy care delivery for research and evidence generation. Dr. Garrick also served as vice president and head of Clinical Trial Development and Delivery for CVS Health, where he launched a large and diverse decentralized clinical trials network and launched a Clinical Trial Diversity solution to improve recruitment of diverse populations into clinical trials.</p>



<p>Dr. Garrick has held leadership positions at several other healthcare organizations, including McKesson, Novartis and Merck. He also has worked on the health insurance side at MetLife, and on the finance side at Goldman Sachs.</p>



<p>Dr. Garrick earned an A.B. (bachelor of arts) in psychology from Princeton University; his M.D. from Yale School of Medicine; and an MBA from The Wharton School, University of Pennsylvania. He's served on several boards including the American Medical Association; the American Psychiatric Association Foundation; Sutter Health; and as a committee member on the Health and Human Services Secretary’s Advisory Council on Human Research Protections.</p>



<p>"I am truly looking forward to this opportunity. I can't wait to get to work helping transform clinical trials at Mayo Clinic," says Dr. Garrick. "The reputation of Mayo Clinic, and the tremendous work the team already has done to expand access to trials for everyone, means Mayo Clinic is positioned to be a clear leader in this space. I'm honored to join the effort."</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-selects-owen-garrick-m-d-as-dean-of-clinical-trials/">Mayo Clinic selects Owen Garrick, M.D., as dean of Clinical Trials</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/OwenGarrick-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/OwenGarrick-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dean of Clinical Trials]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Gregory Gores]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Owen Garrick]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Karen Hartman]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Proceedings, Kidney International publish consensus statement on new approach to identifying kidney disorder</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-proceedings-kidney-international-publish-consensus-statement-on-new-approach-to-identifying-kidney-disorder/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jay Furst]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2023 16:52:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Karl Nath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Vesna Garovic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[edema]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kidney disorder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kidney International]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Proceedings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[membranous nephropathy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nephrotic syndrome]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[proteinuria]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=375899</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Forty-eight international experts on membranous nephropathy have co-authored a consensus report that calls for a new method of classifying diagnoses of the syndrome. They say the change would result in greater accuracy in diagnoses, which would open the door to improved patient care and targeted treatment. To call attention to the report, Mayo Clinic Proceedings [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-proceedings-kidney-international-publish-consensus-statement-on-new-approach-to-identifying-kidney-disorder/">Mayo Clinic Proceedings, Kidney International publish consensus statement on new approach to identifying kidney disorder</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidneys16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-363122" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidneys16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidneys16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidneys16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidneys16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidneys16x9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Forty-eight international experts on <a href="https://www.kidney-international.org/article/S0085-2538(23)00490-8/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">membranous nephropathy</a> have co-authored a <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/article/S0025-6196(23)00372-5/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">consensus report</a> that calls for a new method of classifying diagnoses of the syndrome. They say the change would result in greater accuracy in diagnoses, which would open the door to improved patient care and targeted treatment. To call attention to the report, <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a> and <a href="https://www.kidney-international.org/article/S0085-2538(23)00490-8/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kidney International</a> have published the report simultaneously.</p>



<p>Membranous nephropathy is a kidney disorder that involves immunologic attack on structures inside the kidney that help filter wastes and fluids, and it's a relatively common cause of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/nephrotic-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20375608">nephrotic syndrome</a> in adults. Nephrotic syndrome is a kidney disorder that causes the body to leak relatively large amounts of protein into the urine. It causes swelling, particularly in the feet and ankles, and increases the risk of other health problems.</p>



<p>With current diagnostic processes, in approximately 70% of cases involving membranous nephropathy, it's classified as the primary cause of disease. In the remaining cases, it's classified as secondary to another recognized disease or cause. "Recent discoveries have rendered the primary-secondary classification of membranous nephropathy anachronistic," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/nath-karl-a-m-d/bio-00027413" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Karl Nath, M.B., Ch.B</a>, a co-author of the report and editor-in-chief of Mayo Clinic Proceedings. "In its place, the Mayo Clinic Consensus Report on Membranous Nephropathy proposes a new two-step classification that incorporates recent discoveries, is clinically based and pragmatic."</p>



<p>The consensus report is the result of a Mayo Clinic-sponsored meeting in Rochester, Minnesota, on Oct. 29, 2022, and was made possible by discoveries at Mayo Clinic. The article in Mayo Clinic Proceedings and Kidney International<em>, </em>the journal of the <a href="https://www.theisn.org/">International Society of Nephrology</a>, outlines a diagnostic classification process that incorporates recent discoveries and emerging research. <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/fervenza-fernando-fernando-c-c-m-d-ph-d/bio-00027412">Fernando Fervenza, M.D., Ph.D.,</a> director of Mayo Clinic's <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/mayo-nephrology-collaborative-group/about">Nephrology Collaborative Group</a>, is senior author. First author is <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/sethi-sanjeev-m-d-ph-d/bio-20513111">Sanjeev Sethi, M.D., Ph.D.,</a> a Mayo Clinic pathologist who specializes in kidney diseases.</p>



<p>In <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/article/S0025-6196(23)00403-2/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">a commentary</a> that accompanies the consensus statement in Mayo Clinic Proceedings, Dr. Nath and co-authors <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/erickson-lori-a-m-d/bio-00084505" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lori A. Erickson, M.D.</a>, and <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/garovic-vesna-d-m-d-ph-d/bio-00027747" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Vesna Garovic, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, write that the consensus report makes clear the need for a new approach to diagnostic classification. "This new classification assimilates new knowledge as it emerges and provides a foundation for further discoveries in membranous nephropathy," says Dr. Nath.</p>



<p>Dr. Nath and Dr. Garovic are nephrologists in the Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/nephrology-hypertension/sections/overview/ovc-20464571" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Division of Nephrology and Hypertension</a>, Department of Medicine, and Dr. Erickson is in the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/laboratory-medicine-pathology/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathology</a>.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Proceedings</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a> is a monthly peer-reviewed journal that publishes original articles and reviews on clinical and laboratory medicine, clinical research, basic science research and clinical epidemiology. The journal, sponsored by Mayo Foundation for Medical Education and Research as part of its commitment to physician education, has been published for 97 years and has a circulation of 127,000.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and to providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Jay Furst, Research and Education Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-proceedings-kidney-international-publish-consensus-statement-on-new-approach-to-identifying-kidney-disorder/">Mayo Clinic Proceedings, Kidney International publish consensus statement on new approach to identifying kidney disorder</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidneys1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidneys16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Karl Nath]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Vesna Garovic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[edema]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[kidney disorder]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Kidney International]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Proceedings]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[membranous nephropathy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[nephrotic syndrome]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[proteinuria]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Zooming in on rare bone cells that drive osteoporosis</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/zooming-in-on-rare-bone-cells-that-drive-osteoporosis/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Caitlin Doran]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Madison Doolittle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sundeep Khosla]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[osteoporosis]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=375682</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have developed a new high-resolution, analytical technique to identify the rare senescent bone cells that are known to drive osteoporosis. Senescent cells are malfunctioning cells that build up as people age or as the result of chronic diseases. Once these cells form, they can contribute to developing diseases and consequences of aging. This [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/zooming-in-on-rare-bone-cells-that-drive-osteoporosis/">Zooming in on rare bone cells that drive osteoporosis</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle_NCOMM_Art1-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375683" style="width:840px;height:473px" width="840" height="473" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle_NCOMM_Art1-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle_NCOMM_Art1-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle_NCOMM_Art1-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle_NCOMM_Art1-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle_NCOMM_Art1-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 840px) 100vw, 840px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">High-resolution image showing senescent cells in bone that drive osteoporosis.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have developed a new high-resolution, analytical technique to identify the rare senescent bone cells that are known to drive <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/osteoporosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20351968" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">osteoporosis</a>. Senescent cells are malfunctioning cells that build up as people age or as the result of chronic diseases. Once these cells form, they can contribute to developing diseases and consequences of aging. This new method, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37524694/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">detailed in a paper published in Nature Communications</a>, will enable scientists to better target experimental anti-aging drugs at the cellular level, advancing efforts to find treatments for osteoporosis and other aging-related diseases.</p>



<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle-Madison-L._21598983_202001200201-250x300-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375685" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Madison Doolittle, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-left">"Senescent cells are notoriously challenging to identify. With this work, we are overcoming a barrier that has hindered past research," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/labs/osteoporosis-and-bone-biology/faculty-staff" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Madison Doolittle, Ph.D.,</a> a Mayo Clinic endocrinology researcher and first author of the paper. "We expect this technique will enhance our ability to study these cells in a precise manner, understand the mechanisms of diseases and develop more focused targets for treatment."</p>



<p>This research will inform clinical trials at Mayo Clinic and around the world that are testing experimental treatments for osteoporosis, Alzheimer’s disease, chronic kidney disease and other aging-related diseases. The new technique is already being used to map senescent cells through the National Institutes of Health's&nbsp;<a href="https://commonfund.nih.gov/senescence" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cellular Senescence Network</a>.</p>



<p>The new technique involves mass cytometry, a method scientists employ to analyze the differences among many types of cells and to identify specific cells by the types of proteins displayed on their surfaces or interiors. To pinpoint senescent cells, the researchers looked for the presence of p16, p21, BCL-2, and CD24 proteins, which control the development and survival of senescent cells.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Khosla-Sundeep_10803408_20221205-240x300-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375686" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Sundeep Khosla, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p></p>



<p>"The novel, single-cell approach that Dr. Doolittle developed opens up new ways to identify these rare senescent cells not only in bone but also broadly across tissues," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/khosla-sundeep-m-d/bio-00078126" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sundeep Khosla, M.D.,</a>&nbsp;a Mayo Clinic endocrinologist and senior author of the paper. "From a translational and clinical perspective, this would help in potentially quantifying the burden of senescent cells in patients and their response to interventions that kill or disable these harmful cells."</p>



<p>Dr. Khosla anticipates that future research will focus on applying this technique to identify strategies to improve bone healing and regeneration after skeletal injury.</p>



<p>Dr. Khosla is the Dr. Francis Chucker and Nathan Landow Professor of Research at Mayo Clinic College of Medicine and Science.</p>



<p>For the full list of disclosures and research funding, please see the paper.</p>



<p>This article first published on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/10/05/zooming-in-on-rare-bone-cells-that-drive-osteoporosis/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/zooming-in-on-rare-bone-cells-that-drive-osteoporosis/">Zooming in on rare bone cells that drive osteoporosis</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle_NCOMM_Art1-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Doolittle_NCOMM_Art1-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Madison Doolittle]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Sundeep Khosla]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[osteoporosis]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Advancing ultrasound microvessel imaging and AI to improve cancer detection</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advancing-ultrasound-microvessel-imaging-and-ai-to-improve-cancer-detection/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[asatake]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 13:01:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[artificial intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Azra Alizad]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Mostafa Fatemi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ultrasound]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=375666</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Ultrasound&#160;— a technology that uses sound waves to produce an image — is commonly used to monitor the development of a baby as it grows inside its mother. But ultrasound imaging also can be used to investigate suspicious masses of tissue and nodules that may be cancerous. Tumors consist not only of cancer cells but [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advancing-ultrasound-microvessel-imaging-and-ai-to-improve-cancer-detection/">Advancing ultrasound microvessel imaging and AI to improve cancer detection</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Breast-Cancer-ultrasound-AI-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375668" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Breast-Cancer-ultrasound-AI-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Breast-Cancer-ultrasound-AI-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Breast-Cancer-ultrasound-AI-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Breast-Cancer-ultrasound-AI-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Breast-Cancer-ultrasound-AI-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/ultrasound/about/pac-20395177" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ultrasound</a>&nbsp;— a technology that uses sound waves to produce an image — is commonly used to monitor the development of a baby as it grows inside its mother. But ultrasound imaging also can be used to investigate suspicious masses of tissue and nodules that may be cancerous.</p>



<p>Tumors consist not only of cancer cells but also a matrix of small blood vessels, or microvessels, that cannot be seen in the images produced by conventional ultrasound machines. To solve this problem, physician-scientist&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/alizad-azra-m-d/bio-00085586" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Azra Alizad, M.D.</a>, and biomedical engineering scientist&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/fatemi-mostafa-ph-d/bio-00086282" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mostafa Fatemi, Ph.D.</a>, teamed up at Mayo Clinic to design and study a tool that may improve the resolution of ultrasound imaging. As demonstrated in&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35486168/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">research findings</a>, they developed high-resolution ultrasound imaging software, compatible with many ultrasound machines, that could exponentially improve both the detail and quality of images.</p>



<p>The investigational software, which they've named quantitative high-definition microvessel imaging (q-HDMI), has been evaluated to capture high-resolution 2D and 3D images of microvessels as small as 150 microns, roughly twice the width of a human hair.</p>



<div class="wp-block-media-text has-media-on-the-right is-stacked-on-mobile" style="grid-template-columns:auto 35%"><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p>"If we can visualize and capture the microvessel in the earliest stages of cancer, we can better diagnose and treat it earlier, which improves the outcome for the patient," says Dr. Alizad, who specializes in ultrasound technology for cancer imaging.</p>
</div><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="925" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Alizad-WF3352118_0032-cut-925x1024-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375671 size-full" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Alizad-WF3352118_0032-cut-925x1024-1.jpg 925w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Alizad-WF3352118_0032-cut-925x1024-1-271x300.jpg 271w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Alizad-WF3352118_0032-cut-925x1024-1-768x850.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 925px) 100vw, 925px" /></figure></div>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Artificial intelligence helps detect what we cannot see</strong></h2>



<p>In addition, the researchers identified a series of biomarkers representing specific characteristics of tiny </p>



<p>vessels, such as shape, pattern, irregularity and complexity, and packaged them into an algorithm that can sort the image data into benign or malignant masses.</p>



<div class="wp-block-media-text is-stacked-on-mobile" style="grid-template-columns:37% auto"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="481" height="532" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Fatemi-WF3352118_0019_vertical.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375670 size-full" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Fatemi-WF3352118_0019_vertical.jpg 481w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Fatemi-WF3352118_0019_vertical-271x300.jpg 271w" sizes="(max-width: 481px) 100vw, 481px" /></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p></p>



<p>"This technology provides a quantitative value that shows the probability of malignancy," Dr. Fatemi says. "It's a tool to extract information in a way that can be useful to clinicians."</p>
</div></div>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Applying it in practice</strong></h2>



<p>In a&nbsp;<a href="https://breast-cancer-research.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13058-022-01583-3" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">clinical study</a>, the researchers showed that their new q-HDMI tool combined with artificial intelligence (AI) was able to detect a very small, 3-millimeter-wide, malignant breast cancer mass comprised of miniscule vessels in a 40-year-old woman. Finding and treating cancer lesions when they are this size before they spread, or metastasize, can be lifesaving.</p>



<p>"The questions in radiology really are: benign or malignant? And if it's suspicious, how concerned should we be?" Dr. Fatemi says.</p>



<p>To help radiologists answer these questions, the researchers applied their software and algorithm to further analyze suspicious breast masses from 521 patients who already had received conventional ultrasound imaging. The results were astounding. The new technology yielded a&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35486168/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">nearly 100% rate of accuracy</a>&nbsp;in determining malignant versus benign masses, regardless of the tumor size.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidqCtLfFbWcEoampt"  title="3D images of benign and malignant breast tissue masses" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qCtLfFbWcEo?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>More recently, the researchers analyzed thyroid nodules from 92 patients. Thyroid nodules are common and it is often hard to differentiate between cancerous and non-cancerous ones through imaging. Yet the prevalence of thyroid cancer has increased over the last few decades.</p>



<p>"With conventional ultrasound images, physicians can diagnose whether a thyroid nodule is benign or malignant with only about 35-75% accuracy," Dr. Alizad says. That's why physicians often opt to perform thyroid biopsies, which enable them to more definitively determine if a thyroid nodule is a cause for concern.</p>



<p>The researchers identified 12 biomarkers that can differentiate benign from malignant thyroid tissues. They programmed the AI-powered algorithm with these biomarkers, which sorted the images and had an 84% rate of accuracy. These results were published in the journal&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36980774/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cancers</a>&nbsp;and highlighted by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nibib.nih.gov/news-events/newsroom/how-combination-advanced-ultrasound-and-ai-could-upgrade-cancer-diagnostics" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Institutes of Health</a>.</p>



<p>"If it is cancer, we definitely want to know that. But if we can determine if a thyroid nodule is benign without even having to do a biopsy, that is even better as it spares the patient from the financial and physical burdens associated with an unnecessary benign biopsy," Dr. Alizad says.</p>



<p>The researchers see that their quantitative tool could be particularly useful in parts of the world where there is limited expertise and resources, such as rural areas and developing countries.</p>



<p>They also are collaborating with oncologists to enable them to use the q-HDMI tool to better monitor the effectiveness of cancer treatments and help them adjust therapies for individual patients in real time.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/advancing-ultrasound-microvessel-imaging-and-ai-to-improve-cancer-detection/">Advancing ultrasound microvessel imaging and AI to improve cancer detection</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Breast-Cancer-ultrasound-AI-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Breast-Cancer-ultrasound-AI-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[artificial intelligence]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Azra Alizad]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Mostafa Fatemi]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[ultrasound]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic study sheds light on rare genetic disorder and blood cancers</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-sheds-light-on-rare-genetic-disorder-and-blood-cancers/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Colette Gallagher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2023 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blood cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Alejandro Ferrer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[telemores]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=375616</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In a recent&#160;study, Mayo Clinic researchers examined telomere biology disorders, a group of rare genetic disorders characterized by short telomeres. Telomeres are long segments at the end of chromosomes that protect the DNA from unraveling, similar to the small plastic sheath at the end of a shoelace. Telomeres shorten naturally with age but become abnormally [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-sheds-light-on-rare-genetic-disorder-and-blood-cancers/">Mayo Clinic study sheds light on rare genetic disorder and blood cancers</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Telomere-GettyImages-1486563542_16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375620" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Telomere-GettyImages-1486563542_16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Telomere-GettyImages-1486563542_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Telomere-GettyImages-1486563542_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Telomere-GettyImages-1486563542_16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Telomere-GettyImages-1486563542_16x9.jpg 1763w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>In a recent&nbsp;<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ajh.27086" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>, Mayo Clinic researchers examined telomere biology disorders, a group of rare genetic disorders characterized by short telomeres. Telomeres are long segments at the end of chromosomes that protect the DNA from unraveling, similar to the small plastic sheath at the end of a shoelace. Telomeres shorten naturally with age but become abnormally shorter in telomere biology disorders. People with these disorders often have bone marrow failure and, for unknown reasons, a high risk of developing blood cancer.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers explored the causes of this increased cancer risk by assessing clonal hematopoiesis in patients with telomere biology disorders. Clonal hematopoiesis is also an age-related event that occurs when blood stem cells acquire genetic mutations that make them divide more rapidly than normal. This creates a growing clone in the blood that can evolve into blood cancer. Approximately 10-20% of the population over 70 present an observable clonal hematopoiesis. However, how these clones evolve over time depends on the gene mutation acquired and the surrounding environment of the cells.</p>



<p>The study found that people with telomere biology disorders often have a high percentage of clonal hematopoiesis. Variants in the&nbsp;<em>U2AF1</em>&nbsp;gene are especially common. In contrast, clonal hematopoiesis that occurs because of aging is associated with other mutated genes. This difference suggests that the&nbsp;<em>U2AF1</em>&nbsp;gene may play a role in developing blood cancer, specifically in people with telomere biology disorders.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p><strong>"We need to understand why this gene is so commonly mutated in people with this disorder and its role in cancer development." - Dr. Ferrer</strong></p>



<p></p>
</blockquote>



<div class="wp-block-media-text is-stacked-on-mobile" style="grid-template-columns:32% auto"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="240" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Ferrer-Alejandro_15724913_20220301-240x300-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375623 size-full" /></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p>"<em>U2AF1</em>&nbsp;mutations can affect the expression of specific genes and contribute to the emergence of clonal hematopoiesis in a way that is unique to these patients," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/ferrer-alejandro-ph-d/bio-20503546" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alejandro Ferrer, Ph.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic hematology researcher. "We need to understand why this gene is so commonly mutated in people with this disorder and its role in cancer development."</p>
</div></div>



<p></p>



<p>The findings are especially relevant for people with telomere biology disorders who may be sensitive to standard cancer therapies due to a combination of factors, including preexisting genomic instability, shortened telomeres and the potential effect of these therapies on cancer and healthy cells.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Future Research</strong></h2>



<p>Researchers need to better understand why the&nbsp;<em>U2AF1&nbsp;</em>gene is prominently mutated in people with telomere biology disorders compared to other genes. Assessing the clinical relevance may help advance knowledge and potentially develop targeted treatments tailored to their needs.</p>



<p>The Mayo Clinic&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/cancer/news/clonal-hematopoiesis-clinic-stratifies-risk-for-patients-with-cancer/mac-20543180" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Clonal Hematopoiesis (CHIP) and Telomere Biology Disorder clinics</a>&nbsp;are a collaborative effort between the Division of Hematology and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-individualized-medicine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic's Center for Individualized Medicine</a>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Funding</strong></h2>



<p>This study was funded through the Mayo Clinic Center for Individualized Medicine and the Division of Hematology as part of the Pre-myeloid and Bone Marrow Failure Clinics and the Translational Telomere Program. Review the&nbsp;<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ajh.27086" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;for a complete list of authors, disclosures and funding.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This article first appeared on the <a href="https://individualizedmedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/10/11/mayo-clinic-study-sheds-light-on-rare-genetic-disorder-and-blood-cancers/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">blog of the Center for Individualized Medicine</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-study-sheds-light-on-rare-genetic-disorder-and-blood-cancers/">Mayo Clinic study sheds light on rare genetic disorder and blood cancers</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Telomere-GettyImages-1486563542_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Telomere-GettyImages-1486563542_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[blood cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Alejandro Ferrer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[telemores]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic prepares to biomanufacture a new CAR-T cell therapy for recurring B-cell blood cancers</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/10-10mayo-clinic-prepares-to-biomanufacture-a-new-car-t-cell-therapy-for-recurring-b-cell-blood-cancers/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Buckles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[B-cell blood cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CAR-T]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Hong Qin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Julie Allickson]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=375575</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic research has developed a new type of chimeric antigen receptor-T cell therapy (CAR-T cell therapy) aimed at killing B-cell blood cancers that have returned and are no longer responding to treatment. This pioneering technology, designed and developed in the lab of Hong Qin, M.D., Ph.D., killed B-cell tumors grown in the laboratory and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/10-10mayo-clinic-prepares-to-biomanufacture-a-new-car-t-cell-therapy-for-recurring-b-cell-blood-cancers/">Mayo Clinic prepares to biomanufacture a new CAR-T cell therapy for recurring B-cell blood cancers</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="800" height="450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/CAR_T_cell_therapy_645602-010-0-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375577" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/CAR_T_cell_therapy_645602-010-0-16x9-1.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/CAR_T_cell_therapy_645602-010-0-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/CAR_T_cell_therapy_645602-010-0-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic research has developed a new type of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/car-t-cell-therapy-program/home/orc-20404317" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chimeric antigen receptor-T cell therapy (CAR-T cell therapy)</a> aimed at killing B-cell blood cancers that have returned and are no longer responding to treatment. This pioneering technology, designed and developed in the lab of <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/qin-hong-m-d-ph-d/bio-20492736" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hong Qin, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, killed B-cell tumors grown in the laboratory and tumors implanted in mouse models. The preclinical findings are published in <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Flink.springer.com%2Farticle%2F10.1007%2Fs00262-023-03537-w&amp;data=05%7C01%7CStreed.Joel%40mayo.edu%7Cf9a67a2ec1ff4916319c08dbc9825d9a%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C638325333979964304%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=CA38trFT8PWmeA%2FqNBdQLau0%2F6J%2B1wxj4Q7izGo%2FdQk%3D&amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cancer Immunology, Immunotherapy</a>.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Qin-1x1-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375584" style="object-fit:cover;width:273px;height:273px" width="273" height="273" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Qin-1x1-1.jpg 533w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Qin-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Qin-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 273px) 100vw, 273px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Hong Qin, M.D., Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"This study shows our experimental CAR-T cell therapy targets several blood cancers, specifically chronic lymphocytic leukemia," says Dr. Qin. "Currently there are six different CAR-T cell therapies approved for treatment of relapsed blood cancers. While the results are impressive, not everyone responds to this treatment. Our goal is to provide novel cell therapies shaped to each patient's individual need."</p>



<p>Dr Qin's team developed a cell therapy to target a protein known as B-cell activating factor receptor (BAFF-R) found in patients with B-cell cancers, particularly those with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/chronic-lymphocytic-leukemia/symptoms-causes/syc-20352428" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">chronic lymphocytic leukemia</a>. The BAFF-R protein is linked to tumor growth. The cell therapy under investigation allows the immune system to quash cancer and target tumors that have returned or have resisted available CAR-T cell therapies.</p>



<p>"Our team developed a method to isolate T cells and tumor cells from blood samples of three patients with chronic lymphocytic leukemia. We generated BAFF-R targeting CAR-T cells from the individual samples and then demonstrated in the lab that these genetically modified cells could kill tumors using the patients' own cells," says Dr. Qin.</p>



<p>The results of this early research lay the foundation for an important milestone: Mayo Clinic will biomanufacture this experimental CAR-T cell therapy at its campus in Florida. The research team will advance the CAR-T cells to a phase 1 clinical trial to assess the safety and define the treatment dose in humans.</p>



<p>Depending on the results of the phase 1 clinical trial, it could take 5-7 years for this therapy to become available to patients in the clinic.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic's <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</a>, in collaboration with the Mayo Clinic in Florida <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/hematology-oncology" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Division of Hematology and Medical Oncology</a>, and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/mayo-clinic-cancer-center" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Comprehensive Cancer Center</a>, supports delivering new cell therapies to patients with complex medical conditions.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Transforming cancer care</strong></h2>



<p>CAR-T cell therapy is a regenerative immunotherapy that seeks to unlock the power of the body's immune system to attack cancer. Patients' T-cells are separated from their blood, genetically modified, mass produced and then returned to their bodies to kill cancer.</p>



<p>The experimental therapies have delivered transformative results — &nbsp;in some cases putting B-cell lymphomas and leukemias into remission. However, leukemia and lymphoma tumors can change over time and become resistant to therapies, resulting in a return or relapse of cancer. 40% of patients have had cancer return within two years of undergoing CAR-T cell therapy. &nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Biomanufacturing on-site</strong></h2>



<p>This BAFF-R targeting technology is the first CAR-T cell therapy to both be developed at Mayo Clinic and biomanufactured on-site. The advantages to biomanufacturing in-house are the ability to adjust doses, individualize treatments and more quickly deliver the cells back to the patient.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Allickson-1x1-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-375581" style="width:228px;height:228px" width="228" height="228" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Allickson-1x1-1.jpg 533w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Allickson-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Allickson-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 228px) 100vw, 228px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Julie Allickson, Ph.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"The cornerstone of Mayo's biomanufacturing strategy is accelerating promising new medicines from human sources such as cells to patient care. Biomanufacturing CAR-T cells is a high priority because of the potential to provide healing for patients with few or no other solutions," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/allickson-julie-g-ph-d/bio-20523656" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Julie Allickson, Ph.D.</a>, The Michael S. and Mary Sue Shannon Director of the Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics. "We are very excited to reach this landmark of biomanufacturing the first CAR-T cell therapy developed by Mayo Clinic research." Dr. Allickson is also the Otto Bremer Trust Director, Biomanufacturing and Product Development, Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is expanding its biomanufacturing facilities on all three campuses to quickly move cell therapies from the lab to early-stage clinical trials. From there, Mayo hopes to collaborate with industry to bring new regenerative immunotherapies to routine clinical care for the benefit of patients around the world.</p>



<p>This article first published on <a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2023/10/10/biomanufacturing-a-new-car-t-cell-therapy-for-b-cell-cancers/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discovery's Edge</a>.</p>



<p>###</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/10-10mayo-clinic-prepares-to-biomanufacture-a-new-car-t-cell-therapy-for-recurring-b-cell-blood-cancers/">Mayo Clinic prepares to biomanufacture a new CAR-T cell therapy for recurring B-cell blood cancers</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/CAR_T_cell_therapy_645602-010-0-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/CAR_T_cell_therapy_645602-010-0-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[B-cell blood cancer]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[CAR-T]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Hong Qin]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Julie Allickson]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers identify link between gut bacteria and pre-clinical autoimmunity and aging in rheumatoid arthritis</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-link-between-gut-bacteria-and-pre-clinical-autoimmunity-and-aging-in-rheumatoid-arthritis/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Colette Gallagher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Veena Taneja]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gut bacteria]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rheumatoid Arthritis]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374705</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>While the bacteria in the intestine are helpful for digesting food and fighting infections, they have long been suspected to play an essential role in triggering&#160;rheumatoid arthritis. This chronic inflammatory disorder affects the joints. Mayo Clinic researchers have discovered a link between an abundance of specific gut bacteria and the triggering of an immune response [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-link-between-gut-bacteria-and-pre-clinical-autoimmunity-and-aging-in-rheumatoid-arthritis/">Mayo Clinic researchers identify link between gut bacteria and pre-clinical autoimmunity and aging in rheumatoid arthritis</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="800" height="450" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/gut-bacteria-illustration-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374709" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/gut-bacteria-illustration-16x9-1.jpg 800w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/gut-bacteria-illustration-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/gut-bacteria-illustration-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p>While the bacteria in the intestine are helpful for digesting food and fighting infections, they have long been suspected to play an essential role in triggering&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/rheumatoid-arthritis/symptoms-causes/syc-20353648" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">rheumatoid arthritis</a>. This chronic inflammatory disorder affects the joints.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers have discovered a link between an abundance of specific gut bacteria and the triggering of an immune response against a person's tissue. They also found that this happens even before the clinical symptoms of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/rheumatoid-arthritis/symptoms-causes/syc-20353648" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">rheumatoid arthritis</a>&nbsp;appear. They published their findings in a recent&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37656793/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a>&nbsp;in Science Advances.</p>



<p>"As we age, our gut bacteria and their byproducts change, which impacts our immune system," says senior author&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/taneja-veena-ph-d/bio-00027247" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Veena Taneja, Ph.D.,</a>&nbsp;a Mayo Clinic immunologist. There is a known link between imbalances in gut bacteria, aging, and rheumatoid arthritis, but it is challenging to prove this connection in humans. "This research sheds light on the complex relationship between gut microbiota and rheumatoid arthritis."</p>



<div class="wp-block-media-text is-stacked-on-mobile" style="grid-template-columns:34% auto"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="500" height="600" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/MSS_0001342127.jpg-Veena-Taneja.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374711 size-full" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/MSS_0001342127.jpg-Veena-Taneja.jpg 500w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/MSS_0001342127.jpg-Veena-Taneja-250x300.jpg 250w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p></p>



<p>Dr. Taneja explains that it is difficult to determine if gut microbiota is the cause of the disease in patients because an autoimmune response&nbsp;precedes the onset of clinical symptoms in patients by one to 10 years.</p>



<p>"The gut microbiome may hold the key to understanding healthy aging, how to avoid chronic diseases, and may lead to earlier diagnosis and treatment," says Dr Taneja.</p>
</div></div>



<p>Using a preclinical model (experimenting in the lab and not on patients), the researchers determined that the gut bacteria&nbsp;<em>Eggerthella</em>&nbsp;<em>lenta</em>&nbsp;causes an autoimmune response before the onset of the clinical symptoms of rheumatoid arthritis. In that response, the immune system produces autoantibodies that mistakenly target and attack the body's tissues and cells instead of foreign invaders, such as bacteria or viruses.</p>



<p>This same microbe also reduces amino acids such as arginine, citrulline and tryptophan metabolites to levels more similar to that of much older people, who see a gradual deterioration of their immune system due to aging.</p>



<p>In addition to their findings, researchers noted a connection between Eggerthella lenta and higher levels of these autoantibodies in female patients with rheumatoid arthritis, highlighting the importance of considering gender-specific factors in the disease.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Informing patient care</strong></h2>



<p>Rheumatoid arthritis has a genetic predisposition; however, many at risk may not know whether they are at risk for severe rheumatoid arthritis</p>



<p>This biomarker may help diagnose severe rheumatoid arthritis and assess its progression.</p>



<p>The research suggests that clinicians could use measurements of metabolic byproducts induced by these gut bacteria as a marker for the severity of the disease. In familial cases and people harboring rheumatoid arthritis-susceptible genes, the researchers say that sequencing bacteria, autoantibodies and metabolites — especially in healthy females — may help predict the likelihood of them developing rheumatoid arthritis.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Future directions</strong></h2>



<p>Researchers plan to work on how clinicians can use&nbsp;<em>Eggerthella lenta</em>&nbsp;in their diagnoses, especially in women. They will study whether targeting it using antibiotics or specific genes and metabolites can affect preclinical autoimmunity in rheumatoid arthritis. They are also exploring the link between&nbsp;<em>Eggerthella lenta</em>&nbsp;and its effect on aging.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Disclosures</strong></h2>



<p>The technology has been patented in 11,634,744 "Methods and Materials for Assessing and Treating Arthritis." The patent holders have received no royalties.</p>



<p>This story originally published on the <a href="https://individualizedmedicineblog.mayoclinic.org/2023/09/18/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-link-between-gut-bacteria-and-pre-clinical-autoimmunity-and-aging-in-rheumatoid-arthritis/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Individualized Medicine blog</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-identify-link-between-gut-bacteria-and-pre-clinical-autoimmunity-and-aging-in-rheumatoid-arthritis/">Mayo Clinic researchers identify link between gut bacteria and pre-clinical autoimmunity and aging in rheumatoid arthritis</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/gut-bacteria-illustration-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/gut-bacteria-illustration-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Veena Taneja]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[gut bacteria]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Rheumatoid Arthritis]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic researchers develop calculation to identify high-risk moderate aortic stenosis patients</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-calculation-to-identify-high-risk-moderate-aortic-stenosis-patients/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jay Furst]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2023 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[aortic stenosis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cardiovascular disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Chieh-Ju Chao]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ECG]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[echocardiogram]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[left ventricular dysfunction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Proceedings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[valve disease]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=375161</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic researchers have developed a calculation that can help identify moderate aortic stenosis patients at higher risk of dying from the condition. According to new research published in Mayo Clinic Proceedings, calculating the patient's mean arterial pressure (AugMAP) is a simple and effective way to identify those patients who may benefit [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-calculation-to-identify-high-risk-moderate-aortic-stenosis-patients/">Mayo Clinic researchers develop calculation to identify high-risk moderate aortic stenosis patients</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="682" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/stethescope-EKG-and-heart-icon-1024x682.jpg" alt="stethescope, EKG and heart icon" class="wp-image-350851" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/stethescope-EKG-and-heart-icon-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/stethescope-EKG-and-heart-icon-300x200.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/stethescope-EKG-and-heart-icon-768x512.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/stethescope-EKG-and-heart-icon-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/stethescope-EKG-and-heart-icon.jpg 1688w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> researchers have developed a calculation that can help identify moderate <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/aortic-stenosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20353139?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">aortic stenosis</a> patients at higher risk of dying from the condition. <a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.mayoclinicproceedings.org%2Fpb-assets%2FHealth%2520Advance%2Fjournals%2Fjmcp%2FJMCP4100.pdf&amp;data=05%7C01%7CFurst.Justin%40mayo.edu%7C5d16a2468f2040e9ee1408dbbf71d152%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C638314267939472891%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=o7lxUohCUOgikuv0diORDn%2FyuQEaV51tO4EzShzDw6o%3D&amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">According to new research</a> published in Mayo Clinic Proceedings, calculating the patient's mean arterial pressure (AugMAP) is a simple and effective way to identify those patients who may benefit from more aggressive treatment strategies.</p>



<p>"Physiologically, AugMAP can be considered a marker of global left ventricular contractile function," says Chieh-Ju Chao, M.D., senior associate consultant in the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/cardiovascular-medicine/home/orc-20121930?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Department of Cardiovascular Medicine</a> and the study's first author. "AugMAP is easily calculated from the patient's blood pressure and mean aortic gradient, and we found that low AugMAP is associated with higher mortality in all moderate aortic stenosis patient subgroups."</p>



<p>Aortic stenosis is one of the most common cardiac valvular abnormalities, affecting about 5% of people older than 65 years. For most patients with moderate aortic stenosis, clinical guidelines call only for periodic monitoring with echocardiography, a test that uses sound waves to show how blood moves through the heart. However, growing evidence shows that patients with moderate aortic stenosis have poor longer-term survival rates and could benefit from earlier intervention.</p>



<p>The study looked at 4,563 patients with moderate aortic stenosis who were treated at Mayo Clinic from January 2010 through December 2020. The findings indicate that AugMAP is a better prognostic tool compared to other available measures and can detect early-stage left ventricular dysfunction before a decrease in left ventricular ejection fraction is observed. "With this information, we can identify patients at higher risk of mortality with current management strategies and initiate discussion about other treatment strategies," says Dr. Chao.</p>



<p>"Moderate aortic stenosis does carry a higher risk of morbidity and mortality compared to the general population based on several prior studies," says senior author <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/arsanjani-reza-m-d/bio-20163932?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Reza Arsanjani, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist.&nbsp;"Current guidelines recommend active surveillance although earlier intervention might benefit select patients.&nbsp;Our study could potentially identify high-risk individuals who might benefit from earlier intervention."</p>



<p>The authors say future studies should consider whether patients with lower AugMAP can benefit from earlier intervention rather than periodic monitoring.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic Proceedings</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</a> is a monthly, peer-reviewed journal that publishes original articles and reviews on clinical and laboratory medicine, clinical research, basic science research and clinical epidemiology. The journal, sponsored by Mayo Foundation for Medical Education and Research as part of its commitment to physician education, has been published for 97 years and has a circulation of 127,000.</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong>&nbsp;<br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and to providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Jay Furst, Mayo Clinic Education Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-researchers-develop-calculation-to-identify-high-risk-moderate-aortic-stenosis-patients/">Mayo Clinic researchers develop calculation to identify high-risk moderate aortic stenosis patients</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/stethescope-EKG-heart-icon1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/stethescope-EKG-heart-icon-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[aortic stenosis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cardiovascular disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Chieh-Ju Chao]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[ECG]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[echocardiogram]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[left ventricular dysfunction]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Proceedings]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[valve disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Real-world study confirms reliability of tool assessing 10-year risk prediction of heart disease</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/10-3-real-world-study-confirms-reliability-of-tool-assessing-10-year-risk-prediction-of-heart-disease/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Terri Malloy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 14:36:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rochester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Alzheimer's disease research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[atherosclerosis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cardiovascular disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Francisco López-Jiménez]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Jose Medina-Inojosa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[heart attack]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[statins]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stroke]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=373992</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A recent study based on real-world community patient data confirms the effectiveness of the Pooled Cohort Equation (PCE), developed by the American Heart Association and the American College of Cardiology in 2013. The PCE is used to estimate a person's 10-year risk of developing clogged arteries, also known as atherosclerosis, and guide [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/10-3-real-world-study-confirms-reliability-of-tool-assessing-10-year-risk-prediction-of-heart-disease/">Real-world study confirms reliability of tool assessing 10-year risk prediction of heart disease</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A recent study based on real-world community patient data confirms the effectiveness of the Pooled Cohort Equation (PCE), developed by the American Heart Association and the American College of Cardiology in 2013. The PCE is used to estimate a person's 10-year risk of developing clogged arteries, also known as <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/arteriosclerosis-atherosclerosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20350569" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">atherosclerosis</a>, and guide heart attack and stroke prevention efforts. Study findings are published in the <a href="https://www.jacc.org/doi/10.1016/j.jacc.2023.07.018" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Journal of the American College of Cardiology</a>.</p>



<p>The new study highlights to patients and clinicians the continued reliability and effectiveness of the PCE as a tool for assessing cardiovascular risk, regardless of statin use to lower cholesterol.</p>



<p>The PCE serves as a shared decision-making tool for a clinician and patient to evaluate their current status in preventing atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease. The calculator considers input in the categories of gender, age, race, total cholesterol, HDL cholesterol, systolic blood pressure, treatment for high blood pressure, diabetes status, and smoking status.</p>



<p>Using retrospective data from more than 30,000 patients enrolled in the <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/departments-divisions/quantitative-health-sciences/divisions/epidemiology/research/rochester-epidemiology-project" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Rochester Epidemiology Project</a>, Mayo Clinic researchers found the PCE performed well at the community level and with relative accuracy between sexes, across age groups and race. The use of statin medications to lower cholesterol did not change the value of the predictions, even though the PCE was developed before statins became widely available. The tool also retained its accuracy when using measurement factors, such as blood pressure, age and cholesterol levels, that were outside the original risk profile range.</p>



<p>"We have seen the excellent performance of the Pooled Cohort Equation over the years in clinical practice," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/lopez-jimenez-francisco-m-d-m-b-a/bio-00028001" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Francisco Lopez-Jimenez, M.D.</a>, a cardiologist at Mayo Clinic and senior author of the study. "The study shows that this tool is reliable, not only in light of new cholesterol-lowering drugs, but for patients who previously were not evaluated with the PCE because maybe their blood pressure was higher or lower than the standards, or they did not fit the age profile, for example. By including patients with values outside the accepted range, I think we can calculate the risk for heart attacks in another 20% to 25% of patients, which is not small."<a id="_msocom_1"></a></p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/exjaIFN2nwY" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Francisco Lopez-Jimenez and Dr. Jose Medina-Inojosa discuss the assessment tool study</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeexjaIFN2nwY"  title="Still the one: Assessment tool for 10-year risk prediction of heart disease holds true" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/exjaIFN2nwY?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Sound bites are available in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Name super/CG: Francisco Lopez-Jimenez</strong>,<strong> M.D./Cardiology/Mayo Clinic</strong> and <strong>Jose Medina-Inojosa, M.D./Epidemiology/Mayo Clinic. </strong></p>



<p>Lifestyle modification is essentially the mainstay of cardiovascular disease prevention, and clinicians talk with patients about what to focus on to prevent the serious consequences of a heart attack or stroke.</p>



<p>"Beyond wellness questions about exercise, diet, stress level and good sleep, the PCE guides the conversation to decide if it's time to talk about starting treatment for high cholesterol or hypertension. With this study, we wanted to provide confidence that the Pooled Cohort Equation still performs well at the community level, and our data supports that," says Jose Medina-Inojosa, M.D., a research scientist at Mayo Clinic and first author of the study. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related post:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-who-benefits-from-taking-statins/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Who benefits from taking statins?</a></li>
</ul>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Terri Malloy, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/10-3-real-world-study-confirms-reliability-of-tool-assessing-10-year-risk-prediction-of-heart-disease/">Real-world study confirms reliability of tool assessing 10-year risk prediction of heart disease</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/11/3D-illustration-of-the-heart-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/11/3D-illustration-of-the-heart-16X9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Alzheimer's disease research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[atherosclerosis]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[cardiovascular disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Francisco López-Jiménez]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Jose Medina-Inojosa]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Heart]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[heart attack]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Heart Disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[statins]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Stroke]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss><!-- Static page delivered by HubScale -->