<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Transplant - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/transplant/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/transplant/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 21:09:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>No Place Like Home: David Elder&#8217;s Post-Transplant Care a &#8216;Blessing&#8217;</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/no-place-like-home-david-elders-post-transplant-care-a-blessing/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Osiadacz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Elder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Michael Maniaci]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Patricia Chipi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multiple Myeloma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=378094</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>When David Elder’s back started to hurt in the fall of 2022, he thought his recurrent spasms had returned. But when medication didn’t help like before, his doctor sent him to the ER – and soon after, he was diagnosed with multiple myeloma, a treatable but incurable form of cancer that had caused several painful [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/no-place-like-home-david-elders-post-transplant-care-a-blessing/">No Place Like Home: David Elder&#8217;s Post-Transplant Care a &#8216;Blessing&#8217;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="578" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/David_Elder-16x9-1-1024x578.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-378095" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/David_Elder-16x9-1-1024x578.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/David_Elder-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/David_Elder-16x9-1-768x434.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/David_Elder-16x9-1.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>When David Elder’s back started to hurt in the fall of 2022, he thought his recurrent spasms had returned. But when medication didn’t help like before, his doctor sent him to the ER – and soon after, he was diagnosed with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/multiple-myeloma/symptoms-causes/syc-20353378" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">multiple myeloma</a>, a treatable but incurable form of cancer that had caused several painful breaks in his spine.</p>



<p>“It just hit us out of nowhere,” he says of the diagnosis. “It was shocking.”</p>



<p>Five months earlier, in May, his routine bloodwork had come back normal, says Marcia, his wife of 38 years.</p>



<p>By October, David was fighting for his life.</p>



<p>Twenty years earlier, he had <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/kidney-transplant/about/pac-20384777" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">donated a kidney</a> to his cousin, and now cancer was attacking the remaining kidney, rendering him vulnerable.</p>



<p>David spent nine days at Baptist Hospital South in Jacksonville, Fla., where they rescued his kidney, but this triumph marked the beginning of his journey rather than the end.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>‘Mayo is right here’</strong></h2>



<p>The Elders live in St. Augustine, a northeast Florida community where David has been a worship pastor at Anastasia Baptist Church for 18 years. St. Augustine is about a half hour's drive from <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida.</a></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="300" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-300x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377560" style="object-fit:cover;width:339px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-2048x2048.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure></div>


<p>“It took a little bit of a mind adjustment to realize, OK, this is cancer, and it's a serious type of cancer. But, you know, Mayo is right here, and people move from other states to be here,” David says. “It was a no-brainer to just come here and get the process started.”</p>



<p>The months to come would include more doctor visits, and in February David received a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bone-marrow-transplant/about/pac-20384854" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">transplant using his own bone marrow</a> at Mayo Clinic in Florida.</p>



<p>Following surgery, he was told that he was a good candidate for <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/hospital-at-home/sections/overview/ovc-20551797" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic’s Advanced Care at Home program</a>, which would allow him to heal at home, with Marcia by his side and a clinician just a video call away, day or night.</p>



<p>The Elders jumped at the chance.</p>



<p>Studies have shown that 90 percent of patients who receive care through Advanced Care at Home rate their satisfaction with the program as five out of five. In addition, compared to those who received hospital care, home healthcare patients had a 50 percent decrease in readmissions.</p>



<p>“The only time I left him was during the transplant when they wouldn’t let me in the room,” says Marcia, who provided David’s round-the-clock care at home. “What a blessing it was to be in our house.”</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>No place like home</strong></h2>



<p>With Advanced Care at Home, an initiative of <a href="https://www.mayoclinicplatform.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Platform</a>, patients like David can receive high-acuity care at home, thanks to modern technology and a home-services care team that visits in person at least twice daily and is available 24/7.</p>



<p>Advanced Care at Home teams collaborate to provide at-home care to patients in Jacksonville, Fla., Phoenix, Ariz., and northwest Wisconsin.</p>



<p>A patient’s physician decides if they could benefit from the program with the aid of two artificial intelligence-based algorithms that provide a “fit score” derived from historical home hospital admissions data.</p>



<p>Just a few hours after David’s transplant, he and Marcia learned that he was a candidate for the program. By 6:30 p.m. that same evening, they were back home. And ten minutes after they got there, the medical transport team arrived with all the supplies they needed.</p>



<p>David had been in the hospital for fewer than three days.</p>



<p>At home David could have familiar foods and drinks, watch his favorite channels, and read his own magazines and books. With more furniture at home than in the hospital, he could find a position that didn’t hurt his back as much during his waking hours. And at night, he got more and better-quality sleep without the constant beeping and frequent interruptions common in hospitals.</p>



<p>“It's not infrequent that patients tell me that they didn’t get a good night of sleep in the hospital, or that it’s triggered their stress and anxiety, or it’s made their pain worse, or that the bed was uncomfortable,” says Patricia Chipi, M.D., a hospital medicine physician at Mayo Clinic in Florida who works with Advanced Care at Home.</p>



<p>“With Advanced Care at Home, those concerns are much less. In fact, patients are typically saying, ‘I slept great last night, and I'm starting to feel so much better,’” Dr. Chipi says.</p>



<p>Being near loved ones, too, provides a healing balm for patients at home.</p>



<p>David and Marcia’s two sons and their families are based in Florida and were able to visit during his recovery. When they came over, David would position his chair with a clear line of sight to the toy corner, where their five grandkids would gather to play.</p>



<p>For Marcia, playing an active role in her husband’s daily care was a challenge that provided comfort, too.</p>



<p>“It’s so much better. … At home, there is something I can do, versus at the hospital, where I just have to sit and watch other people do,” she says.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Something old, something new</strong></h2>



<p>In the Mayo Clinic tradition, home healthcare harks back to the household visits that the Mayo brothers provided to patients in the past.</p>



<p>“It's a different way of getting better. It reflects on what we did 100 years ago, when people would heal at home,” says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/maniaci-michael-j-m-d/bio-20054934" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Michael Maniaci, M.D.</a>, chief clinical officer of Advanced Care at Home at Mayo Clinic in Florida.</p>



<p>While it is not a new concept, home-based care is gaining momentum today because innovative technologies are available to help clinicians provide safe, high-quality, hospital-level treatment for complex and acute cases outside the hospital.</p>



<p>“The secret sauce of Advanced Care at Home is the capability to take care of the sickest patients and provide safety and quality while not replicating the hospital experience,” Dr. Maniaci says. “There is something magical about being at home.”</p>



<p>Under the direction of Mayo Clinic physicians, Advanced Care at Home provides comprehensive services, including infusions, skilled nursing, medications, laboratory and imaging services, behavioral health, and rehabilitation services from a network of paramedics, nurses, and other support team members who ensure that the needs of the patient come first.</p>



<p>Advanced Care at Home also gives clinicians a unique view into patients’ lives, which provides valuable information for their care.</p>



<p>“When <a>you're</a> in their home, they feel much more comfortable. You get to see the dynamic between family members, which is helpful,” says physician assistant Jessica Denton, who was part of David’s care team. “I think you get a more honest patient this way.”</p>



<p>Since its launch in 2021, the program has provided care to over 700 Mayo Clinic patients as part of a strategic relationship with Medically Home, a Boston-based technology company that has helped provide care to more than 26,000 people across the U.S.</p>



<p>As the program’s patient numbers continue to grow, word is getting out — and patients are starting to ask whether healing at home is for them.</p>



<p>“Patients are really excited about it. Especially those that have been in and out of the hospital. Now that we've had the program in place for a few years, patients are asking about it more often. They're aware of the program, and they want to be a part of it. … I think that's a great thing for the patient,” says Dr. Chippi.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Looking ahead</strong></h2>



<p>Positive outcomes such as these point to a bright future for home-based healing.</p>



<p>“Virtual care and hybrid care are a large part of the future of medicine,” says Dr. Maniaci.</p>



<p>David Elder takes a positive view of the future, too. He will officially retire in December, and he and Marcia are currently enjoying spending time with their sixth grandchild, born in September.</p>



<p>His advice for anyone who receives a diagnosis like his?</p>



<p>“I would ask them to think about the life that is still yet to come. There could be years and years of it,” he says. “Do not be so taken by the cancer that it takes the life out of you before it takes the life from you.”</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/no-place-like-home-david-elders-post-transplant-care-a-blessing/">No Place Like Home: David Elder&#8217;s Post-Transplant Care a &#8216;Blessing&#8217;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/David_Elder-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/David_Elder-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[David Elder]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Michael Maniaci]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Patricia Chipi]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Multiple Myeloma]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: How innovation is transforming heart transplants</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-innovation-is-transforming-heart-transplants/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sonya Goins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2023 15:31:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[heart transplantation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[innovation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377577</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic doctors are using innovation to improve the lives of people who suffer from congestive heart failure and other chronic heart conditions. The Organ Care System, also known as "heart in a box,” is potentially helping to expand the donor pool, which is crucial, considering that more than 4,000 people in the U.S. are [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-innovation-is-transforming-heart-transplants/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How innovation is transforming heart transplants</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Mayo Clinic doctors are using innovation to improve the lives of people who suffer from congestive heart failure and other chronic heart conditions. The Organ Care System, also known as "heart in a box,” is potentially helping to expand the donor pool, which is crucial, considering that more than 4,000 people in the U.S. are waiting for a new heart. That’s according to the organization <a href="https://donatelife.net/donation/organs/heart-donation/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Donate Life America.</a></p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/lemond-lisa-m-m-d/bio-20308773" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Lisa LeMond</a>, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist, explains how the heart perfusion system works.</p>



<p><a href="https://youtu.be/gD-MmdNumI8" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</strong></a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe id="videoidhttpsyoutubegDMmdNumI8"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute -  How innovation is transforming heart transplants" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gD-MmdNumI8?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (1:07) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/MCM-Heart-transplants.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script.</a></strong></p>



<p>Every single hour, minute and second counts as the transplant team races against the clock to provide organ recipients with a lifesaving gift.</p>



<p>"In this country, there are not enough hearts to meet the needs of all of the patients who could potentially qualify for a heart transplant," says Dr. LeMond.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377570" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-2048x1151.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Technology is improving methods of preserving and transporting donor hearts</h3>



<p>Innovation is improving transplant surgeries. Typically, donor hearts are retrieved from a person who is declared brain-dead but whose heart is still beating. With the relatively new system, heart in a box, doctors can revive the donated heart by perfusing the organ with warm, oxygenated blood.</p>



<p>"We now have new technology that allows us to place the donor hearts into a special machine which delivers blood and controls the temperature to the heart to allow it to start beating," explains Dr. LeMond.</p>



<p>The perfusion system can preserve the donated heart for up to 12 hours. Before this technology, the donor heart would be on ice in a cooler to preserve it during transport, and doctors only had about four hours to get the heart to the recipient. So far this year (as of Nov. 20), the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/home/orc-20203891" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Transplant Center </a>has performed 156 heart transplants across all Mayo Clinic campuses.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Heart transplants are performed in patients with:</h3>



<ul>
<li>A weakening of the heart muscle (cardiomyopathy).</li>



<li>Coronary artery disease.</li>



<li>Heart valve disease.</li>



<li>Congenital heart defect.</li>
</ul>



<p></p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-timeline-of-transplant-innovation/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">A timeline of transplant innovation</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/organ-transplant-innovation-helping-more-people-get-the-gift-of-life/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Organ Transplant Innovation: Helping more people get the gift of life</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/11-16-four-ways-organ-transplants-are-being-transformed-to-save-more-lives/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Four ways organ transplants are being transformed to save more lives</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/11-16-at-81-woman-is-among-worlds-longest-surviving-transplant-recipients/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">At 81, woman is among world’s longest-surviving transplant recipients</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-how-innovation-is-transforming-heart-transplants/">Mayo Clinic Minute: How innovation is transforming heart transplants</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Heart-in-a-box-4-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Heart-in-a-box-2-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[heart transplantation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[innovation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mcthumb >https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Heart-in-a-box-16-x-9-150x150.jpg</mayoclinic:mcthumb >	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Celebrating transplant: A new life of song and service</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/celebrating-transplant-a-new-life-of-song-and-service/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tia R. Ford]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Bradshaw]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lung transplant]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377896</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Editor's note: The following was written and submitted by David Bradshaw. He shares his journey from COVID, to transplant to gratitude for a second wind, including the part Mayo played in his journey. Imagine sailing through life for 68 years — the picture of good health — without major illness, disease or hospital visits. That [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/celebrating-transplant-a-new-life-of-song-and-service/">Celebrating transplant: A new life of song and service</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw316x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377897" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw316x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw316x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw316x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw316x9.jpg 1512w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong><em>Editor's note: The following was written and submitted by David Bradshaw</em></strong>. <strong><em>He shares his journey from COVID, to transplant to gratitude for a second wind, including the part Mayo played in his journey.</em></strong></p>



<p>Imagine sailing through life for 68 years — the picture of good health — without major illness, disease or hospital visits. That was my life ... until <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/coronavirus/symptoms-causes/syc-20479963" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">COVID-19</a> hit me in January 2021. What seemed like a bad case of flu morphed into <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pulmonary-fibrosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20353690" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pulmonary fibrosis</a> lung disease — a sure death sentence, I thought, within two to four years.</p>



<p>My breathing became increasingly difficult. I required an oxygen tank with any exertion at all, even a short walk to the mailbox. I went from swimming 500 meters three times a week to a couch potato overnight. For months, I desperately hoped my case of COVID-19 might improve.</p>



<p>As I struggled to make sense of this new reality, I met with a local pulmonologist in Sarasota, Florida, who promptly referred me to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Jacksonville, Florida</a>. Within a week, I had hope. Mayo reached out with the news that I might be a candidate for a double-lung transplant. Four weeks later, I drove 220 miles to begin the arduous transplant approval process.</p>



<p>Upon arrival, I marveled at Mayo's ultramodern campus and relaxing interiors. Even more refreshing was the patient-centered culture that pervades the entire Mayo team — from front door valets to the nurses, doctors and surgeons — like a finely tuned engine hitting on all cylinders. I was able to stay at the Gabriel House of Care on campus, featured in the 2020 movie "2 Hearts," which is available to accommodate patients and families before, during and after a transplant.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The royal treatment and miracles</strong><strong></strong></h2>



<p>I spent 14 days in Jacksonville. My schedule was filled with lots of testing to determine if I was healthy enough for a transplant. It may be hard to imagine, but there was little or no waiting time for more than 40 appointments! I felt like I was treated like royalty during this time. As someone who loves music and creating, this model of efficiency later inspired me so much that I ended up writing and recording a song, "<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nbKAkWgs5EE" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">The Mayo Royal Treatment<em>.</em></a>"</p>



<p>All of the pre-transplant care at Mayo Clinic was great, especially <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/narula-tathagat-m-b-b-s-m-d/bio-20305908" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. (Tathagat) Narula</a> who convinced me that a transplant was my only viable option. After all the testing at Mayo, I was put on the UNOS list at both Mayo Clinic and Tampa General, due to its closer proximity to Sarasota.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="587" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw2-1024x587.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377901" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw2-1024x587.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw2-300x172.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw2-768x440.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw2.jpg 1075w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>On April 12, 2022, I received the OK to be placed on the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/lung-transplant/about/pac-20384754" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">transplant</a> list, although I was told it would likely take months, a year or even longer to find my new lungs. Yet, within days, the miracles began.</p>



<p>Miracle 1: Just four days after being put on the transplant list, I received a phone call at 10 p.m. requesting I immediately come to the hospital (Tampa General Hospital) for transplant surgery. A matching set of lungs had been found! The urgency of taking this life-changing step of faith confronted me head-on as I, of course, said, "Yes!"</p>



<p>Miracle 2: After the surgery, my surgeon explained the various difficulties he had encountered. The normal time for this remarkable procedure is six to eight hours, but in my case, it lasted for 18 hours. During the surgery, I had flatlined for almost three minutes! Thankfully, I was resuscitated in time, to my family's relief.</p>



<p>Asked about what I had experienced during those three minutes, I explained that I was aware of a change of consciousness, despite the anesthesia, yet felt no fear. I experienced a unique sense of several things, including love, peace and safety. When my surgeon stopped by the next day, I asked him, "Did I die?" His response was classic, "Not on my watch!" He truly is my hero!</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="226" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw5-226x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377902" style="width:243px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw5-226x300.jpg 226w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw5-771x1024.jpg 771w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw5-768x1020.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw5.jpg 1008w" sizes="(max-width: 226px) 100vw, 226px" /></figure></div>


<p>Within days, I began exercising my new heaven-sent lungs. Thanks to the prodding of my tough-loving post-transplant team, I was soon back to eating, drinking normally and up on my feet using a walker. What joy to finally be able to breathe again without supplemental oxygen! I was released from the hospital 18 days later on June 4, 2022.</p>



<p>Ever since, I have followed the doctor's strict orders regarding medications, diet and exercise to ensure that these precious new lungs last as long as possible. I wrote the donor family a thank-you letter expressing my gratefulness. And, of course, being impressed by the selfless gift, I recorded them a song, "<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1y1j9OmfHXo" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">How Can I Say Thanks?</a>"</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Thanksgiving every day!</strong></h2>



<p>The road to recovery over the past 18 months has been long but amazing. I don’t know how I can ever express my thanks to everyone who helped me — all the doctors, nurses, technicians, assistants, as well as my family, friends and, most of all, my donor.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="225" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw1-225x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377899" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw1-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw1.jpg 480w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /></figure></div>


<p>Today I'm walking 2–4 miles a day, swimming laps again and biking. To celebrate my one-year anniversary, I had a custom T-shirt made as a visible expression of my gratitude.</p>



<p>As a retired writer, I wrote my own autobiography and now feel called to teach a writing class at a local Sarasota college. I also serve as a hospice volunteer and prison minister.</p>



<p>In between all my <em>activities</em>, I love spending time with my family, which includes four daughters, 10 grandchildren and four great-grandchildren — all born in the last year!</p>



<p>Following my transplant, I also began volunteering as a <a href="https://unos.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">United Network for Organ Sharing</a> ambassador to speak about the ever-growing need for new organ donors. Did you know that you can be a living organ donor? Many people do not realize this is an option.</p>



<p>During this season of Thanksgiving, my enthusiasm for life overflows. I am so thankful to Mayo Clinic that I've been given a "second wind!" Because Mayo serves, it leads. Serving is my way of giving thanks.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/celebrating-transplant-a-new-life-of-song-and-service/">Celebrating transplant: A new life of song and service</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw31x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/DBradshaw316x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[David Bradshaw]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[lung transplant]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>A timeline of transplant innovation</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-timeline-of-transplant-innovation/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Heather Carlson Kehren]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2023 15:13:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant innovation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377855</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-timeline-of-transplant-innovation/">A timeline of transplant innovation</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="2667" height="12867" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Timeline-FINAL-640x3088-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377854" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Timeline-FINAL-640x3088-1.jpg 2667w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Timeline-FINAL-640x3088-1-62x300.jpg 62w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Timeline-FINAL-640x3088-1-212x1024.jpg 212w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Timeline-FINAL-640x3088-1-768x3705.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 2667px) 100vw, 2667px" /></figure></div><p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-timeline-of-transplant-innovation/">A timeline of transplant innovation</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Transplant innovation]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Organ Transplant Innovation: Helping more people get the gift of life</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/organ-transplant-innovation-helping-more-people-get-the-gift-of-life/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2023 17:31:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic News Network Video Pkg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christopher Leslie]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Kunam Reddy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kidney Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Olivia Leslie]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377793</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic is celebrating 60 years of helping patients receive the gift of life through organ transplants. Over the past six decades, Mayo Clinic has remained at the forefront of research and cutting-edge innovation which is revolutionizing the world of organ transplant. Tens of thousands of people are on organ transplant waiting lists in the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/organ-transplant-innovation-helping-more-people-get-the-gift-of-life/">Organ Transplant Innovation: Helping more people get the gift of life</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris_and_daughter_11-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377809" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris_and_daughter_11-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris_and_daughter_11-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris_and_daughter_11-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris_and_daughter_11-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris_and_daughter_11.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Christopher Leslie and his daughter, Olivia, play at a park</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>Mayo Clinic is celebrating 60 years of helping patients receive the gift of life through organ transplants. Over the past six decades, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/home/orc-20203891" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> has remained at the forefront of research and cutting-edge innovation which is revolutionizing the world of organ transplant.</p>



<p>Tens of thousands of people are on organ transplant waiting lists in the US. The wait can take years. </p>



<p>There is hope.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-300x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377560" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-2048x2048.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure></div>


<p>Innovation is transforming how organ transplants are performed, helping more people get the lifesaving organs they need. A special kidney perfusion pump can help preserve a donor organ, often giving transplant teams a critical edge in the race against the clock.</p>



<p>The pump helped Christopher Leslie get his new kidney. Now he's got his health back and is fulfilling his dream of teaching his daughter about their Native American heritage.</p>



<p></p>



<p><a href="https://youtu.be/jRnuuOe82f4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Watch: Dad teaching daughter about their Native American history following lifesaving organ transplant</strong></a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidjRnuuOe82f4"  title="Organ Transplant Innovation: Helping more people get the gift of life." width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jRnuuOe82f4?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video is in the downloads at the end of this post (2:15).</strong> <strong>Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network."  Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/NATIVE-AMERICAN-TRANSPLANT-FINAL-VIDEO-SCRIPT.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script.</a></strong></p>



<p>Christopher remembers the day five years ago when doctors diagnosed him with <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-surgeons-perform-first-robotic-assisted-kidney-transplant-in-minnesota/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">kidney failure</a>. "I was freaking out because I was planning to join the military or do something else with my life," said Christopher. "I had an eight-month-old at the time, and so I was worried about that."</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-with-Baby-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377864" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-with-Baby-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-with-Baby-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-with-Baby-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-with-Baby-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-with-Baby.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Doctors told Christopher he would need a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/kidney-transplant/about/pac-20384777" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">kidney transplant</a>. While waiting for a donor kidney, he had to begin dialysis. </p>



<p>What gave Christopher, a single father, the strength to fight for his life? </p>



<p>"My daughter," said Christopher pausing between words. "I'm trying not to cry, I'm sorry. I've seen people die on dialysis. And I thought, you know, that could be me. I never wanted that for my kids."</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-and-daughter-3-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377811" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-and-daughter-3-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-and-daughter-3-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-and-daughter-3-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-and-daughter-3-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-and-daughter-3.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Christopher and his daughter, Olivia, enjoying time together after his kidney transplant</strong></figcaption></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Organ transplant - Every second matters</h3>



<p>There are approximately 100,000 in the US on the kidney transplant waiting list. The wait can take years. The minute an organ becomes available, it is a race against the clock to get the donor organ to the recipient as quickly as possible. Each second the donor organ is outside the body, it can start to break down. </p>



<p>Mayo Clinic transplant surgeon <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/reddy-kunam-s-m-b-b-s-m-d/bio-20054489" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Kunam Reddy</a> says he aims to do a kidney transplant within 24 hours of the organ becoming available. In Christopher's case, unexpected delays in the organ allocation process meant the transplant team would need more time. Doctors placed the donor kidney on a special pump that uses hypothermic perfusion technology, an advanced cold pulsatile organ perfusion system. The system helps maintain the viability and function of the organ between the point of retrieval from the donor and transplant into the recipient.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="718" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Kidney-transporter-1024x718.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377814" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Kidney-transporter-1024x718.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Kidney-transporter-300x210.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Kidney-transporter-768x539.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Kidney-transporter-1536x1077.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Kidney-transporter-2048x1437.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>The pump holding Christopher's kidney prior to transplant using hypothermic perfusion technology</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>Christopher's kidney was held on the pump for nearly 45 hours, one of the longest times Dr. Reddy says he has seen in 30 years. Christopher's transplant was declared a complete success. "He had primary (kidney) function working right away," said Dr. Reddy. "He didn't have to have dialysis at all post-transplant."</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Christopher-and-Dr.-Reddy-768x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377816" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Christopher-and-Dr.-Reddy-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Christopher-and-Dr.-Reddy-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Christopher-and-Dr.-Reddy-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Christopher-and-Dr.-Reddy-1536x2048.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Christopher and his Mayo Clinic transplant surgeon, Dr. Kunam Reddy</strong></figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Getting warmer</h2>



<p>One of the latest advances in organ perfusion technology is known as normothermic perfusion. Instead of cold storage, normothermic perfusion uses a warm system. It is not yet being used for kidneys, but it is being used in liver and cardiac transplant. The technology is commonly referred to as "liver-in-a-box" and "heart-in-a box." This is where the donated organ is kept at a warmer temperature that mimics the human body. The organ is also kept alive while being pumped with nutrient-rich blood. This helps minimize organ tissue breakdown, and allows doctors to monitor the organ at all times during transport.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/IMG_5767-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377870" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/IMG_5767-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/IMG_5767-300x225.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/IMG_5767-768x576.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/IMG_5767-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/IMG_5767-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Liver-in-box in an operating room at Mayo Clinic in Arizona being kept warm with normothermic perfusion technology (2023)</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="677" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Jeff-and-Trish-1-677x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377818" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Jeff-and-Trish-1-677x1024.jpg 677w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Jeff-and-Trish-1-198x300.jpg 198w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Jeff-and-Trish-1-768x1162.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Jeff-and-Trish-1-1015x1536.jpg 1015w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Jeff-and-Trish-1.jpg 1114w" sizes="(max-width: 677px) 100vw, 677px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Jeff and Trish Robinson celebrating their 50th wedding anniversary after he successfully became Arizona's first heart-in-a-box transplant recipient (2022)</strong></figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Gratitude, Goodwill, and Generosity</h2>



<p>"So many advances have been made over the past many years. All of the work, what we do, the generosity of the donors, their families, the gift of life, the goodwill and the generosity, that's what makes this a very exciting field for me," said Dr. Reddy.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p>"Seeing both sides, the donor family, how gratified they are in finding something meaningful out of a hopeless situation. Then seeing recipients who have been on their deathbed and suffering, on dialysis for many years, having a new shot at life, it is amazing to be in this field and arrive where we are today."</p><cite>Kumar Reddy, M.D.<br>Mayo Clinic transplant surgeon</cite></blockquote></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-and-daughter-5-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377812" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-and-daughter-5-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-and-daughter-5-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-and-daughter-5-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-and-daughter-5-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-and-daughter-5.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Christopher reading a book to his daughter about their Native American heritage</strong> <strong>after his successful transplant</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>These days Christopher is living out his dreams, like teaching his daughter about their Native American history. Recently the two paid a visit to the Salt River Pima-Maricopa Indian Community's Huhugam Ki Museum in Phoenix, which honors the tribe's cultural heritage. </p>



<p>Christopher said he is grateful to be alive, unlike many of his ancestors.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p>"I'm lucky I was born during a day and age when so much technology is available. Most of our people died from disease and there are not many of us left. Our culture is declining and I want to keep that alive. To the person who gave me this kidney, and their family, thank you for saving my life."</p><cite>Christopher leslie, kidney transplant recipient</cite></blockquote></figure>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related posts:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-barriers-helping-native-americans-in-need-get-the-gift-of-life/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Breaking barriers: Helping Native Americans in need get the gift of life</strong></a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-innovation-new-heart-in-a-box-technology-provides-gift-of-life-to-arizona-man-as-couple-prepares-to-celebrate-50-year-anniversary/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Heart Transplant Innovation: New ‘heart in a box’ technology provides gift of life to Arizona man, as couple prepares to celebrate 50-year anniversary</strong></a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/the-silent-liver-disease-experts-warn-is-on-the-rise-among-hispanics-and-children/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>The silent liver disease experts warn is on the rise among Hispanics and children</strong></a></li>
</ul>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/organ-transplant-innovation-helping-more-people-get-the-gift-of-life/">Organ Transplant Innovation: Helping more people get the gift of life</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Christopher-and-Dr-Reddy-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-and-daughter-3.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Christopher Leslie]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Kunam Reddy]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Kidney Transplant]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Olivia Leslie]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mcthumb >https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Chris-and-daughter-3-150x150.jpg</mayoclinic:mcthumb >	</item>
		<item>
		<title>At 81, woman is among world&#8217;s longest-surviving transplant recipients</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/11-16-at-81-woman-is-among-worlds-longest-surviving-transplant-recipients/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Barber Lindquist]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Charlotte Markle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Burcin Taner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Julie Heimbach]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Thomas Schwab]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kidney Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant innovation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377436</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo recognizes 60 years of transplant innovation Charlotte Markle, 81, is among the world's longest-surviving kidney transplant recipients. Her transplant at Mayo Clinic was over 57 years ago on March 2, 1966. It followed Mayo Clinic's first kidney transplant on Nov. 25, 1963, which was Mayo's first solid organ transplant of any kind. Charlotte is [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/11-16-at-81-woman-is-among-worlds-longest-surviving-transplant-recipients/">At 81, woman is among world&#8217;s longest-surviving transplant recipients</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Charlotte_and_David_Markle_wedding_picture16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Charlotte Markle is among world's longest-surviving transplant recipients. " class="wp-image-377548" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Charlotte_and_David_Markle_wedding_picture16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Charlotte_and_David_Markle_wedding_picture16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Charlotte_and_David_Markle_wedding_picture16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Charlotte_and_David_Markle_wedding_picture16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Charlotte_and_David_Markle_wedding_picture16x9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Charlotte and David Markle in 1965</figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><em><strong>Mayo recognizes 60 years of transplant innovation</strong></em></h2>



<p>Charlotte Markle, 81, is among the world's longest-surviving <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/kidney-transplant/about/pac-20384777" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">kidney transplant</a> recipients. Her transplant at Mayo Clinic was over 57 years ago on March 2, 1966.</p>



<p>It followed Mayo Clinic's first kidney transplant on Nov. 25, 1963, which was Mayo's first solid organ transplant of any kind. Charlotte is Mayo's longest-surviving transplant recipient.</p>



<p>She attributes her place in medical history to her loved ones and her care team.</p>



<p>"I thank my husband and my family and the doctors that I had," says Charlotte, who is from Oconomowoc, Wisconsin. "Without them, I wouldn't be doing as well as I am."</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Timeline-FINAL-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Timeline-FINAL-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377568" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Timeline-FINAL-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Timeline-FINAL-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Timeline-FINAL-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Timeline-FINAL-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Timeline-FINAL-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Transplant innovation begins</strong></h2>



<p>Marking its 60<sup>th</sup> anniversary this month, the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/home/orc-20203891?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Transplant Center</a> is the largest integrated transplant center in the U.S. Mayo's program includes transplant practices at its campuses in Rochester, Minnesota; Jacksonville, Florida; and Phoenix. Since the program began, Mayo Clinic has performed more than 31,000 solid organ transplants.</p>



<p>"What started at Mayo Clinic in Rochester in 1963 has become a world-renowned transplant program," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/taner-c-burcin-m-d/bio-20054935" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Burcin Taner, M.D.</a>, director of Mayo Clinic Transplant Center in Florida.</p>



<p>In October, Mayo Clinic performed its first minimally invasive, <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-surgeons-perform-first-robotic-assisted-kidney-transplant-in-minnesota/">robotic-assisted kidney transplant</a>, which also was the first one performed in Minnesota.</p>



<p>These medical bookends, six decades apart, mark significant steps in transplant innovation, says<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/heimbach-julie-k-m-d/bio-20054676" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">&nbsp;Julie Heimbach, M.D.</a>,&nbsp;director of Mayo Clinic Transplant Center in Minnesota.</p>



<p>"It reflects the spirit of innovation and of recognizing serious and complex disease and how Mayo can contribute to moving the field forward," Dr. Heimbach says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-300x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377560" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1-2048x2048.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure></div>


<p>In 1963, options to care for people with kidney failure were few. Access to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/hemodialysis/about/pac-20384824" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hemodialysis</a>, which can replace kidney function temporarily, was limited. Kidney transplantation was a clinical research option in its infancy in the U.S., following the first successful kidney transplant between identical twins performed in Boston in 1954 by a team that <a href="https://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/article/S0025-6196(11)62883-8/fulltext#:~:text=American%20physician%20Joseph%20Edward%20Murray,transplantation%20occurred%20between%20identical%20twins." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ultimately was awarded a Nobel Prize</a>.</p>



<p>Anti-rejection medication to keep the transplant recipient's immune system from attacking the donated organ was in its early stages but necessary for all transplant recipients except identical twins.</p>



<p>"There were just remarkable hurdles that needed to be overcome," Dr. Heimbach says. "Even very young people were dying of kidney failure. It was one surgical and medical innovation on top of another that allowed this progress to be made."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>'My only option was a transplant'</strong></h2>



<p>Tired. That's how Charlotte, a Waukesha, Wisconsin, native, remembers feeling in her youth. But she recalls serious health problems striking almost overnight in her early 20s. Nausea led Charlotte, a newlywed at the time, to believe she may be pregnant. Before she could see her physician, she began having convulsions. Her local doctors could not determine her problem, and she was flown to Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>Her Mayo team ultimately diagnosed irreversible chronic kidney failure.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XqsnI_PBKRI&amp;t=3s" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kidney function</a> is necessary to live. These two bean-shaped organs remove waste from the blood by producing urine. They also play a role in controlling blood pressure, fluid balance, red blood cell counts, metabolic balance and bone health. Each healthy kidney is about the size of a person's fist. They sit in the abdomen along each side of the spine.</p>



<p>Living well with one healthy kidney is possible; that fact makes <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/living-donor-transplant/about/pac-20384787#:~:text=The%20match%20is%20based%20on,transplant%20center%20policy%20allows%20it." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">living kidney donation</a> an option.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="232" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Roland_Books_cropped-232x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377550" style="aspect-ratio:0.5625;object-fit:cover;width:208px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Roland_Books_cropped-232x300.jpg 232w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Roland_Books_cropped-792x1024.jpg 792w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Roland_Books_cropped-768x993.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Roland_Books_cropped.jpg 1139w" sizes="(max-width: 232px) 100vw, 232px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Roland Books</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Dialysis to clear waste from the blood is a treatment for kidney failure, preceding transplant, but Charlotte had difficulty tolerating those treatments. "My only option was a transplant," she says.</p>



<p>While a kidney transplant was rare in 1966, so was a patient airplane transfer between medical centers. "Nothing was common back then," Charlotte says with a chuckle.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/living-donor-transplant/care-at-mayo-clinic/pcc-20384790" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Donor testing</a> of healthy and willing candidates to identify a matching blood and tissue type for the needy transplant recipient was also in its early stages in the 1960s. One of Charlotte's five older brothers, Roland, was identified as her living donor candidate, and Charlotte recalls learning, "We were about as close to being twins as we could be."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>'She is an inspiration'</strong></h2>



<p>Thomas Schwab, M.D., a retired Mayo Clinic transplant nephrologist, was in eighth grade when Charlotte underwent her kidney transplant. By the time he joined the Mayo staff in 1986 and assumed some of her transplant care, Charlotte already had had her kidney for over 20 years.</p>



<p>"Charlotte's story and outcome is a true inspiration to our transplant teams and especially to those patients in need of a kidney transplant," he says.</p>



<p>Caring for Charlotte has been a privilege, says Dr. Schwab. "It's a reason to get up every morning if you can help patients have an outcome like Charlotte has had."</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/Ozzv7TAHphg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Thomas Schwab talks about transplant recipient</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeOzzv7TAHphg"  title="At 81, woman is among world’s longest-surviving transplant recipients" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ozzv7TAHphg?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites with Dr. Schwab are available in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Name super/CG: Thomas Schwab, M.D./Nephrology/Mayo Clinic.</strong></p>



<p>Charlotte has adhered faithfully to her anti-rejection drug regimen. "I do follow doctor's orders," she says. Any side effects from her medical program have been few, and her transplanted kidney function is remarkably normal for a donated kidney that is more than 90 years old, Dr. Schwab notes.</p>



<p>"A kidney transplant is not a sprint. It's a marathon. It requires paying attention to your health and following the program we recommend. But you're not out there alone. We have an entire team of doctors, nurse coordinators and surgeons that help along the way," Dr. Schwab says.</p>



<p>"Over the years, our record of steadily improving patient outcomes shows that research by Mayo Clinic and colleagues worldwide have developed a recipe for long-term success of our transplant patients."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Pioneering medicine, then and now</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="224" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Hallenbeck_George_1968-224x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377593" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Hallenbeck_George_1968-224x300.jpg 224w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Hallenbeck_George_1968-763x1024.jpg 763w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Hallenbeck_George_1968-768x1030.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Hallenbeck_George_1968-1145x1536.jpg 1145w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Hallenbeck_George_1968-1527x2048.jpg 1527w" sizes="(max-width: 224px) 100vw, 224px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">George Hallenbeck, M.D.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Dr. Schwab calls Charlotte a "transplant pioneer" who accepted an opportunity with many unknowns at the time — so was her surgeon, George Hallenbeck, M.D. He led the pioneering team who performed Mayo's first kidney transplant in 1963. Dr. Hallenbeck's innovative efforts were not limited to transplant medicine. He was part of the Mayo aeronautical research team that designed the antigravity suit, called the G-suit, a garment developed during World War II that pilots and astronauts wear to keep from blacking out during high acceleration force.</p>



<p>In the early days of kidney transplantation, living donor surgeries were sometimes more extensive than for recipients. Donor surgery required a lengthy incision around a third of the body, and sometimes a rib needed to be removed, Dr. Schwab explains.</p>



<p>Since 1999, living kidney donation surgery at Mayo has been performed with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/donor-nephrectomy/about/pac-20384867#:~:text=In%20a%20laparoscopic%20nephrectomy%2C%20the,to%20remove%20the%20donor%20kidney." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">laparoscopic technique</a>s, using smaller incisions to insert surgical instruments and a special camera to remove the donor's kidney. This minimally invasive approach shortens recovery and increases the rate of living kidney donation, which may be arranged in weeks to months compared with an average four- to six-year wait for a deceased donor kidney.</p>



<p>Even into the 1970s, many patients' kidney transplants did not survive one year. Today, one-year survival rates for kidney transplants are over 98%, making it the treatment of choice for patients with kidney failure who are eligible for surgery.</p>



<p>October's robotic-assisted kidney transplant was yet another Mayo milestone. While most kidney transplants are done via open surgery with a 4- to 8-inch incision on the lower abdomen, a robotic-assisted transplant allows the surgeon to make a significantly smaller incision using robotic instruments to complete the transplant, allowing shorter recovery time for the recipient.</p>



<p>Mayo also is focused on research and innovations to expand the kidney donation eligibility pool by helping organs from deceased donors remain viable longer while awaiting transplant. Medical research is being conducted to identify organ failure earlier to delay or prevent the need for a transplant. Mayo transplant experts are developing new practices to help organs last longer after transplantation. In the future, bioengineering of new organs may be possible.</p>



<p>"Our mission is that no patients should die awaiting transplant," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/aqel-bashar-a-m-d/bio-20055093" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bashar Aqel, M.D.</a>, director of Mayo Clinic's Transplant Center in Arizona.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="508" height="677" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Charlotte_with_cane_Sharon_with_walkeOriginalr.jpg" alt="Charlotte Markle is among world's longest-surviving transplant recipients" class="wp-image-377571" style="width:368px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Charlotte_with_cane_Sharon_with_walkeOriginalr.jpg 508w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Charlotte_with_cane_Sharon_with_walkeOriginalr-225x300.jpg 225w" sizes="(max-width: 508px) 100vw, 508px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Charlotte Markle and her sister, Sharon Mertins</figcaption></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>'I owe all that to Mayo Clinic'</strong></h2>



<p>Family and faith have comforted Charlotte during her kidney transplant journey. She recalls praying in the hospital chapel with her mother. "I'm just a strong believer that everything we were doing was the right thing and that everything would turn out," says Charlotte. "I owe all that to Mayo Clinic."</p>



<p>For Charlotte, it's hard to believe how far transplant medicine has come, including a surgeon controlling a robotic instrument to perform the procedure. "It's really something," she says. It pleases her to know that today's female transplant patients may consider pregnancy, which Charlotte and her husband, David, were advised against in the 1960s and 1970s.</p>



<p>Charlotte expresses deep gratitude for her good health during a more than 50-year marriage and a 40-year career as a hospital dietary aide. A widow, she enjoys time with her extended family and quilting and crafting with her sole surviving sibling, her sister, Sharon. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Emotion tugs at her voice when Charlotte speaks of Roland, who, years after donating a kidney, died awaiting a heart transplant. "My brother would be very proud of me," she says.</p>



<p>To future organ donors and recipients, Charlotte has a message: "I wish them all the best and good meaningful years like I have had."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Related content:</h2>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/11-16-four-ways-organ-transplants-are-being-transformed-to-save-more-lives/">Four ways organ transplants are being transformed to save more lives</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/biancas-transplant-journey/">Bianca's transplant journey</a>&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/regenerative-medicine-paves-the-way-for-a-heart-transplant/">Regenerative medicine paves the way for heart transplant</a></li>



<li><a href="https://nam12.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.mayoclinichealthsystem.org%2Fhometown-health%2Fpatient-stories%2Fnew-heart-new-start-for-gregg-bohlig&amp;data=05%7C01%7CStreed.Joel%40mayo.edu%7C9af52ddbf82245afbbe408dbe6b6c19e%7Ca25fff9c3f634fb29a8ad9bdd0321f9a%7C0%7C0%7C638357444825126836%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=%2BjBpxZVGQF3e%2BxZKNhNM0I7v5g3F0cfE9Mdw80aA5Qo%3D&amp;reserved=0">New heart, new start for Gregg Bohlig</a>&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/11-16-at-81-woman-is-among-worlds-longest-surviving-transplant-recipients/">At 81, woman is among world&#8217;s longest-surviving transplant recipients</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Charlotte_and_David_Markle_wedding_picture1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Charlotte_and_David_Markle_wedding_picture16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Charlotte Markle]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Burcin Taner]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Julie Heimbach]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Thomas Schwab]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Kidney Transplant]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Transplant innovation]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Four ways organ transplants are being transformed to save more lives</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/11-16-four-ways-organ-transplants-are-being-transformed-to-save-more-lives/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Heather Carlson Kehren]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 14:36:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Mayo Clinic Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Regenerative Medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377203</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Despite a record year for organ donation last year in the U.S., an estimated 17 people die every day waiting for a transplant. Yet Mayo Clinic transplant experts are optimistic that solutions to some of the biggest transplant challenges are on the horizon, thanks to new technology, research and innovations. Watch: Dr. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/11-16-four-ways-organ-transplants-are-being-transformed-to-save-more-lives/">Four ways organ transplants are being transformed to save more lives</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377570" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-2048x1151.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Despite a record year for organ donation last year in the U.S., an estimated <a href="https://www.organdonor.gov/learn/organ-donation-statistics?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">17 people die every day</a> waiting for a transplant. Yet Mayo Clinic transplant experts are optimistic that solutions to some of the biggest transplant challenges are on the horizon, thanks to new technology, research and innovations.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/dLlAdVJjvpg?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Burcin Taner talks about the start of organ transplant practice at Mayo Clinic</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubedLlAdVJjvpg"  title="Expert talks about organ transplant history and innovation at Mayo Clinic" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dLlAdVJjvpg?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>"Our goal is to transform the transplant practice for future patients. To do that, we are using technology and team science to look at ways to optimize donated organs, liberate patients from anti-rejection medications and enable donated organs to last longer," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/taner-c-burcin-m-d/bio-20054935?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Burcin Taner, M.D.</a>, director of Mayo Clinic Transplant Center in Florida.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is celebrating the 60<sup>th</sup> anniversary of its first organ transplant, which was a kidney transplant from a living donor on Nov. 25, 1963. Today, Mayo Clinic is the largest integrated transplant center in the U.S. Mayo Clinic's transplant centers in Arizona, Florida and Minnesota combined have performed over 31,000 organ transplants.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377558" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>"From the very beginning, organ transplantation has been exciting because it can allow a patient who has end-stage organ failure and who is extremely ill and suffering to get back to a normal life. We need to achieve that for more patients," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/heimbach-julie-k-m-d/bio-20054676?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Julie Heimbach, M.D.</a>, director of Mayo Clinic Transplant Center in Minnesota.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/eJF7a7UeHM8?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Julie Heimbach talks about new advancements</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeeJF7a7UeHM8"  title="Expert alert: Four ways organ transplants are being transformed to save more lives" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/eJF7a7UeHM8?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites with Dr. Taner and Dr. Heimbach are available in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Name supers/CG: Burcin Taner, M.D./Transplantation Surgery/Mayo Clinic</strong> <strong>and</strong> <strong>Julie Heimbach, M.D./Transplantation Surgery/Mayo Clinic</strong></p>



<p></p>



<p>Here are four promising ways transplant is changing:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">1. <strong>Enabling more donated organs to be safely used.</strong></h2>



<p>New technology is helping ensure that more donated organs can get to the people who desperately need them. One of the biggest advances has been organ-perfusion systems. These mechanical devices enable donated organs such as lungs, hearts, kidneys and livers to remain viable outside the body for a longer period of time so that they can be used. It also allows surgeons to restore organs that would otherwise not be safe for transplantation. "Organ perfusion technology has helped us expand the donor pool and deliver lifesaving transplants to more and more patients, all while maintaining some of the best outcomes," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/aqel-bashar-a-m-d/bio-20055093?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bashar Aqel, M.D., </a>&nbsp;director of Mayo Clinic Transplant Center in Arizona.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">2. <strong>Helping transplants last longer.</strong></h2>



<p>The average kidney transplant in the U.S. lasts 10 to 20 years, meaning transplant recipients are often faced with needing a second transplant. But what if those donated organs could last longer? Researchers are looking at ways to keep patients healthier so that these donated organs thrive longer. For example, one of the most common causes of kidney failure is diabetes, which is related to obesity. One innovative approach is to perform bariatric surgery ahead of the kidney transplant to reduce the chance of post-transplant diabetes. Efforts are also underway to improve how organs are matched with patients with the goal of minimizing the need for immunosuppression medication, which can have negative side effects.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">3. <strong>Identifying organ failure earlier.</strong></h2>



<p>The quicker someone is identified as being at risk for organ failure, the sooner they can begin to receive treatment in hopes of delaying — and potentially preventing — the need for a transplant. Researchers are exploring ways to identify subtle warning signs that this is happening earlier via artificial intelligence and biomarkers in the blood.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">4. <strong>Bioengineering new organs.</strong></h2>



<p>It may sound like science fiction, but experts hope that one day there will be a way to engineer new organs using <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">regenerative medicine</a>. That would eliminate the uncertainty of organ donation and long waiting lists. Those efforts are still in the early stages.</p>



<p>While all of these potential advances offer hope, choosing to be an organ donor is a step people can take today to help save more lives. More than 103,000 people are on the waiting list in the U.S. for a transplant, according to the <a href="https://unos.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">United Network for Organ Sharing</a>. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/living-donor-transplantation/overview/ovc-20545462?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Living donation</a> allows people to donate a kidney or part of their liver to someone in need. People also can <a href="https://donatelife.net/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">register</a> to become a deceased donor.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">Mayo Clinic News Network</a> for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Heather Carlson Kehren, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a> </li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Related Content</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/11-16-at-81-woman-is-among-worlds-longest-surviving-transplant-recipients/">At 81, woman is among world's longest-surviving transplant recipients</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/transplant-program-at-mayo-clinic-in-florida-celebrates-its-25th-anniversary-with-vision-for-future-of-transplant/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Transplant program at Mayo Clinic in Florida celebrates its 25<sup>th</sup> anniversary with vision for future of transplant</a>&nbsp;</li>



<li><span style="font-size: 12pt;font-family: Calibri, sans-serif"><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-innovation-new-heart-in-a-box-technology-provides-gift-of-life-to-arizona-man-as-couple-prepares-to-celebrate-50-year-anniversary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span class="normaltextrun"><span style="color:#0563C1">New ‘heart in a box’ technology provides gift of life to Arizona man, as couple prepares to celebrate 50-year anniversary</span><span style="color: blue"> </span></span></a></span></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-diverse-organ-donors-are-needed/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Why diverse organ donors are needed</a>&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/11-16-four-ways-organ-transplants-are-being-transformed-to-save-more-lives/">Four ways organ transplants are being transformed to save more lives</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Graphic-FINAL-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Mayo Clinic Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Regenerative Medicine]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Transplant]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Celebrating a remarkable liver transplant journey</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/celebrating-a-remarkable-liver-transplant-journey/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tia R. Ford]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hepatocellular carcinoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Liver Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[normothermic regional perfusion]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376502</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>For her one-year anniversary, Luana Q., a Mayo Clinic patient, shares her liver transplant story. Luana was the 4,000th patient to receive a liver transplant since the program began at Mayo Clinic in Florida in 1998. For her transplant, the team used normothermic regional perfusion to preserve the donated organ. This innovative approach uses a [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/celebrating-a-remarkable-liver-transplant-journey/">Celebrating a remarkable liver transplant journey</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/MCF-4000-liver-txp16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Operating room staff perform the 4000th liver transplant on the Mayo Clinic in Florida campus." class="wp-image-352528" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/MCF-4000-liver-txp16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/MCF-4000-liver-txp16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/MCF-4000-liver-txp16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/MCF-4000-liver-txp16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/MCF-4000-liver-txp16x9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><em><strong>For her one-year anniversary, Luana Q., a Mayo Clinic patient, shares her liver transplant story. Luana was the 4,000<sup>th</sup> patient to receive a liver transplant since the program began at Mayo Clinic in Florida in 1998. For her transplant, the team used normothermic regional perfusion to preserve the donated organ. This innovative approach uses a machine to pass blood through organs in a donor's body after the heart has irreversibly stopped beating. The procedure also allows for a variety of therapeutic interventions, potentially enhancing the organ's quality before transplantation.</strong></em></p>



<p></p>



<p>On Oct. 22, 2022, I had my <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/liver-transplant/about/pac-20384842" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">liver transplant</a> at Mayo Clinic in Florida. I live in New Smyrna Beach which is an hour and a half away from Jacksonville. I am so thankful for the donor who gave me the opportunity to continue to live a healthy life after my transplant.</p>



<p>I had <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/liver-cancer/symptoms-causes/syc-20353659" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">liver cancer</a> by the name of hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC). This cancer developed from having <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hepatitis-c/symptoms-causes/syc-20354278" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hepatitis C</a> in prior years. Even though I went through the medical treatment of riboflavin and interferon for one year, and the treatment was successful (the hepatitis C was no longer detectable), we continued to monitor my bloodwork and liver biopsies.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="296" height="640" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Luana-Quinette.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376503" style="aspect-ratio:0.4625;width:135px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Luana-Quinette.jpg 296w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Luana-Quinette-139x300.jpg 139w" sizes="(max-width: 296px) 100vw, 296px" /></figure></div>


<p>In 2016, during a routine exam, a lesion was discovered on my liver which turned out to be HCC liver cancer. My doctor made arrangements for me to go to Mayo for further care.</p>



<p>My tumor was larger than acceptable for me to be a transplant candidate; however, the Mayo team did not give up. I was given the opportunity to have Y90 radioembolization, where a special radiation specifically targeted the tumor on my liver to shrink it.</p>



<p>Prayers were answered and the tumor shrank, so I could be placed on the liver transplant list. I had to wait six months for my Model for End-stage Liver Disease (MELD) score to increase, which placed me in a position to be called sooner for a transplant.</p>



<p>On Sept. 23, 2022, I received "the call" to come to Mayo for a possible liver transplant, but, unfortunately, the organ donor's liver was unsuitable for transplant, and the surgery was canceled. That was disappointing, but I am glad my care team thoroughly examined the organ.</p>



<p>Soon after, I was called again on Oct. 22, 2022, and had a successful liver transplant. I was given the best team of doctors and nurses who gave me the most wonderful care. I remained in the hospital for four days and continued my stay at the Gabriel House for another four weeks so I could return to Mayo for follow-up monitoring.</p>



<p>I am so honored to be the 4,000th liver transplant patient and praise Mayo for all the lives they change by successfully caring for each patient and their needs. The teams really care, and I never felt like just a number as that sometimes happens. I truly love the care that I continue to receive.</p>



<p>I feel each day is a special gift, and I truly am thankful to Mayo Clinic and my organ donor. I thank God for his love and mercy for me, and giving me this wonderful gift.</p>



<p><em>- Luana Q</em>.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/celebrating-a-remarkable-liver-transplant-journey/">Celebrating a remarkable liver transplant journey</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/MCF-4000-liver-txp1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/10/MCF-4000-liver-txp16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[hepatocellular carcinoma]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Liver Transplant]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[normothermic regional perfusion]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic surgeons perform first robotic-assisted kidney transplant in Minnesota</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-surgeons-perform-first-robotic-assisted-kidney-transplant-in-minnesota/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Heather Carlson Kehren]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2023 13:51:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=376139</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — Mayo Clinic surgeons successfully performed Minnesota's first robotic-assisted kidney transplant earlier this month. This minimally invasive procedure may be beneficial for patients with a higher body mass index and may reduce the risk of incisional complications, such as hernia or infection. Mayo Clinic's first robotic-assisted kidney transplant was successfully performed on Oct. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-surgeons-perform-first-robotic-assisted-kidney-transplant-in-minnesota/">Mayo Clinic surgeons perform first robotic-assisted kidney transplant in Minnesota</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Dean-robotic-assisted-kidney-transplant-IMG_9667-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-376340" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Dean-robotic-assisted-kidney-transplant-IMG_9667-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Dean-robotic-assisted-kidney-transplant-IMG_9667-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Dean-robotic-assisted-kidney-transplant-IMG_9667-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Dean-robotic-assisted-kidney-transplant-IMG_9667-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Dean-robotic-assisted-kidney-transplant-IMG_9667-16x9-1-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> surgeons successfully performed Minnesota's first robotic-assisted kidney transplant earlier this month. This minimally invasive procedure may be beneficial for patients with a higher body mass index and may reduce the risk of incisional complications, such as hernia or infection.</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic's first robotic-assisted kidney transplant was successfully performed on Oct. 4 on a woman in her 60s who received a kidney from her daughter.</p>



<p>“Mayo Clinic has been a leader in the field of kidney transplants for six decades. We are proud to continue that tradition by completing the first robotic-assisted kidney transplant in Minnesota," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/taner-timucin-m-d-ph-d/bio-20055648?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Timucin Taner, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, division chair of Transplant Surgery at Mayo Clinic. Dr. Taner and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/dean-patrick-g-m-d/bio-20054709?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Patrick Dean, M.D.</a>, performed the robotic-assisted surgery.</p>



<p>For patients with kidney failure, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/kidney-transplant/about/pac-20384777?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">kidney transplant</a> remains the best treatment available. Most kidney transplants are done via open surgery. The surgeon makes an incision 4- to 8-inches long on the right or left side of the lower abdomen to transplant the donated kidney. For a robotic-assisted kidney transplant, the surgeon makes a roughly 2-inch incision around the belly button and a smaller incision to insert the robotic instruments. The surgeon sits at a console that controls the surgical robot.</p>



<p>“A robotic-assisted kidney transplant requires a smaller incision. It lowers the risk that patients will experience complications, such as an infection or hernia. Patients may also have less discomfort and a speedier recovery, potentially meaning less time in the hospital after surgery," says Dr. Dean, surgical director of Mayo Clinic's <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/kidney-transplant/sections/overview/ovc-20203202?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kidney Transplant Program</a> in Minnesota.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/u836QeLwzoA" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Patrick Dean talks about robotic-assisted kidney transplant surgery</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeu836QeLwzoA"  title="Robotic-assisted kidney transplant" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/u836QeLwzoA?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/z9NHA4W-2Ms" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Patient talks about her experience</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubez9NHA4W2Ms"  title="Patient receives first robotic-assisted kidney transplant in Minnesota" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/z9NHA4W-2Ms?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality soundbites with Dr. Patrick Dean and patient Pam Panning are available in the downloads at the end of the post. </strong></p>



<p>For most patients, the traditional kidney surgery method remains the best option. It is safe and successful.</p>



<p>“Robotic-assisted kidney transplant will not replace open kidney transplantation entirely,” Dr. Taner says. “It will, however, offer another option for those who may benefit from an alternative incision site — especially those with higher body mass indexes, previous hernias or prior abdominal surgeries.”</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic is the largest integrated transplant center in the U.S. <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/home/orc-20203891?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Transplant Center</a> in Minnesota performed 311 kidney transplants in 2022 — more than any other transplant center in the state.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Heather Carlson Kehren, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-surgeons-perform-first-robotic-assisted-kidney-transplant-in-minnesota/">Mayo Clinic surgeons perform first robotic-assisted kidney transplant in Minnesota</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Dean-robotic-assisted-kidney-transplant-IMG_9667-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/10/Dr.-Dean-robotic-assisted-kidney-transplant-IMG_9667-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Why diverse organ donors are needed</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-diverse-organ-donors-are-needed/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Osiadacz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2023 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Shennen Mao]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kidney Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Liver Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lung transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Transplant Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[National Minority Donor Awareness Month]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Organ Donation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=372291</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>August is National Minority Donor Awareness Month. It's a time of celebrating organ donation and educating people about transplantation by encouraging donor registration and promoting healthy living. Dr. Shennen Mao, a Mayo Clinic transplant surgeon, says having a diverse pool of organ donors will help serve a growing wait list of those in need. Watch: [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-diverse-organ-donors-are-needed/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Why diverse organ donors are needed</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>August is <a href="https://donatelife.net/how-you-can-help/national-observances-celebrations/national-minority-donor-awareness-month/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Minority Donor Awareness Month</a>. It's a time of celebrating organ donation and educating people about transplantation by encouraging donor registration and promoting healthy living.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mao-shennen-a-m-d/bio-20439463?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Shennen Mao</a>, a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/home/orc-20203891?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">transplant</a> surgeon, says having a diverse pool of organ donors will help serve a growing wait list of those in need.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=enImQP2yYEs" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidenImQP2yYEs"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Why diverse organ donors are needed" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/enImQP2yYEs?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:07) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post.&nbsp;Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network."&nbsp;Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/08/SCRIPT_Mayo-Clinic-Minute-Why-diverse-organ-donors-are-needed.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>In the U.S., <a href="https://www.organdonor.gov/learn/organ-donation-statistics" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">17 people</a> die every day while waiting for an organ transplant.</p>



<p>Nearly 60% of people on <a href="https://minorityhealth.hhs.gov/omh/browse.aspx?lvl=4&amp;lvlid=27#:~:text=In%202021%2C%2018.7%20percent%20of,percent%20of%20white%20living%20donors.">transplant waiting lists</a> come from minority communities, while about 30% of donors are people of color.</p>



<p>"<a href="https://www.life-source.org/latest/does-my-race-ethnicity-matter-in-organ-donation/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Blood types</a> and certain HLA, or antibodies, tend to correlate with various ethnic groups," says Dr. Mao. "So it is not directly related to a particular minority group; however, organs will end up with someone of a similar background because the better matched an organ is, the more longevity that organ has."</p>



<p>Higher rates of heart disease, high blood pressure and diabetes are present in minority communities, contributing to more organ failures.</p>



<p>"The more people we can help the sooner through transplant, the better," says Dr. Mao.</p>



<p>She says living donors do not experience a change in their quality of life after surgery, but a recipient's life can change for the better almost immediately.</p>



<p>"If somebody is approved to be a <a href="https://www.organdonor.gov/learn/process/living-donation" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">living donor</a>, we expect they will live a full and normal life following their donation process," says Dr. Mao.</p>



<p>In most states, <a href="https://www.organdonor.gov/sign-up" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">signing up</a> to be a donor after death can be done online or when registering for a driver's license or identification card. For a <a href="https://www.kidneyregistry.org/for-patients/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">living donation</a>, contact the recipient's care team or a <a href="https://optn.transplant.hrsa.gov/about/search-membership/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">transplant center</a> for more information.</p>



<p><strong>Related posts:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-breaking-barriers-for-patients-who-need-kidney-transplants/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Minute: Breaking barriers for patients who need kidney transplants</a>"</li>



<li>"<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/transplant-program-at-mayo-clinic-in-florida-celebrates-its-25th-anniversary-with-vision-for-future-of-transplant/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Transplant program at Mayo Clinic in Florida celebrates its 25th anniversary with vision for future of transplant</a>"</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-diverse-organ-donors-are-needed/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Why diverse organ donors are needed</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/PensiveMan1x1.jpeg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/PensiveMan16x9.jpeg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Shennen Mao]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Kidney Transplant]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Liver Transplant]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[lung transplant]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Transplant Center]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[National Minority Donor Awareness Month]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Organ Donation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Transplant]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss><!-- Static page delivered by HubScale -->