<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org">

<channel>
	<title>Transplant - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/transplant/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml">
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/transplant/
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastbuilddate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 13:14:40 +0000</lastbuilddate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updateperiod>
	hourly	</sy:updateperiod>
	<sy:updatefrequency>
	1	</sy:updatefrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Living kidney donation can start a chain reaction</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-living-kidney-donation-can-start-a-chain-reaction/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Abby Smith]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 15:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=397700</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;I've signed up on my driver's license to be an organ donor if I die. It's important to me. I've also considered being a&nbsp;living kidney donor. I don't personally know someone who needs a kidney, but I've seen billboards and other advertisements from people seeking a kidney donor. Does that have something to […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-living-kidney-donation-can-start-a-chain-reaction/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Living kidney donation can start a chain reaction</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidney-Transplant-Surgery16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Surgeons performing a kidney transplant" class="wp-image-363125" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidney-Transplant-Surgery16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidney-Transplant-Surgery16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidney-Transplant-Surgery16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidney-Transplant-Surgery16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidney-Transplant-Surgery16x9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>


<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong>&nbsp;I've signed up on my driver's license to be an organ donor if I die. It's important to me. I've also considered being a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/living-donor-kidney-transplant/pyc-20384838">living kidney donor</a>. I don't personally know someone who needs a kidney, but I've seen billboards and other advertisements from people seeking a kidney donor. Does that have something to do with a donor chain? I am not sure how it works. I'm a little scared and not quite ready to commit.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong>&nbsp;First, thank you for considering making a difference in the lives of others with the gift of life through transplant. Participating in your&nbsp;<a href="https://donatelife.net/how-you-can-help/take-action/get-involved-locally/">state donor registry</a>&nbsp;or the&nbsp;<a href="https://donatelife.net/donation/donor-registries/national-donate-life-registry/">National Donate Life Registry</a>&nbsp;helps people make their wishes about organ donation known in case of their death.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/living-donor-transplantation/overview/ovc-20545462">Living-donor transplantation</a>&nbsp;is an option for some organs. For people over 18 born with two functioning kidneys, they can donate one and continue to live a healthy life. An altruistic living-donor kidney transplant chain begins when someone donates a kidney without a specific individual in mind. That can start a chain effect of donors.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Another way to begin a chain is if a person intends to donate to a family member or friend, but they aren't a direct match. Instead, the person donates to someone else who is a match, and that individual's donor then donates either to the original intended recipient or starts a chain effect of individuals whose donors aren't necessarily a direct match to them, allowing many people to get transplanted.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-center-align-caption"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Donor-2-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Example of a transplant donor chain" class="wp-image-385229" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Donor-2-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Donor-2-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Donor-2-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Donor-2-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/04/Donor-2-16-x-9.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Example of a living kidney donor chain</figcaption></figure>



<p></p>



<p>There's no limit on the chain. It can occur within one transplant program or at multiple transplant programs. In fact, we've had chains that have involved the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/sections/overview/ovc-20203894">Mayo Clinic Transplant Center</a>&nbsp;at our three campuses in Rochester, Minnesota; Jacksonville, Florida; and Phoenix; as well as at several institutions around the country.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XqsnI_PBKRI&amp;t=3s" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kidney function</a>&nbsp;is necessary to live. These two bean-shaped organs remove waste from the blood by producing urine. They play a role in controlling blood pressure, fluid balance, red blood cell counts and more. Living with one healthy kidney is possible, making&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/living-donor-transplant/about/pac-20384787#:~:text=The%20match%20is%20based%20on,transplant%20center%20policy%20allows%20it." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">living kidney donation</a>&nbsp;an option.</p>



<p>What I always tell potential donors is that coming forward as a potential donor is a commitment to find out information; it's not a commitment to donate. You can come forward, learn a little bit and decide it may not be for you.</p>



<p><a href="https://connect.mayoclinic.org/blog/transplant/tab/resource-36/">Learning more about the living organ donor process</a>&nbsp;often helps calm people's concerns. While any medical procedure has risks, you should know we expect living donors to live a completely normal life after donation with no restrictions in terms of activities or diet. Typically, donors have a short stay in the hospital, about a day or two. The recovery period is six to eight weeks, but donors often feel back to normal within one to two weeks after donation.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Potential donors go through an&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/living-donor-transplantation-evaluation/gnc-20505893">evaluation</a>&nbsp;online with a basic screening and health questionnaire. Then a donor coordinator contacts you to discuss. If you decide to pursue donation and are a potential candidate, further medical evaluation is done.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The more people we bring into the donor candidate pool, the more benefit to everyone who is waiting for a kidney transplant. We encourage people to reach out among their community members to ensure we have equal opportunity and equal access of living donation to everyone who might need a donor.</p>



<p>The biggest thing I would say is thank you to all of our donor heroes — the deceased donors and their family members and our living-donor heroes who inspire us to do what we do every day.&nbsp;<strong><em>—&nbsp;</em></strong><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mao-shennen-a-m-d/bio-20439463"><strong><em>Shennen Mao, M.D.</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Transplant Surgery, Mayo Clinic, Jacksonville, Florida</em></strong></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-living-kidney-donation-can-start-a-chain-reaction/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Living kidney donation can start a chain reaction</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidney-Transplant-Surgery1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/04/Kidney-Transplant-Surgery16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>(VIDEO) Who should get screened for cervical cancer, and when?</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/who-should-get-screened-for-cervical-cancer-and-when/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Deb Balzer]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 15:30:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Cancer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Diversity]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Cycle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Video]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[diverserepresentation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Kathy MacLaughlin]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=398558</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Editor's note: January is Cervical Cancer Awareness Month. When it comes to healthcare screening, different healthcare guideline organizations may have different recommendations. The same is true for cervical cancer screening. Cervical cancer is almost always caused by a persistent infection with high-risk strains of HPV. Routine screening has dramatically reduced cervical cancer deaths, and regular […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/who-should-get-screened-for-cervical-cancer-and-when/">(VIDEO) Who should get screened for cervical cancer, and when?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"--><img decoding="async" width="1000" height="563" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/03/shutterstock_713436487_Fotor-16x9.jpg" alt="three young women laughing and smiling together" class="wp-image-232440" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/03/shutterstock_713436487_Fotor-16x9.jpg 1000w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/03/shutterstock_713436487_Fotor-16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/03/shutterstock_713436487_Fotor-16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px">



<p><em><strong>Editor's note: January is Cervical Cancer Awareness Month.</strong></em></p>



<p>When it comes to healthcare screening, different healthcare guideline organizations may have different recommendations. The same is true for cervical cancer screening.</p>



<p>Cervical cancer is almost always caused by a persistent infection with high-risk strains of HPV. Routine screening has dramatically reduced cervical cancer deaths, and regular screenings are essential because early detection makes precancer treatment more effective.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/maclaughlin-kathy-l-m-d/bio-20199426" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Kathy MacLaughlin</a>, a Mayo Clinic family physician specializing in cervical cancer prevention, says Mayo Clinic follows U.S. Preventive Services Task Force recommendations.</p>



<p>"They recommend screening for 21- to 65-year-olds, either with a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/pap-smear/about/pac-20394841" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pap smear</a>&nbsp;every three years or, starting at age 30, the Pap/HPV co-test, or the primary&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/hpv-test/about/pac-20394355" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">HPV test</a>&nbsp;every five years," she says.</p>



<p>Starting February 5, Mayo Clinic practices in the Midwest will offer a FDA-approved <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-improving-cervical-cancer-screening-with-hpv-self-collection-tests/">self-collection HPV test</a> to help reduce barriers to screening. This service will later expand to Mayo Clinic in Arizona and Mayo Clinic in Florida.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/Z58PGJPSUUU" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Dr. Kathy MacLaughlin talks about screening for cervical cancer</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeZ58PGJPSUUU" title="Dr. Kathy MacLaughlin – Who should be screened for cervical cancer and when?" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Z58PGJPSUUU?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality sound bites are available in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Name super/CG: Kathy MacLaughlin, M.D./Family Medicine/Mayo Clinic.</strong></p>



<p>For women ages 21–65, the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force recommendations are:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Screening for cervical cancer every three years with cervical cytology alone in women aged 21 to 29 years.</li>



<li>For women aged 30 to 65, screening every three years with cervical cytology alone, every five years with high-risk HPV (hrHPV) testing alone, or every five years with hrHPV testing combined with cytology (co-testing).<br></li>
</ul>



<p>Dr. MacLaughlin says the current guidelines suggest that after age 65, if you've had past negative/normal screening, particularly important in the prior 10 years, it's OK for most people to stop screening, but that might not always be the case.</p>



<p>"People who have previously had precancers (CIN-2 or CIN-3) treated with a procedure called LEEP (loop electrosurgical excision procedure) should not stop screening. If someone is immunocompromised or has had cervical cancer, they should not stop screening. Or if they've had in utero DES (diethylstilbestrol) exposure, they should not stop screening. To exit screening after age 65, there should be none of those risk factors. And then you also need 10 years of either three negative Paps or two negative HPV tests to say, yes, you are done," she says.</p>



<p>If you're unsure if you should be screened, consult your healthcare team to determine what's best for you.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Risk and prevention for cervical cancer</h2>



<p>"Persistent high-risk human papillomavirus infection, or HPV, is the cause of the majority of cervical cancers. Anyone with a cervix who is sexually active is at risk, particularly if they haven't had the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-protecting-kids-from-cancer-with-hpv-vaccine/">HPV vaccine series</a>," says Dr. MacLaughlin.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="vial of human papillomavirus vaccine" class="wp-image-103619" style="width:652px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/10/HPV-vaccine-vial-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure></div>


<p>Along with HPV, other risk factors for cervical cancer include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Smoking tobacco</li>



<li>Lack of screening</li>



<li>Multiple sexual partners</li>
</ul>



<p>Preventing cervical cancer involves three steps:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>HPV vaccination is most effective if given to preteens/teens (females and males), but it is routinely recommended for all 9-26-year-olds and available through a shared decision-making discussion with your clinician for 27-45-year-olds (females and males).&nbsp;</li>



<li>Get screened at recommended intervals.&nbsp;</li>



<li>Appropriate management of abnormal screening results.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What happens with your HPV self-collection results?</h2>



<p>Dr. MacLaughlin says about 85%-90% of people will test negative or not have HPV. They will be advised to have repeat testing in three years — though that could change with future guideline updates to five-year interval screening.&nbsp;</p>



<p>However, for those with positive HPV test results, further testing will be needed.&nbsp;<br><br>Different types of high-risk HPV are being screened for, she says.</p>



<p>"HPV 16 and HPV 18 are the highest of the high risk. They cause 70% of cervical cancers. If either of those is found on the HPV self-collection test, the patient will need a referral to colposcopy, which is an outpatient procedure where the cervix is looked at under a microscope," says Dr. MacLaughlin. "Some small biopsies might be taken from the cervical tissue to ensure that there's not precancer."</p>



<p>Dr. MacLaughlin explains that if other types of HPV are found on the self-collection test (not HPV 16, not HPV 18), the patient will need to return to the clinic for a Pap test to complete their cervical cancer screening, as that information is necessary to guide the next steps. She says there is a difference from a clinician-collected cervical sample for HPV testing because the lab can add a Pap test to the sample of cervical cells but cannot run a Pap test on vaginal samples. This is expected to happen about 10% of the time.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The U.S. Preventive Services Task Force is updating its&nbsp;<a href="https://www.uspreventiveservicestaskforce.org/uspstf/document/draft-evidence-review/cervical-cancer-screening-adults-adolescents" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">recommendations</a>. In its draft recommendation statement, it endorses the HPV self-collection option for people aged 30 to 65.</p>



<p><strong>Related resources:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-improving-cervical-cancer-screening-with-hpv-self-collection-tests/">Improving cervical cancer screening with HPV self-collection tests</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-to-know-about-cervical-cancer/"><strong>Mayo Clinic Q&amp;A:</strong> What to know about cervical cancer</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-black-women-need-to-be-screened-for-cervical-cancer/"><strong>Mayo Clinic Minute:</strong> Why Black women need to be screened for cervical cancer<br></a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-qa-what-to-know-about-cervical-cancer/"><br></a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/who-should-get-screened-for-cervical-cancer-and-when/">(VIDEO) Who should get screened for cervical cancer, and when?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/03/shutterstock_713436487_Fotor-1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/03/shutterstock_713436487_Fotor-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[diverserepresentation]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Kathy MacLaughlin]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beckett gets a lifesaving birthday gift</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/beckett-gets-a-lifesaving-birthday-gift/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[amymittlestadt]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 14:30:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Children's Center]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Samar Ibrahim]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Timucin Taner]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Patient Story]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=398047</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->At birth, Beckett Hoggarth Beyer appeared to be a healthy newborn baby boy, growing and changing like a typical infant. But when his aunt — a physician — visited their home near Fargo, North Dakota, she noticed something was not right. Beckett's stools were light in color, and his skin tone was slightly more olive-toned […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/beckett-gets-a-lifesaving-birthday-gift/">Beckett gets a lifesaving birthday gift</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-in-sidexside-Original-16x9-1-1024x577.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-398054" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-in-sidexside-Original-16x9-1-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-in-sidexside-Original-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-in-sidexside-Original-16x9-1-768x433.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-in-sidexside-Original-16x9-1.jpg 1535w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Beckett Hoggarth Beyer</figcaption>



<p>At birth, Beckett Hoggarth Beyer appeared to be a healthy newborn baby boy, growing and changing like a typical infant. But when his aunt — a physician — visited their home near Fargo, North Dakota, she noticed something was not right. Beckett's stools were light in color, and his skin tone was slightly more olive-toned than expected.</p>



<p>Beckett's parents, Tracie Hoggarth and Ron Beyer, took him to his pediatrician. Blood tests revealed elevated liver enzymes, which often indicate inflammation or damage to liver cells.</p>



<p>To find out more about the cause of Beckett's symptoms, the family traveled to Minneapolis to see a pediatric gastroenterologist. At just eight weeks of age, fearing Beckett had <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/white-stool/expert-answers/faq-20058216" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">biliary atresia</a> — the most common condition associated with his symptoms at this age — they pursued advanced care to investigate the cause of his liver disease.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For the next 13 years, Beckett's care was managed by a few teams of gastroenterologists in Minneapolis.</p>



<p>After several rounds of genetic testing, they discovered that his liver disease was caused by <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/pediatrics/news/mayo-clinics-pediatric-liver-clinic-provides-exceptional-care-for-patients-requiring-transplant/mac-20506620" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alagille syndrome</a>. This rare genetic disease affected his liver and bile ducts by reducing bile flow out of the liver and causing jaundice, which is the darkening and yellowing of the skin and the whites of the eyes.&nbsp;This bile buildup in the liver damages cells, eventually leading to liver failure.</p>



<p>Alagille syndrome can affect the liver, heart, kidneys, skeleton, eyes and blood vessels. Complications of the syndrome may be life-threatening. Fortunately, Beckett's form of Alagille syndrome only affects his liver.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Living with liver disease &nbsp;</strong></h2>



<p>Beckett is a mechanically inclined 14-year-old who likes lawn mowers, riding four-wheelers, and repairing and driving RC cars. But his liver disease was throwing a wrench in his health and keeping him from doing all the activities he enjoys.</p>



<p>For several years, he had a mass growing in his liver that eventually grew to 10 by 13 centimeters in size. "For three years, they monitored it via ultrasound and secondary conditions from his liver disease with endoscopy, which is how we learned his disease was advancing," recalls Tracie. “When they performed an updated biopsy on his liver, they learned he had advanced cirrhosis.” Cirrhosis is severe scarring of the liver, which makes it difficult for the liver to do its job.</p>



<p>Given a liver transplant was becoming a likely future necessity, Beckett’s family wanted the best for their son — so they sought the medical expertise of Mayo Clinic.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In November 2023, Beckett had an initial consultation and testing at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/minnesota" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> in Rochester, Minnesota. The care team at Mayo Clinic recommended that Beckett be put on the liver <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/liver-transplant/home/orc-20211818" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">transplant</a> list before he became more ill.</p>



<p>With stage 4 <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cirrhosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20351487" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">liver cirrhosis</a> and a tremendously enlarged spleen, Beckett dealt with difficulty breathing due to his firm liver pressing against his diaphragm. Not only did he have a distended belly and chronic back pain from his liver disease and his enlarged spleen, but low platelet count put him at an increased risk of bleeding.</p>



<p>He had a yellow cast to his skin and was in end-stage liver disease — things that had just become normal for him. But his blood tests showed he was on the cusp of crisis.</p>



<p>The request to put Beckett on the transplant list was approved, and he was placed on the list in mid-February. During appointments with the liver transplant team, Beckett shared, "Maybe I'll get a liver by my birthday."</p>



<p>His birthday on April 1 was quickly approaching, and getting a liver often takes months, so getting his birthday wish seemed unlikely.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The call that changed everything</strong></h2>



<p>Eleven days after Beckett officially went on the transplant list, Ron received a call from a Minnesota phone number.</p>



<p>"It'd only been a couple of weeks since we were in Rochester, and I thought maybe Mayo Clinic needed more information or was calling about another test," recalls Ron.</p>



<p>But the care team had something else in mind — a liver for Beckett.</p>



<p>The family had eight hours to get from North Dakota to Mayo Clinic in Rochester. Ron called Tracie home from work. He called the school to let them know a liver was available for Beckett and to send Beckett and his sister home immediately. </p>



<p>When the call came in, Beckett was in history class. "The teacher was about to start teaching, but then they said, 'Beckett, you can head to the office.' And I'm like, what for? I didn't think I was in trouble," Beckett says.</p>



<p>Rather than being in trouble, Beckett soon learned that he was in luck.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="575" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-before-transplant-with-team-16x9-1-1024x575.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-398058" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-before-transplant-with-team-16x9-1-1024x575.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-before-transplant-with-team-16x9-1-300x168.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-before-transplant-with-team-16x9-1-768x431.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-before-transplant-with-team-16x9-1-1536x862.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-before-transplant-with-team-16x9-1.jpg 1778w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Beckett in the hospital before his transplant</figcaption></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Out with the old, in with the new</strong></h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/taner-timucin-m-d-ph-d/bio-20055648" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Timucin Taner,</a> a transplant surgeon at Mayo Clinic, performed Beckett's transplant on March 13 — just two weeks before his birthday.</p>



<p>"The only treatment for patients with cirrhosis is a liver transplant. Cirrhosis is a chronic disease that does not get better with other treatments," notes Dr. Taner. "Beckett needed a new liver, without any doubt. Without a transplant, Beckett would have continued to have jaundice, and his fatigue and other symptoms would have continued to get worse."</p>



<p>“I remember it vividly,” Tracie says. “I was astonished and grateful for the surgeon. Dr. Taner even took the time to wheel Beckett in his hospital bed down to the surgical suite.”</p>



<p>After hours of tenuous waiting, the transplant was a success. The transformation was noticeable. The night before the transplant, Beckett's eyes were yellow-tinted, but the morning after the transplant, they were already white, recalls Tracie.</p>



<p>Beckett recovered in the pediatric intensive care unit at Mayo Clinic for the next 10 days.</p>



<p>"I got the power-reclining bed with the remote and all the warm sheets I needed," says Beckett.</p>



<p>Visits from a Caring Equine miniature pony named Munchkin and a pet therapy dog named Benny Burrito were highlights of his stay.</p>



<p>"He was kind of sad to get discharged. He was getting like a five-star hotel experience," laughs Tracie. "It says volumes about the care they got when somebody is sad to get discharged."</p>



<p>Beckett and his parents note that all the staff they encountered were exceptionally kind and professional. The entire team — the pediatric intensive care unit doctors, his gastroenterologists, the nurses and the support staff — cared about Beckett and his journey.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-after-transplant-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-398051" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-after-transplant-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-after-transplant-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-after-transplant-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-after-transplant-16x9-1.jpg 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Beckett following his transplant</figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Loving his new liver</strong></h2>



<p>Since getting the transplant, Beckett can go on long walks. He has more energy, can breathe much better and has less back pain.</p>



<p>"I would get winded just walking, and I couldn't play football or participate in contact sports," says Beckett when thinking back to life before his transplant. "I felt stuffy after I drank or ate a lot. And then when I had my transplant, it felt like I had a lot more space."</p>



<p>Beckett's medication regimen has significantly improved. Previously, he endured a challenging schedule with many daily pills, a bitter-tasting oral medication and daily self-administered injections. Now, he takes a set of pills in the morning and early evening.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/ibrahim-samar-h-m-b-ch-b/bio-20055547" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Samar Ibrahim</a>, a pediatric transplant hepatologist at Mayo Clinic, manages Beckett's ongoing care. Dr. Ibrahim routinely monitors Beckett's medication regimen and watches for signs of rejection or infection in his lab work.</p>



<p>"Beckett's new liver is functioning normally, so his symptoms of end-stage liver disease are gone," says Dr. Ibrahim. "He will get to live his life like any other teen and celebrate many more birthdays."<br><br>For Beckett and his family, receiving a new liver was the best birthday gift they could have imagined. "When he got the liver before his birthday, we were astonished," says Tracie. "We will be eternally grateful for that."</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/beckett-gets-a-lifesaving-birthday-gift/">Beckett gets a lifesaving birthday gift</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-in-sidexside-Original-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Beckett-Beyer-in-sidexside-Original-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Samar Ibrahim]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Timucin Taner]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Patient Story]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>10 patients receive the ultimate gift in a single day at Mayo Clinic</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/10-patients-receive-the-ultimate-gift-in-a-single-day-at-mayo-clinic/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Heather Carlson Kehren]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 16:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Arizona]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=398117</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->PHOENIX, Ariz. — Mayo Clinic surgeons recently performed 10 organ transplants within 24 hours, setting a record for both the hospital and the state of Arizona. On Nov. 19, Mayo Clinic teams worked around the clock to complete seven kidney transplants and three liver transplants. Transplant center colleagues rose to the challenge with one goal […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/10-patients-receive-the-ultimate-gift-in-a-single-day-at-mayo-clinic/">10 patients receive the ultimate gift in a single day at Mayo Clinic</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Phoenix-ER-entrance-2024-16x9-1-1024x577.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-398129" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Phoenix-ER-entrance-2024-16x9-1-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Phoenix-ER-entrance-2024-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Phoenix-ER-entrance-2024-16x9-1-768x433.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Phoenix-ER-entrance-2024-16x9-1.jpg 1108w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>PHOENIX, Ariz. — Mayo Clinic surgeons recently performed 10 organ transplants within 24 hours, setting a record for both the hospital and the state of Arizona.</p>



<p>On Nov. 19, Mayo Clinic teams worked around the clock to complete seven kidney transplants and three liver transplants. Transplant center colleagues rose to the challenge with one goal in mind: Saving as many lives as possible, says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/aqel-bashar-a-m-d/bio-20055093" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bashar Aqel, M.D.</a>, director of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/sections/expertise-ranking/orc-20203899" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Transplant Center</a> in Arizona.</p>



<p>"Ten people received a second chance at life in a single day," Dr. Aqel says. "This milestone would not have been possible without the generous gift of organ donation, advances in technology and the dedication of our highly specialized team."</p>



<p>Heading into the record-setting day, three <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/living-donor-kidney-transplant/about/pac-20569323" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">living-donor kidney transplants</a> were already scheduled. But by evening, the team realized the magnitude of the day ahead of them as precious organs continued to become available. Organ perfusion devices proved critical, enabling the livers and some of the kidneys to be kept viable outside the donor's body for a longer period of time prior to transplant. The team also had to overcome logistical hurdles, ensuring enough operating room space was available to perform all the surgeries.</p>



<p>"Every day, an estimated 17 people die waiting for an organ transplant," Dr. Aqel says. "We are doing what we can to try to reverse that trend with innovation and organ perfusion to save more lives."</p>



<p>John Churan is among the 10 patients celebrating a second chance — one he never thought he would get. He was diagnosed with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/multiple-myeloma/symptoms-causes/syc-20353378" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">multiple myeloma</a> 16 years ago, and when his kidney began to fail in 2020, his diagnosis appeared grim. But thanks to a stem cell treatment at Mayo Clinic, he went into full remission from the cancer, and he was eligible for a kidney transplant. His wife of 36 years, Julia Churan, stepped forward to donate her kidney and was a match.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Churans_current-1024x576.jpg" alt="John and Julia Churan" class="wp-image-398124" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Churans_current-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Churans_current-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Churans_current-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Churans_current-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Churans_current-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>"I would not be here without Mayo Clinic," John Churan says. "I am so grateful for the care I have received and the incredible gift my wife has given me."</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong> <br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Heather Carlson Kehren, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/10-patients-receive-the-ultimate-gift-in-a-single-day-at-mayo-clinic/">10 patients receive the ultimate gift in a single day at Mayo Clinic</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Phoenix-ER-entrance-2024-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Phoenix-ER-entrance-2024-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>A journey of resilience and hope</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-journey-of-resilience-and-hope/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Tia R. Ford]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 16:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Florida]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Maher Baz]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Patient Story]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=397563</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Joshua Abelson, a 63-year-old aviation sales and supply chain professional, has faced numerous health challenges with remarkable resilience. Originally from Fort Worth, Texas, Joshua now resides in Jacksonville, Florida, where he continues to inspire others with his story. Joshua's transplant journey began in 2009 when he first noticed symptoms that led to a diagnosis of […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-journey-of-resilience-and-hope/">A journey of resilience and hope</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="480" height="270" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Joshua-Abelson3-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-397571" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Joshua-Abelson3-16x9-1.jpg 480w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Joshua-Abelson3-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 480px) 100vw, 480px">



<p>Joshua Abelson, a 63-year-old aviation sales and supply chain professional, has faced numerous health challenges with remarkable resilience. Originally from Fort Worth, Texas, Joshua now resides in Jacksonville, Florida, where he continues to inspire others with his story.</p>



<p>Joshua's transplant journey began in 2009 when he first noticed symptoms that led to a diagnosis of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/interstitial-lung-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20353108" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">interstitial lung disease (ILD)</a>, specifically pulmonary fibrosis, after numerous X-rays and scans. This diagnosis marked the start of a long and arduous battle with his health.</p>



<p>After his initial diagnosis, Joshua says, "Nothing really changed, and I was living my normal life, traveling the world for business, playing golf regularly and taking my wife dancing."</p>



<p>In 2016, Joshua experienced a spontaneous <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/pneumothorax/symptoms-causes/syc-20350367" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pneumothorax</a> in his left lung, which required a 10-day hospital stay to reinflate and stabilize his lung. The incident was a significant setback, but Joshua's determination never wavered. "After that, I resumed my normal activities again," he says.</p>



<p>Early 2020 brought another challenge when Joshua and several colleagues fell ill after a business trip to China. "I got sick, and while we weren't testing for COVID-19 yet, I believe I may have had it," he says. The illness further compromised his already fragile lungs. "After that, my lung function began decreasing, and I found I could not fly without supplemental oxygen," he says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Joshua-Abelson2-1x1-1-300x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-397569" style="width:314px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Joshua-Abelson2-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Joshua-Abelson2-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Joshua-Abelson2-1x1-1.jpg 480w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"></figure></div>


<p>In mid-2021, Joshua suffered a gallbladder attack and was hospitalized again. During this time, he was diagnosed with COVID-19, which further deteriorated his lung function, leading him to regularly rely on portable oxygen.</p>



<p>Despite those setbacks, Joshua and his wife moved to Jacksonville in late November 2023 for work. However, during a holiday visit to Texas in December 2023, he contracted pneumonia and spent several days in a Texas hospital.</p>



<p></p>



<p>Upon arriving back to Jacksonville, he made the decision to seek care at <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a>. "Living in Jacksonville, we knew we had two potential choices," says Joshua. "After doing our research and praying about it, we chose Mayo. I had my initial consultations. Everyone agreed I was a candidate, and the evaluation process started." After a thorough evaluation, he was added to the lung transplant waitlist.</p>



<p>"We feel that a patient's quality of life will improve significantly after transplant," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/baz-maher-a-m-d/bio-20534599?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Maher Baz</a>, division chair of Lung Failure and Transplantation at Mayo Clinic in Florida. "Because they're no longer on oxygen, they can be out and about, they can walk farther, they can go vacations and improve their survival."</p>



<p>Joshua received his lung transplant in August 2024. The lungs he received underwent <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/transplant-medicine/news/organ-perfusion-systems-a-boon-to-heart-and-lung-transplants/mac-20518585?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ex vivo lung perfusion (EVLP)</a> technology in which donor lungs are flushed and ventilated while being monitored in isolation. This process allows transplant programs to reevaluate lungs that would otherwise have been discarded. In collaboration with United Therapeutics, <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-and-united-therapeutics-to-increase-lungs-for-transplantation-in-new-building-dedicated-to-medical-discovery-innovation/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida introduced EVLP to its campus in 2019</a>.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Joshua-Abelson1-1x1-1-300x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-397566" style="width:288px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Joshua-Abelson1-1x1-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Joshua-Abelson1-1x1-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Joshua-Abelson1-1x1-1.jpg 480w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"></figure></div>


<p>"We have something called ex vivo lung perfusion, or EVLP," says Dr. Baz. "It is a setup where we put the donated lungs on a breathing machine and we circulate fluid in them. We test them for about three to four hours to make sure that they are good lungs. And that has increased our yield for transplantation. The benefit to the patient is a shorter waiting time because now we are identifying organs at a higher rate by using EVLP."</p>



<p>Today, Joshua's health has improved, and he dedicates his time to promoting organ donation awareness and supporting others on similar transplant journeys. "I feel great, and I am incredibly blessed," says Joshua. "I am in an international Facebook support group for patients and caregivers, so I have heard many stories of people who have had, and continue to have, issues from their transplant, meds and underlying conditions. I have not had any setbacks at this point. I think it's important to stress the need for prehab and rehab. Mayo provided a great opportunity for me to do both, which got me in the best shape possible before my transplant and made my recovery easier."</p>



<p>His story is a testament to the power of resilience and the importance of organ donation. Joshua's journey continues to inspire and offer hope to others facing similar health challenges. "I contacted Donate Life Florida and have now become a registered volunteer to promote organ donation awareness," he says.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-journey-of-resilience-and-hope/">A journey of resilience and hope</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Joshua-Abelson3-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/12/Joshua-Abelson3-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Maher Baz]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Patient Story]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Transplant]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Living kidney donation may be option for those with type 2 diabetes</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-living-kidney-donation-may-be-option-for-those-with-type-2-diabetes/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Susan Barber Lindquist]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 16:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Naim Issa]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=396876</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->DEAR MAYO CLINIC:&nbsp;I was surprised to learn that even though I have&nbsp;type 2 diabetes,&nbsp;I possibly could be a candidate to donate a kidney to my husband who has&nbsp;end-stage kidney disease. Would donating a kidney be safe for me and my husband? I thought diabetes could cause kidney failure.&nbsp; ANSWER:&nbsp;Thank you for considering the gift of […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-living-kidney-donation-may-be-option-for-those-with-type-2-diabetes/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Living kidney donation may be option for those with type 2 diabetes</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image"-->
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/an-older-man-and-woman-smiling-and-listening-together-to-a-cell-phone-16X9-1024x576.jpg" alt="an older man and woman smiling and listening together to a cell phone" class="wp-image-177012" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/an-older-man-and-woman-smiling-and-listening-together-to-a-cell-phone-16X9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/an-older-man-and-woman-smiling-and-listening-together-to-a-cell-phone-16X9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/11/an-older-man-and-woman-smiling-and-listening-together-to-a-cell-phone-16X9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>


<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong>&nbsp;I was surprised to learn that even though I have&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/type-2-diabetes/symptoms-causes/syc-20351193">type 2 diabetes</a>,&nbsp;I possibly could be a candidate to donate a kidney to my husband who has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/end-stage-renal-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20354532">end-stage kidney disease</a>. Would donating a kidney be safe for me and my husband? I thought diabetes could cause kidney failure.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong>&nbsp;Thank you for considering the gift of life through organ donation. I am wishing all the best to you and your husband.&nbsp;</p>



<p>You are correct; diabetes is the top cause of kidney failure. This is why patients with type 2 diabetes previously were ruled out as potential&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/living-donor-kidney-transplant/pyc-20384838">living kidney donors</a>. However, the&nbsp;<a href="https://optn.transplant.hrsa.gov/">Organ Procurement and Transplantation Network</a>&nbsp;updated its&nbsp;<a href="https://optn.transplant.hrsa.gov/media/d2hlvxv1/policy-notice_modify-ld-excl-crit_ldc.pdf">living donor criteria</a>&nbsp;to&nbsp;allow people with type 2 diabetes to donate a kidney if there is no evidence of organ damage or an unacceptable lifetime risk of complications.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The major benefit of this policy change is to open up the door for those who would like to be living kidney donors who could not be donors in the past. This can increase the pool of potential living kidney donors and be a lifeline to many people who suffer from end-stage kidney disease.&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/home/orc-20203891?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">Mayo Clinic Transplant Center</a>&nbsp;also adopted its own more stringent policies to minimize potential risks. In addition to national criteria, Mayo Clinic patients with type 2 diabetes also must meet the following criteria to be a donor:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Be age 60 or older.</li>



<li>Have well-controlled diabetes and not use insulin.</li>



<li>If over age 65, can be using up to two oral medications for diabetes.</li>



<li>Not be overweight.</li>



<li>Have no family history of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/diabetic-nephropathy/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20354562?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">kidney disease</a>.</li>



<li>Undergo a thorough health assessment and individualized risk evaluation.</li>
</ul>



<p>People with&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/type-1-diabetes/symptoms-causes/syc-20353011">type 1 diabetes</a>, however, remain ineligible to be a living kidney donor.</p>



<p>About 89,000 people are on the U.S. waiting list for a kidney transplant, according to the&nbsp;<a href="https://unos.org/data/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">United Network for Organ Sharing</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Unfortunately, kidney disease usually is irreversible and continues to worsen over time. While some types of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/kidney-failure/symptoms-causes/syc-20369048#:~:text=Signs%20and%20symptoms%20of%20acute,Shortness%20of%20breath">acute kidney injury</a>&nbsp;may recover, in general,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/chronic-kidney-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20354521">chronic kidney disease</a>&nbsp;is a progressive disease that leads to dialysis or the need for a kidney transplant.</p>



<p>If someone is facing end-stage disease, one option is to go through dialysis, which temporarily replaces kidney function. That can be done through the blood, called&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/hemodialysis/about/pac-20384824">hemodialysis</a>, or through the abdomen, called&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/peritoneal-dialysis/about/pac-20384725">peritoneal dialysis</a>. However, a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/kidney-transplant/about/pac-20384777">kidney transplant</a>&nbsp;is the gold standard treatment because studies show transplant patients live longer and have a better quality of life than those on dialysis.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Receiving a living kidney donation also typically is faster than a deceased donor kidney, with arrangements taking weeks to months for a living kidney donation compared with an average wait of several years for a deceased donor kidney.&nbsp;Research has shown that people who receive a kidney from a living donor kidney have better outcomes than those who have a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/deceased-donor-kidney-transplant/pyc-20384834">deceased-donor kidney transplant</a>.</p>



<p>Kidney transplant surgery is done through a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/kidney-transplant/laparoscopic-donor-nephrectomy/gnc-20203227#:~:text=In%20laparoscopic%20donor%20nephrectomy%2C%20surgeons,using%20his%20or%20her%20hand.">minimally invasive, laparoscopic approach</a>&nbsp;through small incisions in your abdomen using surgical instruments and a thin tube with a camera on the end called a laparoscope. Patients typically have a short hospital stay and less pain than after an open surgery. Many donors return to work and their activities a few weeks after donating a kidney. —&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/issa-naim-s-m-d/bio-20235178">Naim Issa, M.D.</a>, Nephrology, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-living-kidney-donation-may-be-option-for-those-with-type-2-diabetes/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Living kidney donation may be option for those with type 2 diabetes</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/08/older-couple-man-and-woman-hiking-using-hiking-sticks-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/08/older-couple-man-and-woman-hiking-using-hiking-sticks-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Naim Issa]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>(VIDEO) Derek’s story: Just another face in the crowd</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-dereks-story-just-another-face-in-the-crowd/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Jason Howland]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 12:33:34 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Cycle]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Derek Pfaff]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Samir Mardini]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[face transplant]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Jason Howland]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=396382</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->A 30-year-old Michigan man can smell, swallow, blink and smile for the first time in a decade thanks to a face transplant at Mayo Clinic. In the last 20 years, just a little more than 50 face transplants have been performed worldwide. This is the second face transplant completed at Mayo Clinic. For Derek Pfaff, […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-dereks-story-just-another-face-in-the-crowd/">(VIDEO) Derek’s story: Just another face in the crowd</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-Pfaff-against-building-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-396679" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-Pfaff-against-building-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-Pfaff-against-building-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-Pfaff-against-building-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-Pfaff-against-building-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-Pfaff-against-building-16x9-1-2048x1153.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>A 30-year-old Michigan man can smell, swallow, blink and smile for the first time in a decade thanks to a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/face-transplant/about/pac-20394037?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">face transplant</a> at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>In the last 20 years, just a little more than 50 face transplants have been performed worldwide. This is the second face transplant completed at Mayo Clinic.</p>



<p>For Derek Pfaff, the transformational surgery has been life-changing.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/Nkr8xkHiKQM" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Derek Pfaff's story</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeNkr8xkHiKQM" title="Derek's story: Just another face in the crowd" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Nkr8xkHiKQM?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (6:32) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-Pfaff-Face-Transplant_FINAL.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></strong></p>



<p>On the shore of Lake Huron in a small town with just one traffic light, everybody knows everybody in Harbor Beach, Michigan. A decade ago, the face of Derek Pfaff was well-known in this tight-knit community.</p>



<p>"He was kind of that hometown hero," says Lisa Pfaff, Derek's mother.</p>



<p>The son of Jerry and Lisa Pfaff, Derek was a straight-A student and captain and star running back on the school's only state championship football team.</p>



<p>On the night of March 5, 2014, Derek, then 19, was home from college on spring break when he decided to take his own life.</p>



<p>"I looked across, and the gun cabinet was open … I just … my heart dropped," says Jerry Pfaff, Derek's father.</p>



<p>"He does not remember getting the gun. He does not remember going outside. He does not remember shooting himself," says Lisa. "We met with the doctors, and they told us that there was no way Derek was going to make it."</p>



<p>But Derek did survive. "It's a miracle he lived," Lisa says.</p>



<p>However, most of his face was gone.</p>



<p>"I should have died that night. I'm thankful to be alive," Derek says.</p>



<p>Thankful to be alive, but after 10 years and 58 reconstructive surgeries, what remains of Derek's face is unrecognizable. He has only one eye and is unable to blink. He struggles with speaking and breathing normally, and no longer has a sense of smell. He can't chew or swallow food, and uses a feeding tube to eat.</p>



<p>"After my last surgery, the doctor told my parents that there's nothing more he could do except refer us to a place to get a face transplant," Derek says.</p>



<p>Ultimately, that place would be <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> in Rochester, Minnesota.</p>



<p>"The thought of this surgery is our ray of hope," Lisa says. </p>



<p>"Life-changing for him," Jerry says.</p>



<p>It's a second chance at life for Derek.</p>



<p>"The heart is a lifesaving operation. The kidney, for the most part, is a lifesaving operation. With facial transplantation, it's a life-giving operation. You can live without it, but you're missing out on life," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mardini-samir-m-d/bio-20054870?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Samir Mardini</a>, surgical director of Mayo Clinic's <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/face-transplant/sections/overview/ovc-20564882?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Reconstructive Transplant Program</a>. "Face transplant is a rare surgery. There are only a few teams around the world that are doing them."</p>



<p>Derek's surgery is Mayo Clinic's second face transplant and its most complex and extensive procedure to date. A face transplant replaces all or part of the face with donor tissue. Dr. Mardini estimates 85% of Derek's face needed to be replaced.</p>



<p>"In Derek's case, the donor tissue included part of the forehead, the upper and lower eyelids on the right side, the nose, the mouth, the upper and lower jaws — including the teeth — as well as all of the skin, muscles and nerves of the entire face and neck," says Dr. Mardini.</p>



<p>The most meticulous part of this complex surgery is reconnecting the many small nerves between Derek and the donor to ensure function, like eating, blinking and even smiling, is restored.</p>



<p>In extensive preparation for Derek's surgery, the face transplant team spent nearly nine months, including many weekends, rehearsing the procedure. Detailed scans of the face allowed the team to practice the surgery virtually. The latest technology in medical modeling and 3D printing also played a vital role in the planning and execution of the surgery.</p>



<p>"The restorative nature of the facial transplant makes it very complex," says Dr. Mardini.</p>



<p>In February 2024, a donor becomes available. Six surgeons and a multidisciplinary medical staff numbering more than 80 complete a surgical marathon lasting nearly two and a half days.</p>



<p>"We're trying to give Derek back functions he was missing for 10 years," says Dr. Mardini.</p>



<p>Still healing nearly a month after surgery — and 10 years to the day of his suicide attempt — Derek gets the first glimpse of his new face. In the months to follow, Derek has additional surgeries to refine his appearance, improve his tongue and eyelid function, and ensure the connection of nerves is working properly.</p>



<p>"This is not an aesthetic operation, although the side benefits of it are hugely beneficial for the aesthetics of the patient," says Dr. Mardini. "Derek is looking to be normal. He's looking to walk on the street and not have anyone notice anything on him."</p>



<p>As he approaches a new year in 2025, Derek is just another face in the crowd now — with a new smile.</p>



<p>"It makes my heart so full to see him smile and happy and just be a normal person again," Lisa says.</p>



<p>"It's been 10 years since you've seen a nose, lips and teeth on your son — just totally amazing, a miracle," Jerry says.</p>



<p>"It wasn't just Derek's face that was given. It was his other organs as well. So there were multiple recipients tied to that one donor, and that is the greatest gift that someone can make the courage and the decision to do," Lisa says.</p>



<p>Because of that donor's gift, Derek, now 30 years old, is ready to start the next chapter in his life.</p>



<p>"One day, meet someone, start a family," Derek says.</p>



<p>And he has found purpose as a public speaker for suicide prevention.</p>



<p>"Talk to someone. Tell them how you're feeling," Derek says.</p>



<p>"He's received so many letters that it's kind of like his calling now to continue to impact people and share," Lisa says.</p>



<p>"Hearing their stories and how I helped them, makes me feel pretty good," Derek says. "I lived for a reason. I want to help others anyway I can."</p>



<p><strong>Related content:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-performs-successful-face-transplant-restoring-vital-functions-for-michigan-man/">Mayo Clinic performs successful face transplant, restoring vital functions for Michigan man</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/transforming-a-life-mayo-clinic-announces-its-first-face-transplant/">Transforming a life: Mayo Clinic announces its first face transplant</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayos-first-face-transplant-patient-meets-donors-family/">Mayo’s first face transplant patient meets donor’s family</a></li>
</ul>



<p> &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/video-dereks-story-just-another-face-in-the-crowd/">(VIDEO) Derek’s story: Just another face in the crowd</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-Pfaff-against-building-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-Pfaff-against-building-Smaller-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Derek Pfaff]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Samir Mardini]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[face transplant]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Jason Howland]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic performs successful face transplant, restoring vital functions for Michigan man</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-performs-successful-face-transplant-restoring-vital-functions-for-michigan-man/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Heather Carlson Kehren]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 12:30:14 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Derek Pfaff]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[diverserepresentation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Hatem Amer]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Samir Mardini]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[face transplant]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=396692</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->ROCHESTER, Minn. — A Michigan man can blink, swallow, smile and breathe through his nose for the first time in a decade thanks to a face transplant performed at&nbsp;Mayo Clinic. This transformative and complex procedure underscores Mayo Clinic's skilled multidisciplinary surgical team who provide hope to patients with complex medical needs. Derek Pfaff's life changed […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-performs-successful-face-transplant-restoring-vital-functions-for-michigan-man/">Mayo Clinic performs successful face transplant, restoring vital functions for Michigan man</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-center-align-caption"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-post-face-transplant-pier-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Man standing at pier after his face transplant" class="wp-image-396703" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-post-face-transplant-pier-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-post-face-transplant-pier-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-post-face-transplant-pier-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-post-face-transplant-pier-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-post-face-transplant-pier-16-x-9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px">



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A Michigan man can blink, swallow, smile and breathe through his nose for the first time in a decade thanks to a face transplant performed at&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>. This transformative and complex procedure underscores Mayo Clinic's skilled multidisciplinary surgical team who provide hope to patients with complex medical needs.</p>



<p>Derek Pfaff's life changed forever on March 5, 2014, when a tragic incident during his college years left his face severely damaged by a gunshot.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"I was under a lot of pressure at college. I don't remember making the decision to take my own life. When I woke up in the hospital, I originally thought I had been in a car accident," he says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Despite undergoing 58 reconstructive facial surgeries in 10 years before going to Mayo Clinic in Rochester, he was still unable to eat solid food or speak casually with friends and family. Wearing glasses proved impossible without a nose. This transformational face transplant at Mayo Clinic means the now 30-year-old from Harbor Beach, Michigan, will once again be able to do all those things he has missed. He has also become a passionate advocate for suicide prevention and plans to share his story to encourage others who are struggling to get help.</p>



<p>"I lived for a reason. I want to help others," Pfaff says. "I am so grateful to my donor, his family and my care team at Mayo Clinic for giving me this second chance."</p>



<p>"Mayo Clinic Transplant Center is the largest integrated transplant center in the world. We were the first transplant center in the country to make face transplant part of its clinical practice. That has allowed us to focus exclusively on the needs of each individual patient," says&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/amer-hatem-m-d/bio-20055017" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hatem Amer, M.D.</a>, medical director of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/reconstructive-transplant-surgery/gnc-20203916#:~:text=Reconstructive%20transplant%20surgeons%20at%20Mayo,by%20restoring%20appearance%20and%20function." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic's Reconstructive Transplant Program</a>.</p>



<p>In the 19 years since the first face transplant was performed, more than 50 have been done around the world. Survival outcomes for these transplants are encouraging, according to a recent&nbsp;<a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamasurgery/fullarticle/2823888" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">JAMA Surgery study</a>. Mayo Clinic&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-announces-successful-face-transplant-on-wyoming-man/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">performed its first face transplant</a>&nbsp;in 2016.</p>



<p><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=396382&amp;preview=true" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Derek's story: Just another face in the crowd</strong></a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How the surgery was done&nbsp;</h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic surgeons performed Pfaff's face transplant in February 2024 in a procedure that lasted more than 50 hours and involved a medical team comprised of at least 80 healthcare professionals, including surgeons, anesthesiologists, nurses, technicians, assistants and other specialists.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This multidisciplinary team was led by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mardini-samir-m-d/bio-20054870" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Samir Mardini, M.D.</a>, a facial reconstructive and facial reanimation surgeon and surgical director of Mayo Clinic's Reconstructive Transplant Program. Dr. Mardini estimates that 85% of Pfaff's face, including the mandible and maxilla, was reconstructed and&nbsp;replaced with donor tissue.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Surgeons meticulously planned this complex operation over several months. To ensure precision and accuracy, a digital surgical plan was created relying on detailed scans of both the donor's and recipient's faces, allowing the team to perform the surgery digitally first. Facial nerve mapping also was performed of both the donor and recipient's nerve system to understand the function of each nerve. While the digital aspect ensured preparation, customized 3D-printed cutting guides translated these plans into tangible tools to be used in the surgical suite.</p>



<p>The intricate transplant required replacing virtually everything below Pfaff's eyebrows and part of his forehead, including his upper and lower eyelids and intraorbital fat, upper and lower jaws, teeth, nose, cheek structure, neck skin, hard palate and parts of his soft palate. Relying on the preoperative facial nerve mapping, one of the most critical aspects of the face transplant surgery was ensuring the donor and recipient's delicate facial nerves — 18 branches between the two sides — were properly connected to restore function. A new microsurgery technique also was employed to transplant the donor's tear drainage system, which allows Pfaff's tears to drain normally into his new nose. Pfaff can now express happiness, sadness, joy and disappointment through his transplanted facial muscles and nerves.</p>



<p>"Most organ transplants are lifesaving. With facial transplantation, it's a life-giving operation. You can live without it, but you are missing out on life," Dr. Mardini says.</p>



<p>The medical team included specialists from Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, Transplant, Nephrology, Neurology, Ophthalmology, Dermatology, Pathology, Radiology, Critical Care, Anesthesia, Psychiatry, Infectious Diseases, Histocompatibility, Pharmacy, Nursing, Social Work, Rehabilitation, and Speech and Language Pathology.</p>



<p>"This successful transplant would not have been possible without the donor and his family's generous gift and the care team's collaboration and dedication," Dr. Mardini adds.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.life-source.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">LifeSource</a>, the federally designated organ procurement organization for the Upper Midwest, also played a pivotal role in the transplant, working closely with the&nbsp;family of the donor and Mayo Clinic care teams. Thanks to his face transplant, Pfaff says he is focused on making plans for his future.</p>



<p>"This surgery has transformed my life. I feel so much more confident. I am hoping to one day meet someone, settle down and have a family," he says. "I'm also going to keep sharing my story with others to help as many people as I can."</p>



<p><em>If you or someone you know is experiencing a mental health crisis, you can call the&nbsp;</em><a href="https://988lifeline.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>National Suicide Prevention Lifeline</em></a><em>&nbsp;at 988.&nbsp;</em></p>



<p><strong>Journalists:</strong> <strong>Press kit, including b-roll, photos, interviews and animation available&nbsp;<a href="https://mcmedia.mayo.edu/Share/7q23n68r4745qc36f03x63xd3a7sl3x7?FR_=1&amp;W=925&amp;H=846" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>.</strong> <strong>Derek Pfaff, his mother Lisa Pfaff and Dr. Samir Mardini are available for interviews. Please  contact&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a>&nbsp;to schedule.</strong></p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a>&nbsp;is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Heather Carlson Kehren, Mayo Clinic Communications,&nbsp;<a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-performs-successful-face-transplant-restoring-vital-functions-for-michigan-man/">Mayo Clinic performs successful face transplant, restoring vital functions for Michigan man</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-post-face-transplant-pier-1-x-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Derek-post-face-transplant-pier-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Derek Pfaff]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[diverserepresentation]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Hatem Amer]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Samir Mardini]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[face transplant]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[News Releases]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute:&nbsp; Battling barriers to transplant surgery</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-battling-barriers-to-transplant-surgery/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Sonya Goins]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Dr. Shennen Mao]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395219</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->Each year, there are thousands of people waiting for a kidney or liver transplant in the U.S. Some of those transplant candidates are living with diabetes, high blood pressure or obesity, which can sometimes complicate transplant surgery. Dr. Shennen Mao, a Mayo Clinic transplant surgeon, offers advice on preparing patients for the lifesaving operations. Watch: […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-battling-barriers-to-transplant-surgery/">Mayo Clinic Minute:&nbsp; Battling barriers to transplant surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<p-->Each year, there are thousands of people waiting for a kidney or liver transplant in the U.S. Some of those transplant candidates are living with diabetes, high blood pressure or obesity, which can sometimes complicate transplant surgery.<p></p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mao-shennen-a-m-d/bio-20439463?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Shennen Mao</a>, a Mayo Clinic <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/home/orc-20203891?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">transplant</a> surgeon, offers advice on preparing patients for the lifesaving operations.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/12Ec8VFBBJU" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutube12Ec8VFBBJU" title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Battling barriers to transplant surgery" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/12Ec8VFBBJU?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:06) is in the downloads at the end of the post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/battling-barriers-to-transplant-surgery.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script.</a></strong></p>



<p>Obesity often plays a significant role in a patient's transplant journey. Excess body weight can contribute to type 2 diabetes and hypertension, which can cause harm to vital organs.</p>



<p>"Obesity can also lead to worsening or progression of kidney failure and worse outcomes after either liver or kidney transplant,” says Dr. Mao.</p>



<p>She says it's important that healthcare professionals give patients the tools they need to manage obesity before undergoing liver and kidney transplant operations.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Obesity-health-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="A man with obesity wearing red shirt getting his blood pressure checked," class="wp-image-392104" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Obesity-health-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Obesity-health-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Obesity-health-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/07/Obesity-health-16-x-9.jpg 1479w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Planning for transplant surgery.</figcaption></figure>



<p>&nbsp;"This could include medications, dietary counseling and, in some cases, partnership with our bariatric surgical colleagues to perform bariatric surgery either at the time of transplant or in preparation for transplant,” says Dr. Mao.</p>



<p>Injectable diet drugs are an option for some people, while others might opt for surgery.</p>



<p>“We typically recommend a sleeve gastrectomy, which is a restrictive procedure, meaning it limits the amount of food an individual can eat at one time,” she says.</p>



<p>Eating a nutritious, well-balanced diet and exercising regularly can improve transplant outcomes.</p>



<p><strong>Related Posts</strong>:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-diverse-organ-donors-are-needed/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Why diverse organ donors are needed</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/innovative-program-enables-patients-who-are-obese-to-get-kidney-transplants/">Innovative program enables patients who are obese to get kidney transplants</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-breaking-barriers-for-patients-who-need-kidney-transplants/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">Mayo Clinic Minute: Breaking barriers for patients who need kidney transplants</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-battling-barriers-to-transplant-surgery/">Mayo Clinic Minute:&nbsp; Battling barriers to transplant surgery</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Paired-Liver-Transplant2-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2016/11/childs-feet-on-a-scale-16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[daily]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Dr. Shennen Mao]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>(VIDEO) Harnessing the power of innovation and a patient’s will to survive</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/videoharnessing-the-power-of-innovation-and-a-patients-will-to-survive/
		
		<dc:creator><!--[CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]--></dc:creator>
		<pubdate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 19:30:00 +0000</pubdate>
				<category><!--[CDATA[Arizona]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Diversity]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Featured News]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Health & Wellness]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Healthcare Delivery]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Medical Innovation]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Video]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]--></category>
		<category><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></category>
		<guid ispermalink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=395496</guid>

					<description><!--[CDATA[<p-->At 27 years old, Shraddha Kalgutkar was told she had less than a year to live. Determined to prove everyone wrong, she turned to Mayo Clinic in Arizona. Now Shraddha is living proof of the power of innovation combined with a patient's will to survive. Watch: Harnessing the power of innovation and a patient's will […]<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/videoharnessing-the-power-of-innovation-and-a-patients-will-to-survive/">(VIDEO) Harnessing the power of innovation and a patient’s will to survive</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><!--[CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"--><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Close-up-of-shraddha-on-ECMO_16x9-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395836" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Close-up-of-shraddha-on-ECMO_16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Close-up-of-shraddha-on-ECMO_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Close-up-of-shraddha-on-ECMO_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Close-up-of-shraddha-on-ECMO_16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Close-up-of-shraddha-on-ECMO_16x9-2048x1152.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong><mark style="background-color:#ffffff" class="has-inline-color has-black-color">Shraddha Kaltgutar at Mayo Clinic in Phoenix, AZ</mark></strong></figcaption>



<p>At 27 years old, Shraddha Kalgutkar was told she had less than a year to live. Determined to prove everyone wrong, she turned to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> in Arizona.</p>



<p>Now Shraddha is living proof of the power of innovation combined with a patient's will to survive.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LlFER2E3OEo" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Watch: Harnessing the power of innovation and a patient's will to survive</strong></a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidLlFER2E3OEo" title="Harnessing the power of innovation and a patient's will to survive" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/LlFER2E3OEo?feature=oembed&amp;enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video (4:03) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/11/Shraddhas-story.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a></strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Shraddha's Story</strong></h2>



<p>It was November 2022, just a month shy of her 28th birthday.</p>



<p>Shraddha was wrapping up another day at the medical clinic where she worked as an occupational therapist. Shraddha's job was to help patients regain the ability to perform day-to-day activities following a health challenge like a surgery.</p>



<p>Suddenly that afternoon, Shraddha became the patient who needed help.</p>



<p>"My co-worker looked at me and said, 'Why is your hand all purple and blue?'" Shraddha says. She admits she had been feeling exceptionally tired as of late, but attributed it to a thyroid condition.</p>



<p>Her co-worker checked Shraddha's vital signs and found her blood oxygen level was dangerously low. "I remember her saying, 'If this is right, you wouldn't even be standing.'" A repeat test showed the same result. "The next thing I remember was we were on our way to the hospital," says Shraddha.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="822" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach-822x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395502" style="width:650px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach-822x1024.jpg 822w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach-241x300.jpg 241w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach-768x957.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach-1233x1536.jpg 1233w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach-1643x2048.jpg 1643w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach.jpg 1812w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 822px) 100vw, 822px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><mark style="background-color:#ffffff" class="has-inline-color has-black-color"><strong>Shraddha enjoying the California coastline two years after surviving a condition that nearly took her life</strong></mark></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>At the hospital doctors began looking for the cause of Shraddha's low blood oxygen level.  A series of tests traced Shraddha's condition all the way back to the day she was born.</p>



<p>"When I was born, doctors said I had fatty liver, but they didn't know why so they called it 'undiagnosed,'" says Shraddha. "The doctors thought it wouldn't be a problem because the liver has a tendency to heal itself." It didn't. Shraddha grew up seemingly in perfect health, unaware that her <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/the-silent-liver-disease-experts-warn-is-on-the-rise-among-hispanics-and-children/">liver disease</a> was silently doing damage to her body.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A little girl with a big dream</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="226" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-little-girl-pic-1-226x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395820" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-little-girl-pic-1-226x300.jpg 226w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-little-girl-pic-1-771x1024.jpg 771w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-little-girl-pic-1-768x1019.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-little-girl-pic-1.jpg 1054w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 226px) 100vw, 226px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Shraddah at 5 years old in her childhood home in Mumbai, India</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Shraddha was born in Mumbai, India which is often called the "City of Dreams." At a young age, Shraddha had big dreams of her own.  She wanted to pursue a career in the medical field that would allow her to help others. </p>



<p>Every year Shraddha went to the doctor for her routine physical. Each time she was given a clean bill of health. "I used to do blood tests, but everything always looked good," says Shraddha. Still, the question of what caused her congenital liver condition lingered in her mind.</p>



<p>"I didn't have a family history of any liver condition. I've never had alcohol in my life," says Shraddha. "There was always a question mark. I needed to find out why this happened to me."</p>



<p>At 23, Shraddha became the first person in her family to leave India and go to the U.S. to attend college. She studied occupational therapy and got her master's degree at the University of Southern California. After college, Shraddha found her dream job at a medical clinic in California.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">'<strong>You have less than a year to live</strong>'</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="799" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-sad-1024x799.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395512" style="width:719px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-sad-1024x799.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-sad-300x234.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-sad-768x599.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-sad-1536x1199.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-sad.jpg 1848w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure></div>


<p>All was going well until Shraddha began to noticed she was unusually tired. "When my sister came to visit she noticed I got tired after walking short distances. I went to the doctor and they thought maybe it was my thyroid," recalls Shraddha.</p>



<p>Then came the day her hands turned purple and her blood oxygen level mysteriously dropped. "My co-worker is a nurse so she got the oximeter and checked and it was 78%," says Shraddha. "And I was like, No, that's not possible because I wouldn't be alive." Shraddha's co-worker checked again, looked at the reading and said, "That's it, you have to go to the hospital."</p>



<p>A series of tests at the hospital revealed shocking results. Shraddha's liver condition had silently led to a more serious condition called hepatopulmonary syndrome.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Hepatopulmonary syndrome</strong></h2>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hepatopulmonary-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20373350" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hepatopulmonary syndrome</a> is caused when liver disease shunts blood away from the lungs preventing the body from getting the appropriate amount of oxygen. Doctors told Shraddha the only way she would survive is with a liver transplant. However, she says she was told her condition was so severe and the risk so high, that she would likely not survive a transplant.</p>



<p>She was denied the transplant and given less than a year to live.</p>



<p>"I told the doctors 'that just can't be. I can't have just one year with nothing to bring to this world. I have not served my purpose,'" recalls Shraddha. </p>



<p>Refusing to give up, Shraddha turned to Mayo Clinic in Arizona.</p>



<p>"More than 40% of her blood was being shunted away from her lungs. Because of that she had extremely low oxygen levels in her blood," explains <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/aqel-bashar-a-m-d/bio-20055093" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bashar Aqel, M.D.</a>, director of the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/sections/expertise-ranking/orc-20203899?customer_id=173-378-9621&amp;mc_id=google&amp;campaign=20718088499&amp;geo=9030070&amp;kw=transplant%20center%20arizona&amp;ad=678670770145&amp;network=g&amp;sitetarget=&amp;adgroup=158054873227&amp;extension=&amp;target=kwd-1284412548384&amp;matchtype=p&amp;device=c&amp;account=1733789621&amp;invsrc=transplant&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;gclid=EAIaIQobChMI1bPG-JO5iQMVrjYIBR0f-AKlEAAYASAAEgKkU_D_BwE" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Transplant Center at Mayo Clinic in Arizona.</a> "Shraddha's case was one of the most severe cases of liver disease and hepatopulmonary syndrome."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="205" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Aqel-talking-about-Shraddha-300x205.png" alt="" class="wp-image-395516" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Aqel-talking-about-Shraddha-300x205.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Aqel-talking-about-Shraddha-1024x701.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Aqel-talking-about-Shraddha-768x526.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Aqel-talking-about-Shraddha-1536x1052.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Aqel-talking-about-Shraddha-2048x1403.png 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Bashar Aqel, M.D., Director, Mayo Clinic Transplant Center in Arizona</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Saving Shraddha</strong></h2>



<p>The liver transplant was Shraddha's only hope for survival. "Without a transplant, this disease was progressive and fatal. We don't like to use this word, but it is a very progressive disease," says Dr. Aqel. "There was no other cure than a liver transplant."</p>



<p>Dr. Aqel and his multidisciplinary team of experts at Mayo Clinic went to work on a strategy to save Shraddha. The team came up with a plan using a combination of some of the latest cutting-edge technologies in medicine. </p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">"<strong>Liver in a box</strong>"</h2>



<p>Transplanting any organ is a race agains the clock. Every second the donor organ is outside the body it begins to break down. Surgeons only have a limited time window to transplant the organ. Due to the complexity of Shraddha's case, Dr. Aqel's team knew they would need extra time. They decided to use one of the latest medical breakthroughs in transplant often referred to as <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-liver-in-a-box-is-saving-lives-with-new-technology/">"liver in a box."</a></p>



<p>Traditionally donor organs are kept cold until transplanted. "Liver in a box" uses a warm organ preservation method. The organ is placed in a container that pumps oxygenated, nutrient-rich blood through the liver simulating conditions in the human body. The innovative perfusion system gives surgeons more time to perform the transplant. </p>



<p>"Having the donor "liver in a box" allowed the donor liver to stay healthy while we performed this complex surgery," says Dr. Aqel.</p>



<p>Currently, this warm perfusion technology is primarily being used for <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-innovation-new-heart-in-a-box-technology-provides-gift-of-life-to-arizona-man-as-couple-prepares-to-celebrate-50-year-anniversary/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">heart, lungs and liver transplants</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Liver-In-a-box-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395567" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Liver-In-a-box-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Liver-In-a-box-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Liver-In-a-box-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Liver-In-a-box-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Liver-In-a-box-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">"<strong>Liver in a box" safely preserves donor organ at body temperature until transplant</strong></figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Saving lives with mobile ECMO</strong></h2>



<p>The next challenge was how to keep Shraddha's blood oxygen levels stable after her transplant. Dr. Aqel's team turned to a device called <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/young-patient-with-covid-19-recovering-after-hospital-stay-ecmo-support/">extracorporeal membrane oxygenation, or ECMO</a>. The device often is used when the lungs aren't working properly. ECMO helps with the appropriate gas exchange that must occur to keep the body's blood oxygen level safe.</p>



<p>"It helps in getting oxygen into the blood and carbon dioxide out of the blood through the machine," explains <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/sen-ayan-m-d/bio-20055718" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ayan Sen, M.D.</a>, medical director of Mayo Clinic's Intensive Care Unit in Arizona. "It helped us while her lungs recovered after her transplant."</p>



<p>The Mayo team also used one of the newest advancements in ECMO where the device is mobile. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="723" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-mobile-ECMO-3-723x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395506" style="width:558px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-mobile-ECMO-3-723x1024.jpg 723w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-mobile-ECMO-3-212x300.jpg 212w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-mobile-ECMO-3-768x1088.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-mobile-ECMO-3.jpg 826w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 723px) 100vw, 723px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Shraddha walking on mobile ECMO on December 24, 2022</strong> <strong>- her 28th birthday</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"The best part of the mobile ECMO was that we do it in a way where she could actually walk around with the machine so that we could continue with her physical therapy, which is so important for the healing process after such a complex surgery," says Dr. Sen.</p>



<p>Shraddha was in the ICU for nearly two months. With mobile ECMO she walked nearly every day.</p>



<p>Dr. Sen says mobile ECMO has proved to be a game-changer in critical cases like Shraddha's.</p>



<p>"It is technology that has really expanded from what surgeons do when they do heart surgeries and transplants where now we can do this to save lives at any place that is not a complex environment, like the ICU or the operating rooms," explains Dr. Sen.</p>



<p>Mobile ECMO has become a lifesaving medical breakthrough for many patients.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="178" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Sen-close-up-headshot-300x178.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-395520" style="width:312px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Sen-close-up-headshot-300x178.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Sen-close-up-headshot-1024x607.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Sen-close-up-headshot-768x455.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Sen-close-up-headshot-1536x910.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Dr.-Sen-close-up-headshot-2048x1214.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Ayan Sen, M.D., Medical Director, Intensive Care Unit at Mayo Clinic in Arizona</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"It has enabled us to raise the bar when it comes to saving people, who, until now, could not have been saved in the absence of this heart-lung machine," says Dr. Sen.</p>



<p>A team of highly specialized experts escorted Shraddha on her daily walks, meticulously monitoring her vital signs. Each step required Shraddha to muster every bit of strength she had.</p>



<p>"From the first day, I thought even if it pains me, if it hurts, even if it feels impossible, I still need to put that step forward to do something better today than yesterday," recalls Shraddha. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p><strong>"I was in a race with myself every day"</strong></p><cite>-Shraddha</cite></blockquote></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>'Mayo's mission is now my purpose'</strong></h2>



<p>Almost two years after her harrowing experience, Shraddha is healthy and back at work. She continues her daily walks, only now, at the beach, in solitude, reflecting on how her own experience can make her a better healthcare professional.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="792" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-at-Mayo-792x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-395850" style="width:567px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-at-Mayo-792x1024.png 792w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-at-Mayo-232x300.png 232w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-at-Mayo-768x993.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-at-Mayo-1188x1536.png 1188w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-at-Mayo.png 1406w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 792px) 100vw, 792px"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Shraddha visiting Mayo Clinic after her lifesaving transplant</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Mayo Clinic doesn't like to say no. They set out to achieve the unachievable," says Shraddha. "My goal is to treat patients as they do, making them a priority."</p>



<p>Shraddha says words of thanks alone are not enough to convey her gratitude.</p>



<p>"Dr. Aqel and his team achieved something for me that everyone else thought was impossible," says Shraddha. "It was a gift. I will keep the mission of Mayo Clinic in mind when I am serving my patients. My purpose now is to put forward their purpose and help someone else."</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity">



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Related articles:</strong></h2>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-innovation-new-heart-in-a-box-technology-provides-gift-of-life-to-arizona-man-as-couple-prepares-to-celebrate-50-year-anniversary/">Heart Transplant Innovation: New ‘heart in a box’ technology provides gift of life to Arizona man, as couple prepares to celebrate 50-</a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-innovation-new-heart-in-a-box-technology-provides-gift-of-life-to-arizona-man-as-couple-prepares-to-celebrate-50-year-anniversary/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">year</a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-innovation-new-heart-in-a-box-technology-provides-gift-of-life-to-arizona-man-as-couple-prepares-to-celebrate-50-year-anniversary/"> anniversary</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-barriers-helping-native-americans-in-need-get-the-gift-of-life/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Breaking barriers: Helping Native Americans in need get the gift of life</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/organ-transplant-innovation-helping-more-people-get-the-gift-of-life/">Organ Transplant Innovation: Helping more people get the gift of life</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/videoharnessing-the-power-of-innovation-and-a-patients-will-to-survive/">(VIDEO) Harnessing the power of innovation and a patient’s will to survive</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/10/Shraddha-Still-shot-on-beach_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[#Newsapp]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Mayo Clinic]]--></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><!--[CDATA[Social Sensations]]--></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</atom:link></channel>
</rss> 