<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:mayoclinic="http://mayoclinic.org"
>

<channel>
	<title>Transplant - Mayo Clinic News Network</title>
	<atom:link href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/transplant/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/category/transplant/</link>
	<description>News Resources</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 16:07:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Researchers find promise in new potential treatment for liver failure</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/researchers-find-promise-in-new-potential-treatment-for-liver-failure/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Heather Carlson Kehren]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastroenterology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Scott Nyberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Liver Failure]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=384068</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A new drug has been shown to increase healing and regeneration of the liver after major surgery, according to a study published in the scientific journal Cell. Researchers hope that this could lead to more surgical options for patients diagnosed with advanced liver tumors and liver failure. "This research is significant because [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/researchers-find-promise-in-new-potential-treatment-for-liver-failure/">Researchers find promise in new potential treatment for liver failure</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1000" height="563" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/03/illustration-of-diseased-liver-shutterstock_1118711141_16x9.jpg" alt="illustration of diseased liver" class="wp-image-232247" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/03/illustration-of-diseased-liver-shutterstock_1118711141_16x9.jpg 1000w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/03/illustration-of-diseased-liver-shutterstock_1118711141_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2019/03/illustration-of-diseased-liver-shutterstock_1118711141_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — A new drug has been shown to increase healing and regeneration of the liver after major surgery, according to a <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0092867424002253?via%3Dihub">study published in the scientific journal Cell</a>. Researchers hope that this could lead to more surgical options for patients diagnosed with advanced liver tumors and liver failure.</p>



<p>"This research is significant because this is the first drug of its kind to show an increase in healing and regeneration of the liver after major surgery," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/nyberg-scott-l-m-d-ph-d/bio-00027430" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Scott Nyberg, M.D., Ph.D.,</a> a Mayo Clinic transplant surgeon and co-senior author of the study. "This discovery has the potential to improve the treatment of liver failure, increase the safety of liver transplantation for living donors and potentially avoid the need for a liver transplant in some cases."</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic researchers collaborated with researchers at <a href="https://www.medizin.uni-tuebingen.de/en-de/das-klinikum" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tubingen University Hospital</a> in Germany, who led the <a href="https://www.medizin.uni-tuebingen.de/en-de/das-klinikum/pressemeldungen/628?press_str=">project</a>. "Our drug candidate would not only be an urgently needed treatment option in oncological liver surgery but, by enabling safe living donor liver transplantations, also holds the promise to overcome the major problem of organ shortage in the field of liver transplantation," says Lars Zender, M.D., Ph.D., co-senior author of the study from Tubingen.</p>



<p>Liver disease remains a major health concern, <a href="https://www.journal-of-hepatology.eu/article/S0168-8278(23)00194-0/fulltext#:~:text=Liver%20disease%20accounts%20for%20over,for%20600%2C000%20to%20900%2C000%20deaths." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">causing an estimated 2 million deaths</a> worldwide per year. While healthy livers have a nearly unlimited ability to regenerate themselves, that is not the case for livers that are damaged. As a result, surgeons treating a patient with primary liver tumors are limited in how large of a section of the liver can safely be removed to avoid liver failure.</p>



<p>The study found that a drug called HRX215 inhibits the MKK4 protein found in liver cells. That appears to trigger the self-healing function of the liver, allowing it to regenerate. Before the drug was tested in 48 healthy volunteers within the phase 1 study, it was investigated in animal models. The preclinical study was able to show that the use of HRX-215 increased liver regeneration and prevented liver failure, even after the removal of 85% of the organ. The phase 1 study found excellent safety and tolerability of the drug in people. Additional clinical trials are needed to establish the efficacy of the drug in humans.</p>



<p>Researchers are hopeful that this discovery will one day create more surgical options for patients with advanced liver tumors by allowing more of the liver to be safely removed. It also has the potential to benefit patients with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/acute-liver-failure/symptoms-causes/syc-20352863" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">acute and chronic liver failure.</a> This drug could potentially allow for successful <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/liver-transplant/care-at-mayo-clinic/pcc-20384845" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">liver transplants</a> from a smaller portion of a healthy donor's liver, and thus posing less risk to healthy donors. Often, this liver is too small to successfully take over the function of the full-sized liver removed from the recipient. The hope would be that this drug could allow for rapid liver regeneration, creating a new safe transplant option for people struggling with liver failure. This drug also could potentially eliminate the need for a liver transplant for some patients.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong></p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Heather Carlson Kehren, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/researchers-find-promise-in-new-potential-treatment-for-liver-failure/">Researchers find promise in new potential treatment for liver failure</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/liver-disease-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/05/liver-disease-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Scott Nyberg]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Liver Failure]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Transforming Transplant Initiative aspires to save lives through bioengineering</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/transforming-transplant-initiative-aspires-to-save-lives-through-bioengineering/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Buckles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biotherapeutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Burcin Taner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Wenchun Qu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[organ transplants]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=383047</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mayo Clinic is taking steps to bolster the medical marvel of transplantation while addressing the confounding problem of a critical shortage of donor organs. It created the Transforming Transplant Initiative with a bold goal of providing organ transplants for everyone who needs one. Another objective is to eliminate the waitlist that has grown to more [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/transforming-transplant-initiative-aspires-to-save-lives-through-bioengineering/">Transforming Transplant Initiative aspires to save lives through bioengineering</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="1920" height="1080" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Transforming-Transplant16x9.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-383615" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Transforming-Transplant16x9.jpg 1920w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Transforming-Transplant16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Transforming-Transplant16x9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Transforming-Transplant16x9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Transforming-Transplant16x9-1536x864.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" /></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is taking steps to bolster the medical marvel of transplantation while addressing the confounding problem of a critical shortage of donor organs. It created the <a href="https://college.mayo.edu/about/news/news-archive/faculty-feature-transforming-transplant-and-joining-forces-to-accelerate-discovery-to-practice/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Transforming Transplant Initiative</a> with a bold goal of providing organ transplants for everyone who needs one. Another objective is to eliminate the waitlist that has grown to more than 100,000 people in the U.S.</p>



<p>"My vision is to not just help one patient, but help the thousands who have end-stage organ failure get lifesaving transplants," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/taner-c-burcin-m-d/bio-00027293" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">C. Burcin Taner, M.D.</a>, a Mayo Clinic surgeon who leads the initiative. Dr. Taner is also the chair of the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/home/orc-20203891" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Department of Transplantation</a> at Mayo Clinic in Florida.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Addressing shortcomings of organ transplant</strong>s</h2>



<p>The Transforming Transplant Initiative was created as a collaboration between the Department of Transplantation and Mayo Clinic's <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/centers-programs/center-regenerative-biotherapeutics/about" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics</a>. The project seeks to overcome the shortcomings of transplantation, the greatest of which is the need for more organs. Researchers working to improve transplantation ask tough questions like, "Could we bioengineer organs to reduce or eliminate the wait list?"&nbsp; To answer that question, Mayo Clinic has formed a collaboration with Carnegie Mellon University, pairing medical expertise with engineering know-how to make experimental organs.</p>



<p>"Bioengineering new organs is promising, but complex. We're looking at a research timeline of 10-15 years to potentially bring this new option to patients," says Dr. Taner.</p>



<p>This bioengineering research brings together 3D bioprinting, tissue engineering, biomaterials and cellular materials to grow humanlike organs.</p>



<p>The research is focusing on nine different bioengineering projects ranging from better ways of monitoring the health of transplanted organs to engineering complex organs such as hearts, lungs, livers and kidneys.</p>



<p>The Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics is supporting the project with biomanufacturing, stem cell technology and other resources.</p>



<p>"Regenerative biotherapeutics seeks to repair or replace diseased organs. As such, we are very excited to be part of the Initiative for improving transplantation," says <a href="https://www.mayo.edu/research/faculty/qu-wenchun-m-d-ph-d/bio-20206516" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Wenchun Qu, M.D., Ph.D.</a>, the Jorge and Leslie Bacardi Associate Director, Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics in Florida. "We hope to assist in the build out of this project by providing researchers, workspace, biomanufacturing capabilities and cell and gene technologies."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Making organ transplants more successful</strong></h2>



<p>Another challenge the Transforming Transplant Initiative is trying to address is graft failure or rejection of transplanted organs. Mayo Clinic's vision is to prevent the need for a second transplant. One research project is focusing on whether chimeric antigen receptor-T cell therapy (<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/car-t-cell-therapy-program/home/orc-20404317" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CAR-T cell therapy</a>) could be used to control the body's immune response and prevent organ rejection. CAR-T therapy has mainly been used to treat blood cancers. Applying this technology to transplants would be a new, experimental use of CAR-T therapy.</p>



<p>"Some organ transplant patients have antibodies in their bloodstreams that increase their chances of (organ) rejection. Unfortunately, that makes it difficult to find a proper match," says Dr. Taner. "We hope research will show whether CAR-T cell therapy could harness the immune system to suppress antibodies that are causing rejection." Other Mayo Clinic goals include reducing the number of organs that are discarded and making more organs available through advanced preservation techniques. Another goal is to identify and treat disease early to prevent end-stage organ failure and the subsequent need for a transplant.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Working together to improve transplant options</strong></h2>



<p>Mayo Clinic leaders recognize that overcoming the complex barriers to organ transplantation will require powerful new collaborations. They are actively seeking new ways to work with experts in industry and academia that could bring new ideas, tools, specialized knowledge and energy to the field.</p>



<p>"Organ transplantation is one of the greatest accomplishments in modern medicine. There is also a lot of good expertise outside our organization," says Dr. Taner. "We welcome outside collaborators that could help us improve organ transplantation for patients."</p>



<p>It could take many years to realize the fruits of the Transforming Transplant Initiative. Nevertheless, Mayo Clinic researchers continue to work tirelessly to address the critical shortage of organs and bring the gift of organ donation to more people.</p>



<p>###</p>



<p>Related stories: <br><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/11-16-four-ways-organ-transplants-are-being-transformed-to-save-more-lives/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Four ways organ transplants are being transformed to save lives </a><br><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/transplant-program-at-mayo-clinic-in-florida-celebrates-its-25th-anniversary-with-vision-for-future-of-transplant/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Transplant program at Mayo Clinic in Florida celebrates its 25th anniversary with vision for future of transplant</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/transforming-transplant-initiative-aspires-to-save-lives-through-bioengineering/">Transforming Transplant Initiative aspires to save lives through bioengineering</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Cropped-1-x-1-Physicians-during-transplant-WF3405965_0194-fotor-20240301125742.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/03/Transforming-Transplant16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[biomedical research]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Burcin Taner]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Wenchun Qu]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Center for Regenerative Biotherapeutics]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[organ transplants]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Type 2 diabetes no longer a barrier to becoming a living kidney donor</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/type-2-diabetes-no-longer-a-barrier-to-becoming-a-living-kidney-donor/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Heather Carlson Kehren]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 16:00:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Naim Issa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Pooja Budhiraja]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Shennen Mao]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=382836</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — People who are overall healthy and living with well-controlled Type 2 diabetes can donate a kidney, thanks to a change in national policy. The Organ Procurement and Transplantation Network updated its living donor criteria. It makes some people with Type 2 diabetes eligible to donate a kidney. This marks a "significant shift" [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/type-2-diabetes-no-longer-a-barrier-to-becoming-a-living-kidney-donor/">Type 2 diabetes no longer a barrier to becoming a living kidney donor</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/Diabetes-glucose-monitoring-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg" alt="Person with diabetes having blood checked. Some people with diabetes can be a living kidney donor." class="wp-image-349231" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/Diabetes-glucose-monitoring-16-x-9-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/Diabetes-glucose-monitoring-16-x-9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/Diabetes-glucose-monitoring-16-x-9-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/Diabetes-glucose-monitoring-16-x-9-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/Diabetes-glucose-monitoring-16-x-9.jpg 1604w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>ROCHESTER, Minn. — People who are overall healthy and living with well-controlled Type 2 diabetes can donate a kidney, thanks to a change in national policy.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Issa-Naim-S._14325870_202107130139-250x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-382856" style="width:190px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Issa-Naim-S._14325870_202107130139-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Issa-Naim-S._14325870_202107130139.jpg 667w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><sup>Naim Issa, M.D.</sup></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>The <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/issa-naim-s-m-d/bio-20235178?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Organ Procurement and Transplantation Network</a> updated its <a href="https://optn.transplant.hrsa.gov/media/d2hlvxv1/policy-notice_modify-ld-excl-crit_ldc.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">living donor criteria</a>. It makes some people with Type 2 diabetes eligible to donate a kidney. This marks a "significant shift" in criteria for living kidney donors, says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/issa-naim-s-m-d/bio-20235178" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Naim Issa, M.D.</a>, Mayo Clinic transplant nephrologist.</p>



<p>"This policy change may offer a lifeline to some people with end-stage kidney disease, providing them with a better chance for a successful transplant and improved quality of life," he says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="250" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mao-Shennen-A.-MD_15143457_201809121253-250x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-382857" style="width:192px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mao-Shennen-A.-MD_15143457_201809121253-250x300.jpg 250w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mao-Shennen-A.-MD_15143457_201809121253.jpg 667w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><sup>Shennen Mao, M.D.</sup></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Nearly 89,000 people in the U.S. are on the waiting list for a potentially lifesaving kidney transplant, according to the <a href="https://unos.org/data/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">United Network for Organ Sharing</a>. The average wait for a kidney from a deceased donor is three to five years. People who receive kidneys from living donors also tend to have better outcomes, says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mao-shennen-a-m-d/bio-20439463?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Shennen Mao, M.D.</a>, Mayo Clinic transplant surgeon.</p>



<p>"People in need of a kidney transplant typically receive a living donor transplant much faster than a deceased donor transplant, avoiding many years of dialysis and its associated complications," Dr. Mao says. "On average, kidneys from living donors also last longer than those from deceased donors."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What led to policy change?</h2>



<p>Historically, people with diabetes have been prohibited from being living kidney donors because diabetes can <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/diabetic-nephropathy/diagnosis-treatment/drc-20354562?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cause kidney disease.</a> People with Type 1 diabetes remain ineligible to be a living kidney donor. By expanding eligibility criteria, there's potential to save more lives through increased kidney availability while maintaining a commitment to the safety and well-being of donors.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What is the policy?</h2>



<p>The national policy allows people with Type 2 diabetes to donate a kidney if there is no evidence of organ damage or an unacceptable lifetime risk of complications. Mayo Clinic Transplant Center adopted its own more stringent policies to minimize potential risks for the donor. In addition to national criteria, Mayo Clinic patients with Type 2 diabetes also must meet the following criteria to be a donor:</p>



<ul>
<li>Be age 60 or older.</li>



<li>Have well-controlled diabetes and not use insulin.</li>



<li>If over age 65, can be using up to two oral medications for diabetes.</li>



<li>Not be overweight.</li>



<li>Have no family history of kidney disease.</li>



<li>Undergo a rigorous health assessment and individualized risk evaluation.</li>
</ul>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="227" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Budhiraja-Pooja_21703302_202004070905-227x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-382863" style="width:193px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Budhiraja-Pooja_21703302_202004070905-227x300.jpg 227w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Budhiraja-Pooja_21703302_202004070905.jpg 606w" sizes="(max-width: 227px) 100vw, 227px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><sup>Pooja Budhiraja, M.B.B.S.</sup></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Mayo Clinic donors undergo thorough health evaluations and risk assessments, ensuring that only those with minimal risk of complications are approved to donate," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/budhiraja-pooja-m-b-b-s/bio-20486288?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pooja Budhiraja, M.B.B.S.</a>, Mayo Clinic nephrologist. "Criteria such as age limits, weight requirements and the absence of a family history of kidney disease help mitigate the long-term health risks for donors. Our commitment is to safeguard donor health while expanding transplant possibilities."</p>



<p>Mayo Clinic will also conduct ongoing research to monitor and assess the effect of these policy changes on the long-term outcomes of older living kidney donors with Type 2 diabetes.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/home/orc-20203891?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic Transplant Center</a> is the largest integrated transplant center in the U.S. Learn more about becoming a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/living-donor-transplantation/overview/ovc-20545462?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">living kidney donor</a>.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/ggug7D_Pz3A" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: Mayo Clinic Minute: Expanding the living kidney donor pool to those with Type 2 diabetes</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidggug7DPz3A"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Expanding the living kidney donor pool to people with Type 2 diabetes" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ggug7D_Pz3A?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:08) is in the downloads at the end of the post. Please "Courtesy: Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/SCRIPT-MCM-Diabetes-and-kidney-transplants.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>###</p>



<p><strong>About Mayo Clinic</strong><br><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/about-mayo-clinic?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic</a> is a nonprofit organization committed to innovation in clinical practice, education and research, and providing compassion, expertise and answers to everyone who needs healing. Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>&nbsp;for additional Mayo Clinic news.</p>



<p><strong>Media contact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Heather Carlson Kehren, Mayo Clinic Communications, <a href="mailto:newsbureau@mayo.edu" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newsbureau@mayo.edu</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/type-2-diabetes-no-longer-a-barrier-to-becoming-a-living-kidney-donor/">Type 2 diabetes no longer a barrier to becoming a living kidney donor</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/Diabetes-glucose-monitoring-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2022/09/Diabetes-glucose-monitoring-16-x-9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Arizona News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Naim Issa]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Pooja Budhiraja]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Shennen Mao]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Florida News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Minnesota News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[News Releases]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Expanding the living kidney donor pool to those with Type 2 diabetes</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-expanding-the-living-kidney-donor-pool-to-those-with-type-2-diabetes/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 15:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diabetes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Naim Issa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kidney Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[living kidney donor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=382046</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>With more than 90,000 people in the U.S. awaiting kidney transplants, the demand exceeds the available supply — emphasizing the critical importance of identifying safe ways to broaden the kidney donor pool. Dr. Naim Issa, a Mayo Clinic transplant nephrologist, says, until recently, patients with&#160;Type 2 diabetes&#160;have been ruled out as potential&#160;living kidney donors.&#160;Now, following [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-expanding-the-living-kidney-donor-pool-to-those-with-type-2-diabetes/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Expanding the living kidney donor pool to those with Type 2 diabetes</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>With more than 90,000 people in the U.S. awaiting kidney transplants, the demand exceeds the available supply — emphasizing the critical importance of identifying safe ways to broaden the kidney donor pool.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/living-donor-kidney-transplant/pyc-20384838?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Naim Issa</a>, a Mayo Clinic transplant nephrologist, says, until recently, patients with&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/type-2-diabetes/symptoms-causes/syc-20351193?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Type 2 diabetes</a>&nbsp;have been ruled out as potential&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/living-donor-kidney-transplant/pyc-20384838" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">living kidney donors.</a>&nbsp;Now, following strict criteria, some patients may be eligible to help close the gap on this ever-growing need for living kidney donors.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/ggug7D_Pz3A" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeggug7DPz3A"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute - Expanding the living kidney donor pool to people with Type 2 diabetes" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ggug7D_Pz3A?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:08) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post. Please "Courtesy: Mayo Clinic News Network." Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/SCRIPT-MCM-Diabetes-and-kidney-transplants.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<p>Every eight minutes, a person is added to the national kidney transplant waiting list.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"Unfortunately, in this country, there is a large gap between the demand for kidney transplantation and the supply of organs from deceased donors," says Dr. Issa.Dialysis is an option for patients with end-stage kidney disease. Though Dr. Issa says a transplant is preferred — and having a living donor is best.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="550" height="309" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/kidney-transplant-living-donor.jpg" alt="Medical illustration of living kidney donation" class="wp-image-223197" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/kidney-transplant-living-donor.jpg 550w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/11/kidney-transplant-living-donor-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Medical illustration of living kidney donation</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>"Kidney transplantation offers greater survival benefits and increases the lifespan of people in need of kidney transplant," he says.</p>



<p>And that's a reason why it's important to expand the eligible kidney donor pool.</p>



<p>"Allowing people with Type 2 diabetes mellitus may open the door for some people who have not been eligible before to be potential living kidney donors," Dr. Issa says.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Criteria for a living kidney donor with Type 2 diabetes </h3>



<p>Those eligible must be older than 60, have well-controlled Type 2 diabetes, not on insulin and have no family history of kidney disease.</p>



<p>"Any potential individual who would like to be a candidate for living kidney donation should undergo a very thorough health assessment and very thorough examination to ensure they are healthy enough," says Dr. Issa.</p>



<p>It's about safeguarding the potential donor's overall health — while helping close the gap.</p>



<p>Learn more about what it means to be a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/living-donor-transplant/about/pac-20384787?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">living kidney donor</a>. </p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Read the news release: <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=382836&amp;preview=true" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Type 2 diabetes no longer a barrier to becoming a living kidney donor</a></h4>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-expanding-the-living-kidney-donor-pool-to-those-with-type-2-diabetes/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Expanding the living kidney donor pool to those with Type 2 diabetes</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/12/Senior-African-American-couple-at-home_shutterstock_280357997_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2018/12/Senior-African-American-couple-at-home_shutterstock_280357997_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Diabetes]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Naim Issa]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Kidney Transplant]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[living kidney donor]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Heart transplant patient finding motivation through competition, music and the Mayo Clinic community</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-patient-finding-motivation-through-competition-music-and-the-mayo-clinic-community/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tia R. Ford]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Cardiology Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharing Mayo Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Melissa Lyle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Rohan Goswami]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mark Forbess]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=382327</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The fall It was Good Friday 2023. Mark Forbess was just leaving Mayo Clinic in Florida after his first appointment as a new patient at the heart failure program, when everything went black. "I found myself on the pavement in front of Mayo Clinic," says Mark. "I was emerging from unconsciousness. Everything was dark. I [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-patient-finding-motivation-through-competition-music-and-the-mayo-clinic-community/">Heart transplant patient finding motivation through competition, music and the Mayo Clinic community</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="575" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano16x9-1024x575.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-382337" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano16x9-1024x575.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano16x9-300x168.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano16x9-768x431.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano16x9.jpg 1512w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mark Forbess playing the piano in the Mayo atrium</figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The fall</strong></h2>



<p>It was Good Friday 2023. Mark Forbess was just leaving <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a> after his first appointment as a new patient at the heart failure program, when everything went black.</p>



<p>"I found myself on the pavement in front of Mayo Clinic," says Mark. "I was emerging from unconsciousness. Everything was dark. I opened my eyes to see that my face was pressed onto the hot, black pavement."</p>



<p>People nearby ran to his aid as he experienced excruciating pain in his head, back and neck. From there, he was rushed to the emergency department in the building he was just leaving.</p>



<p>Mark had experienced a devastating heart electrical event.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Where it all began</strong></h2>



<p>At around 33 years old, Mark was diagnosed with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy/symptoms-causes/syc-20350198?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM)</a>, a disease in which the heart muscle becomes thickened. The thickened heart muscle makes it harder for the heart to pump blood.</p>



<p>"Over time, my heart health began to decline," says Mark. "The heart failure turned into devastating episodes of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/atrial-fibrillation/symptoms-causes/syc-20350624?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">atrial fibrillation (AFib)</a> and <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/ventricular-tachycardia/symptoms-causes/syc-20355138?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ventricular tachycardia (V-tach)</a>. During this time, I experienced four V-tach episodes which required my <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/implantable-cardioverter-defibrillators/about/pac-20384692?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">implantable cardioverter defibrillator (ICD)</a> to bring me back to life, in addition to eight cardiac ablations."</p>



<p>In the fall of 2022, he was referred to Mayo Clinic for a PET scan to look for other heart diseases. At the time, nothing was found that met Mayo Clinic's heart failure treatment criteria, so he was not approved as a cardiology patient. However, in March of 2023, after experiencing congestive heart failure while being treated at another medical institution, he was referred to Mayo Clinic again as a candidate for the heart failure program.</p>



<p>The following month, he was approved for the program under the care of <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/lyle-melissa-a-m-d/bio-20491562?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Melissa Lyle, a Mayo Clinic cardiologist</a>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A candidate for transplant</strong></h2>



<p>After the emergency department triage, Mark recalls his cardiologist saying, "Congratulations, Mr. Forbess. You just won a ticket to be evaluated for the heart transplant program." From there, he went through a battery of evaluation tests, which he passed, officially allowing him access to Mayo Clinic's heart transplant program.</p>



<p>"I knew that when Dr. Lyle told me I was entered into the Mayo Clinic heart transplant program that God was in total control of my life," says Mark. "He was guiding her and providing the confidence, from years of training, that I could live a happy life again by having a new heart."</p>



<p>Within a month, Mark was admitted to Mayo Clinic and waitlisted for his new heart. Transplant patients are ranked by necessity, and due to his condition, he was at the top of the list.</p>



<p>Mark had a rare heart deformation in which his left ventricle was very enlarged. This is considered unusual in HCM patients because their heart walls are usually very thick and the ventricles are small. As a result, Mark became eligible for a cardiac device — a small heart pump that helped improve his oxygen blood levels while he waited for his heart transplant.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF_Logo-768x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-382340" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF_Logo-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF_Logo-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF_Logo-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF_Logo.jpg 1512w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The Daytona 500 meets the ICU</strong></h2>



<p>In an effort to lift the spirits of their patients and encourage some much-needed exercise, the nurses on Mark's floor came up with some competitive fun.</p>



<p>"These patients are not your typical ICU patients," says Sara Vilela, registered nurse. "They are often walking and talking, something we are not used to in the ICU. This means we have to make sure we are catering to this special patient population and ensuring that not only their medical needs are being taken care of, but also their social needs."</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="523" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Transplant_Games-1024x523.png" alt="" class="wp-image-382339" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Transplant_Games-1024x523.png 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Transplant_Games-300x153.png 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Transplant_Games-768x392.png 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Transplant_Games-1536x784.png 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Transplant_Games.png 1788w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mark and fellow cardiac ICU playing dominoes</figcaption></figure>



<p>The nursing staff set up a series of games from dominoes to a "Cardiac Device 500" footrace between patients around the hospital unit, measured by the distance they walked each day.</p>



<p>"It was a bit of a leap to think playing games at a time like this was appropriate," says Mark. "After all, we were in the ICU. When you showed up and participated, you were hooked. It was that much fun and necessary. No medical tests, no medicine and no bad news. Nothing but fun, and that’s always good for the soul. I participated in afternoon game sessions with other heart transplant patients, their families, my brother Jeff and the outstanding Mayo nursing staff. We looked forward to the opportunity to meet each other and focus our minds on something we had in common and away from our current health status."</p>



<p>The games were a big hit among the patients, inspiring much creativity, especially the races. They created names for their cardiac devices, team logos and even fake sponsors. Mark named his heart pump "Archie," after his father.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="225" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF11-225x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-382341" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF11-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF11-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF11-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF11.jpg 1512w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /></figure></div>


<p>Mark recalls being barely able to walk a small lap at the beginning of this journey. However, walking more and more each day, motivated by a new heart and some friendly competition, he began walking about five to seven miles a day, even hitting a heart pump record of 10.8 miles.</p>



<p>"By hosting game times, these patients were able to talk to one another about the struggles of waiting for a heart transplant, but also the triumphs, such as beating their previous day's record of laps," says Vilela. "They connected over this unique experience and bond with one another, which resulted in a patient population encouraging each other, remembering they are not alone on this journey."</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Inspired by memories</strong></h2>



<p>Mark lost his wife of nearly 40 years, Michele, in June 2022, approximately 10 months before entering Mayo Clinic on the heart transplant waitlist.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano_1x1-300x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-382338" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano_1x1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano_1x1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano_1x1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano_1x1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Mark_Piano_1x1.jpg 1512w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure></div>


<p>"I had spent many days grieving in the Mayo atrium over my wife," he says. "I wanted to change that to positive, fun memories instead by providing a little entertainment playing the beautiful grand piano and maybe brighten someone else's day." He pursued the opportunity to play with the encouragement of one of his nurses, Frances Ausley, and Rose Grace from the Humanities in Medicine Department. Grace is a concert level pianist herself who occasionally visited Mark in his hospital room to play the keyboard.</p>



<p>"Frances Ausley has incredible capabilities and a very hard work ethic while providing care to all those around her," Mark says. "Rose Grace encouraged me and gave me the confidence that I could play the piano under these circumstances."</p>



<p>While playing the piano helped, he still found himself battling anxiety and sadness around the anniversary of losing his wife.</p>



<p>"Managing anxiety on the one-year anniversary of my wife's passing was going to be very difficult," Mark says. "Wanting to celebrate her life outside, I was stuck in the ICU waiting for a heart, knowing that any high anxiety could trigger severe heart arrhythmia. Carolina Robles de Brady, a wonderful and thoughtful nurse from El Salvador, secretly arranged to reenact the dinner my wife and I had made on our first date — chicken cordon bleu with blueberry fluff as dessert. She asked me the day before about memories of a favorite dinner with my wife. I was pleasantly surprised as Carolina kept me calm while we celebrated my wife's life."</p>



<p>Later on, Mark would nominate Carolina for a DAISY Award, honoring nurses who go above and beyond to provide compassionate care to patients and families. She was selected and recognized with the award in December 2023.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A new heart, a new day, a new future</strong></h2>



<p>On July 14, 2023, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/goswami-rohan-m-m-d/bio-20432467?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Rohan Goswami</a> entered Mark's room. Expecting another donor update, the news was different this time. "I found you the perfect heart," Mark recalls Dr. Goswami saying.</p>



<p>"I never had children, but I’m guessing this is one of the most exciting pieces of medical news you could ever receive," says Mark. "After several months of waiting, Dr. Goswami is telling me I have a heart coming. It was an unbelievable experience. The sacrifice a donor family makes to give organs to another human being is one of the greatest acts of unselfishness and kindness a person can do on this earth. It's real, and it's effective. My donor family will be forever in my soul as I wake up every day thanking them in my prayers."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="225" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF5-225x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-382343" style="width:266px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF5-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF5-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF5-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF5.jpg 1512w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mark Forbess</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Mark received his new heart on July 17, 2023.</p>



<p>After more than 30 years as an investment banker, Mark started thinking about a long-term career goal he'd always wanted to pursue. Since childhood, he wanted to be a screenwriter and filmmaker.</p>



<p>"Before I entered the hospital for my transplant, I purchased screenwriters professional software used to write film scripts and loaded it onto my computer," says Mark. "I always wanted to produce films that would help people find true, long-term happiness in life. If I could write one particular story while waiting for my heart transplant, I would be a happy person myself."</p>



<p>Since leaving the hospital, he has achieved this goal by completing his first screenplay and has begun the process of marketing it to the film industry. As for his health journey, he continues to excel at cardiac rehabilitation, lowering medications every month as his recovery progresses.</p>



<p>Paying regular visits to Mayo Clinic staff since his transplant, Mark acknowledges that everyone he met while waiting for his transplant helped make his experience a good one.</p>



<p>"During this time, I would meet many incredible nurses, doctors, physician assistants, housekeeping team members, Food Services team members and a host of other personnel who took great pride in their roles," says Mark.</p>



<p>His interactions with all staff, even beyond his hospital room, became an expansion of his care team. Many share that Mark had just as much of an impact on them.</p>



<p>"The power of food and how it changes the patient experience by broadening the scope of meal service providing comfort, connection and nutrition is a component of their care," says Casey Wingerter, patient ambassador for Mayo Clinic Food Services. "During Mark's stay at Mayo, meals became a medium for connection, and connection was&nbsp;critical for his transplant journey. He healed while at Mayo, and it was the people that made the difference. That human connection is what he held on to and is why he became a bright spot in our staff's days as well."</p>



<p>Mark recalls how much Wingerter and her team truly made a difference. Before he left the hospital, he says the Food Services team gifted him a small suitcase full of his favorite gum as a way of saying thank you from Wingerter and the Food Services team.</p>



<p>"I firmly believe God answers our prayers," says Mark. "My hope is that my testimony can serve as a powerful tool for you to convey the profound significance of God in our lives. His presence can guide us through seemingly impossible challenges, which will lead to a truly long-term, happy life."</p>



<p><strong>Additional resources:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-know-the-warning-signs-of-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Know the warning signs of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/sharing-mayo-clinic-a-heart-patients-fall-picks-up-something-big/">Sharing Mayo Clinic: A heart patient’s fall picks up something big</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-what-is-hypertrophic-cardiomyopathy/">Mayo Clinic Minute: What is hypertrophic cardiomyopathy?</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-patient-finding-motivation-through-competition-music-and-the-mayo-clinic-community/">Heart transplant patient finding motivation through competition, music and the Mayo Clinic community</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF6_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MF6_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Melissa Lyle]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Rohan Goswami]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mark Forbess]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Celebrating the gift of life: Cousins raise awareness for organ donation on National Donor Day</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/celebrating-the-gift-of-life-cousins-raise-awareness-for-organ-donation-on-national-donor-day/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tia R. Ford]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2024 14:09:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lisa Mitchell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Michelle tatum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381681</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Lisa Brown, 53, of Jacksonville, suffered from severe pelvis and back pain for years. She later learned that her bladder wasn't working due to follicular cystitis, a rare and non-specific inflammatory disease of the bladder, and inflammatory pseudotumor of the bladder. In 2017, her bladder was removed using robotic-assisted surgery and replaced with a "neobladder" [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/celebrating-the-gift-of-life-cousins-raise-awareness-for-organ-donation-on-national-donor-day/">Celebrating the gift of life: Cousins raise awareness for organ donation on National Donor Day</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="810" height="455" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Michelle-and-Lisa5-16x9-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381685" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Michelle-and-Lisa5-16x9-1.jpg 810w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Michelle-and-Lisa5-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Michelle-and-Lisa5-16x9-1-768x431.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 810px) 100vw, 810px" /></figure>



<p>Lisa Brown, 53, of Jacksonville, suffered from severe pelvis and back pain for years. She later learned that her bladder wasn't working due to follicular cystitis, a rare and non-specific inflammatory disease of the bladder, and inflammatory pseudotumor of the bladder. In 2017, her bladder was removed using robotic-assisted surgery and replaced with a "neobladder" that was attached to her ureters, which are the tubes that carry urine produced by the kidneys. Unfortunately, ongoing challenges with her bladder caused permanent damage to her kidneys.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"I had recurring bladder infections to where my kidneys started backing up," says Lisa. "I’d been in late-stage kidney failure since 2018."</p>



<p>Lisa had nephrostomy tubes for more than a year that had to be exchanged every six weeks until her ureters were surgically repaired in 2019. She has also had to have iron infusions periodically because of low kidney function, and battled extreme fatigue, continued low back pain, anemia, and a feeling of constantly being cold. Her nephrologist referred her to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/patient-visitor-guide/florida?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic in Florida</a> to be considered for a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/kidney-transplant/about/pac-20384777?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">kidney transplant</a>.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="225" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Michelle-and-Lisa3-original-225x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381688" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Michelle-and-Lisa3-original-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Michelle-and-Lisa3-original-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Michelle-and-Lisa3-original.jpg 810w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /></figure></div>


<p>After Lisa qualified for a transplant, her cousin, Michelle Tatum, was tested as a match and stepped up to be her donor.</p>



<p>"My decision to donate wasn't made lightly, but I will say it was made easily," says Michelle. "I truly believe God gave me two kidneys when I only need one for this exact purpose." Lisa received her new kidney on Jan. 25, 2024.&nbsp;</p>



<p>"I love Lisa with all my heart," says Michelle, reflecting on what inspired her to become an organ donor. "I watched her health decline over the last five years. I decided to get tested and see if I could donate and said that if it was God's plan, it would all work out, and it did, perfectly. I was raised in a way where generosity and kindness toward others are celebrated and encouraged. I can’t change the world, but I can change one person’s world."</p>



<p>This <a href="https://donatelife.net/how-you-can-help/national-observances-celebrations/national-donor-day/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Donor Day</a>, an annual observance dedicated to spreading awareness and education about organ, eye and tissue donation, Michelle hopes others will also consider being living donors.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="218" height="300" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Michelle-and-Lisa7-original-218x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381691" style="width:182px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Michelle-and-Lisa7-original-218x300.jpg 218w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Michelle-and-Lisa7-original.jpg 582w" sizes="(max-width: 218px) 100vw, 218px" /></figure></div>


<p>"I would definitely encourage others to get tested and consider becoming organ donors," says Michelle. "I have been blessed with a deeper meaning and greater purpose in my life. Some people have thanked me for what I did, but to me, the gifts I received were much greater than the ones I gave."</p>



<p>Lisa shares that her kidney function is perfect now.</p>



<p>"I’m so excited about life again and am truly thankful for my donor," Lisa says.</p>



<p></p>



<p><strong>Additional resources:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-surgeons-perform-first-robotic-assisted-kidney-transplant-in-minnesota/">Mayo Clinic surgeons perform first robotic-assisted kidney transplant in Minnesota</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-breaking-barriers-for-patients-who-need-kidney-transplants/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Breaking barriers for patients who need kidney transplants</a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/lifestyle-changes-can-be-critical-for-kidney-transplant-patients-long-term-survival/">Lifestyle changes can be critical for kidney transplant patients’ long-term survival</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/celebrating-the-gift-of-life-cousins-raise-awareness-for-organ-donation-on-national-donor-day/">Celebrating the gift of life: Cousins raise awareness for organ donation on National Donor Day</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/MIchelle-and-Lisa5-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Michelle-and-Lisa5-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Lisa Mitchell]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Michelle tatum]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Valentine&#8217;s Day story of love, legacy and the gift of life</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-valentines-day-story-of-love-legacy-and-the-gift-of-life/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Marty Velasco Hames]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2024 16:36:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arizona]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiology Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant Patient Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cardiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gift of life]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[heart month]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic News Network Video Pkg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Organ Donation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[organ donor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=381750</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Duffer family’s home is filled with lots of love this Valentine’s Day. They have a new baby girl, and dad got the lifesaving heart transplant he needed. Take a look at the special way the Duffer family is now recognizing love, legacy and the gift of life. Watch: A Valentine’s Day story about love, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-valentines-day-story-of-love-legacy-and-the-gift-of-life/">A Valentine&#8217;s Day story of love, legacy and the gift of life</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="575" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Duffer-Family_16x9-1024x575.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381912" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Duffer-Family_16x9-1024x575.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Duffer-Family_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Duffer-Family_16x9-768x431.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Duffer-Family_16x9-1536x863.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Duffer-Family_16x9-2048x1151.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Harley and Justine Duffer with their newest family member, Peyton</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>The Duffer family’s home is filled with lots of love this Valentine’s Day.</p>



<p>They have a new baby girl, and dad got the lifesaving <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-innovation-new-heart-in-a-box-technology-provides-gift-of-life-to-arizona-man-as-couple-prepares-to-celebrate-50-year-anniversary/">heart transplant</a> he needed.</p>



<p>Take a look at the special way the Duffer family is now recognizing love, legacy and the gift of life.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/fTwBlCmcpAY" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: A Valentine’s Day story about love, legacy and the gift of life</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubefTwBlCmcpAY"  title="Love, legacy, and the gift of life" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fTwBlCmcpAY?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:50) is in the downloads at the end of this post. Please courtesy: “Mayo Clinic News Network”. Read the</strong> <strong><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/A-Valentines-Day-story-about-love-legacy-and-the-gift-of-life.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script.</a></strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Harley’s fight to survive</strong></h2>



<p>Being together as a family has a deeper meaning for the Duffer family this Valentine’s day. In 2021, Harley suffered <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/clinical-trial-finds-cell-therapy-improves-quality-of-life-in-advanced-heart-failure/">heart failure</a> stemming from a rare genetic condition. He says doctors told him his only chance for survival was to get a heart transplant. </p>



<p>“I was basically on my deathbed,” says Harley. “They told me I had six months to live.” Doctors also told Harley the transplant would be the hardest thing he’s ever done in his whole life. </p>



<p>Harley says he had to fight to survive for his family.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-in-coma-1-768x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381931" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-in-coma-1-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-in-coma-1-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-in-coma-1-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-in-coma-1-1536x2048.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Harley was placed in a medically induced coma while on the heart transplant waiting list <br>(photo courtesy: Duffer Family)</strong></figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The wait for a heart donor</strong></h2>



<p>Harley was placed in a medically induced coma at Mayo Clinic to minimize damage to his heart while waiting for a donor organ to become available. Each passing day took its toll on the family.</p>



<p>"There were several instances where the fear of him not making it through set in very heavy. And then you have a daughter at home saying ‘Where’s daddy? Where’s daddy?’ It was a lot to go through,” remembers Justine.</p>



<p>The Duffers got the call they were hoping for - a donor heart was available. Harley underwent a successful transplant and began his long road to recovery. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="922" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-leaving-hospital-1-922x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381874" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-leaving-hospital-1-922x1024.jpg 922w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-leaving-hospital-1-270x300.jpg 270w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-leaving-hospital-1-768x853.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-leaving-hospital-1-1383x1536.jpg 1383w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-leaving-hospital-1-1845x2048.jpg 1845w" sizes="(max-width: 922px) 100vw, 922px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Harley Duffer leaving Mayo Clinic after his successful heart transplant</strong><br><strong> (photo courtesy: Duffer Family)</strong></figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Heartfelt gratitude</strong></h2>



<p>After regaining his health, Harley got the chance to do something he never expected. He was given the opportunity to meet the family of his organ donor, Peyton Nurse.</p>



<p>Both families got together and listened to Peyton’s heart beating healthy and strong in Harley’s chest. </p>



<p>“I could not have asked for a better donor family. They are so caring and welcoming,” says Harley. “I understand they are going through a loss, but I want to be here for them. They are just the best kinds of people.”</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_6429-e1707805436709-768x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381875" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_6429-e1707805436709-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_6429-e1707805436709-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_6429-e1707805436709-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_6429-e1707805436709-1536x2048.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Lesley Nurse listens to the heartbeat of her son Peyton’s donated heart</strong></figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Remembering the life and legacy of Peyton Nurse </strong></h2>



<p>Peyton is remembered as a loving son, a brother, a friend to all, and a star student who always sought to help others in his community. He tragically lost his life in a car accident. His last wish was to be an organ donor. Peyton’s heart became the gift of life for Harley. </p>



<p>“We went to see Peyton’s resting place,” says Harley. “Such bravery and selflessness from a young man. I just want to say thank you to Peyton’s family, for your son’s bravery and the sacrifices he’s made.”</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="745" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Peyton-two-1024x745.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-381872" style="width:840px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Peyton-two-1024x745.jpeg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Peyton-two-300x218.jpeg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Peyton-two-768x559.jpeg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Peyton-two-1536x1117.jpeg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Peyton-two.jpeg 1712w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Peyton Nurse lost his life at the age of 21. His last wish was to be an organ donor</strong> <br>(photo courtesy: Lesley Nurse)</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-at-Peytons-gravesite-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381871" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-at-Peytons-gravesite-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-at-Peytons-gravesite-300x225.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-at-Peytons-gravesite-768x576.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-at-Peytons-gravesite-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Harley-at-Peytons-gravesite-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Harley Duffer visiting the gravesite of his heart donor, Peyton Nurse</strong> <br><strong>(photo courtesy: Duffer Family)</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>Harley and Justine are now back at home with their daughter, Libi, and their newborn baby girl. With their hearts full of love and gratitude, and the hope to carry on the legacy of their heart donor, they named their new baby girl, Peyton. </p>



<p>“We want her to know the importance of organ donation, and that’s why her daddy is still here, to raise his girls, and be here with us all together,” says Justine. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_7376-e1707805696726-768x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-381877" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_7376-e1707805696726-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_7376-e1707805696726-225x300.jpg 225w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_7376-e1707805696726-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_7376-e1707805696726-1536x2048.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Peyton Duffer</strong> <strong>at four weeks old</strong></figcaption></figure>



<p>Carrying on the legacy of her son’s name means the world to his mom Lesley. “I can’t wait to hold baby Peyton in person and hold her in my arms,” shares Lesley. The name “Peyton” holds a special place in her heart because not only was it her son’s name, but a name that was handed down for several generations in her family.  </p>



<p>Lesley shared these two pictures as a Valentine’s Day message to serve as a reminder of the power of love, legacy and the gift of life. </p>



<div class="wp-block-group is-nowrap is-layout-flex wp-container-core-group-layout-1 wp-block-group-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="429" height="640" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/DSC00353_Original.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-381924" style="width:411px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/DSC00353_Original.jpeg 429w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/DSC00353_Original-201x300.jpeg 201w" sizes="(max-width: 429px) 100vw, 429px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Peyton Nurse</strong></figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="576" height="1024" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_6278-576x1024.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-381925" style="width:341px;height:auto" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_6278-576x1024.jpeg 576w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_6278-169x300.jpeg 169w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_6278-768x1365.jpeg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_6278-864x1536.jpeg 864w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_6278-1152x2048.jpeg 1152w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_6278.jpeg 1242w" sizes="(max-width: 576px) 100vw, 576px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><strong>Peyton Duffer</strong></figcaption></figure>
</div>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p><strong><em>“Naming their baby after my son Peyton is the highest honor and symbol of gratitude, magnitude, and love. Thus he, through his gift of organ donation and now his name, is part of their family forever. Names create legacies. We will always be connected in so many ways. </em></strong><br><strong><em>We are forever grateful.</em></strong></p><cite>Lesley Nurse, Heart donor’s mom</cite></blockquote></figure>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p><strong>Related article</strong>s:</p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/heart-transplant-innovation-new-heart-in-a-box-technology-provides-gift-of-life-to-arizona-man-as-couple-prepares-to-celebrate-50-year-anniversary/"><strong>Heart Transplant Innovation: New ‘heart in a box’ technology provides gift of life to Arizona man, as couple prepares to celebrate 50-year anniversary</strong></a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-barriers-helping-native-americans-in-need-get-the-gift-of-life/"><strong>Breaking barriers: </strong></a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-barriers-helping-native-americans-in-need-get-the-gift-of-life/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Helping</strong></a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-barriers-helping-native-americans-in-need-get-the-gift-of-life/"><strong> </strong></a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/breaking-barriers-helping-native-americans-in-need-get-the-gift-of-life/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Native Americans in need get the gift of life</strong></a></li>



<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/organ-transplant-innovation-helping-more-people-get-the-gift-of-life/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Organ Transplant Innovation: Helping more people get the gift of life</strong></a></li>
</ul>



<p><br></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/a-valentines-day-story-of-love-legacy-and-the-gift-of-life/">A Valentine&#8217;s Day story of love, legacy and the gift of life</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Duffer-Heart-Pillow_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/Duffer-Family_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Cardiology]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[gift of life]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Heart Health]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[heart month]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Heart Transplant]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic News Network Video Pkg]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Organ Donation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[organ donor]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mcthumb >https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2024/02/IMG_7377-150x150.jpg</mayoclinic:mcthumb >	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic transplant programs achieve record volumes in 2023</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-transplant-programs-achieve-record-volumes-in-2023/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tia R. Ford]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Bashar Aqel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Burcin Taner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Julie Heimbach]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=379570</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In addition to celebrating 60 years as a leader in organ transplant practice, Mayo Clinic is also celebrating a record year in the number of transplants performed. Mayo Clinic, as the largest integrated transplant center in the country represented by sites in Arizona, Florida and Minnesota, performed a collective 1,987 organ transplants in 2023. Transplant [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-transplant-programs-achieve-record-volumes-in-2023/">Mayo Clinic transplant programs achieve record volumes in 2023</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1013" height="570" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/02/Image3_16x9.jpg" alt="surgeons in blue surgical gowns performing a transplant" class="wp-image-262570" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/02/Image3_16x9.jpg 1013w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/02/Image3_16x9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/02/Image3_16x9-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1013px) 100vw, 1013px" /></figure>



<p>In addition to celebrating 60 years as a leader in organ transplant practice, Mayo Clinic is also celebrating a record year in the number of transplants performed. Mayo Clinic, as the largest integrated transplant center in the country represented by sites in Arizona, Florida and Minnesota, performed a collective 1,987 organ transplants in 2023. Transplant volumes not only exceeded previous records held by Mayo Clinic, but also those of other national transplant programs. Since the organ transplant practice began with the first <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/kidney-transplant/about/pac-20384777">kidney transplant</a> on Nov. 25, 1963, more than 31,000 lifesaving organ transplants have been performed at Mayo Clinic.  </p>



<p>"As we celebrate the 60<sup>th</sup> anniversary of Mayo Clinic's transplant programs, we are also celebrating a record number of transplants," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/heimbach-julie-k-m-d/bio-20054676">Julie Heimbach, M.D.</a>, chair of the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/transplant-center/home/orc-20203891">Transplant Center at Mayo Clinic</a> in Rochester, Minnesota.&nbsp;"Working together across our three destination transplant centers, we have made remarkable progress in patient care which has led to excellent post-transplant outcomes for patients. We have also developed innovative patient care protocols that make transplantation possible even for the most complex patients. We remain focused on the primary value of Mayo Clinic, which is that the needs of the patient come first."</p>



<p>Each of Mayo Clinic's three destination campuses has a large volume and highly successful transplant program. Altogether, Mayo Clinic currently has the largest liver, kidney and heart transplant programs in the country. <em></em></p>



<p>This success can be attributed to several factors, including consistent communication and collaboration between sites, as well as collective expertise-sharing best practices. Each site's transplant program continues to push the limit on ways to increase the availability of organs for transplantation while providing high-quality patient care.<em></em></p>



<p>“When others say no, we say yes," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/aqel-bashar-a-m-d/bio-20055093">Bashar Aqel, M.D.</a>, chair of the Transplant Center at Mayo Clinic in Arizona. "It is not easy at all to become a Category of One. With a passion to do more, to be better every day and unparalleled teamwork, we have achieved that distinction."</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="169" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-300x169.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-377570" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Transplant-Innovation-Theme-FINAL-16x9-1-2048x1151.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure></div>


<p>While performing more organ transplants in 2023 than in any previous year, team physicians and researchers continue to look to the future of organ transplants. The Transforming Transplant strategic initiative aims to transform the field through research and innovation by redefining standards of care for patients in organ failure. The Transplant Specialty Council and Transplant Research Center also are making plans to begin a Transplant Outcomes and Policy Initiative<em> — </em>a structure to invest in data science and build expertise in policy development — in 2024.</p>



<p>“Transplant is a highly complex clinical practice that requires a high degree of coordination throughout the patient journey," says <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/taner-c-burcin-m-d/bio-20054935">Burcin Taner, M.D.</a>, chair of the Transplant Specialty Council and Transplant Center at Mayo Clinic in Florida. "The growing volume of transplants at Mayo Clinic is the ultimate testament that our patients trust our collective expertise. Our successes will spring us to the future in which we envision Mayo Clinic playing an even bigger role in shaping the future of organ transplant globally.”</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-transplant-programs-achieve-record-volumes-in-2023/">Mayo Clinic transplant programs achieve record volumes in 2023</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/02/Image3_1x1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2020/02/Image3_16x9.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Bashar Aqel]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Burcin Taner]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Julie Heimbach]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Q and A: Myths about minority organ donation</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-myths-about-minority-organ-donation/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Barber Lindquist]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q & A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Shennen Mao]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Organ Donation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=374759</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>DEAR MAYO CLINIC: A co-worker was diagnosed with kidney disease last year. He is now on dialysis three times a week as he waits for a kidney transplant. He shared his hope to get a living donor, explaining that he will have a longer wait since there are not as many diverse people signed up [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-myths-about-minority-organ-donation/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Myths about minority organ donation</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/PensiveMan-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-374863" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/PensiveMan-16x9-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/PensiveMan-16x9-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/PensiveMan-16x9-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/PensiveMan-16x9-1-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/PensiveMan-16x9-1.jpg 1656w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>DEAR MAYO CLINIC:</strong> A co-worker was diagnosed with kidney disease last year. He is now on dialysis three times a week as he waits for a kidney transplant. He shared his hope to get a living donor, explaining that he will have a longer wait since there are not as many diverse people signed up as organ donors. Can you explain why this is and what can I do to help?</p>



<p><strong>ANSWER:</strong> </p>



<p>More than 103,000 people in the U.S. are waiting for an organ transplant, according to the <a href="https://optn.transplant.hrsa.gov/data/view-data-reports/national-data/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Organ Procurement and Transplantation Network</a>. Nearly 60% of people on <a href="https://minorityhealth.hhs.gov/omh/browse.aspx?lvl=4&amp;lvlid=27#:~:text=In%202021%2C%2018.7%20percent%20of,percent%20of%20white%20living%20donors.">transplant waiting lists</a> come from minority communities.</p>



<p>Higher rates of heart disease, high blood pressure and diabetes are present in minority communities, contributing to more kidney failure. Almost 89,000 people are waiting for a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/kidney-transplant/home/orc-20203197">kidney transplant</a>.</p>



<p>Though organs are not matched based on race and ethnicity, certain criteria, including blood type&nbsp;and specific antibodies, must be matched to find a compatible organ. People from various ethnic groups will have a better outcome with a donor organ from someone of a similar background.</p>



<p>In general, wait times in the U.S. to receive a deceased donor kidney vary based on region, but can be anywhere from three years up to 10 years. Only about 30% of donor organs are from people of color, so diverse organs are less available.</p>



<p>So, unfortunately, your colleague is correct in that he would likely have a longer wait time for a transplant if waiting on a deceased donor. Finding a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/living-donor-transplant/about/pac-20384787?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">living kidney donor</a> is often a faster route to transplant.</p>



<p>Kidney donation is the most common type of living-donor transplant. Donors give one of their two healthy kidneys to the recipient. People only need one kidney to live a healthy, active life. In 2022, more than 6,400 lives were saved thanks to the generosity of living donors, according to&nbsp;<a href="https://donatelife.net/donation/types/living-donation/">Donate Life America.</a></p>



<p>However, there is a long-standing distrust of the healthcare community in certain minority groups, and many myths have been propagated about the process around organ donation, which has resulted in people being less likely to become organ donors.</p>



<p>Some of the common things I hear from patients include:</p>



<p><strong>Myth: If I agree to donate my organs upon death, the hospital staff won't work as hard to save my life.</strong><strong></strong></p>



<p><strong>Fact:</strong> People who are organ donors will be cared for if they are in the hospital as any other person. When you go to the hospital for treatment, the healthcare team will focus on providing care for you to save your life until your injury or condition is determined to be nonrecoverable. A transplant team will not become involved before your condition is deemed as unsurvivable.</p>



<p><strong>Myth: People who donate organs or tissues can't have an open-casket funeral.</strong><strong></strong></p>



<p><strong>Fact:</strong>&nbsp;Donors' bodies are treated with care and respect. And they're dressed for burial. No one can see that they donated organs or tissues.</p>



<p><strong>Myth:</strong>&nbsp;I'm too old to donate. Nobody would want my organs.</p>



<p><strong>Fact:</strong>&nbsp;There's no defined cutoff age for donating organs. The decision to use your organs is based on strict medical criteria, not age. Don't prematurely disqualify yourself. Let the doctors decide at the time of your death whether your organs and tissues are suitable for transplantation.</p>



<p><strong>Myth: My family will be charged if I donate my organs after death.</strong><strong></strong></p>



<p><strong>Fact:</strong>&nbsp;The organ donor's family never pays for their donation. The donor family pays for all the medical care once you are determined to be a possible donor. Sometimes, families think those costs are for organ donation. But the person who gets the organs for transplant pays the costs for removing the organs.</p>



<p><strong>Myth: Becoming a living donor is a lengthy and costly process. </strong><strong></strong></p>



<p><strong>Fact: Anyone interested in becoming a living donor will have to </strong>undergo online screening and an in-depth physical and psychological evaluation process to ensure they are a good candidate for donation. The recipient's insurance always covers the cost. However, there are some programs available to compensate potential donors for time lost from work or school or to help with travel or dependent care expenses. Once a donor is approved, the timeframe is up to the donor, recipient and the respective care teams.</p>



<p><strong>Myth: Being a living donor will shorten my life span.</strong></p>



<p><strong>Fact: Most healthy people can live with only one kidney. </strong>We expect a person to live a full and normal life following their donation. At Mayo Clinic, we have living donors who have gone on to do incredible athletic feats, including climbing Kilimanjaro, running marathons and having children.<strong></strong></p>



<p><strong>Myth: As a living donor, I must be on medication for the rest of my life. </strong><strong></strong></p>



<p><strong>Fact: </strong>Living donors do not have any long-term medication requirements after donation.</p>



<p><strong>Myth: </strong>I can only be a living donor if I'm a match for someone.</p>



<p><strong>Fact:</strong> Even if someone wants to be a donor for a relative or friend but is found to be incompatible, they can still donate as part of a <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/paired-donation/overview/ovc-20508454?mc_id=us&amp;utm_source=newsnetwork&amp;utm_medium=l&amp;utm_content=content&amp;utm_campaign=mayoclinic&amp;geo=national&amp;placementsite=enterprise&amp;invsrc=other&amp;cauid=100721">paired kidney donation chain</a>. This process allows two or more donors to be matched with appropriate recipients in an exchange.</p>



<p>You can help your colleague by sharing information about organ donation and encouraging others – particularly those with diverse backgrounds – to consider becoming donors. It truly is a gift of life. Go to the <a href="https://donatelife.net/">Donate Life America</a> website to learn more about signing up to be an organ donor. —<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/mao-shennen-a-m-d/bio-20439463"><strong><em>Dr. Shennen Mao</em></strong></a><strong><em>, Transplant Center, Mayo Clinic, Jacksonville, Florida</em></strong></p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related post:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-why-diverse-organ-donors-are-needed/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Why diverse organ donors are needed</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-q-and-a-myths-about-minority-organ-donation/">Mayo Clinic Q and A: Myths about minority organ donation</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/PensiveMan-1x1-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/09/PensiveMan-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Shennen Mao]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Q and A]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Organ Donation]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mayo Clinic Minute: Sickle cell disease explained</title>
		<link>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-sickle-cell-disease-explained/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Deb Balzer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2023 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Children's Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health & Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic Minute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News Cycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transplant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[daily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Asmaa Ferdjallah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sickle cell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sickle cell disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/?p=377492</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Food and Drug Administration is expected to decide by Dec. 8 on a&#160;new therapy to treat sickle cell disease using gene editing technology called&#160;CRISPR, which stands for clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats. Approximately 250 million people worldwide carry the gene for sickle cell disease. It affects those with roots in Africa, Spanish-speaking regions [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-sickle-cell-disease-explained/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Sickle cell disease explained</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Food and Drug Administration is expected to decide by Dec. 8 on a&nbsp;new therapy to treat sickle cell disease using gene editing technology called&nbsp;<a href="https://discoverysedge.mayo.edu/2018/07/24/the-gene-editing-tool-crispr-explained/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CRISPR</a>, which stands for clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats.</p>



<p>Approximately 250 million people worldwide carry the gene for sickle cell disease. It affects those with roots in Africa, Spanish-speaking regions in the Western Hemisphere, Saudi Arabia, India and Mediterranean countries. In the U.S., sickle cell disease is most common in the African American community.&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/biographies/ferdjallah-asmaa-m-d-m-p-h/bio-20518146" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dr. Asmaa Ferdjallah</a>&nbsp;(ESS-mah fer-JALL-ah)&nbsp;a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/departments-centers/childrens-center/pediatric-hematology-oncology-minnesota/overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pediatric hematology, oncology</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/bone-marrow-transplant/about/pac-20384854" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bone marrow transplant&nbsp;</a>physician, is the medical director of Mayo Clinic Children's Center's Comprehensive Pediatric Sickle Cell Program. She says the red blood cell disorder is a lifelong condition with unique challenges.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/G4-3kic-NLc" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: The Mayo Clinic Minute</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidhttpsyoutubeG43kicNLc"  title="Mayo Clinic Minute: Sickle cell disease explained" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/G4-3kic-NLc?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Journalists: Broadcast-quality video pkg (1:03) is in the downloads&nbsp;at the end of the post.&nbsp;Please courtesy: "Mayo Clinic News Network."&nbsp;Read the&nbsp;<a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/12/SCRIPT-MCM-Sickle-Cell.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">script</a>.</strong></p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Genetics</h3>



<p>"Sickle cell disease is a genetic, inherited disorder. It's caused by a mutation in the gene that encodes for hemoglobin," says Dr. Ferdjallah.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For a baby to be born with the disease, both parents must carry a sickle cell gene.</p>



<p>The normally flexible red blood cells turn into rigid crescent shapes — sickle cells— that get stuck in blood vessels. And that can cause problems down the line.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="731" src="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Sickle-Cell-Red-cell-illustration-original-1024x731.jpg" alt="Medical illustration of sickle cell next to red cell" class="wp-image-378212" srcset="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Sickle-Cell-Red-cell-illustration-original-1024x731.jpg 1024w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Sickle-Cell-Red-cell-illustration-original-300x214.jpg 300w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Sickle-Cell-Red-cell-illustration-original-768x549.jpg 768w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Sickle-Cell-Red-cell-illustration-original-1536x1097.jpg 1536w, https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2023/11/Sickle-Cell-Red-cell-illustration-original.jpg 1575w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Medical illustration of a typical red blood cell next to a sickle cell</figcaption></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Screening </h3>



<p>"Fortunately, in the United States, every baby, as part of their newborn screen, is screened for sickle cell disease," says Dr. Ferdjallah.</p>



<p>Babies may not show symptoms until 5 or 6 months, with pain or swelling in the fingertips. And then, later in life,&nbsp;Dr. Ferdjallah says patients experience, "Pain in the extremities, in the back. It's all caused by those sickle cells being stuck in the blood vessels."</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Risks</h3>



<p>Along with pain, the risks for heart and kidney damage and stroke are increased.</p>



<p>"Some of our patients actually experienced stroke, or what we call silent strokes, from the sickle cells actually getting stuck and creating a blockage in the cerebral vessels," Dr. Ferdjallah says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>That's why it's important to work with patients early on and regularly.</p>



<p>"The earlier you go to curative therapy, the better," says Dr. Ferdjallah.</p>



<p>Read more about Dr. Ferdjallah's work with the <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/medical-professionals/pediatrics/news/multidisciplinary-sickle-cell-program-including-curative-bone-marrow-transplant/mac-20525836" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mayo Clinic multidisciplinary sickle cell program</a>..</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/UKbrwPL3wXE" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch: See how CRISPR work in this narrated animation</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="fluidEmbed"><iframe loading="lazy" id="videoidUKbrwPL3wXE"  title="CRISPR Explained" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UKbrwPL3wXE?feature=oembed&enablejsapi=1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Related post:</h4>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/3-facts-about-acute-lymphocytic-leukemia-in-children/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">3 facts about acute </a><a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/3-facts-about-acute-lymphocytic-leukemia-in-children/">lymphocytic leukemia in children</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/discussion/mayo-clinic-minute-sickle-cell-disease-explained/">Mayo Clinic Minute: Sickle cell disease explained</a> appeared first on <a href="https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org">Mayo Clinic News Network</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/09/a-medical-illustration-of-sickle-cell-anemia-1X1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg1x1>
<mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>https://newsnetwork.mayoclinic.org/n7-mcnn/7bcc9724adf7b803/uploads/2017/03/medical-illustration-of-red-blood-cell-and-abnormally-shaped-red-sickle-cells-16x9-1.jpg</mayoclinic:mcimg16x9>
<mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[#Newsapp]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[daily]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Diverse Representation]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Dr. Asmaa Ferdjallah]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Sickle cell]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[sickle cell disease]]></mayoclinic:mctag><mayoclinic:mctag><![CDATA[Social Sensations]]></mayoclinic:mctag>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss><!-- Static page delivered by HubScale -->